<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/peter-luff</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/peter-luff.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Peter Luff MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18769</id>
    <published>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-23-the-strategic-challenges-of-defence-acquisition"/>
    <title>2012/05/23 - The Strategic Challenges of Defence Acquisition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week the Defence Secretary spoke about PR12 marking a new chapter in the long history of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s absolutely right. Balancing the budget is a key part of transforming Defence and making sure we have a Defence Equipment Programme based on firm foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m well aware there may be some here who may be sceptical that this vast programme of change - the root and branch reform of something as large and complex as defence - will succeed. Or indeed actually happen at all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should it work this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well - there are four reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of these is the economic imperative, and a series of events which have led us to this moment. In the foreword to the SDSR the Prime Minister said that bringing the defence budget back to balance is a vital part of how we tackle the  national deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you aren’t convinced by that, just think for a moment about the implications of the gathering storm over the Eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is political will - a determination and commitment which comes from the very top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - this is a process which is gathering momentum on a daily basis. The winds of change are blowing across Defence and across the Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And fourth, there is a growing recognition that everyone has a part to play in this process. And a universal wish - in fact , a real drive - to succeed and see MOD taken off ‘special measures’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now see a general recognition that there is no turning back. Top down meets bottom up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No return to the so called good old days with MOD merrily pushing out fantasy budgets, whipping out a blank cheque book and starting ill-tested projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects which hadn’t a hope of seeing the light of day because, actually, there was no funding in place to ever pay for them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few deluded dissidents, including in industry, seem to yearn for the best forgotten past, but must understand that there will be a heavy price to pay if we don’t grasp this opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A failure to act now would mean a toxic legacy for the future. And wwould threaten both the security and prosperity of our nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a burden which would be shared by future generations of servicemen and women who won’t have the best high tech cutting edge capabilities and solutions. Because we just couldn’t - or wouldn’t - get our act together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indulge me for a moment here in one of my other passions. And let me cite the words of one man who puts this a lot better than I ever could. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shakespeare’s Julius Caesar is one of my favourite plays. It encapsulates so much about life’s dilemmas, conflict and the human condition. About politics, and indeed war.  Albeit a civil one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Act 4 Brutus and Cassius are discussing the final phase of their civil war with the forces of Octavian and Marcus Antonius. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cassius says they should group their forces and take advantage of the secure location to catch their breath. Brutus urges that no - they must act immediately while they have the advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brutus says:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a tide in the affairs of men.&lt;br&gt;
Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune; &lt;br&gt;
Omitted, all the voyage of their life&lt;br&gt;
Is bound in shallows and in miseries.&lt;br&gt;
On such a full sea are we now afloat,&lt;br&gt;
And we must take the current when it serves,&lt;br&gt;
Or lose our ventures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circumstances have created just such a tide and all of us are now afloat on a full sea. But unlike Brutus we will succeed.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper-pr12-defence-transformation-materiel-strategy--equipment-plan"&gt;White Paper, PR12, Defence Transformation, Materiel Strategy &amp;amp; Equipment Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we are to ensure success, more needs to be done. We have the advantage - but we need to do more to maintain it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the  building blocks are in place.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One. The White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has set out our principles on an open approach to procurement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means buying off the shelf where possible, a commitment to opening up more business to SMEs, building in exportability at an early stage. And strong support for exports, as well as a floor in the MOD’s annual Science and Technology budget.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two. PR12 means we can now plan for the future with a certainty that we just couldn’t before as we continued to wrestle with a huge deficit and legacy of overspend.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you are aware, our announcement last week guaranteed the delivery of a number of projects for the Navy, Army and RAF.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted also be able to confirm the establishment of an Armoured Vehicle Pipeline, which provides significant funding for the Warrior Upgrade, Challenger Life Extension, a Utility Vehicle and the Scout programme which is now well into its Demonstration Phase.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pipeline approach enables us to keep a firm control of costs,  numbers, performance and sequencing in order to remain within the allocated profile. The Army, as the end user, will be intimately involved in this process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the Scout, a world-class family of reconnaissance vehicles to which we are now committed, we will first need to reset the programme in order to remain within the pipeline profile. We will then drive hard to a Main Gate 2, when we will finalise production numbers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves the final three building blocks of success. Defence Transformation, The Materiel Strategy and the publication of the Equipment Plan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene’s  Defence Reform recommended devolving most capability planning and resourcing to Front Line Commands -  FLCs - and in turn  a smaller, more strategic and stronger Head Office.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less of the long screwdriver from Head Office - and a lot more giving the FLCs a real opportunity to control their own destinies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant change like this won’t happen overnight. We expect to roll out these changes gradually with an initial operating capability for this model in place for the 2013/14 financial year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embed this new approach I’d ask industry to work closely with the Front Line Commands during this crucial transition process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles of the White Paper will also apply to Front Line Commands:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance they must ask themselves what are the capabilities where we require operational advantage and freedom of action?-  what steps should we take to protect these elements?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we embed open systems and exportability into our procurement processes; and   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we make sure SMEs get access to defence opportunities at an early stage?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am under no illusion that this represents a considerable  challenge for the FLCs - not least to ensure they have the right skills in place as they take on this new responsibility, and accountability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have heard just now from Chris Deverell about ongoing work on the Materiel Strategy, the fourth component of success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you here from industry will be aware that we intend to be a more demanding customer - improving skills and processes at Abbey Wood will ensure we are able to deliver on that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And 2012 will see us announce our 10 Year Equipment Plan after careful scrutiny from the NAO - all funded and accounted for, not just in terms of acquisition but also support costs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fifth component of success will give industry the transparency which they quite understandably, have been pressing for.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that comparisons are still being made with the Defence Industrial Strategy of 2005 - and its much heralded announcement at the time of a 10 year equipment plan.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know this plan never materialised, for the simple fact that, like the Strategy itself, there was no funding plan behind it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we are now in very different place.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a balanced budget and a core equipment programme of £152 billion over 10 years, against a total planned spend of almost £160 billion. That £152 billion includes, for the first time, a centrally held contingency of over £4 billion.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme also includes an additional £8 billion of funding over the next ten years which is unallocated. This means that the budget will have guaranteed headroom which can be allocated to projects as military priorities change.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will open up opportunities to suppliers who are agile, and able to respond with mature products and services as these new opportunities arise.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think , by the way, that we know what we are likely to spend this headroom on. But - it wouldn’t surprise me if we look back in ten years time and discover that changing priorities and technologies had led to very different outcomes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all set to go. Or are we? What are the factors which might hold us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know there are a lot of institutional, governmental and political challenges.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is one main challenge relevant to this audience as far as I am concerned and that is a failure by industry to recognise -  and possibly seize - the opportunities coming your way.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france"&gt;UK-France&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take UK-France collaboration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portfolio of Franco-British programmes sets out to deliver a wide range of capabilities. There’s now real momentum behind this relationship. To some extent we are drawing on each others strengths. And aiming to avoid duplicating capabilities where we don’t need to.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10 year strategic plan for the British and French Complex Weapons Industries encapsulates this.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are real benefits here from our common position on this sector when it comes to budgets, as well as similar military and industry requirements.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the two most capable military powers in Europe, we will look to strengthening our ties with the new French administration to address common security challenges facing both countries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a relationship which has developed around a change of administration here in the UK.  And it is a relationship which will continue to deepen after the recent change in France.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all changes there are risks and opportunities that we will need to address.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will do our bit - but we do need industry to engage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK/France Critical Technologies Study is a case in point where we need you to present a consolidated view. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the White Paper makes clear, we need to focus investment on the ‘critical outcomes’ of what science and technology should achieve, rather than a list of ‘critical technologies’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There needs to be a methodology to do this so we can identify, assess and prioritise as criticalities emerge - and we need industry to contribute to this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve seen - and it’s certainly become very clear in the UK/France High Level Working Group which I co - chair  - is that  French companies are being very proactive when it comes to  getting involved in UK-France equipment collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration is an important principle of the White Paper because it’s essentially about mutual benefit. There are just as many opportunities for our own industrial base.  But you really do have to seize the initiative on this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many of you think that our industrial policy is radically different from that of France. Well, perhaps it is. But I believe that collaboration will only evolve if it can be seen to bring benefits to both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I need your views and ideas on potential opportunities that you see would benefit UK plc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-offset-and-smes"&gt;Industrial offset and SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking about opportunities, I want to say a word here about the issue of offset, and how it impacts on British industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an issue that’s been raised with me on a number of occasions recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offset is a significant challenge to UK exporters, particularly SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while there is limited scope for Government to provide practical help, we will do what we can and work with industry to try and identify measures which help to ease the offset burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reverse of this was, as some of you will be aware, our Industrial Participation Policy which we comprehensively reviewed last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done in the lead up to the publication of the White Paper in February, and was undertaken in liaison with industry members from the UK Offset Strategy Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review factored in the changes that have been going on in the global offset market place in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the review has resulted in a new Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy which remains compatible with our obligations under EU law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this encourages our overseas based suppliers to continue investing in the UK’s defence and security sectors, and to extend opportunities for UK companies to become part of their supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means we will encourage our overseas based suppliers to engage with SMEs in these activities, as they did through our industrial participation policy. And the evidence so far is that they are more than willing to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies such as Boeing are engaging with hundreds of UK suppliers where SMEs are found at every level of the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boeing has over 350 UK suppliers providing parts, services and technology to platforms such as the Chinook and 787. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supply-chain-and-smes"&gt;Supply Chain and SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you’re all pretty aware by now that I’m a determined champion of SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are definitely the innovators of the Defence supply chain, and the life blood of any successful industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up more opportunities for them is one of the deliverables of the White Paper. And a key challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very heartened by the way some of the Primes are engaging with these smaller businesses in such a creative way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I visited General Dynamic in Wales where they have a dedicated technical facility known as The Edge, which searches out new ideas from across the supply chain and academia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just a couple of weeks ago I attended a ‘Meet The Technologist’ event at UKTI, a kind of speed dating event organised by Lockheed Martin who flew over some of their leading experts from the States to hook up with SMEs back here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rather telling that it’s Primes from overseas who seem to be energised when it comes to exploiting this innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder - is there any reason why our domestic primes don’t seem to be showing the same leadership and commitment? Perhaps they are - and they’re just not telling me about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is - and this is my challenge to you - that one of the ways I’ll be evaluating companies will be on the quality of their engagement with the SME supply chain, because to me that flag ups innovation and value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find very interesting about many of these smaller companies is the way SMEs are increasingly establishing themselves by selling to the export market and then marketing themselves back here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re hungry, they’re aggressive and they’re not afraid to get out there and pitch for the business. It’s the key to success and I relish their enthusaism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked today about a new chapter for Defence. And about the challenges for industry in this new era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new era in which Defence is a tougher and more pragmatic customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And also a time when Defence will have to be a more informed and intelligent customer. And we’ve just been hearing about the changes needed to take forward the Materiel Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="total-support-force"&gt;Total Support Force&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing a lot more today about the nature of this challenge. And it will be very interesting to get the perspective of the Front Line Commands themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course transformation and changing the way we do things also brings other opportunities for industry. And there’s one in particular that will now demand greater attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total Support Force - TSF - with contractors having a crucial role to play as part of a fully integrated force structure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re very keen that they’re involved at the earliest opportunity in Op Herrick drawdown and other capability regeneration plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD, in close liaison with Industry, has continued to build upon the success of Contractor Support to Operations. In fact, there are currently over 5,000 contractors directly supporting operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very encouraging that Industry is taking an active and positive role in the development of the Total Support Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The services, together with other areas of Defence, have been working to identify a number of identified a number of potential Total Support Force initiatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’re engaging with industry - directly, and through ADS -   in the work to decide what will be brought to market and how. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas under consideration include equipment support activities currently largely delivered by the REME, as well as some new ideas on airfield support activities, possibly allied to Project Future Brize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that balancing the books has not been easy. It has - quite rightly - been a forensic process and it has taken some time. It’s taken the SDSR, two planning rounds, a three month exercise and then some. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although I enjoyed the comment, the Daily Telegraph wasn’t quite right when it said that we had fed the 5000, cleared the Agean stable and solved the Schleswig-Holstein question all in a single day; it has actually taken two years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to get Defence back onto a firm footing so that we could look to the future and get on with the job. And there is more work to do to ensure the footing is really secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also remember that the job of delivering military success on operations, which is , after all what Defence is all about. And which remains our number one priority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the money, and how we use it, matters. As Chris Deverell’s presentation makes clear, only by looking after the bottom line can we make sure we’re achieving our real objective of looking after the front line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18765</id>
    <published>2012-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-01-helicopter-capability-industry-briefing-day"/>
    <title>2012/05/01 - Helicopter Capability Industry Briefing Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you, for that kind welcome from Paul and his team here in Yeovilton. [Paul Chivers CO Yeovilton]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you to [Kevin and] ADS for organising this event with Wayne’s team in the MOD. [Commodore Wayne Keble, Head of Air Littoral Manoeuvre Capability] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADS does a great job championing this sector, and playing an active role in both the Suppliers Forum as well as the SME Forum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that ADS - and indeed many others here - have contributed to the Defence Rotary Wing Capability Study which you’ll be hearing more about later on from Wayne and his team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also most grateful to Agusta Westland, Rockwell Collins and Lockheed Martin for their kind sponsorship of today’s event - today wouldn’t be possible without you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally I would of course be speaking to you here today in a post PR12 world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very aware that many of you are waiting for this level of direction to inform your planning and decision making in the months ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s regrettable that our discussions today won’t be able to have that level of detail. I can assure you though that we are nearly there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is plenty to talk about when it comes to this sector. And I’m confident that our White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has provided clarity on MOD’s approach to acquisition and support. More about that later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="helicopter-availability-in-theatre---tribute-to-industry"&gt;Helicopter availability in theatre - tribute to industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago ‘helicopter availability’ was a pretty loaded term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopters were very definitely a bad news story for defence -back in 2009 it seemed that barely a day went by without gloomy media headlines denouncing a lack of helicopters in Afghanistan, and claims that this shortage was undermining our operational effectiveness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years on and I’m delighted to say that we’re now looking at a very different picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Afghanistan earlier this year visiting Lashkhar Gar and Bastion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to travel on a range of helicopters, (including by the way an Osprey, if an Osprey is really a helicopter) to talk to the crews, and visit Joint Helicopter Force there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was impressed - and very heartened - by the availability and capability of UK airframes.  And this was also borne out by Commanders I spoke to on the ground.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work being done by the Chinooks responding to medical emergencies, for example, is just incredibly humbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the workhorses of the skies being flown by incredibly courageous crews. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we have enough of these vital assets performing at  an optimum level on a daily basis is - I believe - a testimony to the improved and effective partnership working of defence and industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week on the Terrace of the House of Commons I met members of the Royal Navy and RAF who had been involved in Op Ellamy over and near Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among them were the deck hands of HMS Ocean who got the Apache helicopters off and safely home - black helicopters on a black deck on a black night on a black sea.  Not an easy job with blades whirling, weapons loaded and adrenalin pumping. But what a job those Apaches did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their story really brought home to me once again just how critical rotary power is for our operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s delivering freedom of movement and logistic support, or providing close combat support and an evacuation capability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability of our fleet to operate in these hostile and dangerous environments is - I believe - in very large part due to the hard work and commitment of the companies here in this room today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can still do more, and it is your technological innovation that is helping us to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you will be aware of the very successful cooperation between DSTL, Ferranti, Elbit and Agusta Westland to develop a product to help crews during brown-out landings, which remain one of the biggest risks to helicopter operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that others are actively pursuing solutions in this area too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cooperative investigation has been very successful so far and I very much hope that we will be able to build on this research to provide our pilots with a solution in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry-support-to-uors"&gt;Industry support to UORs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your responsiveness has been particularly striking on the UOR front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agusta Westland’s upgraded Lynx Mk9a has been a real success. We now have a vastly more capable airframe able to cope with the demanding environment of Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 helicopters delivered to the front line in just 18 months was an enormous achievement - and the now fully converted fleet is continuing to turn in a star performance in theatre with over 4,000 hours flown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked to some of the air crew in person when I was in Bastion. They raved about it. And they can’t wait for Wildcat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not all UORs are on this scale, but they are just as important - the kind of emergency practical stuff that’s so essential for keeping our fleet airworthy and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protective floor covering on Chinook and Merlin used on the Medical Emergency Response Team flights, for example, took just 10 weeks to be fitted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s 10 weeks, by the way, from initial concept and drawing board stage to deployment in theatre. A terrific achievement , and one that is helping ensure this life saving capability is maintained. A match indeed for Brunel’s mobile theatre for the Crimea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rotary-wing-capability-study"&gt;Rotary Wing Capability Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotary power is an absolutely critical component of combat power. That’s why the Defence Rotary Wing Capability Study - or Derrick as I believe it’s known colloquially - is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know the study was initiated by VCDS in the wake of the Strategic Defence and Security Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially the study has been looking at capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And taking a long hard look at issues such as basing, force structures, command and control - and of course military helicopter flying training from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, you’ll be hearing more about the conclusions and recommendations of the study from Wayne and his team today -  particularly on areas such as training and simulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of you here today will have been personally involved in the study so I’ve no doubt there will be a lot to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that the study will help to provide industry with direction and clarity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-white-paper"&gt;Defence White Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that our White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ also provides insight into how MOD sees the future, and the changes we need to make to ensure we have a balanced and affordable equipment programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, this means we’ll be adopting an Open Procurement policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means buying off the shelf wherever possible and when appropriate. Where we need technological advantage for security we will maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means collaboration with friends and allies wherever possible. The UK-France Defence Co-operation Treaty is a tangible example of that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a partnership which continues to mature and develop, and the consolidation of the Complex Weapons programme under MBDA is a demonstration that we’re definitely in this for the long term. And it’s a partnership that must bring benefit to both sides. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Procurement also means a commitment to opening up more MOD business to SMEs - organisations which bring innovation and agility to our equipment programme, and which are already winning a sizeable proportion of defence contracts. Changing technology makes this commitment ever more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies are already making an important contribution to this sector - I’m thinking here of companies like Wallop Defence Industries, involved in providing the flares we use to counter MANPADS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper has been described as ‘pragmatic’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is. It was meant to be and it has to be. We have to get the right solution for the Armed Forces at the best possible price for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yes this means it’s sometimes better to do work outside of the UK - elements of the Puma life extension programme are being undertaken in Romania and France rather than on these shores. And actually that was a decision taken by the last government and one I am entirely comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why, for example, we took the decision to build our 14 new Chinooks on Boeing’s Philadelphia production line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there are those of you in the audience that would have liked to have seen these built right here in Somerset. And you made a strong argument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I visited the Boeing factory last year I was left in no doubt that the scale of the operation already in place means that best value for money and lowest risk can only be delivered from there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the realities of Defence procurement in 2012. Of course I would love every penny Defence has to stay in the UK, but apart from anything else, if we want the world to buy our products and services - which we do - we have to be prepared to use theirs when it is right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-industrial-engagement---and-the-defence-industrial-strategy-2005"&gt;Defence Industrial engagement - and the Defence Industrial Strategy (2005)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But has it not ever been so? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…it is important to be clear that we will continue to look to the vibrant and competitive global market place to satisfy our future helicopter requirement…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds rather 2012, white paper in the age of austerity, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it’s anything but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this text is lifted from page 94 of Lord Drayson’s 2005 Defence Industrial Strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DIS contained many commendable aspirations. Most of them were, however, unfunded, which meant it was always going to be something of a wish list - and certainly became one as economic realities unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it had a pretty clear and realistic position on helicopters reflected in the reality of Wildcats assembled just down the road in Yeovil, Pumas modified in mainland Europe and Chinooks being built in America. And, as I saw yesterday at RAF Benson, increasingly effective support for the Merlin fleet in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand you want clarity on industrial engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hope you’ll agree that actually when it comes to this sector, there has been an enduring policy in place for a number of years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see no enduring reason why a competitive British defence industry shouldn’t win business in this sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making you, the Defence industry, more competitive is a central theme of the White paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Government committed without reservation to building an environment conducive to responsible Defence exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we are doing so much to support the SME base, where innovation and flexibility offer us a dynamic that the Primes cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I have for the first time put a floor under the science budget, to ensure that as a nation we remain at the forefront of cutting edge, battle-winning technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is realistic, but it is deliverable. And I firmly believe it should give you more - not less - confidence in the Department as we go forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-base---the-offset-issue"&gt;Industrial base - the offset issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And staying on the industrial theme, I want to say a word here about the issue of what was once known as industrial offset, and the challenge this poses for UK SMEs when exporting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an issue that’s been raised with me on a number of occasions recently - and quite seriously misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of you here will be aware, the MOD conducted a comprehensive review of our previous Industrial Participation policy last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done in the lead up to the publication of the White Paper in February, and was undertaken in liaison with industry members from the UK Offset Strategy Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review factored in the changes that have been going on in the global offset market place in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also acknowledged the challenges faced by UK exporters who are increasingly being asked to fulfil stringent offset obligations, particularly in new and emerging defence markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the review has resulted in a new Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy which remains compatible with our obligations under EU law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this encourages our overseas based suppliers to continue investing in the UK’s defence and security sectors, and extending opportunities for UK companies to become part of their supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also means we will encourage our overseas based suppliers to engage with SMEs in these activities. And the evidence so far is that they are more than willing to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Boeing are sourcing key components for the 14 new Chinooks from UK SMEs and will be basing through life support work in the UK - which will provide further opportunities through the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="looking-ahead---our-helicopter-fleet"&gt;Looking ahead - our helicopter fleet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR clearly set out our long term plans for a helicopter fleet based on four core platforms from 2025 - the post Herrick era as I’ve heard it referred to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are already part of the rotary lexicon: Apache, Merlin, Chinook and Wildcat. I am pleased to say that we have recently secured the release to service for the first Wildcat to start Army training - I look forward to seeing this aircraft this afternoon. And we are looking at options to upgrade the Merlin Mk3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will still need Puma until the future changes can be made and that is why we committed to complete the Life Extension Plan in SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that of course means that there is currently no medium term MOD requirement for a new UK developed airframe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are opportunities here in the civilian market and BIS are taking a very active role in helping the sector in that diversification process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year BIS announced £32 million of government investment in helicopter production, research and development which will provide an important boost to Agusta Westland, for instance in the introduction of the civil AW169 aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that, when it comes to future defence work, the opportunities for many of you here will lie in support and training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the Wildcat flying should sustain hundreds of engineering and technical jobs at Agusta Westland and here in Yeovilton over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And looking ahead there will be opportunities for industry to contribute to our Total Force Support concept which will include a sizeable number of contractors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know there’s more you can be doing when it comes to providing expert support on the ground - in fact this sector is already leading the way, with Vector Aerospace and Boeing UK deploying engineers in theatre doing vital work keeping our Chinooks airborne. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the best way to sustain jobs in the long term will be to widen your customer base. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why supporting exports is another principle of the White Paper, and why we’ve also appointed Susana Mason to co-ordinate exports on the MOD side. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re providing Ministerial support across Government for rotary wing opportunities - particularly the AW101 and AW159 Wildcat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are worldwide export opportunities for Wildcat, with specific interest from other Lynx operating nations such as Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the word pragmatic earlier on to describe our approach to making sure we have a balanced and affordable equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s an approach I would also commend to all of you in this sector as your companies plan and invest for the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, while defence here in the UK may be a shrinking market, there are plenty of other opportunities out there - in the civilian sector as well as overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversification will be the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve covered quite a lot of ground here this morning - and I hope I’ve addressed some of the issues that I know those of you here from industry have been seeking clarity on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18762</id>
    <published>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-28-editorial-intelligence-comment-conference-the-manufacturing-economy"/>
    <title>2012/03/28 - Editorial Intelligence Comment Conference ‘The Manufacturing Economy’</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an economist with a passion for engineering I welcome Editorial Intelligence’s initiative in organising today’s event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a truism but it needs to be said - especially by ministers. The role and contribution of manufacturing in today’s global economy is central to us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this morning’s session has centred on the producer’s view - the industry perspective - of the manufacturing economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the challenges and opportunities companies face in a globalised and technological age. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-manufacturing"&gt;The importance of manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you’ve also discussed the challenge of inspiring young people to get involved in production and manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I feel passionately about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply can’t understand the constant hand wringing in this country about the state of our manufacturing industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gloomy assertions that we don’t - and can’t - make anything any more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the endless claims that in any event the whole process of manufacturing somehow ‘doesn’t count’, and is irrelevant to our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes my blood boil, because all this unhelpful armchair criticism just doesn’t reflect the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if anyone here saw Evan Davies’s excellent TV programme last year on UK manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did a great job in exploding the urban myth that Britain is no longer an industrial nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain - he correctly argued - could not actually survive without its vital manufacturing industries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is, in fact, still a manufacturing powerhouse with upwards of four million people still making everything from high-tech aircraft to supercars. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are people employed in a sector which is - in economic terms - twice as big as financial services. In fact, manufacturing accounts for half UK exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be talking later about the role of the defence industry in our manufacturing industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What concerns me about this endless talking ourselves down and the gloomy media headlines is that it all becomes something of a self fulfilling prophesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - worryingly - acts as a disincentive to young people who might otherwise consider working in industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a real problem. And I see it all the time in the defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a huge demand in this country for well qualified people with the right engineering, scientific and technical skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand is there - but the people aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are subjects which just haven’t been popular options in recent years. And of course there continues to be a noticeable lack of women working in these roles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons behind the recent decision to allow women to serve in Royal Navy submarines is the possibility that we can attract people from the widest pool of talent and skills into the Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies I deal with tell me that these skills shortages are having a direct impact on their growth and productivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got to take steps to reverse this process of decline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And make sure that being an engineer is an attractive proposition. And that it’s a career choice which carries the same status as being a doctor or a lawyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just an issue for Government or industry. The manufacturing sector matters to our wider economy, to our communities. And to our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, nurturing and developing this talent at an early stage is one particularly effective way of developing our skills base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD runs a range of civilian craft and technician apprenticeships across the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Armed Forces as a whole are the largest providers of apprenticeships across the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BAE Systems, one of today’s sponsors, are particularly successful in this area when it comes to development. They are renowned for their huge pull through of apprenticeships to senior management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’re all in agreement that developing our skills base is going to be an essential driver of our economy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have also been talking this morning about the need for growth. And how innovation is central to this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here to talk about the manufacturing economy from the perspective of one of its major customers. The Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be outlining some of the changes we’re making in our approach to buying equipment - in particular our commitment to making the MOD more accessible for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about our determination to become a more intelligent and demanding customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-defence-industry---a-vibrant-sector"&gt;The Defence industry - A vibrant sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defence industry is one of the UK’s most vibrant sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts speak for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an industry currently supporting around 300,000 jobs in this country - many of them in advanced engineering, an area in which this country has such a distinguished tradition and strong track record. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take aerospace for example - a great example of an R&amp;amp;D intensive, high tech industry with technological spin offs to the rest of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has the largest aerospace industry in Europe, and the second largest in the world after the USA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK aerospace has a turnover of £23 billion. Defence accounts for just over half of that - 52% to be precise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this country is the second largest defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of annual sales and a 22% share of the global market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, with the fourth biggest defence budget in the world, the Ministry of Defence is - even in these straitened times - a customer with a lot of spending power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a government department we are also a customer that is accountable to the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure defence has an equipment programme which is balanced and affordable is important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an age of both national and defence austerity it’s absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="materiel-strategy"&gt;Materiel Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this government inherited a Ministry of Defence with a gaping deficit - and an equipment programme in financial freefall. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programme based on the kind of fantasy budgets that I know many of you here from the corporate sector would find it pretty hard to countenance. Or even imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working hard to balance the books. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully it will not be long before we can announce our plans for PR12, and the equipment plan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting a grip of this gaping deficit - and we have - has meant, and will mean, driving forward change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It calls for a new mindset. And a very different approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means defence has to become a more intelligent and demanding customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means taking a long hard look at our processes, and the way we do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upping our game when it comes to having the right skills in areas like financial and project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it calls for significant changes in Defence Equipment and Support - DE&amp;amp;S as it is known - the organisation outside Bristol which heads up our acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Materiel Strategy, as it’s being called, aims to transform DE&amp;amp;S. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure it has the relationships, structures, management and skills it needs to provide the right equipment to our Armed Forces. At the right time and at the right cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have looked at a number of options and we have pretty well already ruled out the status quo. I have already said in public that there have been three options judged most appropriate for further consideration: Trading Fund, Executive Non-Departmental Body and a Government-Owned Contractor-Operated organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already have extensive experience of running Trading Funds - for example the Met Office and DSTL- and so the DE &amp;amp; S has now begun a soft market testing exercise to obtain further information from the private sector about the other options to help inform our decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just stress here that no decisions have yet been taken on this, although we intend to have a clear idea later this year on the best option to take forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper"&gt;White Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be changing our processes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re already changing our approach to acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s necessary for us - and it’s essential for industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because the defence industry - any industry in fact -  has to be competitive if it’s to thrive in today’s global economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re making sure this change happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month we launched our White Paper - ‘National Security Through Technology’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan of action for defence which commits us to adopting a new, open procurement approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, pretty much what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we’ll be seeking to fulfill defence requirements through open competition in the domestic and global market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means buying off the shelf if that represents the best value for money - which it often will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why a competitive British defence industry shouldn’t win that business. Recent history - for example the Foxhound protected mobility vehicle or the Sea Ceptor missile system - shows it generally does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also thinking here of a company like Mabey Bridge Company, which is based in South Wales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mabey is a world leader when it comes to pre-fabricated bridge systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have won a number of contracts to supply logistic support bridging to our Forces in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when British Army engineers took on construction of a 140 tonne bridge to connect two Afghan communities in Helmand -  the biggest bridge our soldiers have built since World War 2 - it was Mabey who won the contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And “modified off the shelf” - buying a platform that’s freely available on the British or international market and then integrating it with, say, electronic counter measures or communication equipment here in the UK - ensures vital system skills are maintained in our domestic manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open procurement means actively looking for ways to collaborate, preferably bilaterally, with other countries because this will often offer economies of scale, and benefits such as longer production runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries such as the US, which is our major bilateral partner and where collaboration allows us access to cutting-edge research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course France with whom we’re now co-operating on a range of defence programmes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together the UK and France account for half of Europe’s defence expenditure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We led last year’s operations in Libya. And we’re now working to develop a Combined Joint Expeditionary Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both countries collaboration means our money goes further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we can maintain a critical mass of demand for skills and industries we might otherwise lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - very importantly - it ensures we can operate our combined forces effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our open approach can best be summed up by the word ‘pragmatic’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that most certainly does not mean any compromise when it comes to this country’s national security and  capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology at the heart of the equipment programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper puts Technology at the heart of our equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of business, technological advantage - quite properly - means making money and increasing your market share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For defence it’s now absolutely crucial to our modus operandi, and  making sure we have operational advantage over potential adversaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to invest in technology to be able to meet an increasingly capable and diverse range of threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why it was so extraordinarily short sighted of the previous Government to more than halve the MOD’s Science and Technology budget between 1997 - 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m determined this process of decline is immediately stopped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has been. The proportion of spending on Science and Technology is now baselined at its current level of 1.2% of the overall defence budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment that’s around £400 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A commitment to technology and open procurement also means opening up defence to providers with agility, innovation and the ability to exploit new and emerging technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means making defence a lot more accessible to SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key principle of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="smes"&gt;SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs are the lifeblood of any successful industry today. And it’s certainly the case in defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, when its agility and innovation we’re looking for - and that’s certainly been the case in recent years when it comes to getting urgent operational requirements out to our forces in Afghanistan - we have found its these smaller organisations which have proved time and again that they can - and will -  deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re determined to open up more of our business to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re already making progress on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, SMEs are currently winning 42% of MOD’s equipment contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In financial terms that’s around £1 billion of new business a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many more SMEs are contributing to defence and security programmes as sub contractors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up our business of course also means that we have to be a lot more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means making sure - for example - that there’s an emphasis on open systems factored in to our requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And scope for these smaller companies to offer the kind of modular systems which enhance major weapons and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cde---helping-smes"&gt;CDE - helping SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making us more accessible of course also means that we need to make sure SMEs know about our requirements - and are able to put forward their ideas and make sure they’re properly assessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the Centre for Defence Enterprise - CDE - comes in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in Harwell it acts as an entry point for new science and technology providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And unlocks the potential of SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE gives practical help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By sending out themed calls for proposals on a range of issues, for example,  and organising ‘one to one’ surgeries providing guidance on how best to pitch an idea to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE cuts through a lot of the red tape which often seems to engulf an organisation as big as ours.  Companies can get advice from the CDE team in Harwell, submit their research proposal online and track its progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that proposal is generally assessed within 25 working days -although it can take as little as 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE was originally launched as a pilot scheme back in 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now time to take it to the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why yesterday I announced an expansion of its role -additional activities which will provide a dedicated focus to SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities such as market place events for SMEs to showcase their projects to defence primes and the venture capital investment community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open engagement events to increase awareness of opportunities within the defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a with a small dedicated team from CDE and our Defence, Equipment and Support organisation who will now act as mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be additional annual funding of up to £2 million through the Small Business Research Initiative - or SBRI as it’s more commonly known. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is money which will be directly used to progress successful CDE projects which show the most potential for defence purposes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s our commitment to sourcing these new providers, and opening up our business, which means that I was particularly intrigued to see that the next session will be debating the role of UK brands in the global market place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, of course, the whole issue of branding can be a bit misleading.  In the old days there was just one label: ‘Made in’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today that same product could probably have a number of different labels to show its provenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such as ‘designed in’; ‘manufactured in’ or ‘developed in’. The global supply chain is a complex one - and that’s as true for defence as any other industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could of course be argued that the individual UK Armed Forces are in themselves a brand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Army. The Royal Navy. The Royal Air Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say these names is to hear their power - as fighting forces and as names that inspire loyalty, affection, respect, trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s probably true that if they are using a particular piece of kit then that’s the kind of endorsement a lot of companies are very keen indeed to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However - the fact is that defence as a customer has no interest whatsoever in brands. We have no ‘brand awareness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just not a factor when we’re deciding what equipment to buy -and how to support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a proposal is innovative, sound and good value it makes no difference to us whether it comes from a household name. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or an up and coming SME. A behemoth or a brash upstart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not dazzled by shiny logos. And we’re not interested in flashy marketing campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not equate familiarity with excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brand - for us - is no substitute for a hard earned corporate reputation for project management, for example. That reputation could belong to an SME just as much as a Prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe me, when I visit our forces in Afghanistan the last thing they’re worried about is who made the equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they want to know is: “Does this work? Will it give me and the people I work with the right support and battle winning capability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us the value of manufacturing is about focusing on the end user. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about ‘who makes the equipment, or piece of kit?’ but rather ‘who will be using it’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Defence that answer will be - our servicemen and women. People whose lives will very often depend on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, indeed, all of you whose liberty could depend on it too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18761</id>
    <published>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-27-cde-showcase"/>
    <title>2012/03/27 - CDE Showcase</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that kind introduction Mark. [Mark Fulop, a Director in the DSTL programme office]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I greatly appreciate it and I’m delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers and politicians often start speeches saying something like that, but today I really, really mean it. I am genuinely delighted to be here, to celebrate CDE’s success and that of its clients - and to announce some changes that should make the organisation even more effective in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE is entering a new phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has already announced that CDE will have an extended remit to cover the UK’s fast growing UK security sector, which is one of the most diverse and technically advanced in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’ll be talking about the organisations which are the real drivers of innovation for defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations which most benefit - indeed really need - the practical support and expertise of the CDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course these organisations are Small and Medium Enterprises, or SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE will be focusing a lot more on SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical ways. Such as organising SME friendly events and engagement programmes. As well as undertaking a mentoring role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be additional funding available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be going into more detail on this later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking about the additional resources, and funding, CDE will get to deliver more support to SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking around this morning’s exhibition I’ve again been struck by the range and inventiveness of the ideas on show, and I sometimes feel I’m in a parallel universe where the MoD can do no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the modular robotic systems by Robosynthesis, to the extraordinary e-textile developed by Intelligent Textiles which distributes electrical power and data without the need for cables -I’m pleased to see they’ve solved their connector problem from last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m told, by the way, it currently holds the Guinness World Record for being the world’s most advanced soldier system uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting our people is about making sure they are well equipped with these future battle winning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also about making sure we provide them with the very best medical care and rehabilitation support if they are injured in the line of duty. These will be of particular interest to my ministerial colleague Nick Harvey who is here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another important strand of CDE’s work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frazer-Nash adaptive bike on display here today is the prototype of a design, with the final version now in use and proving a huge success at Headley Court. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be able to see all this kit first hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on a personal level it’s also been a very welcome opportunity to meet the men and women who are the brains behind these innovative solutions to challenging questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are individuals who come from a range of backgrounds and disciplines, a number of whom had never had any contact with Defence until they started working with CDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s really important. I want CDE to reach out beyond the “usual suspects” to bring fresh thinking to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they will all share, however, is a passion for innovation. And a determination to see their ideas developed and out there helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all our exhibitors here today I’d just like to say ‘Thank you’ for bringing your ideas to Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your solutions are already making a vital contribution to our defence effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am determined we should not rest on our laurels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="role-and-value-of-cde"&gt;Role and value of CDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk about why the work of the CDE is so important. And about our plans to take it forward on to the next phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen today, Defence is a sector with a lot of potential for people and companies with a talent for invention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE unlocks that potential. It acts as the entry point for new science and technology providers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a hub and first point of contact for SMEs, academics and others who want to know how to pitch an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does the CDE add value for MOD?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer’s simple - it gives us reach into areas of fast moving technical innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an area such as maritime innovation, for example, which CDE launched as an open call at the end of January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE held a briefing on a range of technical challenges - from improving navigation capability of unmanned underwater vehicles to next generation submarine sensors and improving the security of data on submarines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or how best to take forward new ISTAR solutions. Recent conflicts have shown us just how important this issue is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguarding our nation and our nation’s interest covers a huge spectrum of activity and effort. The work of CDE reflects that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nearly four years ago - May 2008 to be exact - since the CDE was launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was originally the brainchild of Paul Drayson - a former Minister for Defence Equipment under the previous Government.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Paul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an engineer and entrepreneur he had a deep rooted understanding of just how vital innovation was when it came to delivering cutting edge solutions for defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He played a major role in raising the profile of science and technology across the MOD. Although he must have been disappointed to see S&amp;amp;T fall as a share of MoD’s spending -  something I hope we’ve now put right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul was instrumental in the setting up of CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He knew that if Defence was to be able to exploit new and emerging technologies - which it had to, to meet the challenges it faced - the department would need to be proactively reaching out to people with the ideas.  The sort of people who very often weren’t aware that their ideas could help Defence..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do so it would need to be more accessible - and to be seen to be more accessible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Drayson was absolutely right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why the CDE was set up with three main aims:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To provide visibility of the MOD’s requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To inform and support new supply networks &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And above all to widen the MOD’s supplier base&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think we would all agree that this is an organisation which has more than lived up to these founding principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch the CDE has established a reputation for reaching out across a very wide spectrum of the engineering and scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a dynamic hub, running open and themed calls on key sectors, as well as seminars and workshops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it holds regular surgeries - ‘one to ones’ - where individuals and companies can get personalised guidance on what the MoD is looking for, and practical help on how to pitch an idea to us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results show that this approach has worked - to date over 3,000 proposals have been received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research contracts awarded to date are worth a total of over £23.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today marks the award of the 500th contract - to ITSUS,  an SME based in Wales who I was talking to just before I came in here, which is working to improve network capacity for military operations where bandwidth is a scarce and valuable commodity. This is one of the Holy Grails of Defence - a really central challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract, worth £104,000, is on top of a previous £50,000 CDE contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ITSUS will be using the funds to look at how existing systems can be used more efficiently, and give our forces an enhanced tactical advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing shortly from Jonathan Byrne. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan, as Head of CDE  I understand that you often advise companies when they’re pitching to MOD that they need to make sure their solutions focus on  ‘explicit deliverables’ and ‘compelling outputs’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this practical and no-nonsense approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned that pretty well encapsulates the urgency and relevance of what we’re looking for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE successfully cuts through a lot of the red tape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in very practical ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies can get advice from the CDE team in Harwell, submit their research proposal online and track its progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also - and this is particularly important for SMEs - a proposal can be assessed in around 25 days, though on occasion it will take as little as 15 days. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE demonstrates that Defence is open for business - and hungry for ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper---smes-and-boosting-the-role-of-cde"&gt;White Paper - SMEs and boosting the role of CDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I want to build on the significant achievements of the CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And see even more of these ideas and concepts becoming mature products which contribute to battle winning capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why boosting the role of CDE is one of the deliverables of our recent White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper places technology at the heart of our Defence Equipment and Support effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to. Exploiting new and emerging technologies is central to making sure our Armed Forces have the battle-winning capabilities they need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the SMEs have the agility and innovation required to deliver these solutions. And at the best possible price for the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rapidly changing technologies, we will often find solutions to our challenges not among the big beasts of the defence jungle, but among the smaller, more agile businesses that think quicker and react more immediately to change, challenge and opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why opening up more of our business to SMEs is another commitment from the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just because we agree with the wider governmental growth agenda. It’s because we in defence absolutely need SMEs to deliver our outputs. To solve our problems. To keep our people safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are making progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, SMEs are currently winning around 42% of MOD’s equipment contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In financial terms that’s around £1 billion of new business a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many more SMEs are contributing to Defence and Security programmes as sub-contractors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is more we can do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, that is why we’ll be taking what we call an Open Procurement approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach will focus on ensuring there’s an emphasis on ‘open systems’ factored in to our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will mean there’s scope for SMEs to offer the kind of modular systems which enhance major weapons and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also maximise the opportunities for SMEs at Prime and Sub-contract level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a focus on exportability across our equipment programme will open up new markets for your products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s essential that SMEs - whose issues are often very different from those of Primes - have their own platform within the defence industry to engage with the Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I have established a dedicated SME Forum which addresses the concerns of smaller companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chair these meetings personally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a really useful way of getting together with industry to address the kind of challenges some of you here may be facing - on issues such as IPR for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify issues that MoD needs to address and which the SMEs themselves need to think about too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADS are members of the Forum and I know we’ll be hearing from you later on; Rees I look forward to that speech very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="taking-cde-to-the-next-level---smes-and-active-engagement"&gt;Taking CDE to the next level - SMES and active engagement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Championing SMEs requires us to go out of our way to encourage and champion greater pull through of innovative ideas into applications and contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why the White Paper highlights the need to - and I quote: ‘enhance the role of the CDE, such that it works more closely with the SMEs that it funds, including the facilitation of opportunities to engage with prime contractors to increase the likelihood of exploitation of the most innovative outputs.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means as I’ve already said, taking CDE to the next level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In broadening the reach of CDE to address both defence and security markets, as well as deepening its support to new entrants into the defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, in the words of the White Paper again, ‘enhancing exploitation mechanisms between CDE and our suppliers.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will do this with an active focus on SMEs, and on implementing an active “SME friendly” engagement programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three parts to this initiative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what they all boil down to is this - CDE will be focussing much more clearly on SMEs in its future work through a series of SME initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part one. I talked about CDE’s role as an entry point to Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it also has another function - as a bridge linking the SMEs and the main defence suppliers, as well as investors and wider Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The added value CDE brings here is in facilitating networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later this year CDE will be launching a series of market place events. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be designed for SMEs to showcase their project outputs to Defence Primes; the venture capital investment community and innovation initiatives across government within other government departments such as the Technology Strategy Board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of this SME initiative will be the introduction of nine new ‘Open Engagement’ events to increase awareness of opportunities within the Defence research and development market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these will be working jointly with industry bodies and knowledge transfer networks, as well as specific industry sectors - such as Transport and Healthcare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, we’ve used Formula 1 technology, as you’ll probably know, in the latest of our armoured vehicles - the Foxhound -which we’ll soon be deploying in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And part three of the SME initiative will involve CDE mentoring SMEs - in order to guide and help their approach to maximise opportunities for exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE will be a promoter - giving SMEs the opportunity to present their innovations to leading defence and other suppliers and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD - in common with the rest of the public sector - is heavily constrained when it comes to resources, I have arranged that CDE and DE&amp;amp;S will each be bringing extra focus on supporting SME engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of CDE’s strengths is its fleetness of foot, born of a small, unbureaucratic structure. I don’t want this to change. But I do want to see CDE’s clients access the acquisition programmes of MoD much more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So both organisations, CDE and DE&amp;amp;S, will be devoting a handful of staff - probably four each - to this effort. They will be the Sherpas who help make good ideas real. Who ensure CDE’s clients can reach the summit of their ambition. And so help solve more of MoD’s equipment challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise roles and locations of the staff are yet to be decided, but my key message is that we are committed to SME engagement, we are already delivering against it and we’re going to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing about all of this in more detail from Jonathan Byrne. Jonathan heads up CDE and he and his team will be taking this work forward in the months ahead. And I’ll be keeping a very close eye on it, so make it work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="funding"&gt;Funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also announce that there will be additional funding for the CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under present arrangements, the CDE, which is part of the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory, or DSTL as it’s more commonly known, is funded by the defence research programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sum has also been boosted by another funding route - through the Technology Strategy Board’s support for the Small Business Research Initiative - or SBRI as it’s more commonly known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SBRI already provides funding of up to £1.5 million a year on Phase 1 - the innovation, or new ideas stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m pleased to be able to confirm that the SBRI will also now be providing additional funding to the CDE at the Phase 2 level. This funding will be up to a maximum of £2 million a year, to be used to  progress successful projects which show the most potential for Defence purposes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sum will complement MOD funding, and expands the work Defence can gain from our Science and Technology Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also enables the Technology Strategy Board to support more technology SMEs at vital times in their development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of Government departments working together for the good of UK business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And delivering innovation for our Armed Forces. And I’m very grateful to the TSB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be exploring with my BIS colleagues how the good ideas brought to CDE that don’t neatly suit defence and security demands but have clear potential elsewhere in government or industry can be encouraged into reality too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cde-providing-greater-visibility-of-activity---and-contracts"&gt;CDE providing greater visibility of activity - and contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke earlier about visibility as a founding principle of the CDE when it came to the MOD providing clarity of our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry across the board - Primes and SMEs - have now told us that they would welcome much more visibility as to who has been awarded which contract by CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have also requested more advance notice of CDE plans to issue themed calls so that they are able to plan ahead and be prepared. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies and organisations have told us this is important because it will allow all sectors to start scoping opportunities at an early stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s what we’re going to do. CDE tell me that from today they will publish and maintain on their website their programme of events with a minimum 6 month horizon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from the autumn details of contract awards will also be accessible from the CDE website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this addresses the entirely reasonable concerns of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE started off as pilot scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years on it’s a going concern - and about to enter an exciting new phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is a direct reflection of Defence as a vibrant sector here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a nation with the fourth largest defence budget in the world. And we’re the second largest Defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of sales and 22% of the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts, as they say, speak for themselves. Defence is most definitely a sector of opportunity. And especially innovative smaller businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18759</id>
    <published>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-21-franco-british-council-2012-defence-conference"/>
    <title>2012/03/21 - Franco-British Council 2012 Defence Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je vous remercie pour l’opportunite d’assister a cette reunion du Conseil et d’avoir l’occasion de vous presenter une ou deux de mes pensees a propos de la cooperation franco-britannique dans le domaine de la defense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je suis toujours enchantes de visiter Paris et je suis particulierement content d’etre ici dans un contexte pareil; le succes de notre cooperation en Libye, le succes du Sommet le mois dernier, l’arrive d’un nouveau Ambassadeur et surtout l’approfondissement rapide de la cooperation entre nos armees et dans le domaine des equipements depuis la signature du Traite en 2010 [deux mille dix].  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to be here in the year that the Franco-British Council celebrates its 40th Anniversary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an organisation which has grown in influence and stature over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a well established reputation for exploring the issues of the day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to see that Defence is recognised as an integral part of this ongoing dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I see you also have your own web page on the Franco-British Council site - [www.francobritishdefence.org] which acts as a really useful information hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to thank the President D’Honneur, Madame Chairman and Council Members for their work in supporting - and promoting - this defence relationship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must also thank our Ambassador, (H.M. Ambassador Peter Ricketts) for so kindly hosting our conference. Given his previous role as our National Security Advisor, I am confident that deepening of our Franco-British Defence relationship will be a priority for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france---the-importance-of-our-defence-relationship"&gt;UK-France - the importance of our Defence relationship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is central to the values the UK and France share. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about our Defence relationship, and why it is important to seize this historic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About why it is important to drive forward this process of collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how we are doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me start with looking at why co-operation makes sense for lots of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Excellency Bernard Emie, in a recent speech to the British defence community cited Professor Robert Tombs - the noted Cambridge academic - who I think summed it up pretty well. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Franco British relations over the two centuries since Waterloo could be seen as a transformation from enmity to alliance and finally partnership…Today they are the only European states that maintain ambitions for a world role. Conceivably, both might prefer other partners, but in the world of the 2010s the reality is that we have only each other’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This eloquently defines the strategic necessity for our  bilateral relationship.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A partnership which makes sense because: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are both outward-looking nations, with experience and knowledge of almost every-part of the globe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We recognise we live a dangerous and uncertain world in which taking shelter behind some mythical Fortress Europe just isn’t an option&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We both understand the importance of a strong defence - not only to ensure that our territory is secure - but to contribute to international security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We invest in Defence and meet our NATO responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have battle winning capabilities and highly trained and effective Armed Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And crucially - we share the political will to act - and have the deployable defence capabilities to do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone who doubted that by the way only has to look at Libya. President Sarkozy was absolutely right when he described the UK and France as the ‘heavy lifters’ of European defence  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We share the same responsibilities on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As permanent members of the UN Security Council - as nuclear powers -as leading members of the G8, the EU and NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a similar world view, we share the same geographic space, we are of similar size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With us there is no grand frere et petit frere - although the way our respective media portray our relationship you would think we are more like quarrelling siblings..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, this is a collaboration of logic and sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forces that pull us together are far more powerful than the forces that seek to drive us apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="libya-and-nato"&gt;Libya and NATO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya was a real turning point and an affirmation that forging a new and stronger partnership was the right thing to do.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libya campaign was assisted by operating in a NATO framework.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO provided legitimacy, a Headquarters; as well as a common language and set of procedures.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is established, proven and based on shared values. It is a uniquely capable organisation as Libya - and indeed Afghanistan - have demonstrated.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need NATO to become stronger.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Libya showed us, there were a number of capability gaps which were highlighted by the Libya campaign.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We - the UK and France are now prioritising our joint work in light of lessons identified in areas such as Command and Control; Information Systems and targeting and reconnaissance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course across the Alliance it is ever more essential to ensure nations give priority those capabilities NATO needs. I commend the NATO Smart Defence Initiative. The UK is a keen supporter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="co-operation-in-austerity"&gt;Co-operation in Austerity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our economies and defence budgets are under pressure, the rationale for co-operation in these times of Defence austerity becomes ever stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense, for example, to develop our Combined Joint Expeditionary Force. We hope the CJEF will be up and running by 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French and British units and ships have been undertaking reciprocal training exercises as we continue to develop the new force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m told our forces - like the true professionals they are - operate very well together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there does appear to be some friendly rivalry over who has the best ration packs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, collaboration is an important principle of our approach to Defence equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an efficient way of delivering a balanced and affordable equipment programme. It means we can look to exploit economies of scale when it  comes to harmonising British and French requirements and sharing overhead costs.. It also helps to boost export opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows us to maximise our capabilities - particularly when it comes to sharing technologies, and it allows us to spread the cost - and the risk - of research and acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the case of the UK-France partnership all of these factors also support interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with France is not detrimental to our national sovereignty, provided that we retain operational advantage and freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our view is that it can help to consolidate our equipment programme and sustain aspects of our operational advantage and freedom of action.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we spend around 40% of the nation’s defence budget every year - a figure of around £13 billion - on equipment acquisition, support and technology.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By getting together we can make this money - and indeed both our budgets - go further.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do have the spending power - together the UK and France account for around 50% of European spending on defence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense for us to collaborate. Work together and plan together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we have to look ahead, horizon scan and develop capabilities to meet future challenges… &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why Research and Technology is an area where investment is absolutely key. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to an annual target of 50 million Euros each from the UK and France on joint research shows we’re serious about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular when it comes to critical technologies where the market, civil or defence, may not be sufficiently strong to meet UK and France defence needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be looking to industry to work with us on this - we need their expertise when it comes to identifying vulnerabilities. As well as spotting opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya and Afghanistan demonstrated the usefulness of Unmanned Air Systems, more commonly known as drones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month’s UK-France summit committed us to taking forward our planned cooperation on UAS.  In the longer term these will develop into unmanned combat air systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint funding and interdependence should help sustain industrial capability and deliver cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another programme is A400M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France is taking delivery of this transport aircraft in 2013 and we in the UK get ours in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a common support plan - including spare parts for our future fleets of these aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK-France project is a mature cooperation between democratic nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore we can be open about areas of disagreement and where we have different agendas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the UK has preferred to look to NATO first and then the EU, whereas France has leaned towards the EU. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were delighted when France rejoined the NATO military structures in 2009 and became a full player in that vital organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been significant convergence between our national positions over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the French preparatory work for their next Livre Blanc shows a balance between multi-lateral engagement with the EU and NATO, and bilateral engagement with key partners such as the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the publication of that document in the month after the elections will set the strategic direction for France on a whole range of issues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bigger challenge for European nations is not should our forces work under NATO or the EU but how do we maintain capable forces? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will no doubt be the subject of some lively debate for those taking part in this morning’s workshop .    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-it-work"&gt;Making it Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we have changed our institutional architecture to support the deepening of our bilateral relationship with France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our International Policy France team in the Ministry of Defence provides us with a central hub covering a range of activity - from equipment and procurement to political and military cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yesterday evening it was my pleasure to announce that the defence staff in our embassy here in Paris now have a new name: British Defence Staff-France.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a move which acknowledges the  increase in the Exchange and Liaison Footprint in France, as well as the Defence Section here in Paris. &lt;br&gt;
This is a highly symbolic move.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one other British Embassy across the world which has been accorded similar status, and that is our Defence presence in Washington - known as British Defence Staff - US.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new organisation recognises this change in dynamic and will be a ‘one shop’ stop, co-ordinating the expanding areas of activity and development across our partnership.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include taking forward our portfolio of co-operative equipment programmes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a significant move, and reflects the UK’s commitment to a partnership which is dynamic, and rapidly gathering pace.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill said that ‘difficulties mastered are opportunities won’.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that ethos is - I believe - what our defence relationship - is all about.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about working together on the challenges we face.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding and exploiting opportunities in more areas where we can work together in a smarter, more cost effective way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may always be differences in our styles or our methods.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is invariably true of any successful partnership.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These differences will often play to the particular strengths of each country. To the way we complement; balance and develop our defence capabilities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is going to be very important - and what I know we can achieve - is harmonisation of approach. Three areas in particular are vital to ensuring that we work successfully together over the longer term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political commitment: we will continue to signal the importance that both Governments attach to the defence relationship;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-operation between our Armed Forces; a combined Joint Expeditionary Force is a sign of progress but co-operation needs to be embedded throughout the two organisations and in military doctrine;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint investment in research and technology; this is essential in creating the future capabilities for fighting together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference is a really useful chance to stocktake, challenge some of our assumptions and assess progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I for one am looking forward to ‘having my feet held to the fire’ this morning when I chair the  workshop which I see has the  slightly ominous title of ‘Franco-British Defence Co-operation: the balance sheet’.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. And now, the floor is yours - any questions?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/3594</id>
    <published>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-21-franco-british-council-2012-defence-conference--2"/>
    <title>2012/03/21 - Franco-British Council 2012 Defence Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je vous remercie pour l’opportunité d’assister a cette réunion du Conseil et d’avoir l’occasion de vous présenter une ou deux de mes pensées a propos de la coopération franco-britannique dans le domaine de la défense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je suis toujours enchanté de visiter Paris et je suis particulièrement content d’être ici dans un contexte pareil; le succès de notre coopération en Libye, le succès du Sommet le mois dernier, l’arrivé d’un nouveau Ambassadeur et surtout l’approfondissement rapide de la coopération entre nos armées et dans le domaine des équipements depuis la signature du Traite en 2010 [deux mille dix].   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to be here in the year that the Franco-British Council celebrates its 40th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an organisation which has grown in influence and stature over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a well established reputation for exploring the issues of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to see that defence is recognised as an integral part of this ongoing dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I see you also have your own web page on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.francobritishcouncil.org.uk/" title="Franco-British Council"&gt;Franco-British Council&lt;/a&gt; site which acts as a really useful information hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to thank the President D’Honneur, Madame Chairman and Council Members for their work in supporting, and promoting, this defence relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must also thank our Ambassador, (H.M. Ambassador Peter Ricketts), for so kindly hosting our conference. Given his previous role as our National Security Advisor, I am confident that deepening of our Franco-British defence relationship will be a priority for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france---the-importance-of-our-defence-relationship"&gt;UK-France - the importance of our defence relationship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is central to the values the UK and France share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about our defence relationship, and why it is important to seize this historic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About why it is important to drive forward this process of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how we are doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me start with looking at why co-operation makes sense for lots of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Excellency Bernard Emie, in a recent speech to the British defence community cited Professor Robert Tombs, the noted Cambridge academic, who I think summed it up pretty well. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Franco British relations over the two centuries since Waterloo could be seen as a transformation from enmity to alliance and finally partnership… Today they are the only European states that maintain ambitions for a world role. Conceivably, both might prefer other partners, but in the world of the 2010s the reality is that we have only each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This eloquently defines the strategic necessity for our  bilateral relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A partnership which makes sense because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we are both outward-looking nations, with experience and knowledge of almost every-part of the globe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we recognise we live a dangerous and uncertain world in which taking shelter behind some mythical Fortress Europe just isn’t an option&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we both understand the importance of a strong defence, not only to ensure that our territory is secure, but to contribute to international security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we invest in defence and meet our Nato responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have battle winning capabilities and highly trained and effective armed forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and crucially, we share the political will to act and have the deployable defence capabilities to do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anyone who doubted that by the way only has to look at Libya; President Sarkozy was absolutely right when he described the UK and France as the ‘heavy lifters’ of European defence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We share the same responsibilities on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As permanent members of the UN Security Council, as nuclear powers, as leading members of the G8, the EU and Nato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a similar world view, we share the same geographic space, we are of similar size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With us there is no grand frère et petit frère - although the way our respective media portray our relationship you would think we are more like quarrelling siblings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, this is a collaboration of logic and sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forces that pull us together are far more powerful than the forces that seek to drive us apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="libya-and-nato"&gt;Libya and Nato&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya was a real turning point and an affirmation that forging a new and stronger partnership was the right thing to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libya campaign was assisted by operating in a Nato framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nato provided legitimacy, a headquarters; as well as a common language and set of procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is established, proven and based on shared values. It is a uniquely capable organisation as Libya, and indeed Afghanistan, have demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need Nato to become stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Libya showed us, there were a number of capability gaps which were highlighted by the Libya campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the UK and France are now prioritising our joint work in light of lessons identified in areas such as command and control; information systems and targeting and reconnaissance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course across the Alliance it is ever more essential to ensure nations give priority those capabilities Nato needs. I commend the Nato Smart Defence Initiative. The UK is a keen supporter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="co-operation-in-austerity"&gt;Co-operation in austerity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our economies and defence budgets are under pressure, the rationale for co-operation in these times of defence austerity becomes ever stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense, for example, to develop our Combined Joint Expeditionary Force (&lt;abbr title="Combined Joint Expeditionary Force"&gt;CJEF&lt;/abbr&gt;). We hope the &lt;abbr title="Combined Joint Expeditionary Force"&gt;CJEF&lt;/abbr&gt; will be up and running by 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French and British units and ships have been undertaking reciprocal training exercises as we continue to develop the new force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m told our forces, like the true professionals they are, operate very well together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there does appear to be some friendly rivalry over who has the best ration packs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, collaboration is an important principle of our approach to defence equipment and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an efficient way of delivering a balanced and affordable equipment programme. It means we can look to exploit economies of scale when it comes to harmonising British and French requirements and sharing overhead costs. It also helps to boost export opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows us to maximise our capabilities, particularly when it comes to sharing technologies, and it allows us to spread the cost, and the risk, of research and acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the case of the UK-France partnership all of these factors also support interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with France is not detrimental to our national sovereignty, provided that we retain operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our view is that it can help to consolidate our equipment programme and sustain aspects of our operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we spend around 40% of the nation’s defence budget every year, a figure of around £13 billion, on equipment acquisition, support and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By getting together we can make this money, and indeed both our budgets, go further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do have the spending power, together the UK and France account for around 50% of European spending on defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense for us to collaborate. Work together and plan together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we have to look ahead, horizon scan and develop capabilities to meet future challenges…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why research and technology is an area where investment is absolutely key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to an annual target of 50 million Euros each from the UK and France on joint research shows we’re serious about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular when it comes to critical technologies where the market, civil or defence, may not be sufficiently strong to meet UK and France defence needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be looking to industry to work with us on this; we need their expertise when it comes to identifying vulnerabilities. As well as spotting opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya and Afghanistan demonstrated the usefulness of unmanned air systems (&lt;abbr title="Unmanned air systems"&gt;UAS&lt;/abbr&gt;), more commonly known as drones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month’s UK-France summit committed us to taking forward our planned cooperation on &lt;abbr title="Unmanned air systems"&gt;UAS&lt;/abbr&gt;.  In the longer term these will develop into unmanned combat air systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint funding and interdependence should help sustain industrial capability and deliver cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another programme is A400M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France is taking delivery of this transport aircraft in 2013 and we in the UK get ours in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a common support plan, including spare parts for our future fleets of these aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK-France project is a mature cooperation between democratic nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore we can be open about areas of disagreement and where we have different agendas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the UK has preferred to look to Nato first and then the EU, whereas France has leaned towards the EU. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were delighted when France rejoined the Nato military structures in 2009 and became a full player in that vital organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been significant convergence between our national positions over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the French preparatory work for their next Livre Blanc shows a balance between multi-lateral engagement with the EU and Nato, and bilateral engagement with key partners such as the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the publication of that document in the month after the elections will set the strategic direction for France on a whole range of issues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bigger challenge for European nations is not should our forces work under Nato or the EU but how do we maintain capable forces? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will no doubt be the subject of some lively debate for those taking part in this morning’s workshop.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-it-work"&gt;Making it work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we have changed our institutional architecture to support the deepening of our bilateral relationship with France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our International Policy France team in the Ministry of Defence provides us with a central hub covering a range of activity, from equipment and procurement to political and military cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yesterday evening it was my pleasure to announce that the defence staff in our embassy here in Paris now have a new name: British Defence Staff - France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a move which acknowledges the increase in the Exchange and Liaison Footprint in France, as well as the Defence Section here in Paris.
This is a highly symbolic move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one other British Embassy across the world which has been accorded similar status, and that is our defence presence in Washington, known as British Defence Staff - US.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new organisation recognises this change in dynamic and will be a ‘one stop’ shop, co-ordinating the expanding areas of activity and development across our partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include taking forward our portfolio of co-operative equipment programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a significant move, and reflects the UK’s commitment to a partnership which is dynamic, and rapidly gathering pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill said that ‘difficulties mastered are opportunities won’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that ethos is, I believe, what our defence relationship is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about working together on the challenges we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding and exploiting opportunities in more areas where we can work together in a smarter, more cost effective way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may always be differences in our styles or our methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is invariably true of any successful partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These differences will often play to the particular strengths of each country. To the way we complement; balance and develop our defence capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is going to be very important, and what I know we can achieve, is harmonisation of approach. Three areas in particular are vital to ensuring that we work successfully together over the longer term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;political commitment: we will continue to signal the importance that both governments attach to the defence relationship&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;co-operation between our armed forces; a combined Joint Expeditionary Force is a sign of progress but co-operation needs to be embedded throughout the two organisations and in military doctrine&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;joint investment in research and technology; this is essential in creating the future capabilities for fighting together&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conference is a really useful chance to stocktake, challenge some of our assumptions and assess progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I for one am looking forward to ‘having my feet held to the fire’ this morning when I chair the workshop which I see has the slightly ominous title of ‘Franco-British defence co-operation: the balance sheet’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. And now, the floor is yours; any questions?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18758</id>
    <published>2012-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-16-a-uk-france-vision-of-the-future-of-the-european-aerospace-industry"/>
    <title>2012/03/16 - A UK-France Vision Of The Future of The European Aerospace Industry</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon messieurs et dames, ladies and gentlemen, and thank you [Laurent Collet-Billon] for that kind introduction.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit to Bordeaux this week has been a great chance to catch up with friends and colleagues.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am especially pleased to see some familiar faces here - and some new ones - from industry especially from this side of the Channel. Some of you may well have attended the Anglo-French Industry day last July.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together - at every level, Ministers, Chiefs, Officials and industry - means we are developing a very real understanding at every level.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An understanding of our mutual priorities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as a commitment to continue to explore areas of potential collaboration.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we spend around 40% of our Defence budget every year, or around £13 billion, on equipment acquisition, support and technology.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with industry is at the heart of our defence posture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s High Level Working Group was an opportunity to review our progress on the growing number of areas in which we are now collaborating.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portfolio of Franco-British programmes sets out to deliver a wide range of capabilities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some extent we are drawing on each others strengths. And aiming to avoid duplicating capabilities where we don’t need to.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treaty also makes clear the need to improve access to each other’s markets, and to explore new opportunities to become available to both sets of industries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week has also provided a welcome opportunity to visit an area which is home to a world leading aviation sector.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There really is no substitute for getting out on site and visiting industry at work. When Napoleon said we were a nation of shopkeepers, perhaps he was referring to the industry shop floor.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My trips to EADS, Thales and Dassault Aviation yesterday afternoon were fascinating. This has proved to be a highly informative, productive and enjoyable visit on a number of levels.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hosts have also very kindly given me the opportunity to learn about Bordeaux’s other world famous - and rather more historic -industry. I am of course referring here to your fabulous wine.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france-defence-co-operation-treaty---and-why-it-matters"&gt;UK-France Defence Co-operation Treaty - and why it matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have been reminded - as I so often am these days - that we are natural partners, who share similar aspirations and budgets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk to you briefly about this Defence Partnership. About why it matters, and about what it means for your sector - Aerospace.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, last year’s operations in Libya really did show once and for all that when it comes to Defence the UK and France are - in the words of President Sarkozy - the ‘heavy lifters’ of Europe.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operation Unified Protector showed the world that we have assets we can - and will - deploy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do that, I believe, because we share the same values and global interests.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the same responsibilities. As members of the UN Security Council. And as leaders in the EU and NATO.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to our financial commitment to Defence, I believe the facts speak for themselves.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together France and the UK account for nearly half of Europe’s Defence spending.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-operation means we can make this money go a lot further. It means boosting capabilities. Ensuring interoperability, and working to each others strengths and sustaining world leading defence industries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we can look to exploit economies of scale by buying or developing equipment with France. Or sharing facilities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are opportunities that we must continue to explore.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these tough times, as our Defence Secretary recently said, there can be no security without economic stability.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us in the UK co-operation also means saving money for our hard pressed tax payers as we work hard  to make sure our Defence equipment programme is affordable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="this-weeks-ndi-conference---uk-france-treaty-sme-opportunities"&gt;This week’s NDI Conference - UK-France Treaty: SME opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And co-operation brings opportunities for those of you here from industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of you here today are from SMEs. Welcome to you all. You are a sector we in the UK are very keen to encourage.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to open up Defence as a market and make the MOD a more accessible customer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I attended the annual conference of the NDI -one of the UK’s leading Defence  industry organisations, with a membership of over 200 companies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to see that an important part of the conference was dedicated to discussing opportunities for Small and medium sized enterprises - known as SMEs - offered by the UK-France Defence Co-operation Treaty. You are businesses which we in the UK are keen to encourage.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly pleased to see that the French Ambassador to the UK spoke at the conference with passion and persuasiveness, of the importance of Franco-British cooperation, and the fact that the relationship will endure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this kind of initiative. Enhanced Franco-British cooperation offers just as great opportunities for SMEs -  particularly on the supply chain side - as it does for primes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because SMEs bring innovation and agility.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in the UK have seen that special added value when it comes to getting urgent operational requirements out to our Forces on the front line in Afghanistan.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs have played - and continue to play - an important role in this.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uas---unmanned-air-systems"&gt;UAS - Unmanned Air Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And SMEs are of course essential to making sure we continue to push forward the boundaries in a sector like aerospace. Where the ability to exploit new and emerging technologies will be absolutely vital.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential here is - I believe - hugely exciting.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unmanned Air Systems are now an absolutely crucial asset. Both in today’s  battle space. And as a vital capability for the future.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know this from our operations in Afghanistan.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again of course Libya was another example.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month’s UK-France Summit committed us to taking forward our planned co-operation on UAS within a long term partnership framework  that encompasses the different levels.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From tactical to Medium Altitude Long Endurance  - MALE - in the mid term. And Unmanned combat Air systems in the longer term.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint funding and interdependence should help sustain industrial capability and deliver cost savings. Work is proceeding at pace and industry input will be important.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On MALE we now have a joint office in Bristol and our next step will be to advance the jointly funded risk reduction studies for the MALE. We will look to take further decisions after the outcomes of the study.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say a word here about Watchkeeper.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome French interest in acquiring this Unmanned Aerial capability, and we are looking at opportunities to organise trials in France next year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both sides agree there is a lot of mutual benefit to be had when it comes to co-operating on this system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch this space, as they say.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="unmanned-combat-air-system"&gt;Unmanned Combat Air System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next couple of years are going to be very busy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will be a period of vital importance - I believe - when it comes to shaping the future of European Combat Air.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead to when Rafale and Typhoon come out of service in the 2030+ timeframe, both the  UK and France will have a requirement to examine the options for the next generation of Combat Air Systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong correlation has been found between UK and French needs and aspirations in the combat air sector.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common vision on the “Combat Air” sector has been shared -  and is being developed - between Governments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should ensure that we have the necessary skills and technological capbilities to take development forward of this complex military air system.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year we intend  the UK and France to undertake a joint Future Combat Air System Demonstration Programme.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pending national approvals and decisions points on both sides, we’ll be starting work as soon as possible on a specification for this demonstration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a jointly funded contract under the industrial leadership of our national fighter aircraft industries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will need both an investment in the right technologies - and of course the skills required.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, those of you here today from industry have an important stake in this. Opportunities for business will exist across the supply chain and we will be looking to you for your support.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-weapons"&gt;Complex weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now developing a 10 year strategic plan for the British and Fench Complex Weapons industries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim on this is to benefit from our common position on this sector when it comes to budgets, as well as similar military and industrial requirements.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joint strategy will help us to consolidate our Complex Weapons industrial base.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as  help both countries to offer competitive products on the global market which will be essential to sustain a thriving industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this strategy forward will require a process of transformation across the industry as a whole in both countries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MBDA is providing the industry lead for the sector through what is known as the Centre of Excellence model.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a400m-transport-aircraft"&gt;A400M transport aircraft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support and training are areas where collaboration can bring us tangible benefits.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at a project like the A400M transport aircraft, which is a great example.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial deliveries to France are expected in early 2013, with the first UK delivery due in September 2014.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a common support plan - including for spare parts - for our future fleets of these transport aircraft.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An integrated support contract will be negotiated with Airbus Military before the arrival of the first French operational aircraft next year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also have a joint user group when it comes to co-operation on training.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-research--technology"&gt;The importance of Research &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already talked today about innovation as the key driver to developing the high-tech, battle winning solutions UK and French Forces will need in the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of solutions which could well be deployed when our Combined Joint Expeditionary Force - and deployable Joint Force Headquarters - becomes operational in just a few years time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why Research and Technology is an area where - as far as I am concerned - it is imperative that we continue to invest.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to an annual target of 50 million Euros each from the UK and France on collaborative research and development shows we are serious about this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative research of course also means that we need our top brains working together. I’m confident our new joint PHD programme will be a catalyst for this.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s essential that the UK start defining priority areas for this  research. And of course industry has an active and important role to play in this.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need you to be working with us. In identifying the gaps. Spotting the opportunities and coming up with solutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take an area such as Critical Technologies where commercial off the shelf technologies may not be sufficient to meet UK and France Defence needs.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why are already working on a joint plan to identify the key technologies both countries will need over the next 12 to 15 years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is of course advancing all the time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have to do - Government, the military and industry - is to make sure we’re thinking creatively.  Again, this is something SMEs excel at. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no time to lose on this. We may not know what the future holds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do know it will remain uncertain.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be prepared.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic Defence Co-operation Treaty laid strong foundations for two great nations to work together in an area which is so important to the safety and security of us and future generations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now embarked on a wide range of ambitious programmes which - I believe - will ensure we are ready and able for the challenges of the 21st century.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will of course be looking to you - industry - to deliver. I know we can count on your energy and support in making this happen.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/3589</id>
    <published>2012-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-16-a-uk-france-vision-of-the-future-of-the-european-aerospace-industry--2"/>
    <title>2012/03/16 - A UK-France vision of the future of the European aerospace industry</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon messieurs et dames, ladies and gentlemen, and thank you [Laurent Collet-Billon] for that kind introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit to Bordeaux this week has been a great chance to catch up with friends and colleagues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am especially pleased to see some familiar faces here, and some new ones, from industry especially from this side of the Channel. Some of you may well have attended the Anglo-French industry day last July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together, at every level, ministers, chiefs, officials and industry, means we are developing a very real understanding at every level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An understanding of our mutual priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as a commitment to continue to explore areas of potential collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we spend around 40% of our defence budget every year, or around £13 billion, on equipment acquisition, support and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with industry is at the heart of our defence posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s High Level Working Group was an opportunity to review our progress on the growing number of areas in which we are now collaborating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portfolio of Franco-British programmes sets out to deliver a wide range of capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some extent we are drawing on each others strengths. And aiming to avoid duplicating capabilities where we don’t need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treaty also makes clear the need to improve access to each other’s markets, and to explore new opportunities to become available to both sets of industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week has also provided a welcome opportunity to visit an area which is home to a world leading aviation sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There really is no substitute for getting out on site and visiting industry at work. When Napoleon said we were a nation of shopkeepers, perhaps he was referring to the industry shop floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My trips to &lt;abbr title="European Aeronautic Defence and Space"&gt;EADS&lt;/abbr&gt; [European Aeronautic Defence and Space], Thales and Dassault Aviation yesterday afternoon were fascinating. This has proved to be a highly informative, productive and enjoyable visit on a number of levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hosts have also very kindly given me the opportunity to learn about Bordeaux’s other world famous,  and rather more historic, industry. I am of course referring here to your fabulous wine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france-defence-co-operation-treaty-and-why-it-matters"&gt;UK-France defence co-operation treaty and why it matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have been reminded, as I so often am these days, that we are natural partners, who share similar aspirations and budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk to you briefly about this defence partnership. About why it matters, and about what it means for your sector, aerospace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, last year’s operations in Libya really did show once and for all that when it comes to defence the UK and France are, in the words of President Sarkozy, the ‘heavy lifters’ of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operation Unified Protector showed the world that we have assets we can, and will, deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do that, I believe, because we share the same values and global interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the same responsibilities. As members of the UN Security Council. And as leaders in the EU and Nato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to our financial commitment to defence, I believe the facts speak for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together France and the UK account for nearly half of Europe’s defence spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-operation means we can make this money go a lot further. It means boosting capabilities. Ensuring interoperability, and working to each others strengths and sustaining world leading defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we can look to exploit economies of scale by buying or developing equipment with France. Or sharing facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are opportunities that we must continue to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these tough times, as our Defence Secretary recently said, there can be no security without economic stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us in the UK co-operation also means saving money for our hard pressed tax payers as we work hard  to make sure our defence equipment programme is affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="this-weeks-ndi-conference---uk-france-treaty-sme-small-and-medium-enterprises-opportunities"&gt;This week’s &lt;abbr title="Northern Defence Industries"&gt;NDI&lt;/abbr&gt; conference - UK-France treaty: &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; [Small and medium enterprises] opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And co-operation brings opportunities for those of you here from industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of you here today are from &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. Welcome to you all. You are a sector we in the UK are very keen to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to open up defence as a market and make the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; [Ministry of Defence] a more accessible customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I attended the annual conference of the &lt;abbr title="Northern Defence Industries"&gt;NDI&lt;/abbr&gt; [Northern Defence Industries], one of the UK’s leading Defence  industry organisations, with a membership of over 200 companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to see that an important part of the conference was dedicated to discussing opportunities for small and medium sized enterprises, known as &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, offered by the UK-France defence co-operation treaty. You are businesses which we in the UK are keen to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly pleased to see that the French Ambassador to the UK spoke at the conference with passion and persuasiveness, of the importance of Franco-British cooperation, and the fact that the relationship will endure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this kind of initiative. Enhanced Franco-British cooperation offers just as great opportunities for &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, particularly on the supply chain side, as it does for primes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; bring innovation and agility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in the UK have seen that special added value when it comes to getting urgent operational requirements out to our forces on the front line in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; have played, and continue to play, an important role in this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uas-unmanned-air-systems"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Unmanned Air Systems"&gt;UAS&lt;/abbr&gt;: Unmanned air systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; are of course essential to making sure we continue to push forward the boundaries in a sector like aerospace. Where the ability to exploit new and emerging technologies will be absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential here is, I believe, hugely exciting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unmanned air systems are now an absolutely crucial asset. Both in today’s  battle space and as a vital capability for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know this from our operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again of course Libya was another example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month’s UK-France summit committed us to taking forward our planned co-operation on &lt;abbr title="Unmanned Air Systems"&gt;UAS&lt;/abbr&gt; within a long term partnership framework that encompasses the different levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From tactical to ‘Medium altitude long endurance’ (&lt;abbr title="Medium altitude long endurance"&gt;MALE&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the mid term. And unmanned combat air systems in the longer term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint funding and interdependence should help sustain industrial capability and deliver cost savings. Work is proceeding at pace and industry input will be important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;abbr title="Medium altitude long endurance"&gt;MALE&lt;/abbr&gt; we now have a joint office in Bristol and our next step will be to advance the jointly funded risk reduction studies for the &lt;abbr title="Medium altitude long endurance"&gt;MALE&lt;/abbr&gt;. We will look to take further decisions after the outcomes of the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say a word here about Watchkeeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome French interest in acquiring this unmanned aerial capability, and we are looking at opportunities to organise trials in France next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both sides agree there is a lot of mutual benefit to be had when it comes to co-operating on this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch this space, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="unmanned-combat-air-system"&gt;Unmanned combat air system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next couple of years are going to be very busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will be a period of vital importance, I believe, when it comes to shaping the future of European combat air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead to when Rafale and Typhoon come out of service in the 2030+ timeframe, both the  UK and France will have a requirement to examine the options for the next generation of combat air systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong correlation has been found between UK and French needs and aspirations in the combat air sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common vision on the ‘Combat Air’ sector has been shared, and is being developed, between governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should ensure that we have the necessary skills and technological capbilities to take development forward of this complex military air system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year we intend  the UK and France to undertake a joint ‘Future combat air system demonstration programme’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pending national approvals and decisions points on both sides, we’ll be starting work as soon as possible on a specification for this demonstration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a jointly funded contract under the industrial leadership of our national fighter aircraft industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will need both an investment in the right technologies and of course the skills required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, those of you here today from industry have an important stake in this. Opportunities for business will exist across the supply chain and we will be looking to you for your support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-weapons"&gt;Complex weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now developing a 10 year strategic plan for the British and French complex weapons industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim on this is to benefit from our common position on this sector when it comes to budgets, as well as similar military and industrial requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joint strategy will help us to consolidate our complex weapons industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as  help both countries to offer competitive products on the global market which will be essential to sustain a thriving industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this strategy forward will require a process of transformation across the industry as a whole in both countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Matra BAE Dynamics Alenia"&gt;MBDA&lt;/abbr&gt; [Matra BAE Dynamics Alenia] is providing the industry lead for the sector through what is known as the ‘Centre of Excellence’ model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a400m-transport-aircraft"&gt;A400M transport aircraft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support and training are areas where collaboration can bring us tangible benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at a project like the A400M transport aircraft, which is a great example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial deliveries to France are expected in early 2013, with the first UK delivery due in September 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a common support plan, including for spare parts, for our future fleets of these transport aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An integrated support contract will be negotiated with Airbus Military before the arrival of the first French operational aircraft next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also have a joint user group when it comes to co-operation on training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-research--technology"&gt;The importance of ‘Research &amp;amp; technology’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already talked today about innovation as the key driver to developing the high-tech, battle winning solutions UK and French Forces will need in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of solutions which could well be deployed when our Combined Joint Expeditionary Force, and deployable Joint Force Headquarters, becomes operational in just a few years time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why ‘Research and technology’ is an area where, as far as I am concerned, it is imperative that we continue to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to an annual target of 50 million Euros each from the UK and France on collaborative research and development shows we are serious about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative research of course also means that we need our top brains working together. I’m confident our new joint PhD programme will be a catalyst for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s essential that the UK start defining priority areas for this  research. And of course industry has an active and important role to play in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need you to be working with us. In identifying the gaps. Spotting the opportunities and coming up with solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take an area such as critical technologies where commercial off the shelf technologies may not be sufficient to meet UK and France defence needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why are already working on a joint plan to identify the key technologies both countries will need over the next 12 to 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is of course advancing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have to do, government, the military and industry, is to make sure we’re thinking creatively.  Again, this is something &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; excel at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no time to lose on this. We may not know what the future holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do know it will remain uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic defence co-operation treaty laid strong foundations for two great nations to work together in an area which is so important to the safety and security of us and future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now embarked on a wide range of ambitious programmes which, I believe, will ensure we are ready and able for the challenges of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will of course be looking to you, industry, to deliver. I know we can count on your energy and support in making this happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18757</id>
    <published>2012-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-14-building-for-growth"/>
    <title>2012/03/14 - Building for Growth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning. I’m delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to David Bowles as NDI’s outgoing Chair. It’s been a pleasure working with you over the last couple of years David. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to your vision and leadership the NDI is a flourishing organisation with a growing membership and a great deal of influence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And welcome to your new Chairman, Mike Maiden. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike, I’ve got to know you in your capacity as Deputy, and also through your contribution to my Defence Supplier Forum SME Group. I’m delighted you’ll be taking up the reins. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your expertise and insights are always tremendously useful. NDI members and Defence have a busy agenda ahead. I for one am looking forward to some very interesting times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="work-of-cde"&gt;Work of CDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Jonathan [Jonathan Byrne - Head of CDE - providing the opening address] for such a fascinating insight into the work of CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work you’re doing - in reaching out to SMEs, entrepreneurs and the academic world - is playing a vital role in helping to promote innovation and widen our supplier base. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very keen for CDE to have a more prominent role when it comes to sourcing cutting edge solutions to some of the emerging challenges facing our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re looking at ways to make the organisation still more effective in its important work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very fitting that this conference is taking place during our national Science and Engineering Week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper we published last month emphasised the contribution - no, actually that’s too weak a word - the fundamental place that technology has in providing our defence and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations like CDE and DSTL - our Defence Science and Technology Laboratory - are playing a vital role in promoting the contribution science and engineering make to Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed industry across the board is too, in particular when it comes to SMEs. More and more the technology we need is being developed outside defence - by people like you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to understand it, and how to use it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we - the MOD - have to facilitate this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means getting to grips with some of our procurement processes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making them more transparent, consistent and streamlined will help. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We really need to get cracking on cutting through a lot of the red tape enveloping a large organisation like the MOD. And we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be talking later about how measures outlined in our White Paper ‘Defence Through Technology’ will be overcoming some of these obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="role-of-the-ndi"&gt;Role of the NDI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that Lockheed Martin and HITEK among others have chosen to sponsor this important event. The NDI is an organisation with clout - and certainly from my point of view as a Defence Minister you are important stakeholders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NDI is - I believe - a really good example of an energetic and proactive industry hub supporting its members with a range of consultancy and project management interventions designed to create business opportunities. Now that sounds like a direct lift from the NDI website, but it is one I am happy to reiterate!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does a superb job in representing its members and championing Defence and its interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NDI works with the Primes, and brings the major players and smaller companies together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, it gives those of you here from SMEs a voice and a platform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NDI members I meet tell me that what they really appreciate is the fact that this is an organisation which is membership focused at grass roots level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you keep your members in touch with a dynamic and evolving market. Whether it’s spreading the word about new and emerging opportunities, or developments in a particular sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course organising major events such as this year’s conference which brings together a range of industry sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad your theme is ‘Building for Growth’, which could be adopted as something of a motto for the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased that speakers have been focusing in a very specific way on business opportunities. Because from our point of view I can tell you that the opportunities are there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not think so if you read some of the ill-informed comment in the national media, but Defence is big business. And will remain so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still in the process of reviewing our equipment programme, but we plan to continue to invest a significant amount in defence equipment and its support. This will be a figure of some £150 billion or more over the next decade.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful organisations like NDI will adapt and change. I know, for example, that you’re now focusing on Aerospace, Space and Security markets. But Defence remains the cornerstone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I welcome the fact that the NDI is also keen to explore opportunities through the implementation of the Franco-British Treaty. I know that you heard something similar from the French Ambassador yesterday and I naturally endorse this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="franco---british-treaty-opportunities-and-smes"&gt;Franco - British Treaty: Opportunities and SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to see that the NDI is taking a lead on this, by devoting an important part of this year’s conference to industry’s perspective on the business opportunities offered by the Treaty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I particularly commend the way the NDI is actively building links with an organisation like Team Cote D’Azure. And for the more cynical among you, I am assured by NDI and my own officials that the defence industries are very strong in this agreeable part of France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Steve McCarthy, our Director General for International Security Policy at the Ministry of Defence, spoke to you about our relationship with France yesterday afternoon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greater Franco-British cooperation should open up great opportunities for SMEs as it does for primes. The recent Summit highlighted many areas.  Over time I expect SMEs to do particularly well from our increasingly deep collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, a tremendous amount has already happened over the past year in our Defence partnership with France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s been particularly striking is just what a turning point Libya was for us - the UK and France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of further consolidating existing links between us. And also in the way we’ve been able to identify the sort of areas where we should now be prioritising our joint work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In key areas like command and control; information systems; intelligence; surveillance; targeting; as well as reconnaissance and precision munitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, there’s now a lot of work going on between us across just about every area of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research and Technology is a good example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later today I’ll be heading over to Paris and on to Bordeaux -  another area of France perhaps better known for something other than its strong defence industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There the High Level Working Group will be briefed by industry on Critical Technologies, such as Radar Absorbent Material, Optronics and technologies used in manufacturing radars. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a number of French SMEs attending the conference in Bordeaux, and it’s going to be extremely useful to hear their views on how we here in the UK can take forward industry’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France and the UK continue to account for nearly half of Europe’s Defence spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-operation on equipment makes compelling  sense for both countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main reasons for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - It allows both of us - the UK and France - to maximise our already considerable purchasing power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - it enhances interoperability.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - Bilateral collaboration is an important principle of today’s UK Defence equipment programme. It helps to sustain a strong industrial base. And underpins both British and French security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course that opens up more opportunities for you on both sides of the Channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I particularly welcome NDI’s initiative in dedicating an important part of this event to exploring opportunities for SMEs in the UK and France to work together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-white-paper---the-offer-for-smes"&gt;Defence White Paper - the offer for SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to extend a special welcome to SME who has joined us from France today.  This event is a great chance to network with a range of decision makers spanning commercial; operational and technical fields across industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s global market place SMEs are the life blood of any successful industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is definitely true when it comes to the Defence industry. As the success of our Urgent Operational Requirements  process demonstrates time and again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have been making a vital contribution when it comes to getting battle winning capability out to the front line in Afghanistan to meet the evolving threats our forces have faced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you’re able to be this responsive - I believe - because you have the innovation and the agility. You’re able to exploit new and emerging technologies which create solutions - very often in niche capabilities - and, crucially, are cost effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs have a vital role to play in making sure our Forces have the best kit and the best support. At the right price for the British tax payer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk about why you matter to the MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why our recent MOD White Paper ‘Defence Through Technology’ commits us to a range of measures which are aimed at opening up more of our business to you. And making us a more accessible customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically four strands to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - building on the work already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, for example, the MOD changed its policy to minimise the use of Pre-Qualification Questionnaires for low risk procurements under £100,000. A significant sum for many SMEs if not for the MOD itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department also now uses the Government’s Contract Finder portal to advertise requirements over £10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - Successful implementation of the new measures we have signed up to in the White Paper itself. With a view to making the whole application process for smaller contractors more streamlined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to help you develop new products, and make sure you get the expert advice you need to help you export.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways we’ll be doing this. For example, we will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adopting an Open Procurement approach by ensuring individual procurement strategies maximise the potential for you at prime and sub-contract level. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making sure there’s an emphasis on ‘open systems’ factored in to our requirements. So that there’s scope for you to offer the kind of modular systems which enhance major weapons and platforms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expanding our e-procurement system to speed up invoicing and billing. I know this is of particular benefit as far as SMEs are concerned. Cash flow is a critical factor for SMEs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third - We - the MOD - have to ensure these changes become part of the department’s DNA. This is as much about cultural change as changing rules and regulations. I am glad that NDI has already made some very good suggestions in this regard and I am grateful for this support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the fourth - and final strand - of this activity is doing what we can to energise the Primes into becoming part of this drive.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, we are making progress. I wonder how many of you here today from the SME sector are aware of just how much MOD business comes your way? In fact, you’re currently winning 42% of MOD’s equipment contracts. In financial terms that’s around £1 billion of new business a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many more of you are contributing to Defence and Security programmes as subcontractors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know however that for many SMEs out there - and this is certainly something we’ve been hearing from the NDI - Defence appears to be a complex and bureaucratic customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was definitely reflected in the feedback we had during our extensive consultations in the lead up to the White Paper. I believe the final paper reflects this, but you must let me know if not.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-white-paper---open-procurement-approach"&gt;Defence White Paper - Open Procurement approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open procurement means that wherever possible we’ll be seeking to fulfil Defence requirements through open competition in the domestic and global market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent awarding of the MARS contract - the construction of four new ships for the Royal Navy - to Daewoo Shipbuilding and Marine Engineering (DSME) in South Korea is tangible evidence of this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although a number of British companies took part in the international competition - which was quite rightly initiated by the previous Government - none of them submitted a final bid for the build contract.  Of course I would have preferred it if there had been a competitive British bid. But there wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of this, we decided that the best option for Defence, and value for money for taxpayers, is for the tankers to be constructed in South Korea by DSME. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just note by the way that there will also be up to £150 million of associated contracts for the MARS project. And again there have been opportunities here for SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open procurement also means buying off the shelf if that represents best value-for-money, as it often will. There is no reason why a competitive British defence industry shouldn’t win that business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will be pragmatic. We have to protect our national security. And that is why the  White Paper also sets out our approach to maintaining the UK’s operational advantages and freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boosting our exports is another principle of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence exports give us leverage and influence - and enhance interoperability with the Armed Forces of close partners such as France and the US. And indeed NATO and beyond. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times of austerity, exports may also have the benefit of reducing the cost of long term programmes, and removing some of the associated risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why exportability will be integral to our future equipment programmes. I’m confident this will help companies reach new markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Defence is a vibrant sector here in the UK. In fact, we’re the second largest Defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of sales and a 22% share of the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m equally confident you’ll be able to win business here and overseas on your own merits. Indeed, building an open and competitive UK Defence sector is the best guarantee of the industry’s future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the EU single market increasingly extends to Defence and Security under the new procurement directive, the competitiveness and technological excellence of our industry in the UK, and SMEs in particular, will be a real strength for the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a key part of what I see as a real industrial policy for defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is also about cultural change. Changes in MOD processes and the way we do business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why the Defence Equipment and Support organisation is also under review.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence transformation also means taking a long hard look at our processes, and the way we do business. It means upping our game when it comes to having the right skills in areas like financial and project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means change for DE&amp;amp;S and the way it operates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Materiel Strategy, as it is called, is being taken forward by Major General Chris Deverell on behalf of Bernard Gray, the Chief of Defence Materiel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five options have been considered as part of the Materiel Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we have pretty well already ruled out the status quo. And we will not be going down the privatisation route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves three options. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option one: DE&amp;amp;S becomes a Government-owned, Contractor-operated set up - a GoCo - along the lines of the Atomic Weapons Establishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option two: is for an Executive non-departmental public body with a Strategic Partner, similar to the Olympic Delivery Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, Option three: it becomes a trading fund along the lines of DSTL, the UK’s Defence Science and Technology Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the final decision, the review will need to factor in the need to improve skills and processes. And, crucially, ensure a more disciplined relationship between DE&amp;amp;S and MOD customers, including Front Line Commands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re determined to make some pretty bold decisions. And we’ll be as radical as we need to be - no more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is ongoing work, but there will be changes ahead. The MOD must - and will - become a more intelligent and demanding customer. This will be good for your competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-white-paper---a-commitment-to-st"&gt;Defence White Paper - a commitment to S&amp;amp;T&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked at some length about our approach to our equipment programme, and the principles we’ll be guided by as we work to ensure a balanced and affordable equipment programme in the years ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to make clear is that technology and innovation are absolutely central to this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something I feel pretty passionate about. It’s staggering to think that under the last Government, the Science and Technology budget more than halved between 1997 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was short sighted in the extreme. I’m determined that this process of decline must be stopped.  And it has been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proportion of spending on Science and Technology is now baselined at its current level of 1.2% of the overall Defence budget. This firm intent is clearly set out in our White Paper. And it’s another key component of an effective approach towards the Defence and Security industries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sum is currently over £400 million a year. I’m hoping - not committing - that it will be possible for this figure to grow as a result of a well planned and sensibly managed equipment programme. Some of this will be from collaboration with our French colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sme-forum"&gt;SME Forum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is a high-level guide which provides direction. For us in Defence, and you in industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also a living document and we remain open to further measures and improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly when  it comes to SMEs. Which is why I’ve established a dedicated SME Forum to address your concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the NDI, membership also includes ADS; the Federation of Small Businesses; Engineering Employers Federation and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally chair these meetings. I find them a really valuable way of getting together with key representatives from industry to tackle some of the current issues and challenges we all face. And its not just trade bodies, but real SMEs also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SME Forum took part in the extensive consultation process which informed the White Paper. I’d like to take this opportunity to thank SME Forum members for their important contribution to that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad the White Paper was well received by industry, and I am grateful for that intelligent response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly delighted that the paper is acting as a catalyst for action by industry itself, led by bodies such as NDI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference has focused on building for the future. Looking ahead, making plans, building capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a future which looks increasingly unknowable. Where all sorts of eventualities will have to  be considered and planned for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where there will be new and emerging challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of which - and I’m thinking here of areas like Cyber, and Space - will also present opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am quite certain about, however, is that strong and effective partnerships - between us in the MOD and you in industry - will be vital when it comes to safeguarding our future and making sure our forces have battle winning capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fourth largest Defence budget in the world behind us I know we can - and will - continue to deliver on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for all that you have done and will continue to do in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18755</id>
    <published>2012-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-02-21-international-armoured-vehicles-conference"/>
    <title>2012/02/21 - International Armoured Vehicles Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen. Good morning. I’m delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a major event in the industry calendar, and an important forum for sharing knowledge and expertise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that for many of you here today this conference is also an opportunity to explore some of the common challenges we all face. As we seek to secure and fund the best defence solutions for our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the great work being done by ‘Help for Heroes’ - as we just heard - brings that effort into sharp focus. And I endorse everything that Mark just said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a reminder that our servicemen and women often carry out their duties at great personal risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that when they are placed in harm’s way their lives will depend on the protection of the vehicles that we provide. And which are manufactured by those of you in industry here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course that goes for all our equipment on the front line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a great story in the news last week about Lance Corporal Denis Larubi, from 2nd Battalion The Mercian Regiment, or as I still think of them, the Worcestershire and Sherwood Foresters. In  a period of just 48 hours he was twice shot at by insurgents while on sentry duty at  a check point in Helmand.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun newspaper reported that the on the first day a shot struck ballistic glass in the guard tower right in front of his face, but could not penetrate the toughened window.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the next day - when he was shot at again - the bullet hit the shoulder of his body armour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Corporal emerged unscathed from both incidents. His verdict on two lucky escapes - and I quote - was pretty succinct. “Thank God for decent equipment” he said.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of testimony I often hear on my visits to theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know - as your commitment demonstrates - just how aware industry are of this responsibility.  I also know that for many it is a very personal effort and commitment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Minister responsible for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology I share that sense of responsibility and commitment. Supporting our people with the very best protection and battle winning capabilities is the essence of my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And looking ahead, our people on the ground will continue to need high tech, cutting edge armoured vehicles. It is an enduring requirement. What will change, however, is the way we acquire them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about these changes. About this new approach to the way we’ll be procuring these vehicles and other military equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our recent  White Paper ‘Defence through Technology’ sets this out. I’ll be talking about the implications - and opportunities - for industry a little later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper has been launched during a period of tremendous change as we work to shape our military effort in the coming decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change which will also have ramifications for our relationship with you, our industry partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by talking about some of these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the change taking place in the Ministry of Defence as the Department of State which supports and equips our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And also throughout our Armed Forces which are also undergoing transformation through the Defence Reform Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start briefly with the Armed Forces, and the Army in particular. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is currently reviewing its structure as it seeks to evolve into a yet more integrated force, making greater use of Reservists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An agile force with the right capabilities.  A robust contingent capability.  A capacity for major combat operations.  Together with an ability, for example, to contribute to overseas capacity building and security sector reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change is already underway.  Crucially, the Chief of the General Staff is gaining more autonomy when it comes to the allocation of resources and generating capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demands, in turn, a new relationship with our Defence, Equipment and Support organisation. Or DE&amp;amp;S as it is more commonly known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Joint Forces Command has also been set up as part of this process of reform.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will improve the planning and execution of joint operations. Managing and delivering joint capabilities will be an important part of this.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means key joint enablers, like intelligence, cyber and training, will have a stronger voice than ever before.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Chief Marshall Sir Stuart Peach took up his post as the first Commander of Joint Forces Command in December. The JFC Initial Operating Capability - with a Command HQ - will begin at the start of April. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing more about this work on Future Force 2020 from the Chief of the General Staff himself in his closing address tomorrow afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now a word about some of the reforms taking place at the Ministry of Defence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will underpin the structural changes across the military. And, it’s probably fair to say, change the way we work with industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of acquisition this means the MOD becoming a more intelligent and demanding customer. An end to what’s been referred to as a ‘conspiracy of optimism’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we have to be more disciplined when it comes to costing programmes before we are committed to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as making sure you - industry - deliver. To order, on time, and within budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence transformation also means taking a long hard look at our processes, and the way we do business. It means upping our game when it comes to having the right skills in areas like financial and project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means change for DE&amp;amp;S and the way it operates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Materiel Strategy, as it is called, is being taken forward by Major General Chris Deverell on behalf of Bernard Gray, the Chief of Defence Materiel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Deverell will be telling you more about it later today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five options have been considered. However, we have pretty well already ruled out the status quo. And we will not be going down the privatisation route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves three options. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option one: DE&amp;amp;S becomes a Government-owned, Contractor-operated set up - a GoCo - along the lines of the Atomic Weapons Establishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option two is for an Executive non-departmental public body with a Strategic Partner, similar to the Olympic Delivery Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, Option three; it becomes a trading fund along the lines of DSTL, the UK’s Defence Science and Technology Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the final decision, the review will need to factor in the need to improve skills and processes. And ensure a more disciplined relationship between DE&amp;amp;S and MOD customers, including Front Line Commands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re determined to make some pretty bold decisions. And we’ll be as radical as we need to be - no more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked a lot today about the need for change. And this is where the White Paper comes in. It sets out how this change will be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets out our approach to purchasing equipment, support and technology.  An approach which I am confident will also drive forward a new culture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An approach which I believe will be good for British industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to our support of technology; for SMEs and for exports. A commitment to open procurement. And clear direction on where we stand when it comes to ensuring we have operational advantage. And maintaining freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that a number of you in industry have welcomed the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Thales, for example.  They have said, and I quote: ‘We …welcome the clarity that the White Paper brings, and support the use of ‘Off the Shelf acquisition’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took some time to finalise the White Paper as you will know - we wanted to make sure we had consulted widely across all our stakeholders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADS - one of our leading trade associations representing the industry - have acknowledged the value of this process of deliberation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their view, this had in fact - and I quote again - ‘allowed for meaningful dialogue’ and resulted in ‘deeper understanding of industries’ concerns within Government.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper gives direction on our policies and priorities. And it puts technology and innovation back as the main driver of our equipment programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may have inherited an equipment programme in freefall and a gaping deficit exceeding £38 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can categorically state here and now that spending on a vital area like Technology and Science will no longer be the first target when it comes to cutting costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder how many of you are aware that one of the last acts of the previous Government was to remove a further £100 million from the Science and Technology programme? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the S&amp;amp;T budget more than halved as a proportion of the MOD’s total budget between 1997 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have drawn a line in the sand on this. The proportion of spending on S&amp;amp;T is to be baselined at its current level of 1.2% of the overall Defence budget - currently a sum of over £400m a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope it will be possible for this figure to grow as a result of a well planned and sensibly managed overall equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policy of open procurement commits us to actively seeking out what the global market has to offer our forces in terms of cutting edge, high quality kit. At the right price for the British taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever possible, we’ll be looking to meet our Defence requirements through open competition in both the domestic and global market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the strength of British industry means our companies should not fear this competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the five year period between 2006 - 2011 the MOD awarded nearly 40,000 new contracts with an approximate total value of just over £67 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And out of that figure, the number of new contracts placed where the majority of work occurred within the UK remained consistent at around 85% - 95%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If British industry is as competitive as I believe it to be and its export record suggests, then I see no reason why these figures needs to decline significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, in reality the policy on open procurement under EU competition rules haven’t changed that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If necessary though, we will protect those areas where the UK either needs advanced technology. Or particular products to maintain our operational advantage or freedom of action. Particularly during operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will help sustain the necessary skills, infrastructure and intellectual property we need to allow us to build and safeguard our national security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This open procurement approach is particularly good news for those of you here today from SMEs - that is Small and Medium Sized Enterprises, rather than Subject Matter Experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to say this approach is already working. Tarian Quickshield is a great example of new battle winning capability developed in partnership with an SME. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case DSTL worked with AMSAFE in Bridport to develop a new form of RPG netting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incredibly light, it’s been described as ‘band aid’ for bar armour, but it actually does the job more effectively and at less cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s already in service with the Army in Afghanistan. And Singapore Technologies Kinetics have signed a memorandum of Understanding with AMSAFE so that it is available to the customers of their armoured vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of innovative technology which I am sure will do well in the export market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to make sure the MOD is more accessible.  The new SME Forum which I chair is a realisation of that pledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also do this by ensuring individual procurement strategies maximise the potential for SMEs - and I commend those exhibiting here today - at prime and sub contract level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ll be making sure there’s an emphasis on ‘open systems’ factored in to our requirements. So there’s scope for you to offer the kind of ‘add on’ systems which enhance major weapons and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010 - 2011 the MOD placed 42% of its contracts with SMEs - that is, direct contracts. You offer innovation and flexibility. We’re keen to do a lot more business with you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to see more of the bigger names harnessing this potential. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some are already seizing the initiative. Take General Dynamics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I visited their site in South Wales which has a dedicated technical facility known as The Edge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Edge searches out new ideas from across the supply chain and academia. And it also works with organisations such as the MOD sponsored Centre for Defence Enterprise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t about duplication of effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about partnership working which means that across the board we are all maximising our Research and Technology spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have already indicated, boosting our export market is another principle of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence exports leverage influence with our allies - and boost interoperability with their Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in these straitened times, exports can also reduce the cost of long term programmes and remove some of the associated risks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exportability will therefore be integral to our future equipment requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m confident this is the kind of measure which will help companies reach new markets. And again I’m thinking here of the potential of a capability like Tarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is already the second largest Defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of sales and a 22% share of the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with this drive to boost the chances of UK industry abroad, we will also be continuing to develop the collaboration and partnership we have with close allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allies  such as the US and France. And allies in NATO, and indeed beyond. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with other countries offers significant economies of scale which enable us to spread the cost and the risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m confident that effective collaboration will enhance our status as a global partner of choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, we’re still reviewing our equipment programme. But we are close to a conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can confirm however that across the board we will be investing more than £150 billion in military equipment over the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year Philip Hammond, the new Secretary of State, announced a £1 billion upgrade to the Infantry’s Warrior fighting vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the intention to proceed with a separate £400m package of protected vehicles and Counter IED technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A package which will include an additional 100 Foxhound Light Protected Vehicles. A vehicle with great export potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department plans to spend £5.5 billion on its core armoured vehicle programme over the next decade. And we’re reviewing just how we’ll achieve this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will involve managing the legacy of Afghanistan as we draw down our operations there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making some decisions about which Urgent Operational Requirement vehicles - over 2,000 of them approved at a cost of £2.8 billion - will now be brought into the MOD’s core equipment programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the success of our UOR process pretty much encapsulates our new approach when it comes to off the shelf purchase and innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vehicles based on the US Cougar fleet and the Bronco from Singapore were purchased as off the shelf base vehicles and then adapted here in the UK - often by SMEs. And then shipped out to Afghanistan as new battle winning capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process of high tech adaptation and integration calls for cutting edge skills in the UK. These are exactly the kind of projects which will help to develop and sustain our skills base here in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The servicemen and women I’ve met on my visits to theatre speak very highly of the agility and protection provided by these vehicles which they know by their new, adoptive names. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Names like Mastiff; Ridgback; Wolfhound and Warthog which have now entered the military vernacular. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pragmatic and innovative approach is definitely the way forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to more simplified and realistic acquisition strategies across our equipment programme, and particularly when it comes to Armoured Vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce cost. Mitigate risks. And to make sure that adaptability is factored in from the outset, as opposed to rigid over specification at the drawing board stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I have already said, there are no hard and fast rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will not be prescriptive when it comes to making sure we have the best solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Foxhound is a UK design and 90% of the companies involved in its production are UK based. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In common with all recent UORs, it exploits state of the art technology. In this case, that includes the UK’s world-leading motorsport industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an amazingly agile piece of kit, with an engine which can be removed and replaced in just 30 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an ideal vehicle for our Partnering and Mentoring role we’ll be taking on as the process of transition gathers pace in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound is on schedule to be operating in Afghanistan this summer. The soldiers I have spoken to are genuinely excited by the prospect of its arrival. And they should be. I have driven it. I know just how good it is. And just how easy it is to drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the size of our future vehicle fleet, the decisions we make will need to make sure our forces are ready and prepared. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a dangerous world, and the future remains uncertain. Our people must be properly equipped and well supported if they are to meet these emerging challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the bottom line is that we will retain the capability to project power abroad and meet our NATO obligations. And we’ll do that supported by the world’s fourth largest Defence budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. I look forward to hearing your views on some of these and other issues. The floor is yours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
