<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/philip-dunne</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-dunne.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Philip Dunne MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28542</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-46-million-submarine-command-system-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £46 million submarine command system contract</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Design Services Arrangement contract will ensure that the system, which is used to navigate vessels as well as gather intelligence and defend against attacks, is maintained and developed over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy operates three classes of submarine, totalling 10 vessels, which are used to safeguard the UK’s interests around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, different combat systems are used across the fleet. This new contract will help drive adoption of a common combat system across all current and future Royal Navy submarines, with considerable benefits to training, maintenance and updating costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="John Hudson, Philip Dunne and Rear Admiral Simon Lister" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1364/20121206subs01_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;John Hudson, Managing Director of BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines, Philip Dunne, and Director Submarines Rear Admiral Simon Lister (library image) [Picture: Mike Vallance, BAE Systems]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s submarine fleet is second-to-none and plays a key role in protecting our waters and interests both at home and abroad. This latest commitment to maintain and develop this vital technology throughout the fleet will ensure that we can continue delivering first class capability for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Command Systems on board our submarines contain many vital technologies and it is very important that our submarines retain their technological edge, both now and in the future. This contract will help secure that position for the MOD and UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/our-company-rzz/our-businesses/maritime---submarines" title="BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines"&gt;BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines&lt;/a&gt; and will safeguard around a total of 30 jobs at the company’s sites in Ash Vale in Surrey and Weymouth in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17638</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-helps-small-firms-showcase-defence-innovation"/>
    <title>MOD helps small firms showcase defence innovation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organised by the Ministry of Defence’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.science.mod.uk/engagement/enterprise.aspx" title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;Centre for Defence Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;, the event gives small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a unique opportunity to engage with big business and offer up ideas and technology that could be used by the Armed Forces in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs were joined at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre in London by academics and researchers from two of the country’s leading universities - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/" title="University of Bristol"&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/" title="Lancaster University"&gt;Lancaster University&lt;/a&gt; - who also had products to pitch to industry representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies on show at the event were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbsr.co.uk/" title="Blue Bear Systems Research"&gt;Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s ‘Morphing Wing’ - based on the dynamics of a bird’s wing, this is designed to enable the next generation of unmanned aerial vehicles to be faster, more agile and have greater stability and duration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dreampact.com/" title="Dreampact Ltd"&gt;Dreampact Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s compact heat-sensing video camera - a handheld camera that can also be mounted on a rifle to allow more effective surveillance operations in pitch darkness, bad fog or dust.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1288/DSC_0837.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne speaks at the inaugural Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s ‘Marketplace’ provides a shop window for small and medium-sized enterprises in the most practical sense, helping those which have received research and development funding from the MOD to access their full potential for commercial applications in the UK defence sector and the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation is vital to our national security and the country’s economic growth. We remain committed to providing our Armed Forces with the very best equipment available, which is why we will continue to invest over £400m a year in Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jono Byrne, Head of the Centre for Defence Enterprise, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we have broken fresh ground in developing the Department’s engagement with small and medium-sized enterprises and academia. Over half of our contracts go to small and medium-sized enterprises and academia and it is vital that we are able to bring these Centre for Defence Enterprise-funded innovators, their ideas and capabilities, into the defence supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne chats with delegates" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1289/DSC_0941.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne chats with delegates at the Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted with the response and support we have had from prime contractors as they too understand the benefits such a concept can bring. This is only the start for the ‘Marketplace’ and, like all good innovation, I look forward to further improvement; for example, making use of online tools and involving investment companies as well as defence companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Kurth, Managing Director of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.boeing.co.uk/Products-Services/Boeing-Defence-UK" title="Boeing Defence UK"&gt;Boeing Defence UK&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to attend the inaugural ‘Marketplace’ event and look forward to seeing the areas of technology the Centre for Defence Enterprise has identified in support of our Armed Forces. We see the ‘Marketplace’ as a fantastic opportunity to engage with small and medium-sized enterprises that have relevant innovation and technology for potential work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise (CDE) is committed to finding new revolutionary ideas and working to make them a reality in the future. Since 2008 the CDE has received more than 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at over £35m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17595</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-contracts-safeguard-hundreds-of-uk-shipyard-jobs"/>
    <title>MOD contracts safeguard hundreds of UK shipyard jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contracts cover the long-term maintenance of the Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) Flotilla of naval support ships. They have been awarded to five British companies and will secure a further five years of maintenance support for the 13-strong RFA Flotilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of fuel tankers, stores ships, a medical facility and landing ships, the RFA provides essential support such as food, fuel, munitions and other vital supplies to the Royal Navy at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cammell-laird.com/" title="Cammell Laird website"&gt;Cammell Laird Shiprepairers &amp;amp; Shipbuilders Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Birkenhead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ap-group.co.uk/" title="A&amp;amp;P Group website"&gt;A&amp;amp;P Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt; (ship repair facility), based in Falmouth&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lr.org/default.aspx" title="Lloyd's Register website"&gt;Lloyd’s Register&lt;/a&gt;, based in Bristol&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.trimline.co.uk/" title="Trimline Ltd website"&gt;Trimline Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Southampton&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hempel.com/" title="Hempel UK Ltd website"&gt;Hempel UK Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Cwmbran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="United States warship alongside RFA Cardigan Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1283/FJ120053055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;United States warship USS Devastator (left) alongside the Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Cardigan Bay (library image) [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Simpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships are crucial to the work of the Royal Navy and without them it simply could not operate. These substantial contracts will not only safeguard hundreds of UK jobs but will ensure that these ships can continue in their roles for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Commercially Supported Shipping for Defence, Equipment and Support, Commodore (RFA) David Preston, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These contracts represent the best value for money for Defence and each of the companies has a proven track record in supporting the Royal Fleet Auxiliary on a worldwide basis. This ability to support the Royal Navy wherever they are deployed is critical to UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA personnel are uniformed civil servants employed under the UK Merchant Shipping Act. They are structurally aligned with the Royal Navy and have a high level of specialist military training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17580</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/25m-mod-weapons-contract-sustains-450-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£25m MOD weapons contract sustains 450 UK jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has agreed to purchase additional &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/paveway4.cfm" title="Paveway IV"&gt;Paveway IV&lt;/a&gt; bombs from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raytheon.co.uk/" title="Raytheon UK"&gt;Raytheon UK&lt;/a&gt;. These weapons are to be carried by our Tornados in Afghanistan and will also provide a key capability to be carried by the Typhoon and Lightning II aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract announced today will sustain around 450 jobs at Raytheon UK’s plants. It will secure 300 highly skilled defence sector jobs in Glenrothes, Scotland, and 150 in Harlow, Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also sustain a number of jobs at Raytheon’s subcontractors - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.portav.com/" title="Portsmouth Aviation"&gt;Portsmouth Aviation Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, Exelis in Brighton, Chemring in Ardeer and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thalesgroup.com/" title="Thales Group"&gt;Thales&lt;/a&gt; in Basingstoke, Hampshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paveway IV proved highly effective during the 2011 air campaign over Libya. Its global positioning system technology gives the UK the capability to conduct 24-hour precision attacks against a wide range of targets. Aircrew also have the ability to reprogramme the weapon during a mission, offering capability to attack a wider range of targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This highly sophisticated UK-developed and manufactured weapon is the backbone of the RAF’s precision bombing capability. This contract to boost the MOD’s weapon stocks will sustain hundreds of skilled jobs in the defence manufacturing sector in both Scotland and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By balancing the Defence Budget, we are able to commit with confidence to equipment programmes which help to safeguard our national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paveway munitions have long been a success story for the Royal Air Force in terms of their precision bombing capability. The ability to operate in any weather means that we are able to support operations 24/7. Paveway IV weapons are a real asset, not only to the Royal Air Force, but also to Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the MOD has this year awarded contracts worth more than £100m to Raytheon for orders of around 1,600 Paveway IV bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17808</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-12-03-centre-for-defence-enterprise-marketplace"/>
    <title>2012/12/03 - Centre for Defence Enterprise Marketplace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning to everyone, and thank you Richard [Brooks] for that kind introduction. I am very pleased that so many people have been able to make it here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an exciting moment for the Centre for Defence Enterprise (&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched by the previous Government in 2008 as a delivery mechanism for allowing better access for technology &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; (Small and Medium Enterprises) to defence research and ultimately the wider Defence Market, I see the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now as helping the Ministry of Defence achieve two principle goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;firstly to act as the entry point for new science and technology innovation bringing new thinking and ideas to Defence &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and secondly to act as a key bridge linking &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to the main defence suppliers, as well as investors and wider Government, as part of the MOD’s priority to raise participation by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in defence procurement &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; calls for, receives and assesses research proposals. It then funds, supports and promotes projects that it regards as plausible with potential to meet defence needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It encourages innovative companies to address Defence issues through face to face surgeries, unclassified and open conferences, and through its innovative electronic contracting portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this activity is run from a small base in a commercial office block at the Harwell Science and Innovation Campus in Oxfordshire. One of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strengths is its fleetness of foot, born of a lean and efficient structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To provide visibility of the MOD’s requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To inform and support new supply networks that widen the MOD’s supplier base &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And above all to get the best and most innovative ideas into MOD’s Science and Technology Programme &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks another important milestone of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. A new turn in &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s evolving journey to discover innovation, and then help in the realisation of those ideas into defence and security capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what innovation has been discovered. In the last four years the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has received nearly 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in some 600 contracts, worth around £35 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few projects have made it directly into the hands of users, but that is an exception for most research work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to see those &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities who have successfully demonstrated innovative technology, to have the chance to present their capabilities to our prime contractors - boosting their prospects of being taken into the supply chain. And that’s what today’s marketplace is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some amazing ideas and technologies which have been developed by the innovators we have funded. I hope you will be able to stay and hear the details today, some of which are also on view in the exhibition downstairs on the second floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="exhibition-examples"&gt;Exhibition Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward shortly to going round this exhibition, and to meeting the people who are working to deliver innovative battle winning capabilities which support the front line. And I encourage you all to look around if you have the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example, on display downstairs is Blue Bear Systems Research and their morphing wing for small Unmanned Air Vehicles based on the dynamics of a bird wing. This project exploits the design work already done by Mother Nature, to help ensure our next generation of UAVs can be both faster and more agile, as well as having greater endurance when required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the compact, high performance heat sensing video camera developed by Dreampact, which can be handheld or rifle mounted for surveillance or gunsight use in conditions of total darkness, fog, smoke or dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our universities are also represented today with ingenious electronics and autonomously learning logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the projects featured demonstrate the ingenuity and practical focus of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities that we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation to flourish is vital to our national security and our prosperity, contributing to export led recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wider-st-policy"&gt;Wider S&amp;amp;T Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my new role I have responsibility also for Defence exports as well as procurement, so encouraging responsible Defence exports is a particular priority for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is partly to stimulate this growth which is why the MOD has protected its annual investment in Science and Technology at 1.2% of the Defence Budget - over £400 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is protecting this budget so important? Well, in a future that is so unpredictable, defence science and technology provides insurance against the future threats and conflicts we may face; and supports the MOD’S ability to be an intelligent customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our defence transformation programme transfers responsibility for primary equipment procurement to the Commands, each will need to build capability to look forward to its future needs. This will better align our science and technology spend to the research and development priorities of our front line commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence is about developing Armed Forces and Defence capability that can deal with a broad range of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blueprint for agile, adaptable Armed Forces is Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be effective Future Force 2020 must have the best equipment available: class leading platforms, complex weapon systems and supporting ISTAR assets. Our personnel need the best training and personal equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector and our world class academic institutions will be central to deliver this Future Force. The complexity of much of these platforms needs, by necessity, substantial industrial capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cyber, to space, to nano technology, Britain has world leading companies underpinned by world leading scientific research, some of which I have already seen helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profitable and high tech British Defence and Security sector is essential to achieving all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although many of the platform projects will be managed through large system level contracts by our Prime contractors, there will be numerous participants in the supply chain, from large companies, to academia, to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="smes"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; make an enormous contribution to the economy and in particular to innovation. And I want to take a moment to emphasise their role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; are not the only source of original thinking in our sector, but they often provide the niche expertise which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know that The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in supporting &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in this area, helping them to commercialise their high tech ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank my predecessor, Peter Luff, who I am delighted to see is with us today. Peter did much to champion Science and Technology, the crucial role of Small and medium sized enterprises to delivering innovation, and to starting the conversation that led to this event today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, like him, am a champion of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; doing innovative work in the Defence and Security sector. They are the lifeblood of any sector. In defence they deliver innovation, flexibility, efficiency and agility, when responding to our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; - whose issues are often very different from those of Primes - have their own platform within the defence industry to engage with the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why I chair a dedicated &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Forum which addresses the concerns of smaller companies, and why the MOD is taking a significant number of steps, alongside wider Government to work to ensure &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; can reach their potential when responding to defence requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has a detailed action plan, led by our &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Champion, Les Mosco, who will be talking to you later today, to drive forward &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; involvement in defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have addressed some really important issues such as the treatment of IPR for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify issues that MoD needs to address and which the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; themselves need to think about too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are encouraging our prime contractors to inform us of the part &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; play in their own supply chain and I have personally invited the Chief Executives of our top twenty suppliers to attend today’s event - and I am particularly pleased to see some of them here today and I am grateful for the leadership they are showing at the senior level in support of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, even to a business as small as a one-man band, is to support, not stifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cde"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final word about &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. Since its launch the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has established a reputation for reaching out across a very wide spectrum of the engineering and scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has worked closely with the Technology Strategy Board and benefited through working with its Knowledge Transfer Networks and Small Business Research Initiative and I am glad to see that Mark Glover from TSB is here today to see the blossoming fruits of this collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But above all else, it is you, the defence and security community, that shaped the advances that we see within in the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; today. Thank you for your strong support of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; started off as pilot scheme. And four years on it has become a going concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But innovation never stops, there is always something new to try, something that can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now an exciting new phase has begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our White Paper ‘National Security through Technology’ committed Government to broaden &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s remit to cover both the defence and security domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 3rd October, here in this building, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; held its first event for GCHQ and MI5. This attracted over 300 &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and resulted in over 170 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘National Security through Technology’ also committed &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; to provide more support to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in understanding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how MOD and National Security operates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development of routes to market for potential defence and security products; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to enhance exploitation mechanisms between &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;, the wider MOD and our suppliers &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognising fears expressed by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in the consultation, we committed to keep &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; small and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am most grateful that Richard Brooks, the Programme Director for MOD’s Science and Technology Programme who is here organising this day, is ensuring that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; is not distracted or inhibited by bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst staff numbers have grown, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; remains small and agile with only 12 staff, yet now able to run more research calls, more seminars and more workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; can hold more regular surgeries - ‘one to ones’ - where individuals and companies can get personalised guidance on what the MoD is looking for, and practical help on how to pitch an idea to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set a target of 150 one-to-one appointments for this financial year. This figure will be passed before the end of this month and &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now expects to hold more than 200 such appointments by the end of the financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="marketplace"&gt;Marketplace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through our science and technology budget, we fund &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to work on specific projects for us. They keep the intellectual property rights for their work, and can develop them however they want, once they have completed their project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the effort so far has been focussed on the engagement of &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities and supporting the best ideas with proof of concept funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to help more - which brings us, finally, to today’s Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all this event is a start, and I look forward to seeing this idea develop and innovate rapidly like all the best &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for those of you, &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, universities and Prime Contractors, who have contributed already to the thinking of how today’s Marketplace will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim is an MOD-facilitated initiative whereby &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; gives &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities, who have successfully demonstrated their credibility and capability, the opportunity to present their innovations and capabilities to the UK’s key defence suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By providing this opportunity, the MOD is seeking to ensure that these &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; will have an increased probability of development funding and mentoring, so that they can fully develop their ideas into products suitable for the defence, security or other civilian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that the MOD does have an important role to play in helping to maintain a dynamic pool of innovation which can drive defence applications forward and lead to economic benefits for the whole nation, beyond the immediate Defence objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will only get this by leaving companies free to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And free to work together. So today is all about bringing people together. Then it is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to take a couple of questions before we move downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34762</id>
    <published>2012-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-37m-viking-regeneration--2"/>
    <title>Green light for £37m Viking regeneration</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Used extensively by the Royal Marines, the 99 Viking vehicles, which can be launched straight from the back of a ship and propelled through water before landing for a beach assault, are in line for a major overhaul by BAE Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were deployed to Afghanistan in 2006 for their versatility across tough terrains before they were later replaced by Warthog. Viking will now be fitted with new mine blast protection bodywork and brought back to their original amphibious standard, having been adapted for the rigours of land operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £37 million mid-life upgrade to the Viking fleet of amphibious vehicles will keep these highly capable vehicles in service with the Royal Marines into the 2030s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With a balanced defence budget, for the first time in a generation, we are able to deliver with confidence the equipment our Armed Forces require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Marines from the Armoured Support Group Yeovil 'test drive' a Viking amphibious all-terrain vehicle onto HMS Bulwark via the ship's well dock (library image)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1671/Green_light_for__37m_Viking_regeneration2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from the Armoured Support Group Yeovil 'test drive' a Viking amphibious all-terrain vehicle onto HMS Bulwark via the ship's well dock (library image) [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Martin Carney, Crown Copyright/MOD 2007]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commandant General Royal Marines, Major General Ed Davis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that the contract for the regeneration of our Viking amphibious vehicles has been announced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Viking is an essential asset for the Royal Marines in conducting short notice crisis response operations around the world and any modifications which enhances operational effectiveness and makes life that bit safer for our personnel is always welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 99 Viking vehicles, 19 are set to be fitted with top-mounted guns and nine more will allow the firing of an 81mm mortar from the vehicle. All will have improvements made to their braking and suspension systems. As well as new front and rear car hulls the Vikings will have the latest mine-protected v-shaped underbody which is designed to protect the occupants should it drive over an explosive device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regeneration programme is expected to be completed by the end of 2014 and will secure the vehicle’s service life until its expected out of service date of 2031.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35325</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-defender-moves-into-her-new-home"/>
    <title>HMS Defender moves into her new home</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship’s arrival at her new base brings Defender a step closer to her first deployment. She will now undergo sea trials before being declared ready for operations in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with the world-leading Sea Viper missile defence system, the 7,500-tonne vessel is able to defend against multiple attacks from even the most sophisticated anti-ship missiles, approaching from any direction and at supersonic speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Peter Luff, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This latest addition to our fleet of state-of-the-art destroyers marks the remarkable progress being made on the Type 45 programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Defender, together with her five sister vessels, will form a formidable fleet and ensure that the Royal Navy remains a powerful maritime force on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Defender passes between the harbour walls at Portsmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1678/HMS_Defender_moves_into_her_new_home2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Defender passes between the harbour walls at Portsmouth [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Claire Myers, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;HMS Defender is the fifth of six Type 45 warships built for the Royal Navy, and was launched at the BAE Systems’ Govan shipyard in Glasgow in October 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Type 45s will provide the backbone of the UK’s naval air defences for the next 30 years and beyond. The destroyers will be capable of carrying out a wide range of operations, including anti-piracy and anti-smuggling activities, and disaster relief work and surveillance operations, as well as high intensity war-fighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Ship Support (Alliance), Commodore John Newell, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Entry into HM Naval Base Portsmouth of this very powerful and advanced warship is not only a great day for the Royal Navy but also for the Destroyers Project Team and our industry partners who ensured this magnificent vessel was ship-shape and ready to be accepted from BAE Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Defender is a welcome addition to the fleet and, when she enters service, she will help ensure that the Royal Navy can react to any defence challenges anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final vessel in the Daring Class, Duncan, is due to undertake her first set of sea trials later this year, and is due to be accepted into service in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
