<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/philip-hammond</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-hammond.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Philip Hammond MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45359</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-21-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>2012/11/21 - Delivering Value for Money and Innovation in Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces exist to protect our country and provide the ultimate guarantee of its security and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be the first duty of Government, and everything we do in Defence is directed at supporting that objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating the military capability required to meet the needs of national security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And delivering that capability on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most fiendishly complex tasks of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the most expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With resources as tight as they are, the obligation to deliver value for money is paramount:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure every pound of taxpayers’ money spent on Defence has a tangible impact on delivering capability to the front-line and on the security of the nation;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, enhancing the efficiency of Defence delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today I want talk about how, over the last two and a half years, we have set about reforming the way Defence is managed to deliver that improved efficiency:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restructuring the MOD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Re-configuring our Armed Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balancing the budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting the equipment programme on a sustainable course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And because none of this would be possible without the people who make up Defence, I want to say a bit about how we will modernise the offer that we make to the men and women of our Armed Forces, so that their terms and conditions, while they will never look like those associated with civilian employment, better reflect lifestyles in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to start by re-capping the scale of the reform challenge we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review kick-started one of the biggest change programmes taking place anywhere in the Western world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change programme essential to ensuring that our Armed Forces can continue to defend our country, protect our interests and project our values abroad;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of a complex range of threats in a rapidly changing environment; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the powerful, adaptable and, crucially, sustainable Armed Forces we require;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipped with some of the best and most advanced technology in the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all at a cost that the country can afford and on a scale that we can sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this change programme isn’t just about meeting the Future Force 2020 structure set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also about changing the way we deliver Defence to make sure we don’t repeat the mistakes of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this Government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene’s Defence Reform Review set out clearly what the problems were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A focus on short-term affordability at the expense of long-term value for money and a lack of financial rigour throughout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Head Office, which was trying to micro-manage from the centre, disempowering the people who actually deliver in the Service Commands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confusion over who was accountable for what&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Few levers for those who wanted to innovate and change behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An over-complicated and fragmented structure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And an unbalanced relationship between the Department and its suppliers - with poorly aligned incentives driving sometimes perverse behaviours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting these problems resolved is every bit as important as eliminating the inherited black hole in the budget if we are to deliver sustainable, long-term change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will re-materialise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are getting on with implementing Lord Levene’s recommendations which we accepted in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the behaviours so that we do not repeat the same mistakes again;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focussing on long-term value, not short-term cash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering value for money by making sure we have modern, innovative ways of doing business;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where people accept responsibility for decisions and have the power to make them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing us to weed out duplication, red-tape, perverse incentives, waste and delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken as a whole, this is a 10 year reform plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, halfway through this Parliament, and half way between two SDSRs; a year and a half on from the Defence Reform Review; it is worth reflecting how far we have come already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the Department, many of the tough decisions on force structure had already been taken: to shrink the size of the MOD; to rationalize our equipment programme; and to reduce the size of the Navy, Army and the Air Force, while increasing investment in the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They just needed implementing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the senior management was beginning the process of changing the way Defence was managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make no apologies for the fact that I chose to focus on the money first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no option of continuing the ‘finger in the dam’ approach to Defence budgeting, which had resulted in the MOD lurching over a decade from budget crisis to budget crisis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salami-slicing each year in the hope that “something would turn up” to fund the programme in the next;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing projects further and further to the right in an unsustainable and ever-expanding bubble;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeting based on fantasy rather than reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ill-served the tax-payer, who ended up paying more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ill-served the Defence Industry, who found it impossible to invest with any certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it ill-served our Armed Forces, who could not plan with confidence politicians promised them would be delivered on time, to requirement and in the numbers expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have instituted an integrated financial and military capability planning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming prudently rather than optimistically, so that we can focus on value rather than on cash management; with a proper centrally held contingency reserve against the equipment programme, and (an innovation in MOD terms) an annual Departmental Unallocated Provision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving from a culture of spending first and working out how to afford the long-term costs later to one of only committing to what we can be confident that we can deliver;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living within our means, rather than systematically planning beyond them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our new cost controls in place, no project can be committed without a 10-year budget line to cover not only its procurement, but also its support costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we allocate projects to the committed core programme only at the point when they need to be committed in order to be delivered on time, and only in accordance with the military assessment of priority at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ending a long-established “conspiracy” between the industry and the Department to “lock in” unaffordable projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By maintaining these simple disciplines, sensibly managing in-year budgets, and forecasting prudently, we are changing the dynamic in the equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we still have to live with the legacy projects - against which we have now made prudent provision of financial contingency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will continue to have a negative effect on the Department’s public reputation for project management as their original fantasy budgets and timelines are exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can now make choices, based on military priorities, about which new capabilities we can afford, rather than which bits of the programme we have to cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by delivering this budgetary discipline we are already demonstrating the benefits to the Armed Forces and to Industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding projects when it is safe to do so, not cutting them because we have run out of cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I announced in May that we had achieved a balanced budget, I have been able to give the go ahead to some half a billion pounds of further investment in Equipment and Support, including targeting pods for fast jets, better protection systems for Tornado GR4, enhancements to MERLIN Helicopters and new FOXHOUND vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And further announcements are imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is, I am told by old lags in the Department, the first in living memory that the MOD has not had to sit down in September and decide which programmes need to be cut or delayed in order to remain within spending control targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major step forward for the MOD and for the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Reform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sustainability is considered in every decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building-in a focus on value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing structures and incentives to change behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging innovation to improve delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locking in the significant reductions in running costs we are achieving by making the organisation more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already on course to save approximately £2bn in non-frontline costs in the year 2014/15, compared to 2010/11 baseline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of this saving will be sustainable reductions, so we can expect to maintain high-levels of savings in following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a ten year period we expect to save around £15bn of non front line costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how"&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we are pushing authority and accountability down the chain of command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Top Level Budget holders the freedoms and incentives they need to drive efficiencies and improve delivery in their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head Office is becoming smaller, on course to shrink by 25% by 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly constituted Defence Board, which I chair, has been meeting regularly over the last year, providing strategic direction to the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delegated operating arrangements for Service Commands will go live in April 2013, including for the new Joint Forces Command which was stood up in April of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Service is doing detailed work on its own operating model, identifying which activities are to be modified or stopped, and where to prioritise resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the bottom line is that they will have much greater control over planning for future capability requirement;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding where to concentrate resources to provide maximum effect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking responsibility for living within the means provided, but with the freedom to innovate and establish better ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing we are doing is bringing in private sector skills where we judge it necessary to help change behaviours and drive efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Business Services has been set up in a partnership with SERCO, who are providing the external management team to transform the organisation into a lean and effective shared services centre, building on best practice outside the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Infrastructure Organisation brings together all aspects of Defence infrastructure asset management and facilities management under one organisation for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now in the process of recruiting a strategic partner to help transform its business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps most significantly, the work to overhaul procurement, the Materiel Strategy, is developing fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms of the acquisition process in the Defence Reform Review were anticipated by Bernard Gray’s report for the previous Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, Defence has lacked the right business skills and capabilities to manage what are some of the largest capital and infrastructure projects being undertaken in today the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the MOD has, too often, been a poor customer for industry - and in some cases, a soft touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are setting out to create a proper interface between the Defence Equipment &amp;amp; Support organisation and the Defence customers it serves enabling it in turn to be a more effective customer for its suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will require the recruitment of a private sector partner to deliver the high-level commercial and management skills that we currently lack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently testing the value for money case for a Government Owned, Contractor Operated - or GOCO - entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final decision on the precise structure will be made in due course, but the bottom line is that the reformed DE&amp;amp;S, supported by a strategic partner, will be better by design at negotiating and managing contracts for the benefit of the tax-payer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the private sector partner injecting key disciplines, processes, skills and management freedoms into MOD’s procurement activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By refocusing the Head Office to providing strategic direction rather than micro-management, by empowering the Service Commands and other parts of Defence to deliver and to innovate, and by bringing in private sector partners with the skills and flexibilities to help them, this programme will deliver behaviour change from the bottom up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people"&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive change agenda: In the Armed Forces, in the MOD and across the support organisations like DE&amp;amp;S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And change is often uncomfortable for the people at the heart of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me say unambiguously that our people in Defence are our biggest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces - Regular and Reserves; the civilians who support them; and the people who work in the industries which supply them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to rebuild the trust of all of them after a period of sometimes traumatic change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to say something this morning specifically about how we will address the challenges of recruiting and retaining for the Armed Forces once the lure of deployment on operations is gone as we withdraw from our combat role in Afghanistan by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, hopefully, against the challenge of a healthier civilian economy as a competitor for talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="service-personnel"&gt;Service Personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my big learning curves over the last year has been understanding the unique nature of what the military call the “moral component” of Defence; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that provides the “will to fight”, and the determination to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that allows us to recruit some of the best people the country can provide to preserve the unique attributes of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gives us our edge over other countries, many of whom have larger Armed Forces and similar equipment to us, but very, very few of which can come close to matching our military capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our people that give Britain’s Armed Forces their special quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that some of them feel, perhaps many of them feel, they have taken a bit of a pounding over the last couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redundancies; downsizing; re-structuring; relocation; re-roling for the post Afghanistan world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all while fighting a long and difficult counter-insurgency and stabilization campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must often have felt like the perfect storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future Armed Forces will continue to offer careers that are exciting, challenging and rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we want to continue to recruit and retain the best people, both Regulars and Reservists, that may not be enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service Personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-employment-model"&gt;New Employment Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in doing so, we need to achieve three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to secure for Defence the people it needs - both in terms of quality and quantity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recruiting to preserve the unique attributes of the Armed Forces by drawing adventurous, spirited and committed people to the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we need to reflect the changes in social, demographic and economic conditions in our society and the complexities of modern family life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no identikit Service career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a young recruit wants from the package may be very different from an NCO in his late 20s with a wife and small children - and we have to make sure that what we provide is an attractive offer for both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attractive to Service personnel and fair to the tax-payer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me be clear: this is not a cost cutting exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call this project “the New Employment Model”, or NEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about overnight transformation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to meet the expectations of a generation that has yet to join the Service, as well as our current Servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some elements are capable of being delivered relatively early while others will take longer to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more stability to service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="housing--spousal-employment"&gt;Housing &amp;amp; Spousal Employment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodation lies at the heart of this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of our Regular Service personnel rely on publically provided accommodation because the job currently demands a very high degree of mobility around the UK - and sometimes beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 22 year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want this to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enabling the children of Service personnel to be settled in one area and to avoid frequent changes of school;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making it easier for partners of Service personnel to find work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we do must of course be done in a way which continues to support operational capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our goal is to enable Service Personnel more freedom to make the choices that other people make:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About where to live;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about whether to rent or buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, home ownership rates among current and former members of the Armed Forces are comparatively low, suggesting an element of systematic disadvantage - something which the Armed Forces Covenant commits us to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, alongside a steady improvement in the quality of service accommodation, we want to increase access to home ownership for Service personnel, providing realistic lifestyle choices to our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways this could be achieved and we will look at developing a range of options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark fact is that people in the Armed Forces, with a generous, non-contributory pension scheme, are accumulating significant wealth during their service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a significant part of their total remuneration package cost that wealth creation but without them being able to access it to facilitate house purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that disadvantages them compared to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the challenge we have set ourselves is to explore models that would allow our people either to directly access some of that accumulating wealth or to use it to collateralise mortgage borrowing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting forces home ownership;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And removing an important element of disadvantage service people face relative to their civilian counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would not, of course, remove the need for Service accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially for younger, single service people, this will often be the right choice, or indeed, the only one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces will continue to provide subsidised accommodation for those who require it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whether you are in the Forces or in a civilian job, taking on the responsibility of homeownership these days often requires two reliable incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So making it easier for the partners of service people to find and keep work is a critical precondition to boosting home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making military basing more settled will be a big step forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also recognise that some bases, by necessity, are in relatively remote locations with limited employment opportunities for partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the areas I want to explore urgently in 2013 is how we could use parts of the military estate to stimulate local economic growth and employment generation around garrisons - by providing incentives for business relocation to land that we hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus creating conveniently located job opportunities for the Armed Forces community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a whole, the New Employment Model will include everything from the accommodation and home ownership issues which I have discussed today, to overall pay structure, training and education needs, career management and manpower control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NEM will support both Regular and Reserve personnel - and will build on the Whole Force concept and the integration of Regular and Reserves which I set out earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, we will begin consulting with Service personnel, and testing some of the ideas we are developing on the people they are designed to benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have set out this morning, the progress we have made on one of the most ambitious transformation programmes ever undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programme necessary to ensure that our Armed Forces are affordable and sustainable, as well as flexible and effective in the face of both fiscal challenges and strategic uncertainties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not undervalue what we have already achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have defined the new structure of our forces and the shape of the MOD that will support them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have developed our plan to bring the army home from Germany;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And an Equipment Programme which can be delivered and afforded;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms to maintain budget discipline are in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that is, relatively speaking, the easy bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that requires a motivated and engaged workforce;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that recognises the challenges we are facing;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shares our vision for the future of Defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understands the plan for delivering it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And feels a valued part of that plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of redundancy and pay restraint, that is a big challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the one we must now address;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through greater empowerment, both personal and professional;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through better delivery of value to the individual from the remuneration package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45365</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-08-future-reserves-2020"/>
    <title>2012/11/08 - Future Reserves 2020</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Michael [Michael Prescott, BT Director of Corporate Affairs], for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BT has been a prime mover in the Partnering for Talent initiative over the last 12 months and a proud track record of supporting the men and women who serve in our Armed Forces - both Regular and Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BT has recruited over 800 ex-service personnel in the last couple of years, and will be recruiting another 250 in the coming months - People who will serve the company well in the years to come, just as they have served the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of their induction, BT is actively supporting the maintenance of military links through service in the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is the Reserves that I’ve come here want to talk about today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I am publishing the MOD’s consultation on the future of the United Kingdom’s Reserve Forces, entitled ‘Future Reserves 2020: Delivering the Nation’s Security Together’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades, our Reserves have fought alongside their Regular colleagues, in the Balkans, in Iraq, in Afghanistan, taking the same risks, making the same sacrifice, decorated with the same honours and deserving the same recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like our Regular Forces, they have been stretched, but have risen to the challenges they have been set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time, the structure of our Reserve Forces has been allowed to wither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite six reviews since the Cold War, their true potential remains unrealised, particularly that of the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declining in number, starved of resources, with training cut, opportunities reduced, and morale suffering - they have had many years of a raw deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long, the Reserves have been the forgotten part of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today marks the beginning of a fresh start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fresh-start"&gt;Fresh Start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re setting out our commitment to a larger Reserve, both absolutely and as a proportion of overall service manpower;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better resourced, with an injection of £1.8bn over the next 10 years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means better equipped and better trained, using the same kit as their Regular counterparts and becoming the sole repository of some specialist skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, in the future they will be part of a fully integrated force of Regulars and Reserves, able to deploy as formed units and sub-units, as well as continuing to augment Regular forces as individual Reservists where required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes I am proposing today, amount to a paradigm shift in the role of Reservists’ in delivery of the nation’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shift which will see Reservists routinely sharing responsibility for activities once the exclusive domain of Regular Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this shift, wider society will need to play a larger part in the delivery of national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Security is everyone’s business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new relationship is required between the State and Armed Forces on the one hand and individual Reservists, their families and their employers on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exciting new proposition bringing with it new opportunities, and new challenges for Reservists, and for their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Reservist - more responsibility, bringing with it more support, more respect, and more reward;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the employer - an open relationship based on mutual benefit, better exploiting the skills and motivation Reservists offer as employees, with appropriate packages, for different types of employer, of accredited training, recognition and impact reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for employers, Reservists and their families alike, greater predictability of liability for call-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this Green Paper will affect all Services: the Maritime Reserve, the Royal Marine Reserve, the Royal Auxiliary Air Force, and the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will be most keenly felt by the Army, who, on the basis of the plans set out this year for Army 2020, will need to fully integrate their Reservists into the very fibre of the force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will concentrate most of my remarks today on the challenge facing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very nature of the TA’s new role will require a step change in organisation and approach to force generation, as well as in the relationship with employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change that, I believe, should be reflected in a change in name to ‘The Army Reserve’ - and that is one of over 30 propositions that we will be consulting on over the next two months as part of a process leading to a white paper published in the Spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I put some flesh on the bones of these proposals, let me set the transformation of our Future Reserves in the context of the wider changes taking place in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review called for redesign of our Forces to meet the new security challenges which will face them post-Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Future Force 2020, we are building an adaptable, integrated Whole Force fit for a more uncertain world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer focussed on the Cold War model of mass territorial defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor the predictable pattern of deployment to enduring operations in Iraq or Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But configured instead to project power and respond to a diverse set of contingencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile, high-tech, structured to allow rapid reaction and expeditionary warfare;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capable of conducting the full spectrum of operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to command as part of a coalition and more interoperable with our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller, but better equipped;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because now that we’ve a balanced budget, with a sustainable equipment programme, our Armed Forces can be confident that they will receive the cutting-edge equipment that has been promised as we build the formidable capability that Future Force 2020 represents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation is necessary to prepare our Armed Forces for the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to deal with the legacy of the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multi-billion pound black-hole in the Defence Budget that had to be filled, before we started to make a contribution to reducing the overall fiscal deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant some very tough decisions: relinquishing some capabilities, to invest in new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting smaller numbers, to ensure we can equip people properly for the job we ask them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-reserve-legacy"&gt;The Reserve Legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the SDSR implementation process, the Prime Minister set up an Independent Commission to provide an authoritative picture of the state of our Reserves and recommendations for optimising their use in the context of modern threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report they published in July last year makes for sobering reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They found that individual Reservists had made, and continue to make, an essential contribution to national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At their peak, Reservists made up 20% of our Forces in Iraq and 12% in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best trauma unit in the world - the Camp Bastion Hospital - has been staffed, on average, 40% by Reservists and has nearly 50 Reservist medics currently on its staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 25,000 Reservists have deployed on operations overseas in the last 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;29 have paid the ultimate price, with many more injured, sometimes seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, given that this is remembrance week, I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to all those who have sacrificed so much to preserve our national security and protect our national interests - serving and veteran; regular and reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the amazing efforts of individual Reservists to make a difference, and the hard work of many unsung Reserve Units up and down the country from all the services, the Commission found an organisation in institutional decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting smaller, getting older, less well trained, less motivated;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not matched to the new security environment - with major units of the TA still configured to provide mass reinforcements to counter the Soviet threat; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not able to be mobilised for routine deployments - with the legal position not supporting the use of Reserves for standing tasks;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not matched to the new configuration of the regular Armed Forces;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forming too small a part of our overall military capability, both in comparison to our closest allies of similar tradition - and indeed by our own historic standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even during the last decade of enduring operations, to which the TA made such a contribution, its nominal strength fell by almost a third with the Reserves Commission reporting some estimates of genuine trained strength as low as 14,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long, the Reserves were considered a soft target by the last administration as they desperately tried to find in-year savings measures to cover their failure to control the spiralling cost of the equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restrictions on live round firing;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of equipment curtailed;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, the then Government tried to cut the TA’s annual budget by 30% with a reduction in drill nights and weekend training, to balance the in-year budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of all of this has been Reserve Forces failing to realise their potential; failing to recruit to requirement, with a proposition that is simply not attracting enough potential Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A diminishing return on capability and a diminishing return to Defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So change is not just desirable, it is essential for the future of our Reserve Forces and the contribution they make to the Defence of our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that change is required not only in the organisation, structure and role of Reserve Forces - and how they are integrated with Regular Forces - but it is required in the proposition we make to Reservists and in the relationship we have with their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what will the Future Reserve of 2020 look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this mean for what we ask of our Reservists, their families and their employees?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is the fresh start we are proposing today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-reserves-2020"&gt;Future Reserves 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is fully committed to delivering the Reserve Forces the country needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investing an additional £1.8bn in the Reserves over the next 10 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support an increase in our Reserve Forces…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…to a trained strength in the Army Reserve of 30,000;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maritime Reserve of 3,100;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Royal Auxiliary Air Force of 1,800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in 20 years the planned trajectory is up, not down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the effect of this investment is already beginning to show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already reversed the decline in the Army Reserve in terms of recruitment and total strength - with enlistments this year 3% up against the rolling average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New training and new equipment is being rolled out progressively, with delivery of new uniforms, new vehicles and new radios, in line with those used by Regulars, already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening, I was at Fulham TA Centre visiting the Royal Yeomanry to see their new light reconnaissance vehicles and Bowman radios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more money, higher numbers and better equipment, however welcome, will not alone turn our Reserves into the efficient, effective, and deployable Force our national security requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Whole Force concept of full integration between Regular and Reserves will require us to redefine the role that Reserves will play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to restructure them to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Forces will continue to deliver specialist capabilities which cannot be cost-effectively held in Regular Forces, particularly in the medical field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we intend to extend the range of specialities, drawing on skills from the civilian workforce, such as intelligence, information technology and cyber. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also provide functions that do not require complex unit-level training to maintain readiness, such as some aspects of logistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reserves will fulfil a general role in homeland security, such as the support they provided to the Olympics, and to national resilience tasks, such as flood relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will provide, as they do now, vital support to short-term high impact operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will provide resilience to longer term stabilisation operations, like the Balkans and Afghanistan - providing a higher proportion of the committed force than is currently the case, increasing the longer the operation goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual Reservists will continue to be mobilised as augmentees for regular units as now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be deployed as formed units and sub units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Reserve Forces will be expected to fulfil new roles too, including contributing to standing commitments such as the Falklands and to defence engagement work abroad, such as conflict prevention and capacity building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This financial year, over 20 new overseas training exercises will take place for the Army Reserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hundred Reservists from the 6th Battalion, the Rifles recently spent two weeks in Germany training alongside their Regular Regimental colleagues from 5 Rifles in Exercise Leopard Star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise centred on the Warrior Armoured vehicle and was designed to develop the kind of integration between regular and Reserve that will be necessary to meet the demands of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such exercises were rare in the past; they will be more common in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists will routinely be part of deployments at home and abroad and will routinely train with the Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will require a change in legislation, redefining the circumstances in which Reserves can be mobilised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, they will be a fundamental part of how we provide military capability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of a ‘Whole Force’, alongside their Regular counterparts, the civilians who support them and the Defence Industry which supplies them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘Whole Force’, designed to ensure the nation’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are some who have questioned whether we can achieve the growth in Reserve Forces that we have set out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these new levels are well within historic norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1990, the TA was 72,500 strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army Reserve we are proposing is modest in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the new targets are ambitious, they are clearly achievable, and I am determined to deliver them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, we will need the support of employers, as well as potential Reservists and their families to deliver this ambition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="proposition-for-reservists"&gt;Proposition for Reservists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying respective Reservists, we’re looking for people who are going to turn out when they’re required to turn out, who are going to do the training they need to do and who are available for deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Army Reserve, they will be expected to undertake an extended training regime of around 40 days a year after basic training is completed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will be structured as one 16 day deployment and the balance at weekend and evenings, avoiding any added burdens on employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the message to future Army Reservists is clear: promise us you will make the commitment; turn up regularly to train and be prepared to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in return, we promise to equip you, train you, fund you and use you as an integral part of the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because you will be integrated with the Regulars and deployed more routinely, there will be greater opportunities for promotion and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balanced package of remuneration and support will be developed for Reservists and their families and provided as part of the ‘New Employment Model’ the MOD is developing for our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will support an integrated approach to pay and allowances and enable a much closer alignment of regular and Reservist careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will provide a much better deal for the families of Reservists, with help to access the support and networks available to Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outwith a genuine national emergency, we will also provide predictability to deployment, which will help at home as well as at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Routine liability in the Army Reserve will be for no more than one six month deployment in 5 years - although the total period of mobilisation would be longer - in some cases up to a year - to encompass operation specific training and post-operation recuperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some mobilisations will be much shorter - for example the Reserve element of the contribution to Olympics was only mobilised for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will be able to indicate in advance when the potential period of deployment will occur for any individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all these changes, this is an exciting proposition for Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenging, yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the Reserve Forces of the future, we need people who genuinely want to serve their nation and are committed to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this proposition will be appealing to those leaving the Regulars, as well as to the Volunteer Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an average year, over 18,000 people leave the regular forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, they have a liability for reserve service for a time limited period after they leave the regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few serve actively in this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could make better use of this asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making an attractive offer to departing regulars to remain voluntarily engaged in the Reserve we will do two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll help ourselves with numbers - just 10% of departing regulars taking up active Reserve Service would take us a significant part of the way to meeting our target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will also strengthen the resilience of the Reserves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more ex-regulars we have in the Reserves, the easier it will be for the Reserves to integrate with the Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-relationships-with-employers"&gt;New Relationships with Employers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this proposition for Reservists themselves is only one part of the jigsaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often in the past we’ve recruited the Reservist and then left him or her to worry about how to tell the employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though our plans call for a Reserve that will represent only 0.1% of the total UK workforce, I do not believe that we can achieve our ambitions without the active cooperation of employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this fresh start for the Reserves is also a fresh start for the relationship between the Armed Forces and the businesses who employ their Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to work with employers, building partnerships that deliver mutual benefit from Reserve Service;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joint approach to leadership and management training;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration on skills training;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to develop potential in students before they graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All will require a genuinely open relationship between Employer, Reservist and the Military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the employer understanding the Reservist’s liability and the Reservist confident that his service will not prejudice employment or promotion prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And underpinning this new relationship will be a tailored approach for different types of employer, reflecting the different benefits and impacts Reserve Service can have on companies in different sectors and of different sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that Reserve Service will affect small employers differently from large ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the truth, of course, is that with the growth of statutory leave entitlements - and other flexible working practices - employers of all sizes are becoming much more used to managing periods of absence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it is likely that public sector and large private sector organisations will be best placed to manage Reservists in their workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I see a real opportunity to work with major employers, like BT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employers who are already engaging through the Partnering for Talent Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies take great pride in supporting our Reservists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They see it as part of their corporate social responsibility; a great way of showing commitment to society at large&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are leading the way and helping us shape an adaptable and flexible Defence Force with an increased role for the Reserves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only right that we recognise these companies and the Green Paper suggests a new ‘Kitemark’ type award for Reserve-friendly employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not just about Corporate Social Responsibility: it must also be about mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many employers see very clearly the benefit that Reserve training and experience brings to them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering motivated, skilled, talented employees representing the values of the wider Armed Forces - integrity, application and commitment;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership training that is different from its civilian counterpart, adding a dimension to the skills of the work force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will consult on expanding the accreditation of skills and experience gained in reserve service through recognised civilian qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing direct benefit to employers through reduced training costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will consult, too, on the scope for linking apprenticeships and Reserve service in a package. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable this open relationship we are proposing to introduce a voluntary charter for employers of Reservists, recognising the contribution that good employers make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will also consider anti-discrimination legislation if we see evidence of systematic disadvantage to the Reservist in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the shape of the fresh start for our Reserve Forces and our proposition to employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Reservist: an exciting opportunity to be an integrated and respected part of the Defence of the nation - at the centre, not sidelined - with greater opportunities and better rewards - but with more responsibilities and commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the employer: a new relationship of mutual benefit - with packages designed for specific types of business - helping them to make better use of the skills, talents and training of Reservists - as well as an opportunity to support our Armed Forces and be recognised for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for Reservists, their families and employers alike - greater certainty and greater predictability to Reserve Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the investment we are making, the Reserves are no longer the forgotten part of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we go forward, they will be at its very heart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45349</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-01-air-power-partnership-in-the-21st-century"/>
    <title>2012/11/01 - Air Power: Partnership in the 21st Century</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;101 years ago today, on the first of November 1911, an Italian pilot threw four hand-held bombs out of a plane, from all of 600 feet, on Ottoman positions in what is now part of modern day Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although no-one was reported killed, and the only Ottoman response was, I’m told, a complaint of ungentlemanly conduct, this is generally regarded as the first bombing mission undertaken by aeroplane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, the Royal Flying Corps was formed, and over the last century, air power has moved from a peripheral role in military strategy, to a central one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Air Force today is integral to the defence of the United Kingdom and an indispensible part of operations to protect national security:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, helping to provide the Libyan people with the protection, and indeed the courage, they needed to overthrow the brutal dictator who had oppressed them for so long;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, policing the skies over London to ensure the delivery of a safe and secure Olympics; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I speak now, in the skies over Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all of these operations, air-power alone would not be enough; but in none of these operations could success have been achieved without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk today about the future development of the Royal Air Force and its contribution to the security of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as the theme of this conference suggests, I will do so in the context of partnership - international and domestic - military and civilian - government and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships that the RAF will need to enhance if it is to continue to assure the delivery air power in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A century in which space and cyber space will emerge as increasingly important domains of the overall strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in which the evolution of technology is already changing how air power can be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that the pilot of an aircraft need not be sitting in a cockpit, but can be in a bunker 3,000 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me first set out the overarching framework within which the Royal Air Force will continue to transform its capability, structure and infrastructure over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I became Secretary of State just over a year ago, the campaign in Libya was entering its final phase - with Gaddafi and his family expelled from Tripoli and holed up in Sirte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first day on the job was partly taken up with targeting decisions for air strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any notion that Defence was ‘just another Government Department with a budget problem’ was quickly dispelled.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I was having to navigate my foundation lesson in “military speak”, that impenetrable language designed to repel outsiders, and to underline just how different Defence is from other parts of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw at first hand, literally on my first day, that of course the first priority was then and will remain, success on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the very raison d’etre of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that our country is defended, our national security interests protected at home and abroad, and our values projected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan we are clear that we will end combat operations by December 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime, we must complete the mission: training and preparing the Afghan Forces to take on the burden of security, so that we can bring our personnel home, while protecting the gains that we have so expensively made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we and our ISAF partners draw down, we will be more dependent than ever on the air-bridge, and the RAF’s work in sustaining this link is critical to delivering success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of the Royal Air Force’s strength is currently contributing directly to operations and standing commitments -  in Afghanistan and on other tasks defending the UK and our dependent territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF is an integral part of the front-line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just as I am clear on the priority of operations, I am equally clear that without budgetary discipline, the need for the kind of reductions and tough decisions taken as part of the 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review, would come upon us again - and we will have gained nothing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, budgetary discipline has to be the supporting foundation of the transformation to Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence equipment programme needs to be balanced and sustainable if the Armed Forces are to have the confidence that the capabilities promised will actually be delivered, on time and to requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now half-way through this Parliament and I can confirm that we in the Ministry of Defence now have a balanced budget with an affordable equipment programme, backed by, although you might not realise it reading the British media, what will still be the fourth largest Defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this changes the dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By maintaining discipline, sensibly managing in-year budgets, and tightening our long-term projections, we can begin to release the contingencies that we have built into the budget, to support further investments in capability, confident that there is a sustainable funding stream to deliver them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, since the beginning of this financial year, the new discipline in our budgetary regime has allowed us to give the go ahead for a series of equipment projects for the air environment over and above the committed equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes targeting pods for fast jets, better protection systems for Tornado GR4, and enhancements to MERLIN Helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The powerful, adaptable RAF of Future Force 2020 is taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The re-formation of 13 Squadron at RAF Waddington, announced last week, will double the RAF Predator capability in the skies over Afghanistan, flying these remotely piloted air systems from ground stations in the UK for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was proud earlier this year, to be in Fort Worth to take delivery of the UK’s first F-35 Lightning II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning II is one of the clearest examples of Britain’s determination to stay in the top rank of military powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the clearest examples of our determination to maintain an advanced, powerful and flexible combat air capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of our regeneration of Carrier Strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A world-class capability, able to deploy anywhere in the world and jointly operated by the Royal Navy and the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With land based initial operating capability in 2018, allowing the platform to deploy as part of the UK’s contingent combat air capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And initial flights off HMS Queen Elizabeth in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a decade away, as our critics complain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just over 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deployed outside home waters, the new Carrier will routinely have Lightning II jets embarked with personnel from both Services, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been speculation in the media, much of it, as usual, ill-informed, around our intentions for operating the Carrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be absolutely clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF and the Royal Navy are working together to deliver a joint force that can operate from land bases in the UK, from the carriers when they are at sea, and from forward operating bases when deployed abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the direction of the Chief of the Defence Staff, the concept of operations for carrier enabled power projection is being developed in line with the adaptable posture set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concept of operations that will embrace both carrier strike and littoral manoeuvre operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is a substantial process, and dependent in part on decisions due to taken as part of the next SDSR in 2015 on the use of the second carrier to produce continuous carrier capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a joint asset, Lightning II will provide us with a flexible capability that will out-perform anything we’ve been able to put in the air before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with the UK enjoying a 15 % share of the industrial work, the peak production period is likely to sustain 25,000 jobs in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Strike Fighter project was conceived as a multi-national programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s tier one status in the programme speaks eloquently of the UK’s close partnership with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to turn now to the theme of international partnerships - because that relationship with the US is the UK’s most important, but by no means only, relationship upon which we rely to deliver our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-partnership"&gt;International Partnership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;100 years on from that very first aircraft bombing mission in Libya, NATO’s Operation Unified Protector last year proved the versatility of the RAF’s combat capabilities in the very same skies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just the precision weapons in the arsenal like Storm Shadow, dual-mode Brimstone and Paveway IV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also in the employment of Typhoon in its first multi-role contribution to operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the mission critical ISTAR assets such as Sentinel and E3-D Sentry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the strategic level, the mission demonstrated once again how air power can provide politicians with political choices short of intervention on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as the Chief of the Air Staff has previously said, Libya is not the archetype for conflict, anymore than Afghanistan is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can learn the very valuable lessons of both campaigns as we work to deliver adaptable Armed Forces, best configured to deal with the contingencies of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The striking feature of both campaigns is the breadth of the coalition taking part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libya operation saw 260 aircraft from 16 countries flying 26,500 sorties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of cooperation, in particular, between the RAF and the French Armee de l’Air during the campaign, was a potent demonstration of the new momentum in UK-French defence cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, the International Security Assistance Force is now some 50 nations strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAF assets operate alongside those of our fellow ISAF partners…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… the Tornado GR4 force at Kandahar airport shares Tango Ramp with F16s from the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camp Bastion airfield in Helmand, controlled by the RAF, ranks as one of the busiest multi-national airfields in the world, handling up to 450 movements a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level and sophistication of the integration between coalition partners, forged in campaigns such as Afghanistan and Libya, needs to be maintained and then taken forward long after those campaigns are behind us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the RAF, this interoperability with allies has become second nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last century, from the Allied air campaigns of the 2nd world war, through the Berlin Air Lift, to the Gulf War, Balkans and Kosovo campaigns of the 1990s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this century in Iraq, Afghanistan and Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF has honed its understanding and interoperability, operating as part of multi-national coalitions over many, many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wide international audience that I see before me today, is testament to the strength of the relationship that the RAF has forged with its fellow military aviators from across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That operational experience is now being built upon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tornados from RAF Marham have deployed to the Middle East for a series of exercises to work with partner nations on Exercise SHAHEEN STAR - and soon Typhoons from RAF Leuchars will be joining exercises in UAE and Oman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Typhoon has also been flying with allies from the Five Power Defence Arrangement as part of Exercise BERSAMA LIMA 11, in Malaysia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all part of putting into practice the kind of interoperability we will need in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-partnership-challenge"&gt;The Partnership Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there is another strategic lesson we can draw from recent operations, particularly Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the one hand, Libya showed the strength of our the NATO alliances and our partnerships, the operation also, to be frank, cruelly exposed the imbalances and weaknesses in NATO and thus the scale of the task facing European NATO nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as former US Defence Secretary Robert Gates pointed out at the time, “The most advanced fighter aircraft are little use if allies do not have the means to identify, process, and strike targets as part of an integrated campaign”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could argue this is the very nature of coalition operations, with each partner providing the skills and assets that it can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of Libya it shone a bright light on relative military and political capabilities in terms of who “could but wouldn’t”; and who “would but couldn’t”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the United States reflecting, in its strategic posture, the growing importance of the developing strategic challenge in the Pacific, the nations of Europe must find the political will to take on more responsibility for our own back yard, and fund the capabilities to allow that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly that means, shouldering the major burden in the Balkans and the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also being prepared, if necessary, to take a bigger role in relation to North Africa and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that Europe, as a whole, needs to do more, at a time when the reality is that, across the continent, aggregate defence expenditure is certain to fall in the short term and, at best, recover slowly in the medium term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the challenge is stark: if we can’t spend more, we must do things differently;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maximising the capability we can collectively squeeze out of the resources we have; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing interoperability, closing capability gaps through joint working and greater specialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the UK is overhauling its ISTAR, strategic lift and combat air capabilities as part of the transition to Future Force 2020 with the new Atlas and Voyager fleets operating alongside the C17, Sentry, Sentinel, and Airseeker as well as a range of remotely piloted air systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These forces will allow us to offer capacity to share with our international partners in new, innovative and mutually beneficial ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, for the time being at least, we will depend on others for support with maritime patrol aircraft, when we need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is not just about smart behaviour by NATO members per-se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Britain, Smart Defence is also about making the Alliance more flexible, encouraging collaboration among groups of allies within the Alliance, and with partners outside the Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Libya and Afghanistan have shown how agile NATO can be in incorporating the contributions of outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should capitalise on this experience in making it easier for non-NATO nations and key potential partners to contribute to NATO’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The partnership challenge encompasses more than just bi-lateral and multi-lateral government-to-government or military-to-military relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also encompasses those who supply and support our equipment too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partnership-with-industry"&gt;Partnership with Industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With shrinking Defence budgets in many advanced countries, and ever greater appetite and capability for involvement in design, development and production of sophisticated military equipment in the emerging economies, it is a tough business environment out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition will be intense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic challenges involved in maintaining a high tech, highly capable, air force now and in the future are considerable -and the technical challenges equally high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success will require a genuinely transparent collaboration in aerospace, between industry and government to keep overheads down, to maintain essential R&amp;amp;D, and to build healthy export order books while making sure the unit cost is affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are embarking on some major changes to make the MOD a more capable and intelligent customer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restructuring equipment acquisition and through-life support;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing in private sector management skills through a partnership to re-inforce the military and civilian specialists who form the backbone of the Defence equipment and procurement organisation;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at how the acquisition processes can take better account of the commercial landscape - building in exportability - making sure the wider package on offer to potential customers is as attractive as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those years of over-programming in Defence created a climate of uncertainty that was beneficial neither to our Armed Forces, nor to industry - with neither side able to plan properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide industry with as much information as possible to plan, we will be publishing a summary of the equipment plan in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide greater granularity than ever before about how money will be spent across the breadth of capabilities by breaking down spending for equipment and support alongside the judgement of the National Audit Office on the robustness of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong aerospace sector in the UK - manufacturing, servicing, and crucially exporting - is a vital part of the Government’s strategy for rebalancing our economy so it can return to sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also an onus on our suppliers to provide better value for money for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need our partners to be lean and flexible, capable of operating in a more competitive defence marketplace, responsive to the needs of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry support for air operations in Libya last year shows what can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering and sustaining capability - as well as supplying equipment and developing new technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently 5,000 contractors directly supporting our operations in Afghanistan, including the vital role played by the RAF. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Total Support Force’ concept, set out in the White Paper, seeks to integrate more fully the contribution of the private sector to operations. Industry, the Armed Forces, MOD, civilians and industry working more closely than ever to achieve their mutual goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Future Force 2020, we are building a force fit for a more uncertain world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we may not know in advance what conditions we will be fighting in;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we can only hope to meet the challenges of modern conflict and protect national security by exploiting all the advantages we possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of our advanced technology and industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of our international alliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the advantage of our highly trained, highly capable people -  working together as a total force to deliver the world’s most effective expeditionary military capability outside the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF brings unique capabilities to the delivery of joint effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid reaction, speed, agility and precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control of the air and the ability to exploit that domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategic lift to project power at range;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactical manoeuvre and re-supply on the battlefield;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the real-time intelligence and awareness that airborne ISTAR provides of the battle space as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the people of the RAF that deliver this effect. Our people are our principal asset. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just the pilot; the air crew, the engineers, the planners, the whole edifice of the RAF that supports the delivery of British air power at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as we enter the remembrance period, and honour those who have sacrificed so much for the freedom of this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us express our confidence in the men and women of today’s Royal Air Force; in their determination to demonstrate the same spirit and commitment to duty as their illustrious forbears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that our skies will continue to be safe in their hands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45362</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-15-ssafa-annual-defence-industry-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/10/15 - SSAFA Annual Defence Industry Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kevin [Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, SSAFA Chair] for that introduction; and for your kind invitation to make the address this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Royal Highness, Chief of the Defence Staff, my Lords, Ladies and Gentlemen, it’s a great pleasure to be back here at SSAFA’s annual dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I spoke at the Annual Dinner last year it was my first speech as Defence Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After just days in the job, I was confidently asserting all sorts of things with very little direct personal knowledge of whether they were true or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year on, a little more au fait with the military jargon, and a lot more familiar with the challenges facing our troops and their families, I can pay full tribute to the vital work that SSAFA does, based on a personal understanding of the need you are meeting and the difference you are making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week, I heard at first hand at Queen Elizabeth Hospital in Birmingham how facilities such as SSAFA’s Norton House allow visiting families to focus their energies on their injured loved one without having to worry about finding and paying for accommodation close to the hospital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the range of activities, outlined by the Chief of the Defence Staff earlier, the work you do is hugely appreciated and highly valued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on behalf of all of us in Defence, let me say “thank you” to you and the industry who support you so magnificently, for everything that you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is one year to the day since my first day in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an old civil service legend that’s told about Sir Alec Douglas-Home when he was appointed Foreign Secretary under Ted Heath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first weekend box, he was confronted with a two-inch thick report on Icelandic fisheries and a note from his Private Secretary, which read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Secretary of State may care to read this over the weekend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Alec returned the report the following Monday with his own note, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A kind thought, but wholly erroneous.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I arrived in the MoD, I had been prepared for the worst: a stereotypical bureaucracy seeking to frustrate ministerial intent at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have to say, my experience has been very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into a Department as complex as Defence has been quite an eye-opener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly wasn’t appointed because of my knowledge of fighter jets or aircraft carriers or armoured vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if I’m honest, I probably came into the Department with a focus on the budget challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly understood that, while the budget is crucially important, Defence is about much more than a set of balanced books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="afghanistan"&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first day in post, one of the first duties of my Military Assistant was to inform me of the death in Afghanistan of Rifleman Vijay Rai of the 2nd Battalion, the Royal Gurkha Rifles, and to explain to me the process of kinforming and repatriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a very sober introduction to my new responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to the reality of our operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those operations remain, of course, the first priority of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we come towards the end of our mission there, it’s important for us to remind ourselves why our troops are there; how much they’ve achieved; and how we are going to get them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we are in Afghanistan is simple: to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the only reason, in my book, to ask our troops to put themselves in harm’s way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is clear: training the Afghan Forces to take on the burden of security so that we can bring our troops home while ensuring the gains that we have made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And coming home they will be: another 500 by Christmas, and we expect to make further, significant reductions by the end of next year, with all UK combat operations finishing by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="balancing-the-budget"&gt;Balancing the Budget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move towards the end of our mission, we need to plan now for the post-Afghanistan environment and the Transformation of Defence to meet the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has been dominated by the urgent need to eliminate the black hole in the MoD budget; to learn lessons from the failures of the past; and to ensure that our forces are prepared for the very different challenges they will face in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has meant taking some tough decisions: to shrink the size of the MoD; to rationalize our equipment programme; and to reduce the size of the Navy, Army and the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-way through this Parliament, we now have a balanced budget with an affordable equipment programme and a deliverable plan Future Force 2020, backed by what will still be the fourth largest Defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people---the-future-of-our-armed-forces"&gt;People - The Future of our Armed Forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the budget is crucially important, but it is not an end in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a means to enable us to deliver, sustainably, the Defence of this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the key to doing that - what really delivers Britain’s battle-winning edge - is the people that make up Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces - Regular and Reserves; the civilians who support them and the Defence Industry which supplies them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my big learning curves over the last year (and there have been a few) has been understanding the unique nature of what the military call the “moral component” of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that provides the “will to fight”, and the determination to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes our people so special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of our people feel they have taken a bit of a pounding over the last couple of years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also know that I have got a big job on my hands to build their trust and win their confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having fixed the budget problem and begun the process of Transforming the Department, it is now time to focus on our people, and their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I cannot avoid the need for change, what I can do is give people clarity and certainty about their individual futures as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already completed the Armed Forces Pension review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering a new, non-contributory scheme that remains one of the very best pension offers anywhere in the public or private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the end of the year, we will announce the re-basing plan, so that families will know where their future homes will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will do everything we can to minimise the number of compulsory redundancies as we bring the Army to its future size over the next couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that our service men and women want certainty that at the end of these changes, they will be part of UK Armed Forces that remain amongst the very best and most respected in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many countries will have more people in their armed forces, and some may even have similar equipment, very few will be able to begin to match the military capability of our people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this process of transformation, I am confident that we will have the most capable, deployable armed forces outside the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strengthening--the-covenant"&gt;Strengthening  the Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want our servicemen and women to know that the Government and society as a whole recognises the debt of gratitude we owe to them and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have enshrined the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant in law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Covenant is now becoming entrenched across Whitehall - so much so that Ministers in other departments are now coming to me asking how they can do their bit to support our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor, with £35 million from banking fines redirected to service charities;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Education Secretary, increasing and extending the scope of the service pupil premium;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And across Government, a commitment to give Reservists a minimum 10 days’ additional paid leave each year for their training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud that upholding and strengthening the Covenant is taken so seriously across Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have more work to do, but the process is now irreversibly established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-year-ahead"&gt;The Year Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the year ahead, as well as the proper priority that we will give to our operations in Afghanistan, we will make progress on three important parts of Defence transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, working to build our new Reserve capability and integrate the Reserves with our Regular forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, we’ll publish our Reserves Green Paper, setting out our new offer, backed by an additional £1.8 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In return for properly equipping, training, and funding our Reserves we will expect them to turn up regularly to train, and to be prepared to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite thousands of them having served in Afghanistan and operations around the world, too often our Reserves have been the forgotten part of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer: in the future, they will be more vital to our force projection than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will treat them as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we will accelerate work on the New Employment Model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making service terms and conditions more flexible, better reflecting the complexity of modern family life and delivering our goal of higher levels of home ownership among members of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And third, restructuring our equipment and support acquisition, bringing in private sector management skills to support the military and civilian specialists who form the backbone of DE&amp;amp;S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined that the MoD will be a much better customer in the future - an organization with which the Defence industry can do business far more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in return, we need the industry to be leaner, more cost-conscious suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that with shrinking Defence budgets in many countries, it is a tough environment out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by working together to create the equipment our Armed Forces need, at a cost we can afford and at a price that makes it exportable, we can continue this country’s proud tradition of excellence in Defence manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last couple of years haven’t been easy for anyone in Defence, least of all for those in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the budget back in balance and the bulk of the tough decisions taken, we can now look ahead to the future with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handing over security in Afghanistan to the Afghan;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming our Armed Forces for the future;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the battle-winning platforms and weapon systems our forces need;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforming procurement;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And building our integrated Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most importantly, we can begin the process of rebuilding confidence in the future among our people after years of uncertainty and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a challenge for me and for the Department - indeed for the whole of Government and society as we build on the commitments of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is one that we will be hugely better able to rise to with the magnificent support of the fantastic service charities such as SSAFA and your generous supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you again for everything you do - and please, keep up the good work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45361</id>
    <published>2012-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-23-address-to-the-royal-college-of-defence-studies"/>
    <title>2012/07/23 - Address to the Royal College of Defence Studies</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me here to speak to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as you approach the end of your course I know you will have made the most of the opportunity presented here at the Royal College Of Defence Studies to get to grips with some of the very complex issues facing defence and defence diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of which are common to the United Kingdom and its allies and partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international nature of this course is one of its strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your generation of leaders will have a key role in addressing these challenges; and in forging the bi-lateral and multi-lateral defence relationships that the Defence and Security arrangements of every country, even the United States, is likely to rely on in the future to protect its national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to talk this morning about some of the strategic challenges we’re facing in UK Defence and more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And pose you some of the questions that will have to be answered during your generation’s tenure in the top jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strategic-picture"&gt;Strategic Picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategically, the world is a far less certain, and in some ways, a less threatening place than it was 25 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we faced an adversary with the means, and the intent, if an unpredictable and paranoid leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, at least, the paranoid leaderships are still struggling to obtain the means!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly technology is racing ahead; changing the way we protect critical infrastructure more likely to be rendered inoperable through a computer virus than a bombing raid; requiring multi-level C4ISTAR - capabilities which are not as obvious to the public and an aircraft carrier, a tank or a jet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of ‘invisible’ capabilities like this presents a challenge to politicians who need to demonstrate to the public who are paying for them, how we are spending their money and how we are keeping them safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a geo-political level, the dispersion of power that began as the Berlin Wall crumbled has gathered pace with the emergence of new potential military powers and greater strategic competition between growing economies, both regionally and globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, the impact of globalisation means there are diminishing levers available to individual national governments to effect change, manage their economies, and protect their national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic realities facing the mature economies show how linked we are; how easily contagion can spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the medium term, those charged with the task of protecting national security, in economies set for relative decline as the pattern of wealth adjusts, will have to do so in an environment of constrained resources &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the future in which you will lead in your respective services and in your respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And although this future will be unpredictable and volatile, we can clearly see some of the issues that will dominate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-means"&gt;Economic Means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - The economic backdrop. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic strength underpins national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a requirement for generating military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at what is driving the changed pattern of military power today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at what settled the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without strong economies and public finances it is impossible to build and sustain, in the long-term, the military capability required to project power and maintain strong defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, today, the debt crisis should be considered the greatest strategic threat to the future security of western nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is also why, although NATO has often talked of distributing the burden of collective defence more equitably, in the current fiscal climate, it is essential that we no longer talk, but begin to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that too many member states are failing to meet their financial responsibilities to NATO, and so failing to maintain appropriate and proportionate capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many are opting out of operations or contributing but a fraction of what they should be capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have to be realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic and fiscal circumstances in which most developed countries find themselves, makes this problem difficult to fix in the short term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the alliance, aggregate defence expenditure is certain to fall in the short term and, at best, recover slowly in the medium term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So more money is not going to be the answer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the challenge is to maximise the capability we can squeeze out of the resources we have available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="political-will"&gt;Political Will&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to my second point: alliance structures are only as strong as the political will of individual nations to meet their responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It matters that NATO countries meet their commitments on funding Defence - to ensure the means to protect our collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is no good having the means if you lack the will to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya showed what can be achieved when many of the stars are in alignment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Security Council, NATO, regional powers, the political will of those with the capabilities to act, and of course the will of the majority of the Libyan people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also showed quite starkly the imbalances in NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imbalances in the hardware (and increasingly software) available to the Alliance from national contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also imbalances in the will to act, the will to deploy, the determination to take part and commit nationally owned capabilities that have absorbed many billions of taxpayers’ cash in order to make us all collectively safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are untapped reserves of resource in European NATO which need to be tapped to support our collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few years, the United States will put into practice its ‘tilt’ to the Asia-Pacific theatre - a focus that is very much in our interests as the US rise to meet the strategic challenge set by the emergence of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US will expect Europe to do more to of the heavy lifting to ensure security in our own region, and our near abroad - the Middle East, North Africa, and the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How European nations respond to this pivot will set the context for the multi-lateral environment British Armed Forces and others will operate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my third point: cohesion of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="meeting-threats"&gt;Meeting Threats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to confront head on a real tension within the NATO alliance: basically to answer the question, what is NATO for in the 21st Century?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threat from a monolithic Soviet Union no longer exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the approach to Russia differs across the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us further back, west of the old iron curtain, the threat is no longer a territorial, but global terror and rogue states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a passive defence of national territory is no longer adequate protection for our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are starting from a reality that it is much better to fight in the space of our adversaries rather than at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this is relatively easier to do if your adversary is a terrorist, rather than a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this requires rapidly deployable, adaptable, agile, flexible, expeditionary forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is what the UK’s Strategic Defence &amp;amp; Security Review was all about; responding to these three drivers - the economics, the evolving alliance pattern, and the evolving threat pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaping the spread of capabilities we will maintain, in the face of fiscal restraint, to the future character of warfare - and to maintain national security by acting at distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future posture of Russia is by no means certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with political change sweeping across North Africa and the Arab world, change that is far from at an end, far from predictable, and has the potential to leave a less secure and less safe neighbourhood, we cannot rule out the return of a strategic threat to territorial Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this has been about striking the right balance between our own direct national needs and those of the NATO alliance upon which we continue to rely for collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recognising the likely future shape of operations in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future-shape-of-operations"&gt;The Future Shape of Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have had the opportunity during your course to look at current operations and to draw lessons from them for the future character of warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya showed the utility of precision weapons in an era where minimising collateral damage and civilian deaths will be part of the strategic objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it also exposed shortfalls in the European contribution to NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Libya has tested another concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The utility of air-power as an alternative to ‘boots on the ground’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya has shown how air power can provide politicians like me with political choices short of intervention on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have not drawn the conclusion that ground intervention will be unnecessary in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a ground campaign in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could not have proceeded without NATO airpower support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was decisive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was undertaken by Libyans, not NATO troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 10 years of enduring campaigns, you do not have to be a political sage to recognise that the public’s future appetite for open-ended interventions is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we do not yet know the end outcome of the Libya intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Displacing the old regime was, relatively, the easy bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what comes after is not yet completely clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So modern warfare requires firepower and political sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that requires a deep understanding of the situation on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, our troops have had to wear the face of both the warrior and the diplomat - fighting one moment - and taking tea with the elders the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political dimension of warfare is crucial to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can win the battle but lose the war unless you are focussed on what you really want to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will usually be the case that force of arms alone cannot deliver victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is certainly the case in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the comprehensive approach - marrying politics, finance, military capability, diplomacy, development - not just across national government, but internationally too - will be so important in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, against that backdrop, let me bring this discussion closer to home and say something about the future shape of the UK’s Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future-shape-of-uk-armed-forces"&gt;The Future Shape of UK Armed Forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is still very much the priority in terms of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the end of the combat mission is now in view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, intellectually, we have moved on to look beyond 2014 at the shape of the Forces we will need for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The needs of the mission in Afghanistan, and before it Iraq, have dominated for a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the dangers and complexities of those missions they have provided some predictability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have known, often two years in advance, when they are going to be deployed; they know how long they are going to be deployed for; often they have known exactly where they are going to be deployed to before they go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have bent our military, our Army in particular into the shape required for this six month rotational enduring conflict in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the process, we have lost some contingent capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post 2014, the move from enduring campaign to contingency, signals an end to the predictability of the roulement cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It heralds a Future Force geared toward being ready to deal with the unexpected and unplanned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we make this change against a background of fiscal constraint driven by the economic health of the country as a whole, and the legacy of mismanagement in the defence budget in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation we are undertaking is challenging - probably the most complex change programme being undertaken anywhere in the western world at the current time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The black hole that existed in the defence budget, the weakness of the equipment programme, and the shape of the country’s finances, have militated against simply bailing the budget out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be hard to justify excluding the Defence Budget, the fifth largest call on the public purse, from the programme to exert fiscal control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the books and creating a sustainable forward Defence programme has meant reducing personnel numbers, retiring some capabilities, and taking some calculated and managed risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I told an audience in Washington last week - it is far better to have a smaller but well-equipped and well-trained force; with an equipment programme that offers a high level of confidence that we will deliver it; giving our Armed Forces the ability to plan for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the announcements I have made over the last couple of months on the Defence Budget, the Equipment Programme, Army 2020 and the Reserves we have put in place the vision set out in the SDSR of sustainable Armed Forces, equipped with some of the most capable and most technically advanced platforms in the world, configured to respond to the unexpected -  and to go anywhere to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have also set out a blueprint for the reform of the management of defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renewing the way strategic direction is provided;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing authority and accountability down the chain of command;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging innovation and budgetary responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And developing a new strategy for the procurement of defence equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeking to instil private sector skills and disciplines to our acquisition process, driving up productivity, by bringing a private sector partner into the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And creating clearer and harder relationships between the different functions in the Defence procurement chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To read some of the comment in the media, often fuelled by retired officers whose view of the world was shaped in the Cold War era, you would think that Britain was getting out of the force projection business altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing could be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when this programme is complete, we will still expect to have the fourth largest defence budget in the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceeding the NATO standard of 2% of GDP; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending £160bn on our equipment programme over the next 10 years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering the next generation of military technology and platforms that will help provide a battle-winning edge;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller Armed Forces but better equipped and confident that they will receive the equipment that has been promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile, high-tech, Capable of conducting the full spectrum of operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structured to allow rapid reaction and expeditionary warfare;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to deploy overseas and sustain a Brigade-sized force indefinitely, or a Division-sized force in time of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to command in the coalition context and more interoperable with our main allies;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully integrated between Regular and Reserves, with predictable obligations for the Reservists that will require a real commitment to service;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a more systematic use of contractors for support and logistics; allowing greater focus of military manpower on fighting tasks;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, structured to be able to generate mass and capabilities if the threat picture changes or the fiscal position eases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the British Armed Forces that some of you will be leading in - or for our partners overseas - the British Armed Forces you will be operating with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many of you who are from overseas will be seeing similar transformations in your own militaries over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you are here because you have been identified as having the qualities needed for top level responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the moral component of leadership is one of the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this transformation is to be realised, and national and collective security to be guaranteed, you will need to be focussed, positive, full of ideas, prepared to change, to challenge convention, and willing to drive change in others, inspiring those around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is a challenge at a political level too, for people like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Secretary of State, I have responsibility for Defence but as a Cabinet Member, I have responsibility to look wider and help to balance national priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an immediate or existential threat shrinks, the public appetite to fund Defence shrinks with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are lucky in the UK, particularly compared to other European nations, that the public feels a strong affinity with our Armed Forces and has a greater inclination to give defence a higher priority than many of our neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the legacy of Iraq and Afghanistan has undoubtedly left us a public which is without appetite for enduring campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And politicians need to think carefully about how we are going to maintain public support for Defence spending in the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially when more and more of the capabilities we are investing in will not be traditional military assets - and indeed will often be invisible to taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many actions in hand to manage the transition from a period of enduring campaigns to one of contingent readiness; and I have described a few today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have answered by no means all the questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the future focus of NATO;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About how we maximise the military effect that we get from limited budgets across the Alliance;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the balance of capabilities between traditional kinetic effect and investment in C4ISTAR, cyber and space;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the type of warfare we need to prepare to fight;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about the future of European Defence industries in the face of rapidly changing export markets and shrinking domestic purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, and many other questions, will form the challenges that the next generation of military and political leaders will face over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I look forward to hearing your thoughts on them!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45360</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-18-address-to-the-centre-for-a-new-american-security"/>
    <title>2012/07/18 - Address to the Centre for a New American Security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Bill [Bill Lynn, former Deputy Secretary of Defense, now CEO of DRS Technologies] for that introduction and it’s a great pleasure and a privilege to be here at CNAS this afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was here in Washington in January, I spoke about how Europe needed to respond to the challenge laid down by Bob Gates in the seminal speech he made in Brussels - a challenge which was reiterated by Secretary Panetta when he took up his role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked about how serious imbalances in NATO capabilities, demonstrated so starkly by the Libya campaign, represented a further challenge to the European NATO Allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How the twin requirements to collective security and economic stability, meant that, in the short to medium term, given the pressure on budgets across the Alliance, more money is not in reality likely to be the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, in an era of budgetary austerity, NATO’s Smart Defence initiative required greater collaboration between NATO Allies, and with our trusted partners, to produce capability more efficiently, and that the greatest effect would be generated by small groups working together, not through cumbersome mechanisms designed for unanimity at 28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since January, I have taken that message to Europe: to Berlin, to Paris, and to Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I believe we are heading in the right direction. Everybody gets it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the NATO summit in Chicago we laid the groundwork for an Alliance based on more equitable burden-sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have to make this a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, I want to zero in on one of the most effective drivers of collective North Atlantic military capability - the relationship between the United States and United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to explain to you the reforms the UK is making to the way we deliver military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I want to reassure you about our resolve to remain a capable ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to begin to sketch out for you the next phase of the collaboration between our two great countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-essential-alliance"&gt;An Essential Alliance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama during his State visit to Britain last year, described the Anglo-American relationship as “one of the oldest and strongest alliances the world has ever known.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he identified the role of the relationship in driving wider collaboration. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At a time when threats and challenges require nations to work in concert with one another, we remain the greatest catalyst for global action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was thinking particularly of the Libya campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of our alliance is based on the twin pillars of common values and common interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our common values of democracy, the rule of law, the free market, freedom of speech and freedom of conscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our common interests in maintaining an open, free-trading, stable and secure international environment in which our citizens can prosper and our values can spread and flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our economic and cultural relationship is significant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are each other’s largest single foreign investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are each other’s top partners in science, innovation and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is our Defence relationship which stands out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forged in the furnaces of the world wars of the 20th century;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintained through the long watches of the Cold War;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now tempered over the last decade in the sands of Iraq and in the shadow of the Hindu Kush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our Defence relationship is not a backward-looking one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are about to enter a new phase in our long history together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As President Obama said in January “we are turning a page on a decade of war”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, as for the US, this will mean bringing an end to more than a decade of enduring operations in the wake of 9/11, as we transition from a combat role in Afghanistan to a contingent posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me set out to you how the United Kingdom is taking this opportunity to reconfigure our Armed Forces to face the new threats that await us in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain highly capable, agile Armed Forces, supported by balanced budgets, disciplined processes, with an efficient and effective Department of State behind them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prepared for a future of contingency rather than predictability;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For rapid reaction rather than long-planned rotations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting the future character of warfare with investment in ISR, cyber and unmanned technologies;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, more interoperable with our primary international partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-transformation-of-uk-defence"&gt;The Transformation of UK Defence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation to a contingent posture is, of course, complicated by the need to deal with the fiscal challenge facing our economy; a challenge shared by many of our allies, including the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action being taken by the UK to bring our fiscal position under control is in itself an essential strategic underpinning to future sustainable defence capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiscal integrity and economic robustness is the well-spring of strategic strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, surely, is one of the primary lessons of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also had to deal with an equipment plan beset by overspends and over-optimistic programming - problems, I know, that are not entirely unknown on this side of the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have acted early.  We have been decisive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to assure you of our resolve to remain a strong and capable ally of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review set the strategic direction and began the process;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting the legacy of the Cold War behind us;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focussing on the deployable, expeditionary, well equipped forces we will need in the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have now taken this process forward, going through the equipment programme line by line;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing honesty into our Defence plan;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordering only what we can fund and sustain;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by doing so, not only bringing our Defence Budget back into balance for the first time in a generation;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But providing our forces with the reassurance that if it is in the programme, we have the budget to pay for it, and it is going to be delivered to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So they can start plan with certainty for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also set out the design for the British Army of 2020 as we recover capabilities from Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intelligent approach that minimises the impact on military effect of a reduction in regular manpower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integrating more fully regular and reserve forces;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And using our contractors more effectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that manpower reductions are taken in areas where Reserves and contractors can most rapidly provide support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maximising teeth, by transforming the way we deliver the tail.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing a core of highly trained Reaction forces, supported by an Adaptive force able to undertake standing tasks, overseas capacity building, homeland resilience and provide the capability for sustained operations when required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An army that will remain the most capable deployable fighting force outside the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have set out a blueprint for the reform of the management of defence as well;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renewing the way strategic direction is provided;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing authority and accountability down the chain of command;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging innovation and budgetary responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And developing, as Bill mentioned, a new strategy for the procurement of defence equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeking to instil private sector skills and disciplines to our acquisition process, driving up productivity, by bringing a private sector partner into the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And creating clearer and harder relationships between the different functions in the Defence procurement chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a necessary precursor to re-setting the relationship with the defence industry - offering new opportunities for collaboration; but demanding in exchange renewed pursuit of efficiencies in the delivery of military programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of what we have done has been painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the books and creating a sustainable forward Defence programme has meant reducing personnel numbers and retiring some capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has meant accepting, and managing, some capability risks. The reductions we are making are broadly proportionate to those being planned in the Pentagon, but of course from a baseline an order of magnitude smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are difficult decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as Bill said in his farewell speech last year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Keeping programs alive on the hope that there will be more funds in the future is dangerous behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is better to have a smaller but ready force, and fewer but healthy programs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even when our retrenchment is complete, we will continue to have the fourth largest defence budget in the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceeding the NATO standard of 2% of GDP; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending £160bn - around $250bn - on our equipment programme over the next 10 years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering the next generation of military technology and platforms that will help provide a battle-winning edge;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regenerating our carrier strike capability with our new Queen Elizabeth Class carriers and superb F-35B aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retaining sufficient mass to play a significant role in large coalition operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, supported by the political will to deploy our forces when required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout this process, the watchword has been capability, not size - capability that can be deployed swiftly within a force posture that is inherently adaptable and configured to tackle the full range of potential threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have taken great care to protect those capabilities that underpin our value as an ally to the US and in NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our command capability; our special forces; our industrial and technology base; the knowledge and experience of interoperability embedded in our structures and personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, heeding Bill’s advice in that speech, the force we will be able to field in 2020 will be smaller, but better equipped, better supported and better configured to meet the challenges of the new security environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Regular Army - smaller yes, but more agile;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better integrated, with a more deployable Reserve;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structured to allow rapid reaction and expeditionary warfare;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capable of conducting the full spectrum of operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to deploy and sustain a Brigade-sized force indefinitely or a Division-sized force in time of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Royal Air Force that will be operating fleets of multi role Typhoon and ground attack Tornado aircraft before the introduction of the F-35 Lightning II - with a support fleet of C17, A400M transport aircraft and Voyager transporter and Air-to-Air refueller, as well as a full suite of UAVs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy operating one of the most advanced anti-aircraft destroyers in the world, the Type 45, with work advancing on our new Type 26 Global Combat Ship and the nuclear Astute Class submarine programme nearing completion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying the STOVL version of the F-35B will allow us quickly to generate strike capability from our next generation aircraft carriers - the largest warships ever to enter service with the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am extremely grateful to the US Navy and Marine Corps for the support they are providing to allow us to maintain and regenerate the skill sets we need to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course this core force is supplemented by the whole panoply of joint-force enablers including C4ISTAR and our world class Special Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is underpinned by our continuous, at sea, nuclear deterrent which we are committed to retaining and replacing in due course as it reaches the end of its current life expectancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the criticism in the domestic press, these are not the Armed Forces of a nation in retreat, but of one determined to provide the most effective, capable and deployable Armed Forces after those of the United States itself;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ready and able to protect the national interest and to contribute to global security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong enough to protect our own interests;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large enough to command coalition operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced enough to operate alongside the US anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the shape of the future British Armed Forces that you in the US can expect to be operating alongside you in the field as your most capable and committed military ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pivot"&gt;The Pivot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we draw down from Afghanistan, our shared analysis of the future security environment points to a period that is unpredictable, volatile and with diverse threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threats that need to be met as they evolve, upstream and at distance, rather than waiting for them to come to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in which the rising strategic importance of the Asia-Pacific region requires all countries, but particularly the United States, to reflect in their strategic posture, the emergence of China as a global power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from being concerned about the ‘tilt’ to Asia Pacific, the European NATO powers should welcome the fact that the US is willing to engage this new strategic challenge on behalf of the Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recognise that, as a result, European nations, including the UK, will need to do much more of the heavy lifting to ensure security in their own region and in the Middle East, North Africa and the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the ‘end of Atlanticism’, but the beginning of a new, more balanced era in the relationships within the Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The priority of the UK will remain, after the protection of our homeland and dependent territories, to ensure the enduring security and stability of Europe and its near abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recalibration of burden-sharing is the way close allies should respond to shifts in the geopolitical landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, the defence relationship with the US will always be paramount. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in order to support your rebalancing, we will seek to work more closely with our neighbours in Europe, particularly France and Germany, to enhance the capabilities of our own region, for homeland defence and for intervention abroad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that Europe makes its contribution to upholding the international system that underpins our collective security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a division of labour which is firmly in our mutual interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this makes UK/US co-operation any less important. On the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said in January, no country, not even the United States, can hope to tackle successfully all the threats we face in common, by acting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the UK will continue to stand alongside the US in tackling these threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we in the UK have faced up to the challenge set first by Secretary Gates, and then by Secretary Panetta. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set out our Transformation programme and have begun to deliver it. We identified the role that we need to play as the Alliance responds to the US pivot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already on the road to delivering the sustainable Armed Forces that will give us the capability we need for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we are ready to map out the next steps in our cooperation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we drawdown from this decade of continuous operations - and continuous military co-operation, the circumstances are changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so our relationship needs to evolve in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the immediacy of those enduring operations, that we’ve had for the last 10 years, we need to act to maintain the immense knowledge, skills and habits of co-operation built up between our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will require a renewed emphasis on training and exercising after 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good start will be to make full use of the training potential of the recently announced decision to rotate US-based Brigade Combat Teams through the NATO Response Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to go further, do more, if we are going  to maintain the extraordinary level of mil-mil cooperation built up over the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me set out three areas where I think the national interest of our countries, and the collective interests of our partners, would be served by more far reaching US-UK co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - in new capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of our defence strategies are based on retaining the technological edge of our armed forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this environment of rapid technological change and significant resource constraint, we should do more to align requirements more closely and work collaboratively to deliver them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in neither of our interests to duplicate research and development for new systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no two countries are better placed to work together for the common good than Britain and the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern, battle winning equipment and weapons have become extraordinarily expensive, so there is merit in cooperating more fully - pooling demand, investment and technology - as we have done with the F35.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an age of Smart Defence it is even more vital that we do more together both on the battlefield and in development of future systems.  Working together to ensure our forces have the best equipment and can operate side by side whenever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly - new domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of our countries recognise that the character of conflict is changing.  The threats that are arising in cyberspace are not limited by geography nor can they be addressed through conventional military action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to think differently about the way we protect critical infrastructure more likely to be rendered inoperable through a computer virus than a bombing raid.  And we have to work together to help our defence industries protect themselves from espionage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill has been a tireless advocate for greater co-operation between our countries in tackling some of these threats. It’s thanks to him that we now have great co-operation underway at CYBERCOM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cyber Collaboration Memorandum signed last year, has established the framework for our nations to work more closely in this domain and we should capitalise on the opportunities it presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly - I want to suggest we need a new approach to security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of our defence strategies call for tackling threats upstream before they become crises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both recognise that prevention is better than cure. And we are both changing the structure of our Armed Forces to be better prepared for building the capacity of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting opportunities to work together, to burden share and to learn from each other, just as we have done over the last decade of stabilisation and counter insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the key lesson we have learnt from Iraq and Afghanistan is that security cannot be delivered by our militaries acting alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to align all of our levers of national power and influence to achieve our objectives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, our Strategic Defence and Security Review - precisely that, not just defence but a broader security review- concluded that we need to marshal our development assistance, diplomatic efforts and defence engagement if we are to truly tackle the root causes of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the US government is also looking at how it can make its security assistance as effective as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest that this effort cannot end at national borders though. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be truly effective we need to make this a multi-national as well as multi-agency approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British military officers, working with American development experts; British diplomats working with US military stabilization teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to conclude Ladies and Gentlemen, it can sometimes seem that we take for granted, that when needs must, the Armed Forces of the US and UK can operate in the field together, in tough circumstances, sharing the dangers and risks, in appearance of seamlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this capability is not “for granted”; it didn’t occur by chance; the apparent effortlessness is born of hard work and constant attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one single month earlier this year, UK military personnel took part in 10 separate training exercises with US forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, when we do go to war together, we trust each other, we understand each other, we respect each other, and we can rely on each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bonds between our Armed Forces are special, just as the bonds between our people are special.  They took time to build and they run very deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been tested over the last decade, in the wake of 9/11, and found to be robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we now enter a new era where meeting the needs of national security and collective defence requires us to re-balance the way we do things as an Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe doing more in its own back yard as the US tilts to the Asia-Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain retains the military power to help drive this process in Europe, with France and Germany, creating greater capability, backed up by political will to act, while reinforcing our partnership with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new era for Atlanticism - still based on shared values and shared interest, but increasingly too, on a burden shared more equitably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not underestimate the challenges ahead in energising the NATO alliance to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all acutely conscious of economic and fiscal pressures to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that the threats we face are many, varied and uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing we can be certain of in this uncertain world is that we will achieve more, reach further, and be safer, if Britain and the US make a conscious decision to preserve and strengthen the remarkable and enduring collaboration we already have at so many levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my purpose in coming here today is to assure you that now, more than ever, we are ready and able to do that. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45372</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-18-f-35-lightning-ii-handover-ceremony"/>
    <title>2012/07/18 - F-35 Lightning II Handover Ceremony</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK is delighted to be the United States’ Tier One partner in this project and to be the first overseas customer to take delivery of the F-35 Lightning II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took some difficult decisions two years ago to sort out our Defence Budget that had spiralled out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That included the very tough decisions to retire early the Ark Royal aircraft carrier and its Harrier jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this has allowed us to invest in more modern, cutting edge technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is the clearest example of that as we can see before us how Britain is regenerating its Carrier Strike capability with modern, fifth generation, jets to compliment our two new aircraft carriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having spoken to some of our personnel out here I know they are very much looking forward to taking delivery of our first aircraft and are excited about the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy and Royal Air Force will start receiving frontline jets in 2016, with land-based testing and training flights through 2017, followed by initial test flights from the Queen Elizabeth carrier in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stealth jets will give us a leading role in maritime power projection and by far exceed the capabilities of the old Harriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magnificent aircraft behind us typifies the depth of the US-UK Defence relationship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not Just a Government to Government relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not even an Armed Forces to Armed Forces relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a deepening industry to industry relationship too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are continuing to build on the joint strengths of our nations’ proud histories of close co-operation to deliver truly world-beating equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having committed $2bn to the development of the F-35 Lightening II, the UK is enjoying a 15% share of the production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period of peak production is likely to sustain 25,000 jobs in the UK across a number of contractors and sub-contractors including, for instance, BAE Systems and Rolls Royce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lightning II will provide us with a flexible capability that will out perform anything we have been able to put in the field before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like to thank all those involved in getting us where we are today, from across the Armed Forces, across Government and across industry, on both sides of the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all I pay tribute to the UK personnel for all their work in achieving clearance for this aircraft today and making the Operational Test and Evaluation phase a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also very conscious that the UK’s recent decision to procure the STOVL variant has caused considerable extra effort by the Project Office and Lockheed Martin. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is very grateful to you all for your flexibility and the support you have shown as we work through these changes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am especially grateful to the Department of Defense, the US Navy and Marine Corps for their unstinting support, without which the regeneration of UK carrier capability would not be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are fully committed to the programme and the coming year will see a quickening of the pace, as we order the long lead materials and early aircraft deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larry, Bob, Frank, I am delighted to be here to witness this most important landmark in Defence aviation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handover of BK1 to the United Kingdom represents a new chapter in the long story of co-operation between our nations and industries - and a crucial step toward regeneration of Britain’s carrier strike capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now invite Lockheed Martin to start the transfer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45355</id>
    <published>2012-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-07-address-to-the-royal-united-services-institute-land-warfare-conference-2012"/>
    <title>2012/06/07 - Address to the Royal United Services Institute Land Warfare Conference 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against the backdrop of the most difficult economic situation to face the country since the 1970s and an inherited budget deficit which is the biggest in our peacetime history, the Coalition Government has been getting to grips with the long-term challenges facing Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An overheated Defence programme with a £38bn black hole at its heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, after a decade of enduring operations, the need to reform our Armed Forces to face the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Defence and Security Review has set us on a course to a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the implementation of this vision of a formidable, adaptable and flexible Future Force 2020 requires transformation in every corner of the Defence establishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A transformation that is underway, with tough decisions already taken over the last year or so, on the shape of Defence Reform, on the balance of Regular and Reserve forces, and size of the Regular Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, the decision to procure the STOVL variant of the Joint Strike Fighter for the Carriers currently being built, delivered the last piece of the jigsaw that allowed the defence budget finally to be brought back into balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with an end to enduring operations in Afghanistan now in sight, our attention turns to recovering capabilities that have been subordinated for a decade to the needs of Operations TELIC and HERRICK; planning in detail the shift to a smaller Army with its focus moving from campaigns to contingency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army 2020, as we call it, will deliver a new structure designed to meet the needs of a smaller, more flexible and agile Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set on a firm foundation, in terms of both men and materiel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well trained, well equipped, and crucially, fully funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, in opening this conference with the Chief of the General Staff, I want to talk about some of the drivers of this transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will of course appreciate that decisions on the future structure of the Army are yet to be finalised, and I so cannot and will not go into specific detail until that process is complete, whereupon I will make a full announcement to Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to set out the key underpinnings today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainability: making sure the Army is put on a stable financial footing so that everyone involved can be confident about its future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capability: making the best use of resources by maximising military effect at the front-line - reforming to prepare for the conflicts of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, integration: making sure that all elements of the Army are useable and complementary to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And properly interoperable with the Navy, the RAF, and the Marines, and with our Allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, getting the Regular-Reserve balance right as we transition to the lower regular manning levels of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want this morning to address the issue of continuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retaining the regimental system that has served the British Army so well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting the proud links to the past, while making sure the Army reflects the Britain of today and is focussed firmly on the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="facing-the-future"&gt;Facing the Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let me set this coming transformation in context, because while we can look ahead to a move from campaigns to contingency, we are not yet there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Security Strategy sets out the analysis of the environment we can expect to operate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-polar, unpredictable, with diverse threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A future in which no single country can protect all aspects of its national security acting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to meet threats as they evolve, upstream and at distance, rather than waiting for them come to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That requires the UK’s Armed Forces to be intelligent, flexible and adaptable, both in approaching the fight and during the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an expeditionary capability and a theatre-entry capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future Force 2020 is about transforming to face this future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I should be clear; our first priority at the moment remains the mission in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of this mission is a national security imperative - preventing Afghanistan from again being used as a safe haven for international terrorists and posing a threat to the UK and its allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we owe it to all those who have given so much, over the decade since operations began, to make sure that, as we draw down in concert with our Allies, we do so achieving that central aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HERRICK has been a joint operation, with critical contributions from all parts of Defence, but the Army has provided the bulk of the forces on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Army has taken the bulk of the casualties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting the Army’s contribution to Afghanistan has meant that the transformation required by the SDSR has been felt to date more keenly by the other services, particularly in regard to the move to the lower manning levels of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that, for the Army, some of the most difficult decisions are still to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move towards 2014, and an end to this enduring stabilisation operation, the pace of transformation in the Army will quicken, as we reconfigure to meet the needs of the adaptable posture with a smaller force of 82,000 regular soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many aspects of this change will be welcomed and there is a widespread understanding of the need for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a process after all being driven by the Army itself - not imposed upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience now embedded in this battle-hardened generation of service men and women is arguably greater than at any time since the Second World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must make sure we retain the skills and qualities that they have developed and that have served us so well over the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the transformation to a smaller, more flexible, agile force will see some valued colleagues leave and some units disband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty can be debilitating and impacts not just on those inside the service but on families and local communities too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot protect people from the inevitability of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can do is eliminate the uncertainty as quickly as possible so people can plan for the future and get on with their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will act as swiftly as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this important human impact, it is vital that the need for change and the direction of change is fully understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to the strategic issues I set out a few moments ago: sustainability; capability; and integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sustainability"&gt;Sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army 2020 is led by the need to recover the Army from a decade of enduring operations and transform it to face the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of us here recognise the reality that this process is not taking place in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wider national interest requires that we build for the future with strict financial discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the fiscal deficit and returning the economy to sustainable growth are themselves strategic imperatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whatever the circumstances facing the country as a whole, sorting out the huge imbalance in the Defence budget would have been necessary in any event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliminating the black hole and putting the Defence Budget and Equipment plan back into balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making certain the Armed Forces have confidence that projects in the programme are funded and will be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this has been painful: the manpower reductions; the allowance revisions; the platform deletions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they were all necessary and we have now brought the Defence Budget back into balance for the first time in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting an affordable, fully-funded core programme of just under £152bn over 10 years, which, together with the £8 billion of available unallocated headroom, delivers the equipment for Future Force 2020 and supports our current commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we move forward, you will see a new financial discipline in the way we manage that Equipment Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on long-term value rather than on short-term cash management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building-in proper contingency for the future so that the whole programme doesn’t get blown off course because a project runs over its budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Core Committed Equipment Programme includes a £4.5 billion programme of new armoured fighting vehicles for the Army such as Scout, and a £1 billion upgrade of Warrior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will now be looking at where we can bring forward further projects that enhance Army capabilities and are judged necessary on the basis of military priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking into account the recovery of platforms from Afghanistan that have been procured through the Urgent Operational Requirements system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t just some kind of book-keeping exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Efficiency and the successful application of military force are not mutually exclusive concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, military productivity, which binds them together, is a key concept in the future management of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value that our Armed Forces produce for the country is based on their capability to deliver standing military tasks and project formidable power when national security requires it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, not balancing the books, is the raison d’etre for our Armed Forces and the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But within the current financial climate, the capabilities we deliver must be efficiently produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to how we produce capability in an environment of constrained resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capability"&gt;Capability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have set out here at RUSI before, I am determined the move to Future Force 2020 will strengthen our future Defence capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining critical skills and capabilities that would be irrecoverable if we lost them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retaining the ability to scale up in the future if the threat demands it and the means permit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also determined that we rethink the way we deliver every aspect of military effect in order to maximise capability at the front-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing joint forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking innovatively about how combat service support is provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using more systematically the skills available in the Reserve and from our contractors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working closely with partners to operate logistics more rationally through Alliance structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking, sometimes, to others to provide the tail, where Britain is providing the teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving command and control to provide a stronger linkage between strategic objective and tactical effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building manoeuvre around mechanised infantry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With firepower geared to precision, rather than suppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structures much more aligned to operation in a coalition and much more aligned to the comprehensive approach across government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the ‘whole force concept’, built on three pillars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces, both Regular and Reserve; the civilians who work alongside them; and the contractors who support them on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to the third strategic issues I want to talk about today - the integration of Regular and Reserve forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="integration"&gt;Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reserve Forces currently make a significant contribution to operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade some 25,000 members of the Reserve have served in Iraq or Afghanistan, including over 18,000 members of the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Afghanistan today 679 members of the Territorial Army are currently serving in roles as diverse as infantry, medic, and explosive ordnance disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the independent report, led by the Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, concluded, the Reserve has witnessed a significant decline and, by historic standards, forms too small a part of our overall military capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By some estimates, the Territorial Army has a trained strength as low as 15,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Army 2020 provides the opportunity to transform the role of Reserve Forces in delivering capability on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be investing an additional £1.8bn over the next ten years in our Reserve Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing a progressive adjustment of the Regular/Reserve balance, while maintaining the land forces capability set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Reserves must be structured to provide, as they do today, some niche specialists capabilities that simply aren’t cost-effective to maintain on a full time basis - for example in areas of cyber, medical, or intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Future Reserve must also be able to provide on a routine basis, those capabilities across the spectrum of tasks requiring less intensive complex training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integrated Army concept means, for instance, that light infantry battalions will be reinforced on deployment through a permanent partnership with reserve units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for less complex tasks a Reserve unit could, in the future, form the basis of an operational deployment with augmentations from Regular Forces - particularly on homeland resilience duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fundamental change in role requiring a fundamental shift in approach: a New Deal for Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A higher quality Reserve that will have a far greater expectation of use and whose level of contribution will be planned, programmed, and properly resourced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Requiring more commitment from individual reservists to training and to force preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forging a new relationship between the Armed Forces, individual reservists and their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the needs of employers in this challenging economic environment and working with them as a priority to make sure that the availability the Armed Forces require is delivered to mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="continuity"&gt;Continuity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have talked about some of the big strategic issues facing the Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial discipline required to squeeze every ounce of capability from the resources available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shape of an adaptable force that meets the needs of an uncertain future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole force concept and the integration of Regular and Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also understand that people worry about how, in the midst of all this change, we will maintain a strong thread of continuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retaining the ethos, traditions and connections that are part of what makes the British Army so effective - particularly, a regimental system and regionally-focussed recruiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are perhaps the most emotionally charged issues across Army 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, a Regular Army of 82,000 will have a different structure to one of 102,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some units will inevitably be lost or will merge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to change and adapt - and that means letting go as well as building anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me be clear, we value the history and the heritage because they deliver tangible military benefits in the modern British Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not because we are slaves to history and heritage, but because they are building blocks for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that, in the words of Field Marshall Viscount Slim, “tradition, instead of being a pair of handcuffs that fetters you, will be a handrail to steady and guide you in steep places.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me say it clearly: There is no question, as some have suggested, of abandoning the regimental system in the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that does not mean that we can avoid difficult decisions as the Army gets smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in making those decisions, the military voice must prevail; ensuring that the Army remains the capable and agile force envisaged in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting the generation of coherent capability first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, that even with a reduced Regular manning requirement, the Army faces a major recruitment challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to 2020, the Army will recruit against the backdrop of, we hope and expect, a growing economy, and without the recruiting-sergeant of an enduring overseas operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demographic changes suggest particular challenges in some regions to supply the number of recruits to the infantry that are required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against a background of an increasing UK population overall, it is projected there will be around 12% fewer males by 2020 in the typical infantry recruiting age range. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although all regions face this decline, there is some local variation: in particular, the south and south east of England will see the lowest decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we are determined to maintain an effective regimental system, it must be based on the realities of today, and the primacy of capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means focussing on analysis of recruitment performance, demographic trends and future recruiting needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking account of regional identities, previous mergers, disbandments and deletions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to support proper career advancement for soldiers and officers alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the criteria against which our decisions must be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on which I expect to make announcements to Parliament in the coming weeks, as soon as the CGS has completed that important piece of analytical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, the Army has seen several transformations since the end of World War II; the transition from a wartime structure to the Cold War; from conscription to a professional force; and the downsizing at the end of the Cold War in Options for Change and Frontline First. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now it is embarking on another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle-hardened structure, grown used to the predictable cycles of deployment imposed by TELIC and HERRICK, will need to re-learn the skills of agility and flexibility as we move from campaigns to contingency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the balanced, capable and adaptable force structure required to face the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting capability and prioritising combat effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the whole force concept and integrating the reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through it all, maintaining its identity in the face of significant change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The values of the Army have sustained it through countless previous transformations; they have sustained it over the last decade of enduring campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those same values - courage, discipline, respect, integrity, loyalty, selflessness - will sustain it through this transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, no doubt, through many further iterations in the decades and centuries ahead as this most enduring of British institutions looks confidently to a future in which it continues to adapt to an ever changing world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55366</id>
    <published>2012-05-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/injured-personnel-display-garden-at-chelsea-flower-show"/>
    <title>Injured personnel display garden at Chelsea Flower Show</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staff and patients are exhibiting their display, the Courtyard Garden, at the prestigious event for the first time today. It will give them the chance to show how successful their horticulture as therapy scheme has become at Headley Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chelsea installation, designed by the show’s longest-serving exhibitor Geoff Whiten, is an example of a permanent garden that has been built at Headley Court to help patients rehabilitate from their injuries. It is also a collaboration with military charity Gardening Leave, who work with the Armed Forces community to improve the mental and physical well-being of personnel using horticultural therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical evidence has shown horticulture provides physical, neurological, cognitive and psychological rehabilitation. It tests patients’ motor skills, as well as their strength and endurance. There is also evidence to suggest that being in an outdoor environment reduces stress, leading to improved concentration and helping individuals think through their problems or concerns.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain David Henson (centre) and Sergeant Craig Gadd, a Royal Engineer from 23 Engineer Regiment, with Chelsea Pensioner Frank Melton at the debut of Headley Court's Courtyard Garden at the Chelsea Flower Show" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5011/Injured_personnel_display_garden_at_Chelsea_Flower_Show_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain David Henson (centre) and Sergeant Craig Gadd, a Royal Engineer from 23 Engineer Regiment, with Chelsea Pensioner Frank Melton at the debut of Headley Court's Courtyard Garden at the Chelsea Flower Show [Picture: Sergeant Alison Baskerville RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Exhibiting at the Chelsea Flower Show is a great achievement and shows the determination of our injured Service personnel when recovering from injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By using innovative ways to provide rehabilitation, the staff at Headley Court have shown time and time again the facility gives first-class treatment for those who need it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Peter Le Feuvre, a military physiotherapist at Headley Court and a keen gardener himself, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The horticulture as therapy project has really grown over time. It started off with the refurbishment of some greenhouses and creation of allotments in the grounds of Headley Court. It became clear a bigger garden would provide an outside rehabilitation area and somewhere for patients to be able to have some contemplative time to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Headley Court ‘Test Track’ garden features slopes, steps, uneven surfaces and different cambers. Learning to negotiate these different terrains is critical to enable the successful use of a prosthetic limb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The garden introduces these features in a gradual way, enabling the patients to increase their skills on a prosthetic and allows us to see the improvement in someone’s motor skills through the repetition of activities such as walking up steps.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Test Track garden has been built with help from a team from Sutton and East Surrey Water, with the planting devised and undertaken by horticulture lecturer Thomas Meenagh and students from Oatridge College in Ecclesmachan, Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Meenagh’s son, Private Scott Meenagh, from 2nd Battalion The Parachute Regiment, has been treated at Headley Court after he lost both legs when he was caught in an improvised explosive device blast in Afghanistan last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Meenagh said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very proud to be involved in the rehabilitation garden project as Headley Court has helped my son and his colleagues to recover from the injuries they sustained in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is an incredibly worthwhile project for Headley Court to undertake and it also gives my horticulture students the chance to do practical work in a different environment to what they may already be used to and gain valuable experience for their studies.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Meenagh added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I never thought I would follow my dad’s interest in horticulture but being involved in the gardening project at Headley Court has really helped my rehabilitation following my injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think the new Test Track will help other patients come to terms with the challenges of learning to use prosthetics and to navigate everyday obstacles like steps. The garden will add to the fantastic facilities that are already here at Headley Court.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18768</id>
    <published>2012-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-14-address-to-the-3rd-annual-electrical-infrastructure-security-summit"/>
    <title>2012/05/14 - Address to the 3rd Annual Electrical Infrastructure Security Summit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to be here today at the 3rd annual EISS summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am extremely grateful to James [ARBUTHNOT], not just for his work as Chair of the Defence Select Committee, but for the efforts he makes personally to ensure attention in the UK is focussed on the threats it needs to be focussed on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can take personal credit for opening my eyes to the problems we face in protecting the critical electrical systems and our critical networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most positive aspects of this annual event is that it brings together people from very different professional backgrounds, with different skill-sets and different expertise - but who share a common interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to make sure threats to our infrastructure, whether from natural or man-made sources, are investigated, assessed, monitored and indeed mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists and security analysts; energy experts and astronomers; the public and the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a multi-disciplinary problem, so it means all of us working together across traditional boundaries, including across government departments - sometimes the most difficult bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a global problem, so it means countries working together across international borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to give a particular welcome to the representatives from around the world who are gathered here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand representatives from 20 countries are here today, working together to address a complex set of problems, demanding a complex set of responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A part of the intricate web of threats we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-layered, asymmetrical, unconventional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often requiring a defence and security response that is not based on traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That cannot be met using infantry, or jet planes or destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one of the big challenges we face as politicians, particularly at a time of limited resources, is to make the case for spending on defence and security solutions that cannot readily be seen by the taxpaying public who are financing this - that cannot be shown off on the parade ground - that sometimes cannot be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk today about the progress the UK Government has made, since the EISS summit in Washington last year, in strengthening resilience in the face of specific threats to electrical networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Secretary of State for Defence, I have a particular concern to ensure that we deter and prevent any prospect of a large-scale malicious attack and that the UK’s Armed Forces have the ability to respond to such an event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me first talk about the profile of the threat, because in an era of fiscal challenge, limited resources must be deployed with pin-point accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That needs a deep understanding of the risks and the discipline to tailor our response rigorously and proportionately to those risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scattergun is not an affordable weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="vulnerability"&gt;VULNERABILITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the developed world, our connected, high-technology societies are massively reliant on electronic networks, and becoming ever more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, electronic technology reaches into every part of government, every business, every home, and increasingly, with mobile and wi-fi technology, pretty much every pocket in the country. Dependence creates vulnerability, and connectivity compounds that vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take away the technology and our modern life-support system falters - it’s not just light and heat - it’s the digital computers and automated systems that help run many things we rely on - from health care to the transport system, from ATMs and EPOS terminals to the food distribution network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sustained black-out covering a large geographical area could have crippling consequences and do serious damage to the welfare of our citizens, as well as the functioning of our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the resilience of the systems that help run our society is a concern of our domestic civil contingencies organisation, and assessing the risks to those systems is a matter of national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, we take a holistic approach to risk assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working through the National Security Council, with its multi-disciplinary cross-government approach, we ensure or try to ensure that all avenues are explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest National Risk Register for Civil Emergencies was published in January and the update of the National Security Risk Assessment, last undertaken as part of the 2010 National Security Strategy, will be completed later this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have a robust foundation upon which our plans are laid and resource allocation decisions are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of today, I want to address two risks to our electrical infrastructure that I know are of concern, and which formed the basis of a recent House of Commons Defence Select Committee Report, and set out how we are acting to mitigate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is man-made and hostile: the employment of a nuclear weapon to generate a high-altitude electro-magnetic pulse, or HEMP, taking out electrical and digital systems over possibly thousands of square miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A threat in which I, as Defence Secretary, have an obvious and specific interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is natural and impossible to prevent: a severe electro-magnetic storm caused by solar activity that has the capacity to cause significant disturbance to communication and power systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="high-altitude-electro-magnetic-pulse"&gt;HIGH-ALTITUDE ELECTRO MAGNETIC PULSE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me deal first with the issue of a HEMP attack using a nuclear weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me be crystal clear:  A HEMP attack using a nuclear weapon against, or affecting, the United Kingdom, or our vital interests, or those of our allies, would be considered a nuclear attack on the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences for the perpetrator of a nuclear weapon being used as a HEMP device would therefore be severe and any potential aggressor should be aware that we will respond proportionately against any state that launches or enables such an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s nuclear weapons are an important element of our capability so to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, although we must remain alert to the risk, we judge the likelihood of a HEMP attack against our homeland to be low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would require a combination of warhead and missile capabilities that is restricted at present to a few states, none of whom, we judge, currently have the intent to conduct a HEMP attack, and all of whom would understand the severe consequences of such aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not expect that development of a HEMP capability would be a priority for a non-state actor when weighed against the other options they may have the capacity to achieve - such as a dirty bomb or other asymmetric methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK focus is therefore aimed at preventing a HEMP threat becoming imminent and immediate - through deterrence, counter-proliferation and multi-lateral disarmament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work to better understand and promote awareness of the threat, including internationally, supporting the International Electrotechnical Commission’s work on HEMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot discount the risk that a nuclear-based HEMP threat to our vital interests will not emerge by 2050, which is our planning horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while large nuclear arsenals and the possibility of proliferation exist, nuclear deterrence at a minimum effective level, will remain an important element in our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no complacency and the significant resources we are investing in the UK maintaining and, in 2020s, renewing Trident are testament to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the low likelihood of a HEMP threat arising means that extra resources may be better directed towards threats, for example, in the cyber domain, where an attack against our electronic arteries would be deniable, cheaper, have a more certain effect and therefore be more likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is just what the Government is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the UK considers a nuclear HEMP attack to be of low likelihood, we consider there is the significant possibility of a space weather event over the next 5 years that has the potential to cause disruption to the United Kingdom’s electrical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="space-weather"&gt;SPACE WEATHER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With cyclical solar activity set to peak next year we should prepare for the possibility of some level of disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is when and how much, not if.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low level disruption due to solar activity is of course a fact of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is how we prepare for an event of sufficient magnitude that widespread damage is caused to satellite systems or electrical circuits, leading to the sustained interruption of power or communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have in place monitoring systems and predictive models that deliver sufficient warning of severe events to enable us to take preventative action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need to have a far better understanding of the vulnerabilities in our networks, better to deploy our mitigation effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will enable systems to be hardened only where they need to be and for resources to be used wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By focussing on the most critical systems we can minimise the cost and maximise the effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a world class scientific base, and so we are well positioned to contribute to the collaborative efforts taking place internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Survey has a leading role in the EU space weather forecasting project for satellite operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Geological Society is working with European partners to assess the threat posed by magnetic storms to power distribution networks in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing partnership between the UK Met Office and the US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) is particularly encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Memorandum of Understanding signed between the Met Office and NOAA last year has paved the way for the creation of a space weather model capable of indicating where, when, and for how long, space weather effects will persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Summit can of course contribute greatly to the understanding of the issues we face in common and help to focus the work that is on-going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, government departments have been working extensively with space weather scientists and engineers, industry and regulators to gain the best available quantitative assessment of the risk to UK infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a broad and diverse programme of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has worked with external experts to review the National Risk Assessment to make sure new and emerging risks are detected and the understanding of current risks is right up to date. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Energy Emergencies Executive Committee keeps contingency plans up to date and has provided the National Grid and the Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change with a solid body of work to help analyse the impacts of space weather events and build predictive models that will improve contingency planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supergrid transformer design requirements have changed as a result, and strategic reserve holdings of transformers are being increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Grid is working with the British Geological Survey to make sure there is robust real-time network monitoring in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Space Security Policy is due to be published later in the year and will look at all these risks in a much wider context, to make sure all parts of Government are working effectively together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of Britain’s military equipment is designed to work in challenging electro-magnetic environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shielding developed in this context - against interference, discovery or detection for example - can provide some protection against electro-magnetic effects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critical military infrastructure can, of course, operate independently of the national grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD’s Defence Science and Technology Laboratory has a great deal of expertise in working with industry hardening and assessing electronic systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want the MOD to contribute actively to the improvement of the UK’s civil infrastructure resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is quite a lot of information on EMP protection from the Government and others that is already in the public domain, for example that published by the International Electrotechnical Commission, and the MOD itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD will now explore with others in Government whether there is more that we can share with civilian infrastructure providers, including, for example, sensitive elements of the Defence Standards on EMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectively, we have to change the way people think about Defence and Security. This is a challenge for us all. It is about recognising the new dependencies and vulnerabilities that flow from the way people now live their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about recognising that the solutions may require committing resources to defences you can’t see or hear or touch.  And persuading our taxpayers that it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting the hi-tech networks that power our global society is part of this new way of thinking - and new way of acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predicting and monitoring; preparing and mitigating; nationally and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assessing risk and responding proportionately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that today is another step forward in helping us banish any lingering complacency and that we can continue to work together to ensure that the dependence on electrical networks and digital control systems that has so enhanced our quality of life and standard of living, does not become our Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
