<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/philip-dunne</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-dunne.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Philip Dunne MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65593</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T10:38:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-pistols-for-uk-armed-forces"/>
    <title>New pistols for UK Armed Forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Armed Forces are to be supplied with more than 25,000 new Glock sidearms to replace the ageing Browning pistols currently in service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://us.glock.com/products/model/g17gen4" title="Glock 17 Gen4 pistol web page"&gt;Glock 17 Gen4 pistol&lt;/a&gt; is not only much lighter than the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/forceprotection/browning9mmpistol.cfm" title="Browning 9mm pistol web page"&gt;Browning L9A1&lt;/a&gt;, it is also more accurate and its magazines can carry more bullets. It has an increased magazine capacity of 17 rounds, compared to 13 rounds for the Browning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel across all 3 Services will begin to receive the new 9-millimetre (mm) calibre Glock 17s in the coming weeks and troops deployed to Afghanistan will be among the first to use the new weapon. The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.vikingarms.com/" title="Viking Arms Ltd website"&gt;Viking Arms &lt;abbr title="Limited"&gt;Ltd&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Harrogate, Yorkshire, also includes more than 25,000 holsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Glock 17 pistol (left) and a Browning 9mm pistol" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6012/ArmyHQ-2013-003-052_aGlock_17_pistol_EMBARG_00.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Glock 17 pistol (left) and the Browning the new pistols will replace [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Mark Anderson, Royal Marines, who trialled the new weapon before the contract was awarded, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pistols are vital in close combat and are a key part of a soldier’s armoury. Reliable, light and easy to carry, the Glock inspires confidence and performs exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide our troops with the best possible personal kit available and these new Glock 17s will give them greater firepower and accuracy on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Glock pistol is fired on a range" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6013/Emb_DES-2013-003-0250.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines firearms instructor Sergeant Steve Lord demonstrates the new Glock pistol on the range at Woolwich Barracks in London [Picture: Andrew Linnett, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sidearms are a valuable weapon for servicemen and women on the battlefield, and the new Glock, manufactured in Austria, will complement the wide range of weapons already available to our forces, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA80A2 assault rifles, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light machine guns, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharpshooter rifles, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;general purpose machine guns, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;combat shotguns, which fire 12-gauge cartridges; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sniper systems, which fire 8.59mm rounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Glock pistols will replace the Browning which after being used by the Armed Forces for more than 40 years has become increasingly expensive to maintain. The contract for a replacement pistol was put out to tender 2 years ago and is not in response to any specific or increased threat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60241</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:25:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-258-million-sea-king-helicopter-support-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £258 million Sea King helicopter support contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MOD has agreed a £258 million contract to support Sea King helicopters, which will sustain 500 jobs across the UK.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; fleets of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-Mk5" title="Sea King Mk5"&gt;Sea Kings&lt;/a&gt; are best known for providing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/UK/Search-and-Rescue" title="Search and Rescue"&gt;Search and Rescue&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt;) services in the UK and Falkland Islands. They can also be used to carry troops and provide airborne surveillance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extension to the Sea King Integrated Operational Support (&lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt;) contract will ensure continued technical and maintenance support for the 90-strong helicopter fleet for the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD originally signed the &lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt; arrangement with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.agustawestland.com/" title="AgustaWestland"&gt;AgustaWestland&lt;/a&gt; in 2005 and this is the final phase of the deal which is expected to sustain around 500 jobs at AgustaWestland’s UK headquarters at Yeovil, in the industry supply chain and at several &lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt; bases across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5786/45153254g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter is pictured on an operation over Helmand Province, Afghanistan (stock image) [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This phase of the contract will provide support until Sea King is retired from service in 2016 and replaced by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin MK1"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Sea King helicopter fleet has been in service for over 40 years providing a vital capability in air/sea rescue and surveillance. This maintenance agreement, securing 500 jobs across the UK, demonstrates our commitment to keeping this aircraft in top condition until it is retired from service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy Captain Tony Gray, Defence Equipment and Support Sea King Team Leader, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing this contract ensures value for money for the taxpayer while maintaining the provision of search-and-rescue helicopters around the UK, 24-hours-a-day throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56977</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-to-auction-off-radio-spectrum"/>
    <title>MOD to auction off radio spectrum</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Ministry of Defence is planning to auction some of its radio spectrum in the first direct sale of its kind by a government department.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radio spectrum refers to the radio waves over which all wireless communication takes place, including radio, television, radar, satellite, mobile voice and data. Under plans announced today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to auction around 200 Megahertz (&lt;abbr title="Megahertz"&gt;MHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) of its spectrum usage rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes as market demand for extra spectrum is mounting, fuelled by the sharp rise in the use of spectrum-hungry devices such as smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale will give private operators the chance to buy more spectrum to support the introduction of fourth-generation mobile services to people in cities, towns and villages across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively the spectrum could be used by fixed-line operators to provide wireless access to broadband services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum being sold by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is all below 15 Gigahertz (&lt;abbr title="Gigahertz"&gt;GHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is regarded as the most useful and valuable part of the radio spectrum because of its wide range of applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of all spectrum below 15GHz is held by the public sector and is used for a broad range of services including defence, emergency services, transport and science. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; holds around three-quarters of all publicly-held spectrum and one-third of all spectrum below 15GHz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome this opportunity to free up much-needed spectrum. We hope that the sale will help drive the roll-out of new generation networks and universal access to broadband, both of which are vital to the UK’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale follows the announcement made in the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/spend_index.htm" title="Spending Review"&gt;2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; that at least 500MHz of public spectrum below 5GHz will be released by 2020 for new mobile communications uses. The spectrum to be sold off is being cleared of military users to contribute towards this target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are expected to start at the end of 2013, with the auction completed by the summer of 2014. Ahead of this, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to produce an Industry Brochure in early spring 2013 and to host an Industry Day in early summer 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55926</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65 million contract to refit HMS Ocean</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65 million upgrade, securing more than 600 UK jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The warship was moored on the Thames during the London 2012 Olympic Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at Devonport Royal Dockyard in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project, securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to the ship’s radar, gun, command system and living quarters. In addition, around 1,200 metres of new pipework will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter Number 10 Dock at Devonport Royal Dockyard to begin her refit [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympics duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28542</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T17:03:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-46-million-submarine-command-system-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £46 million submarine command system contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A £46 million contract to support and maintain a new combat system across the Royal Navy's submarine fleet has been awarded to BAE Systems.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Design Services Arrangement contract will ensure that the system, which is used to navigate vessels as well as gather intelligence and defend against attacks, is maintained and developed over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy operates three classes of submarine, totalling 10 vessels, which are used to safeguard the UK’s interests around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, different combat systems are used across the fleet. This new contract will help drive adoption of a common combat system across all current and future Royal Navy submarines, with considerable benefits to training, maintenance and updating costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="John Hudson, Philip Dunne and Rear Admiral Simon Lister" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1364/20121206subs01_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;John Hudson, Managing Director of BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines, Philip Dunne, and Director Submarines Rear Admiral Simon Lister (library image) [Picture: Mike Vallance, BAE Systems]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s submarine fleet is second-to-none and plays a key role in protecting our waters and interests both at home and abroad. This latest commitment to maintain and develop this vital technology throughout the fleet will ensure that we can continue delivering first class capability for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Command Systems on board our submarines contain many vital technologies and it is very important that our submarines retain their technological edge, both now and in the future. This contract will help secure that position for the MOD and UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/our-company-rzz/our-businesses/maritime---submarines" title="BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines"&gt;BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines&lt;/a&gt; and will safeguard around a total of 30 jobs at the company’s sites in Ash Vale in Surrey and Weymouth in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17638</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T15:39:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-helps-small-firms-showcase-defence-innovation"/>
    <title>MOD helps small firms showcase defence innovation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>MOD held its first 'Marketplace' event today allowing small UK businesses to pitch ideas to some of the world's biggest defence companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organised by the Ministry of Defence’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.science.mod.uk/engagement/enterprise.aspx" title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;Centre for Defence Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;, the event gives small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a unique opportunity to engage with big business and offer up ideas and technology that could be used by the Armed Forces in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs were joined at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre in London by academics and researchers from two of the country’s leading universities - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/" title="University of Bristol"&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/" title="Lancaster University"&gt;Lancaster University&lt;/a&gt; - who also had products to pitch to industry representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies on show at the event were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbsr.co.uk/" title="Blue Bear Systems Research"&gt;Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s ‘Morphing Wing’ - based on the dynamics of a bird’s wing, this is designed to enable the next generation of unmanned aerial vehicles to be faster, more agile and have greater stability and duration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dreampact.com/" title="Dreampact Ltd"&gt;Dreampact Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s compact heat-sensing video camera - a handheld camera that can also be mounted on a rifle to allow more effective surveillance operations in pitch darkness, bad fog or dust.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1288/DSC_0837.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne speaks at the inaugural Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s ‘Marketplace’ provides a shop window for small and medium-sized enterprises in the most practical sense, helping those which have received research and development funding from the MOD to access their full potential for commercial applications in the UK defence sector and the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation is vital to our national security and the country’s economic growth. We remain committed to providing our Armed Forces with the very best equipment available, which is why we will continue to invest over £400m a year in Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jono Byrne, Head of the Centre for Defence Enterprise, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we have broken fresh ground in developing the Department’s engagement with small and medium-sized enterprises and academia. Over half of our contracts go to small and medium-sized enterprises and academia and it is vital that we are able to bring these Centre for Defence Enterprise-funded innovators, their ideas and capabilities, into the defence supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne chats with delegates" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1289/DSC_0941.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne chats with delegates at the Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted with the response and support we have had from prime contractors as they too understand the benefits such a concept can bring. This is only the start for the ‘Marketplace’ and, like all good innovation, I look forward to further improvement; for example, making use of online tools and involving investment companies as well as defence companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Kurth, Managing Director of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.boeing.co.uk/Products-Services/Boeing-Defence-UK" title="Boeing Defence UK"&gt;Boeing Defence UK&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to attend the inaugural ‘Marketplace’ event and look forward to seeing the areas of technology the Centre for Defence Enterprise has identified in support of our Armed Forces. We see the ‘Marketplace’ as a fantastic opportunity to engage with small and medium-sized enterprises that have relevant innovation and technology for potential work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise (CDE) is committed to finding new revolutionary ideas and working to make them a reality in the future. Since 2008 the CDE has received more than 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at over £35m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17595</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T15:05:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-contracts-safeguard-hundreds-of-uk-shipyard-jobs"/>
    <title>MOD contracts safeguard hundreds of UK shipyard jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Around 800 jobs in the UK maritime sector have been safeguarded after the MOD extended five maintenance contracts worth a total of £349m.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contracts cover the long-term maintenance of the Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) Flotilla of naval support ships. They have been awarded to five British companies and will secure a further five years of maintenance support for the 13-strong RFA Flotilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of fuel tankers, stores ships, a medical facility and landing ships, the RFA provides essential support such as food, fuel, munitions and other vital supplies to the Royal Navy at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cammell-laird.com/" title="Cammell Laird website"&gt;Cammell Laird Shiprepairers &amp;amp; Shipbuilders Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Birkenhead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ap-group.co.uk/" title="A&amp;amp;P Group website"&gt;A&amp;amp;P Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt; (ship repair facility), based in Falmouth&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lr.org/default.aspx" title="Lloyd's Register website"&gt;Lloyd’s Register&lt;/a&gt;, based in Bristol&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.trimline.co.uk/" title="Trimline Ltd website"&gt;Trimline Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Southampton&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hempel.com/" title="Hempel UK Ltd website"&gt;Hempel UK Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Cwmbran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="United States warship alongside RFA Cardigan Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1283/FJ120053055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;United States warship USS Devastator (left) alongside the Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Cardigan Bay (library image) [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Simpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships are crucial to the work of the Royal Navy and without them it simply could not operate. These substantial contracts will not only safeguard hundreds of UK jobs but will ensure that these ships can continue in their roles for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Commercially Supported Shipping for Defence, Equipment and Support, Commodore (RFA) David Preston, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These contracts represent the best value for money for Defence and each of the companies has a proven track record in supporting the Royal Fleet Auxiliary on a worldwide basis. This ability to support the Royal Navy wherever they are deployed is critical to UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA personnel are uniformed civil servants employed under the UK Merchant Shipping Act. They are structurally aligned with the Royal Navy and have a high level of specialist military training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17580</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T14:58:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/25m-mod-weapons-contract-sustains-450-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£25m MOD weapons contract sustains 450 UK jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Manufacturing jobs in the British defence industry have been secured by a £25m contract for Paveway IV precision weapons for the RAF.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has agreed to purchase additional &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/paveway4.cfm" title="Paveway IV"&gt;Paveway IV&lt;/a&gt; bombs from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raytheon.co.uk/" title="Raytheon UK"&gt;Raytheon UK&lt;/a&gt;. These weapons are to be carried by our Tornados in Afghanistan and will also provide a key capability to be carried by the Typhoon and Lightning II aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract announced today will sustain around 450 jobs at Raytheon UK’s plants. It will secure 300 highly skilled defence sector jobs in Glenrothes, Scotland, and 150 in Harlow, Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also sustain a number of jobs at Raytheon’s subcontractors - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.portav.com/" title="Portsmouth Aviation"&gt;Portsmouth Aviation Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, Exelis in Brighton, Chemring in Ardeer and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thalesgroup.com/" title="Thales Group"&gt;Thales&lt;/a&gt; in Basingstoke, Hampshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paveway IV proved highly effective during the 2011 air campaign over Libya. Its global positioning system technology gives the UK the capability to conduct 24-hour precision attacks against a wide range of targets. Aircrew also have the ability to reprogramme the weapon during a mission, offering capability to attack a wider range of targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This highly sophisticated UK-developed and manufactured weapon is the backbone of the RAF’s precision bombing capability. This contract to boost the MOD’s weapon stocks will sustain hundreds of skilled jobs in the defence manufacturing sector in both Scotland and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By balancing the Defence Budget, we are able to commit with confidence to equipment programmes which help to safeguard our national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paveway munitions have long been a success story for the Royal Air Force in terms of their precision bombing capability. The ability to operate in any weather means that we are able to support operations 24/7. Paveway IV weapons are a real asset, not only to the Royal Air Force, but also to Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the MOD has this year awarded contracts worth more than £100m to Raytheon for orders of around 1,600 Paveway IV bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
