<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/philip-hammond</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-hammond.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon  Philip Hammond MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2011-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14825</id>
    <published>2011-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/independent-review-recommends-a-fresh-start-for-the-management-of-england-s-strategic-roads"/>
    <title>Independent review recommends ‘a fresh start’ for the management of England’s strategic roads</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major savings for taxpayers and benefits for the national economy could be unlocked by reforming the government’s management of England’s motorways and trunk roads, says an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/strategic-roads-network"&gt;independent review&lt;/a&gt; published today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the day of the publication of the review, Alan Cook said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The management of our strategic roads is at odds with every other major infrastructure sector in the UK. By applying the lessons learnt by the best performing companies in other sectors, there is the potential to save taxpayers at least £200 million a year after 5 years, and to provide a much better service for road users and the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The report recommends that the Secretary of State for Transport should take on a new, more strategic role in the management of the network, providing longer-term funding certainty for the organisation and acting as a champion for the interests of road users and the economy through a performance specification with tough new targets for efficiency and customer service. Alongside of this, the report also recommends reforming the status of the current Highways Agency, giving it a more independent board, which can make better and more flexible commercial decisions with greater financial autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The importance of this network to the growth of the economy is enormous. It handles a third of all traffic in England and two-thirds of all freight traffic. But policy makers need to be much clearer about what they want the network to deliver in return for the public money that is spent on it. Meeting the country’s current economic and financial challenges demands a change in our approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/strategic-roads-network"&gt;full report and a set of frequently asked questions is available&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The review was announced in April 2011 by the Secretary of State for Transport. It has been led by Alan Cook, who is the Non-Executive Chairman of the Highways Agency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For further details, or to request an interview with Alan Cook, please contact Amelia Yeodal on 07789 017 212 or email &lt;a href="mailto:amelia.yeodal@highways.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;amelia.yeodal@highways.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16143</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/transport-times-national-transport-awards"/>
    <title>Transport Times, National Transport Awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction. It’s a pleasure to be with you all this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event is a celebration of excellence and achievement by some of the brightest and the best in the transport industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With everything from innovations in transport planning, to improving safety, to safeguarding the environment, the shortlist of nominations for this year demonstrates clearly the innovation and dedication that exists throughout this exciting sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen nominations for individuals and teams; employees and operators; small projects and big projects; local and national initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All very different, yet all with something in common - because every single one of them shows the difference that the people of this industry make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-infrastructure---a-fundamental-component-of-the-economy"&gt;Transport infrastructure - a fundamental component of the economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason this event matters is because transport matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started this job, nearly 18 months ago, I made clear that Britain’s transport system should be an engine for economic recovery - playing a vital role in getting this country open for business again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern transport networks are the arteries of commerce, moving people to the workplace and goods to the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we modernise our infrastructure, and encourage more sustainable forms of travel, we can cut carbon emissions, improve air quality, and offer a cleaner, greener transport system and a better quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having inherited a deficit greater than any in our nation’s peacetime history, it would have been easy for us to slash capital investment and side-step the politically challenging cuts in current spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest, for decades this has been the traditional response of British governments to fiscal pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And transport is usually a favourite target of the swinging axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, not this time, and not this government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been prepared to take the tough decisions on current spending programmes and on welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-investments"&gt;Transport investments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from being targeted, transport capital emerged as a major winner in last year’s spending review - with a commitment to invest over £30 billion in road, rail and local transport capital projects right across our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s more than Labour invested in the previous four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are prioritising the projects that will get Britain back on the path to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest programme of rail investment since the Victorian era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2,700 new rail carriages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive rail electrification programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green light for Crossrail and Thameslink and the Intercity Express Train&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multi-billion pound tube upgrade programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re investing £400 million in support for ultra low emission vehicles to progressively green our car fleet - while bringing a new Nissan production line to Sunderland with hundreds of new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping to get Britain making things again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="re-inventing-how-we-work"&gt;Re-inventing how we work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So transport investment can be a driver for economic growth. But transport also has to contribute to deficit reduction. And our commitment to investment must be balanced with a determination to re-examine and re-invent the way we do business, so we maximise efficiency and value for public money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on our railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you all know, our railways are among the most expensive in Europe - with some of the highest fares in Europe and the highest levels of taxpayer subsidy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the short term, we’ve had to take another tough decision: to increase fares above inflation, so we can carry on investing to tackle overcrowding and unreliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it simply isn’t sustainable to go on paying for the inefficiency of the railway with above inflation fare rises and massive public subsidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to solve this problem from the bottom up - by improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Theresa Villiers, the rail Minister, and I will shortly publish a comprehensive blueprint for reforming our railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking the hard questions about taxpayer subsidy…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and considering the options for greater local commissioning of services,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as we seek to drive cost-saving innovations in service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking again at the role of government, Network Rail, and the train operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aligning the interests of all the parties&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making Train Operators more accountable to their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and Network Rail more accountable to the train operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And giving railway employees a real interest in the success of the companies they work for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also looking ahead to the future with our plans for a new high speed rail network linking London, Birmingham, Manchester and Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a project that would transform the social and economic geography of Britain - slashing journey times and putting desperately-needed new capacity on our railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as helping to close the North-South gap that has plagued our economy for so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aviation"&gt;Aviation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking of the longer term, we’re also working with the industry to develop a new long-term strategy for aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working out how best to plan for aviation expansion on a sustainable basis, within the limits implied by our carbon reduction targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting out a way forward for the next 40 years that will generate economic growth, meet our decarbonisation objectives, and manage the noise, and other impacts on local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kickstarting what will be, I hope, a new chapter in the aviation policy debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="roads"&gt;Roads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we are thinking smarter about how we get our roads and motorways working better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re investing £10 billion in our roads as part of the spending review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’ve already talked about our intention to ensure that the car can retain a place in our future transport plans - by focussing on the real enemy, the carbon, rather than bashing the motorist, and making sure Britain becomes a leader in Europe in low-emission vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also have to be innovative and flexible about making the best use of the roads we have already paid for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one area, it might be peak time, or even permanent, hard shoulder running to ease congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another, it might be variable speed limits to keep traffic flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, we’re consulting on a new motorway speed limit - a move that would put Britain back in the fast lane of global economies, boost productivity and deliver hundreds of millions of pounds of economic benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping ensure our strategic roads become the arteries of commerce they were always intended to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="localism"&gt;Localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just about our national networks. The transport issues that most concern communities are often local in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, for far too long in this country, important decisions about local transport have been taken, and monitored, centrally - by Ministers and civil servants sitting in Whitehall, ticking boxes and filling in forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we overhauled the way funding is delivered - slashing the number of separate local transport grant streams from 26 to just four, giving local authorities much greater flexibility and freedom to decide their own priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have recently announced my intention to consult on how we can fully devolve decisions and funding for local capital transport improvements to ‘Local Transport Consortia’, each made up of a number of local enterprise partnerships and their constituent local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting decision making power where it belongs - in the hands of local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="all-the-nominees-should-feel-very-proud-of-themselves"&gt;All the nominees should feel very proud of themselves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are important times for the transport industry - no doubt about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we seek to ride out the economic storm, we must continue to target investment where it makes the most difference, find new and innovative ways to fund capital expenditure, and continue relentlessly to control the costs of the projects we undertake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, it will be a tough challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if these awards tonight demonstrate anything, it is that those who work in our transport sector have the capability, the ingenuity, and the commitment to meet that challenge head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because when push comes to shove, it’s the people in transport who really make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make the difference because they understand the needs of the businesses and individuals that use our transport networks every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make the difference because of their commitment to meeting those needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they make the difference through the skills they bring to delivering those vital transport improvements on the ground (or in the air!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who, and what, we are honouring tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And over the coming months and years, I look forward to working with all of you to make our shared vision of a world-class British transport system a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thank you for listening, have a great night and the best of luck to all the nominees as they wait to hear if they have won an award.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14860</id>
    <published>2011-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-bridge-over-the-mersey"/>
    <title>New bridge over the Mersey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond today gave the green light for up to £470m of funding for a new bridge across the River Mersey between Runcorn and Widnes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new dual three-lane bridge and associated link roads will form a major new transport route improving links between the Liverpool City region, north Cheshire and the wider North West to the rest of the country.  It will also ease the significant congestion currently experienced by users of the Silver Jubilee Bridge, reducing journey times by up to 10 minutes at peak times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction of the new bridge - known as the Mersey Gateway Bridge - is expected to begin in 2013 and is due to be open for traffic in 2016.  The construction cost (including land) is around £600m which the Department for Transport will support with a mixture of capital grant and revenue funding for the bridge’s continued operation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existing Silver Jubilee Bridge, located 1.5 miles to the west of the planned bridge, will be converted into a local traffic bridge with priority for buses and improved conditions for pedestrians and cyclists.  There will be toll charges for those using both crossings to help fund a significant proportion of the scheme.  The funding provides for discount schemes, which would be prioritised for local and regular users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Mersey Gateway Bridge is an important transport project which will improve journeys and boost economic growth.  It will not only provide much needed traffic relief for the existing Silver Jubilee Bridge, but also help to regenerate the Borough of Halton, the Liverpool city region and the wider north west by improving transport links, maximising local development and regional economic growth opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In response to the Government’s request to reduce costs, Halton Borough Council have achieved savings of around £30m on the original proposed cost - meaning the scheme will offer better value to the taxpayer, whilst bringing vital improvements to the region. Further cost savings are expected through a competitive procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was determined to ensure that the agreed funding package represented a robust and sustainable funding model for the bridge that protected both the taxpayers and the residents of Halton.  This is a good result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have already committed to support local transport schemes across England to the value of £870m in the current spending review period, with a further £650m worth of schemes expected to be funded in December. This means we will have invested £1.5bn on improving local transport across the country in the current spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-benefits-of-the-new-bridge-include"&gt;The benefits of the new bridge include&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relieving congestion on the Silver Jubilee Bridge and improving public transport links across the River Mersey between the two parts of Halton; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving accessibility in the region;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving local air quality and enhancing the urban environment; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging increased use of cycling and walking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steve Nicholson, Director, Mersey Gateway Project, said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been working very closely with Government over recent months to finalise the details of this agreement and I am delighted with the results. This agreement represents the best possible deal for the public purse and means that we can focus on delivering a project that will bring benefits to local people, commuters and businesses from across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This announcement allows Halton Borough Council to start the procurement process for the project which will take around two years.  Final approval enabling construction to begin will be subject to successful completion of the procurement process. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport will provide £86m in capital grant towards land and remediation and up to £14.55m per year in long term revenue support for 26.5 years from opening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Following the spending review, local authorities were challenged to look again at the cost of proposed transport schemes to ensure value for money.  Nine schemes were given the go ahead in February after £45.5m (14%) of savings were identified. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Mersey Gateway Bridge was a more complex project with a detailed and complex financial structure which has taken longer to assess and conclude the funding agreement with Halton Borough Council. Halton Borough Council have identified cost savings for the new bridge of around £30m (5%) with further savings expected to be delivered through the procurement process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The approved scheme will have a 1000m length span, with three towers of up to a maximum of 140m in height in the River Mersey. It will also include link roads from the existing highway network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction cost is expected to be £589m (including land purchase and remediation)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tolls will be levied on the new bridge and the existing Silver Jubilee Bridge with toll levels expected to be similar to those seen on the Mersey Tunnels (currently £1.50 per car).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both bridges will be operated by a Mersey Gateway Crossings Board - an independent subsidiary of Halton Borough Council.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A private sector operator will build, finance and operate the bridge (inc managing toll collection) in return for an annual payment from the Crossings Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Crossings Board will raise the revenue to cover the annual charge from the tolls paid by those using the bridge and will also benefit from the grant from DfT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3118  &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14783</id>
    <published>2011-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-proposes-80mph-motorway-speed-limit"/>
    <title>Government proposes 80MPH motorway speed limit </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond has announced his intention to consult on raising the national speed limit on motorways from 70 to 80 miles per hour. The government plans to launch a full public consultation on the issue later this year with a view to implementing any change in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vehicles have changed dramatically since the current national speed limit was set in 1965. Technological advances mean that cars are significantly safer then they were - contributing to a fall of more than 75% in the number of people killed on British roads since 1965. That is why the government feels it is now time to look again at whether the speed limit set in 1965 is still appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road safety is a top priority for the government and action is being taken to tackle uninsured driving and help police enforce against drink and drug driving. However, the government believes safety cannot be the only consideration when setting speed limits. Previous analysis shows that raising the motorway speed limit would generate significant economic benefits, worth hundreds of millions of pounds per year from savings of travel time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial work by the department suggests that setting the motorway speed limit at 80 mph is likely to represent the best balance of costs and benefits and it is similar to the motorway speed limit in other EU countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many as 49% of drivers currently break the 70mph limit. Ministers believe that raising the limit to 80mph would mean that millions of otherwise law-abiding motorists would be brought back inside the boundary, restoring the moral legitimacy of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to make sure that our motorway speed limit reflects the reality of modern vehicles and driving conditions, not those of 50 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we must ensure that our roads remain among the safest in the world, we must also consider the huge economic benefits that can be created by shortening journey times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Increasing the speed limit on motorways from 70 to 80 miles per hour for cars, light vans and motorcycles could provide hundreds of millions of pounds of benefits for the economy and I will put forward formal proposals for making these changes later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An increase to the national motorway speed limit would apply to England and Wales. Responsibilities are devolved in Northern Ireland and are planned to be devolved in Scotland.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased motorway speed limits would apply to cars and motorcycles. Lorries on motorways are subject to lower speed limits and we have no proposals to increase them. The consultation is however likely to seek views about the position related to vans/light goods vehicles on motorways.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A thorough impact assessment which takes account of the full environmental, social and economic costs and benefits is being progressed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some stretches of motorway would be likely to retain a 70 mph limit because of their engineering and environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are also considering the case related to increasing the speed limit on other high standard, near-motorway dual carriageways. Changes would be implemented case by case and we are not proposing to consult about raising the default national speed limit of 70 mph for all purpose dual carriageways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3118  &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292   &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14216</id>
    <published>2011-09-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/building-a-sustainable-future"/>
    <title>Building a sustainable future</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, distinguished guests. Today I want to talk to you about how we go about building a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case I’m going to make has three core arguments: The first is that “sustainability” must be defined in its widest sense; a policy will only, in practice, be sustainable if it supports our environmental and economic goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that while there may sometimes be a tension, there is not necessarily conflict between these two crucially important objectives - it is possible to achieve both in tandem. And the third is that, along with power generation, transport has an absolutely pivotal role in delivering that sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="paying-tribute-to-japans-unbreakable-spirit"&gt;Paying tribute to Japan’s unbreakable spirit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go on to make those arguments, I’d like to take this opportunity to say a few words about the earthquake and tsunami that struck Japan back in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like everyone in Britain, I was shocked and saddened by the destruction and the tragic loss of life caused by that terrible event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have also been deeply impressed, by the resilience of the Japanese people and their almost super-human efforts to recover from the effects of the disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work you have done, the progress you have made and the determination you have shown is hugely impressive and, on behalf of my Government and my country, I want to pay tribute to Japan’s unbreakable spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="global-challenges---environmental-and-economic"&gt;Global challenges - environmental and economic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake and tsunami were, of course, natural disasters. So, while we can always prepare for events like these, we will never be able to prevent them, or stop them in their tracks. The same cannot be said of climate change. Climate change threatens our planet and imperils our future. That’s not science fiction, it’s science fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is a man-made problem - which means that it is possible for us to do something about it. Individually as countries, and collectively as an international community, it is within our power to tackle climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in order to build a sustainable future it is imperative that we meet this global challenge. But Japan, Britain, all of the mature economies, face a second global challenge - the challenge of maintaining economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake and tsunami took a heart-breaking toll in human lives. But they have also hit Japan’s economy - from a recovery bill totalling trillions of Yen, to the inevitable downward pressure on national GDP as output dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because Japan is one of the biggest economies in our increasingly inter-connected world, there has been an inevitable knock-on effect for the entire global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, the global economic consequences of what happened in March would have been serious and significant. But they were also part of an unprecedented coincidence of international events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has witnessed the euro-zone debt crisis, the downgrading of America’s credit rating and rocketing commodity prices in everything from food and oil, to copper and gold - as well as the tsunami and earthquake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, their impact has been magnified beyond the sum of their parts. In effect they have conspired to grind-down confidence and whip-up uncertainty in the financial markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End result - right around the world the conditions for generating growth have become much, much tougher. And, just as it is vital that countries reduce their deficits and live within their means, so it is crucial that we grow our economies. That’s the only way to secure the recovery, put people back to work and spread prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if we want that sustainable future, not only must we commit ourselves to the fight against climate change, we must also commit ourselves to delivering economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am clear that those objectives do not need to be incompatible. There does not have to be a choice between safeguarding the environment and generating economic growth. This is not a zero sum game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the key areas where we will see this truth demonstrated is in transport. When the coalition government came to power in Britain last May, we inherited a deficit greater than any in our nation’s peacetime history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual, no family, no business can carry on spending more than they earn indefinitely. There will always come a day of reckoning when the credit card bill lands on the doormat and you either pay off the debt or go bust. The recent upheaval in the global financial markets reminds us that, ultimately, the same goes for governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, from day one in office, our government was clear that our number one priority was - and is - restoring Britain’s public finances to order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, British governments have responded to fiscal pressure by slashing capital investment - avoiding the politically challenging cuts in current spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not this time. In spite of intense pressure on budgets, we made the choice to invest in infrastructure, and transport infrastructure in particular. And for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that transport investment is a key economic driver - strengthening the arteries of commerce, moving people to the workplace and goods to the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, transport investment supports job creation through the development, manufacture and application of new technologies and the construction and maintenance of infrastructure across the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the longer term, it drives the productivity growth which is the key to future competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this investment will also be a key part of our plan to make Britain cleaner and greener. Economic growth and decarbonisation. Being delivered hand in hand across the transport sector. Let me take you through some of the steps we have taken in pursuit of our double-headed goal of sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sparking-a-green-motoring-revolution"&gt;Sparking a green motoring revolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few years, UK government policy, focussed on the need to tackle climate change, drifted into what appeared to be an unthinking hostility to cars and motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a “war on the motorist” is not sustainable. Motorists are voters, and a sustainable policy, in a democracy, must be a policy that voters will support. So our government recognises the absolute centrality of the car to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many journeys it is, and will remain, the only practical and convenient choice. Indeed, 84% of all journeys in the UK are undertaken by car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enemy is not the car, it’s the carbon. So, in Britain we have ended the war on the motorist and are prosecuting the war on carbon - sparking a green revolution in motoring with a blend of supportive public policy and dynamic private enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say that Japanese investment and Japanese companies are playing a central role by committing early and clearly to our “Plug-In Car Grant” which gives consumers a 25% subsidy, up to  £5,000, if they buy an ultra-low emission car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this new grant is our “Plugged-In-Places” Programme, designed to meet the infrastructure needs of electric car drivers, setting up a targeted network of electric vehicle recharging points around the country - everywhere from streets, to car parks, to retail and leisure facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re using it to understand how the infrastructure to support electric vehicles needs to develop. That will differ from country to country - depending on culture, travel and work patterns and existing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, in Britain, on-street re-charging is certainly part of the answer. But we have concluded that putting a charge-point on every street corner is not the right approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many drivers, perhaps most, will find it better suits their daily routine to plug-in at home, at night-time when electricity is cheaper, or while they’re at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are reforming planning controls to make it easier for private enterprise to play its part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By committing to this programme, we have ensured that the UK has been and is an attractive launch market for ultra-low emission vehicles and an attractive location for major private sector companies to build these new products for the European market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nissan is leading the way by constructing a plant to manufacture its electric vehicles and batteries in the North East of England. Others will follow and the supply chain and supporting technology development companies are already moving in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly sustainable approach, promoting the change that will deliver our environmental objectives - while creating high quality jobs, regenerating our regions and rebalancing our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, reduced emissions from private cars can be mandated by regulation - but must ultimately be delivered by the private sector. Our government also believes it’s important to support more environmentally friendly forms of public transport - an area where we have more direct levers to influence behaviour. For example, in promoting low carbon buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These use at least 30 per cent less fuel and emit nearly a third less carbon than a conventional bus. Yet, when my government came to office, they made up just 0.2 per cent of the country’s bus fleet. So, we have invested in a multi-million pound Green Bus Fund which will kick-start the market by helping operators with the up-front cost of buying low carbon buses - as well as maintaining ongoing enhanced subsidy for green bus operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We estimate that, by March next year, this will result in more than 500 new hybrid and electric low carbon buses being on the roads - meaning that public transport will be making a contribution to shrinking the carbon footprint of road transport, just as the private sector is beginning to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The railways are another essential part of Britain’s public transport networks. And they offer carbon reduction possibilities in everything from regenerative braking to trackside energy storage. Making existing rail journeys more carbon efficient, and attracting more and more passengers from other, less carbon-efficient, modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important way that our government is tapping into this potential is through a major programme of rail electrification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric trains emit no air pollution at the trackside and they generate less CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; than their diesel counterparts. So electrification of the railway - going hand in hand with de-carbonisation of the power generation sector, makes good environmental sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But investing in electrification makes good business sense too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because electric trains are much more reliable than diesels, they are cheaper to operate and often cheaper to buy, they require less maintenance and have lower energy costs and they are also lighter and so cause less damage to the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon reduction - and greater efficiency. Environmental and economic benefits, hand in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as part of that electrification programme, we have given the go ahead for the £4.5 billion Inter-city express programme - which will mean new trains, more capacity and better reliability for passengers using some of Britain’s busiest rail routes. And, again, a Japanese company, Hitachi, is helping us to deliver this project as part of a consortium with the British infrastructure company John Laing. With Hitachi building a new train factory in a high unemployment area of Britain and creating 600 jobs, here is another example of transport investment providing an economic shot in the arm, as well as delivering the goods for passengers and for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="high-speed-rail"&gt;High speed rail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Japan, you will also know the potential of high speed rail networks to attract passengers on to trains and away from more environmentally damaging forms of travel, such as long-distance driving and short-haul flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, you will understand the way that high speed rail can transform a nation’s social and economic geography for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan has a long and proud record as a high speed rail pioneer. Indeed, we in Britain have looked on with admiration at your achievements in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have learned from your experience, as well as admired your progress. And now we are proposing a national high speed rail network in our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that, as in Japan and in France and Spain, such a network would not only slash journey times between our major cities and regions, but transform the way our economy works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving connectivity for our communities and our businesses; boosting productivity and improving competitiveness. And by making high speed rail the mode of choice for long-distance inter-city journeys, we will reduce the carbon footprint of domestic travel still further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aviation"&gt;Aviation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot talk about reducing transport emissions without highlighting the urgent need to tackle the aviation sector’s fast growing emissions. Aviation plays a vital role in the global economy. However, in Europe and increasingly in other parts of the world, governments are facing demands to ensure that aviation is put on a sustainable path that it can deliver growth with decarbonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that aviation emissions will best be managed at international level, but this can take a painfully long time. That is why, alongside operational and technological measures, the UK fully supports the inclusion of aviation in the EU Emissions Trading System or &lt;abbr title="Emissions Trading System"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;. The &lt;abbr title="Emissions Trading System"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt; delivers an emissions cap in a cost effective, monetised and flexible way, allowing airlines to choose how best to meet their emissions quotas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise the concerns that have been raised in the last few months, but doing nothing is not an option. In addition to taking concrete steps, we will continue to work with like-minded states, such as Japan, in international negotiations in the International Civil Aviation Organization (&lt;abbr title="International Civil Aviation Organization"&gt;ICAO&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the hope that we can deliver an ambitious global agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="shipping"&gt;Shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maritime transport is another area where carbon emissions must be reduced. The adoption of the Energy Efficiency Design Index, as championed by Japan at the International Maritime Organization earlier this year, was very gratifying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an important first step towards securing a comprehensive global agreement. So some progress has been made - but not yet enough. Once again, the EU is prepared to set the pace with a unilateral scheme if IMO cannot deliver the goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, in the UK, look forward to working with the new Secretary-General, Mr Sekimizu, on this and IMO’s many other challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In speaking to you today I have argued that, in our present circumstances, the only sustainable policies are those which deliver carbon reduction and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything else will be rejected by an electorate that is more currently focussed on jobs and prosperity than the climate change agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must focus on initiatives where there is overlap in delivery of these twin objectives and prioritise them, for the moment at least, over those where environmental objectives are at odds with the urgent need for growth and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud to say that the transport sector can lead the way in demonstrating the path to green growth; in showing how we can maintain the momentum of decarbonisation while delivering the growth and jobs our electorates demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The twin challenges of economic growth and climate change; both urgent and both fundamental to our future. To meet them will require a particular focus and determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not unlike the focus and determination Japan has shown in response to the effects of the earthquake and tsunami. This country and its people have reminded us that all things are possible with courage, determination and vision. And we will need plenty of all three to meet the twin challenges of climate change and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Japan’s example, I know that it’s possible for us to come together, and work together, to build that truly sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16160</id>
    <published>2011-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-local-enterprise-partnerships-network--3"/>
    <title>Speech to Local Enterprise Partnerships Network</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="government-agenda"&gt;Government agenda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you David,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you ladies and gentlemen. It’s a great pleasure to join you today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the coalition was formed last May, we knew we faced perhaps the toughest and most challenging agenda of any government in modern British history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from day one, we were absolutely clear about our priorities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling, first and foremost, the record budget deficit we inherited from our predecessors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And rebuilding and rebalancing our economy, after a decade of lopsided growth, followed by one of the longest and deepest recessions in our history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now working to put Britain back on the path towards sustainable growth and prosperity, while delivering on our commitment to carbon reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have set out a clear and credible plan to eradicate the structural current deficit during this Parliament and get debt falling as a percentage of GDP. We are clear that this is the right course for Britain, and we will stick to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our economy, while delivering deficit reduction measures, has, in the first six months of this year, outperformed the US economy - despite Obama’s massive fiscal stimulus package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our market interest rates have fallen, while other countries’ have soared; our credit rating is secure while others’ have faltered; and Britain, despite the choppy recovery that was always predicted, is being hailed as a safe haven in a global economic storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course there is more still to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the tough global economic climate, we must continue to build on the foundations that sound public finances provide to secure the growth, the jobs, and the private sector investment that will drive our prosperity in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-key-to-growth"&gt;Transport key to growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure investment - and transport infrastructure in particular - is a key part of our plans to drive economic recovery. It provides not just welcome demand stimulus in the short term, but a vital improvement in productivity over the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern transport networks are the arteries of commerce, moving people to the workplace and goods to the marketplace. They connect communities, support businesses and enhance social mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we modernise our infrastructure, and encourage more sustainable forms of travel, transport can help us cut carbon emissions, improve air quality, and offer a cleaner, greener gateway to a better quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why transport emerged as a major winner in last year’s spending review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a tough public spending climate, £30 billion of capital funding was announced over the spending review period - more than was invested in the previous four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to transport means we can invest in ambitious national infrastructure projects like high speed rail, that can help transform our economic geography and spread prosperity right across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also recognise that, if we are to unleash the growth potential of our regions and to get maximum value from our strategic infrastructure investments, we cannot afford to neglect the local transport networks that connect to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we should never forget that the vast majority of journeys Britons take are under five miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-and-localism"&gt;Transport and localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that many of the most important transport issues are local in nature. Sometimes very local.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roadworks. Local road congestion. Reliability of bus services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local issues that are understood by local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And local transport problems that are best solved by local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best-value transport investments are often in smaller-scale projects - ones that help tackle congestion, and improve connectivity, road safety, and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet for far too long in this country, important decisions about local transport have been taken, and monitored, centrally - by Ministers and civil servants sitting in Whitehall, ticking boxes and second guessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years, the top down, ‘Whitehall knows best’ approach has perpetuated a system that is not only bureaucratic and inefficient, but which also hampers local enterprise and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is time for reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for the coalition, that preferred reform is localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give local communities and businesses real control over their own destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To unlock the growth potential of our cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support economic regeneration from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to move towards a more transparent, accountable and responsive way of designing and providing public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-so-far"&gt;Progress so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have already heard today from Greg Clark about the significant progress we’ve made in re-designing the old top-down structure of delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whitehall has been slimmed down. Quangos have gone. Government Offices for the Regions have closed their doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their place we have announced a massive transfer of power to councils, communities, and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill should receive Royal Assent at the end of this year, and many more reforms will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I, for my part, am determined to place the local role in the delivery of transport projects centre stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rail, for example, we are exploring how we can devolve more responsibility and budgets for commissioning local and regional services away from the centre to more local bodies - where there is greater accountability to local communities and passengers, and a better understanding about the local consequences of the decisions they take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in local transport, we have radically overhauled the way grant funding is delivered - to get the best results for communities, and the best value for taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already slashed the number of separate local transport grant streams from 26 to just four, giving local authorities much greater flexibility and freedom to decide their own priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="next-steps-to-localism"&gt;Next steps to localism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to go further. I want to explore how we can devolve the capital funding for local major transport schemes - those with a value greater than…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These transport projects are not just key to economic growth - they are also essential to our decentralisation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously they were managed through Labour’s Regional Funding Allocation process, which had a veneer of decentralisation, but little of real substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial decisions were taken by unelected and unaccountable regional bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And their role was purely advisory. Central government remained the ultimate decision-maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the regional tier of government is being dismantled, we have the opportunity to develop a fresh, and genuinely decentralised, approach that is fit for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that genuinely shifts power away from the centre, to allow the businesses and communities who depend on transport infrastructure, to shape it, making decisions accountable at the sub-national level, and responsive to local economic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any change we make will be effective for the next round of local authority major schemes funding, covering the period 2015-2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But local major transport schemes can take around four years to move from business case to the start of construction. That means, if we are to maximise the potential of decentralisation to kick-start sub-national and local economic growth, we must act now to put these new freedoms in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because some of the local authority major schemes are indeed ‘major’, sometimes £100 million plus, any formula-distributed grant needs to flow in a way that ensures that even the largest projects could get funded over a number of years. That means that, in most cases, distribution by formula to a single &lt;abbr title="Local enterprise partnerships"&gt;LEP&lt;/abbr&gt; or local authority would not deliver the desired result. A larger effective unit, reflecting real economic and transport geographies, but ‘chunky’ enough to deliver worthwhile sums of capital through the formula, has to be devised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I am announcing my intention to launch a consultation on what that structure might look like - on how we can fully devolve decisions and funding for local capital transport improvements to a number of, what I will call for shorthand, ‘Local Transport Consortia’, each made up of a number of &lt;abbr title="Local enterprise partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; and their constituent local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach, if correctly designed, will ensure more local decision making…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… without losing the essential focus on the strategic needs of a sub-national economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing focus on decisions that place higher weight on local priorities and needs, while maintaining the focus on generating maximum economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And saving a huge amount of time and effort that was previously wasted at the interface between local project promoters and Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local enterprise partnerships, designed around functional economic geographies, are an obvious starting point. But the Consortia, like the &lt;abbr title="Local enterprise partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; themselves, must be ‘bottom up’ creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the scale, geography and structure must be right for local circumstances: we do not have to adopt a standardised approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Local enterprise partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; are uniquely placed to contribute to strategic decisions which best align transport investment with growth potential, while local authorities can bring significant transport expertise - and local accountability - to the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful local transport consortium must be able to integrate major scheme transport investment with wider plans for growth, including planning, housing, skills and training, enterprise, health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some areas, this will mean building on existing arrangements, while others will wish to explore opportunities with new partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will invite thoughts on the structure, optimum size, configuration, governance and accountability arrangements that would be most appropriate to ensure the proper use of public money and the delivery of value for money, while achieving genuine local ownership of the prioritisation and delivery of sub-national transport investment projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there will be challenges. The purpose of the consultation will be to explore the different options and establish a consensus on the best way to take this agenda forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions that consortia make must be seen to be transparent and scrupulously fair if they are to win the confidence of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are other, wider challenges that cut across the government’s localism agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None more pivotal than accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ministers, we rightly expect to be held accountable for the delivery of a national agenda by the electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With power and responsibility should come accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we progress with decentralisation, we recognise that there will be some tension between seeking to encourage genuinely devolved decision-making and an ingrained instinct on the part of the electorate to hold ministers accountable for all but the most local spending decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will get nowhere unless we are prepared to meet this challenge head-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So local transport consortia will need to be able to put in place measures that demonstrate accountability; proper financial management and propriety; an ability to deal with cost overruns and delays to schemes; and a commitment to delivering value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than civil servants spending hours monitoring and appraising individual schemes, the role of central government should be to ensure that local transport consortia are ready, and able, to maximise value for money and to make decisions which best support the economy and promote sustainable development. And that arrangements are in place for them to be held accountable by the communities and businesses they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some consortia may progress more quickly than others. Some may be able to ‘go it alone’ with the management and delivery of budgets and projects straight away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others may prefer to walk first, with a shared approach to project appraisal and prioritisation, to make sure schemes are based on robust evidence, and meet sub national and local growth priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I am clear that my department’s long-term role does not lie in individual scheme appraisal or management of delivery, we will be ready to adopt a flexible approach to the transition, if that is what local transport consortia wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we will play a light-touch role with local partners - and, let me assure you, that role will be as light as I can possibly make it - we will also be there to help you find effective working solutions to whatever challenge you face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will work closely with local transport consortia so each is able to adapt to the changes - ensuring the end result is a decentralised decision-making system that genuinely unleashes local growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as soon as Parliament reconvenes after the party conferences, I will launch a 3-month consultation to seek your views on these proposals and the best way to proceed with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope as many of you as possible will take part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a learning process - no doubt about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is inevitable when we’re transforming the way local infrastructure is planned, funded and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of previous governments has taught us that real, meaningful localism is easier to talk about than deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when this government talks about localism, we mean it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, localism isn’t an essentially centralised decision making structure dressed up in a localist wrapper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real localism, genuine localism, means a culture change across central and local government, to drive a radical shift in power away from Whitehall, and into the hands of local people, local businesses and local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires local authorities, &lt;abbr title="Local enterprise partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;, businesses and communities to work together in partnership - and be prepared to accept compromise and necessary trade-offs to unlock barriers to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to capital projects, it will require a high degree of political maturity to pursue sub-national priorities: this process will not succeed if capital funds are divided into penny packets for each constituent part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it requires a local commitment to transparency and accountability, to engender trust and confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we will meet these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m convinced that we will emerge with a robust model of decentralisation that will transform local transport delivery for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way, we can deliver the world-class networks that will set Britain back on the path to sustainable growth and lasting prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, and I look forward to working with you to take this agenda forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16352</id>
    <published>2011-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/sale-of-trust-ports--4"/>
    <title>Sale of trust ports</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 3 August 2011, I announced the criteria that the government will consider particularly relevant to the appropriateness of the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales under the Ports Act 1991. This followed the consultation that I announced on 16 May 2011 and which closed on 27 June. I regret that it was not possible to announce this first by written ministerial statement to the House, but I did not wish to delay consideration of the application by Dover Harbour Board for a transfer scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that Dover Harbour Board has now considered the criteria, intends to proceed with its application for a transfer scheme under the Ports Act 1991, and proposes to submit a new set of documents containing a further elaboration of its scheme for decision by the Minister of State under the new criteria. If interested parties would find it useful and seek my department’s assistance, we would be happy to consider ways in which properly to facilitate discussions on all the options before the Dover Harbour Board submits its elaborated proposal. I should make clear that the decision minister would take no part in such discussions and would continue to perform her statutory functions in an objective, impartial manner whatever the outcome of any such discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following paragraphs set out the revised policy which the Secretary of State expects to follow when considering an application under the Ports Act 1991 for the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales. This covers the consideration of any proposal for a transfer scheme submitted under section 9 or 10 of the 1991 Act, together with the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions in respect of the subsequent sale of the port to which the scheme relates. The Secretary of State also intends to have particular regard to the policy considerations set out below before making a transfer scheme himself under section 12 of the 1991 Act or subsequently approving the sale of a port to which such a scheme relates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="essential-criteria"&gt;1. Essential criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation - the Secretary of State will not approve an application for the sale of a trust port under the 1991 Act unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an enduring and significant level of community participation in the port. Such participation could take a variety of forms, but must include the ability to influence the port’s long term development and may include the right to receive a share in the profits of the port, or the future increase in its value. It does not necessarily require a community role in the operation of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future investment in, and development of, the port - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an ownership model with the capability and access to capital to meet future investment needs and to exploit development potential of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair price - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to represent good value for money, having regard not only to Exchequer proceeds and market conditions, but also to other benefits including those to the community and the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair competition - the Secretary of State will not approve an application that is likely to deliver an ownership model which results in unsatisfactory levels of competition in the relevant sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="highly-desirable-criteria"&gt;2. Highly desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport networks - It is highly desirable for an application to be likely to deliver an ownership model which will cause the port to be operated so as to contribute to reliable, resilient and efficient transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sale process - It is highly desirable that the sale should be conducted in such a way as to give all bona fide prospective purchasers a fair and equitable opportunity to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desirable-criteria"&gt;3. Desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employee involvement - It is desirable for an application to be likely to deliver port employee participation in the ownership of the port, such as the right to receive equity shares or a share in its future success*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*This is without prejudice to the Ports Act 1991 section 5(3) requirement to have particular regard to the desirability of encouraging the disposal of the whole or a substantial part of the equity share capital of the successor company to managers or other persons employed by the port company etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20110516"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110516i/"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports in England and Wales - Consultation on revised criteria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17418</id>
    <published>2011-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bank-holiday-rail-services"/>
    <title>Bank holiday rail services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond has welcomed the news that the rail industry will be keeping more trains running this August bank holiday weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 49,903 trains will be carrying an expected 5 million rail passengers to destinations across the country - 1,700 more trains than were operational during last year’s bank holiday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail’s engineering teams will still be out working hard to deliver the vital improvements to the railways over the holiday weekend, but 95 per cent of normal train services will be running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bank holiday weekends are always a busy time to travel, but a great deal is being done to ensure that travellers get to their destinations as smoothly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While Network Rail will be carrying out important improvement works in some areas, 95% of normal train services will be running this weekend which is around 1,700 more trains than ran last August bank holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course everyone should still allow plenty of time for their journeys and plan well in advance, but a lot of work is going into keeping Britain moving this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of intense pressure on the public finances the government is undertaking one of the biggest programmes of rail improvements since the Victorian era. These include a green-light for Crossrail, Thameslink and a programme of additional carriages for our most rail crowded lines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most travellers there should be no disruption because of the improvement works. But, as always, travellers should check with their train operator or national rail enquiries before they travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14245</id>
    <published>2011-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bringing-an-end-to-rush-hour-road-works-disruption"/>
    <title>Bringing an end to rush hour road works disruption</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovative measures to cut the number of rush hour road works were announced today by Transport Secretary Philip Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under ‘lane rental’ schemes councils would be able to charge utility companies to dig up the busiest roads during peak times when road works cause the most disruption. Companies would be able to avoid the charges by carrying out works during quieter periods or, if appropriate, at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone knows how frustrating it can be when you are sat in a traffic jam, unable to get to work or drop off the children at school because someone is digging up the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This disruption is expensive as well as inconvenient, with one estimate valuing the loss to the economy from road works congestion at £4 billion a year. We simply cannot afford this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why I am putting forward proposals which would incentivise utility companies and local authorities to carry out their works at times when they will cause the minimum disruption to the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has today published a consultation and draft guidance to councils outlining how lane rental schemes could be implemented. Any councils wishing to put in place a lane rental scheme would need to gain approval from the Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to gather evidence on the effectiveness of lane rental, the Department has proposed that schemes should initially be used in one urban and one non-metropolitan area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals are clear that lane rental charges must be avoidable and proportionate to the costs of congestion. Councils are also being encouraged to apply the same principles to their own works and come forward with lane rental schemes which fit the needs of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any revenue raised from the implementation of lane rental charges would be used by councils to fund measures which could help to reduce future road works disruption. This could include infrastructure work, research or measures to improve the management of works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will close on 31st October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-25"&gt;consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local councils will need to propose charge levels that are appropriate to their individual circumstances. In particular, they will need to show that their charges are proportionate to the costs imposed by works on the roads in question. This is subject to a proposed maximum charge of £2,500 per day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The primary legislation (section 74A of the New Roads and Street Works Act 1991) provides the necessary powers for local highway authorities to put in place lane rental schemes, subject (in England) to the approval of the Secretary of State, and allows Regulations to make further provision about such schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lane rental pilot schemes were operated in Camden and Middlesbrough between 2002 and 2004, but no further schemes have since been implemented. As a result of subsequent changes to various aspects of street works legislation, the existing lane rental Regulations are now out of date and, in effect, inoperable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3118  &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292   &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15494</id>
    <published>2011-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/new-franchising-programme"/>
    <title>New franchising programme</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to a major reform of rail franchising that will benefit passengers and taxpayers alike. In preparing our policies we have paid careful attention to the views the rail industry, and others, have expressed to us. Our reforms will create longer, less prescriptive franchises that will give the industry more freedom to innovate, address passenger needs, and more incentive to invest. The reforms will also help achieve the radical efficiency changes needed for a sustainable lower cost railway for the long term. This will include a more equitable balance of risk between the public and private sectors, including replacement of the ‘cap and collar’ revenue support mechanism with one linked to economic indicators. There will also be stronger emphasis on partnership and closer working between train operators and their local Network Rail route teams, allowing integrated decision-making which benefits passengers and drives out cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new type of rail franchises will replace existing ones, as and when they expire, and I have today published a comprehensive forward timetable for the re-letting of rail franchises that represents a deliverable and balanced programme. My aim in doing so is to give the market clarity about the timing of the opportunities that will arise. In producing this timetable, I have had regard to the impact on bidders and their sub-contractors of trying to compete for too many franchises at once, and the likely reduction in value for money to the taxpayer that would result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the new programme is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have already announced, the new Inter City West Coast franchise will commence in December 2012, with an invitation to tender (ITT) issued to the pre-qualified bidders in January 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following First Group’s decision not to exercise its contractual entitlement to take up a 3-year extension on its existing Greater Western contract from 2013, this will now be the next long-distance franchise to come to market, with the new franchise commencing in April 2013, instead of 2016 as originally planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, and to avoid having to offer more than one long-distance franchise competition at the same time, with possible consequences for taxpayer value, the new Inter City East Coast franchise will commence in December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to commuter franchises, there is no change in my plans for Essex Thameside, with the new 15 year contract due to commence in May 2013. The same is true for South Eastern, where the new franchise will start in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of the likely delivery timescales for Thameslink rolling stock, I judge it right to exercise my contractual entitlement to bring forward the start of a new franchise to September 2013. The franchise is likely to be shorter than 15 years, with a focus on managing services through the major Thameslink infrastructure upgrade. It would then be re-let at the end of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accommodate the changed dates for Thameslink and Inter City East Coast, I intend to move the start of the long term 15 year Greater Anglia franchise to July 2014, exercising the 12 month extension that is included in to the short franchise that is currently being competed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded an agreement with First Keolis TransPennine Express (&lt;abbr title="TransPennine Express"&gt;TPE&lt;/abbr&gt;) which extends the current franchise. The extension incorporates the flexibility to terminate the franchise between April 2014 and March 2015. This flexibility could allow the start dates for the new Northern and TransPennine franchises to be aligned in April 2014, by also exercising the short extension provision in the current Northern franchise. Having both existing franchises end at the same date could allow for these franchises to be combined, or split in different ways. I will be considering the optimal configuration and intend to seek views on the optimum structure from local interested parties. The timescales outlined above will allow for proper consultation and consideration of the possibilities of a radical restructuring in the Northern/&lt;abbr title="TransPennine Express"&gt;TPE&lt;/abbr&gt; area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, Great Western and Thameslink have come forward (by 35 months and 18 months respectively), the Northern and &lt;abbr title="TransPennine Express"&gt;TPE&lt;/abbr&gt; franchises could now be aligned with a start date of April 2014 - so that we have greater flexibility in re-letting - and 2 other franchises (Inter City East Coast and Greater Anglia) have been pushed back to accommodate the acceleration of Great Western and Thameslink. Three franchises (Inter City West Coast, South Eastern and Essex Thameside) remain unchanged.
I have already been clear that not all of these franchises will look the same. I believe in horses for courses and a pragmatic, not dogmatic, approach. I will be guided by what drives value for the taxpayer and service for the passenger on each individual franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some commentators have suggested this represents a huge programme of work and a major culture shift in government. I agree with them. It is arguably the biggest programme of franchising since the industry was originally privatised. But it is also a major programme - and a significant culture shift - for bidders. There should be no doubt about our determination to deliver on this agenda, nor the importance of managing it properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revising the programme in this way, while remaining clear about our objectives reflects my view that success depends on having a crystal-clear and unwavering strategy, coupled with a willingness and ability to be agile and tactical in implementing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result of this work will be a new rail franchising system that delivers better outcomes for passengers and better value for money for taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/rail-franchising-pin"&gt;Rail franchising &lt;abbr title="Prior Information Notice"&gt;PIN&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
