<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/theresa-villiers</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/theresa-villiers.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon  Theresa Villiers MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-27T13:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14966</id>
    <published>2012-10-27T13:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-27T13:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rail-franchising"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In May this year, the then Secretary of State announced that the next InterCity West Coast franchise would start on 9th December 2012. It was further announced that the department intended to enter into negotiations with the incumbent franchisee (West Coast Trains Ltd and Virgin Rail Group) to secure affordable and value for money operations until the start of the new franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that the department has now agreed an extension with West Coast Trains Limited and Virgin Rail Group. This agreement will extend their current franchise on the InterCity West Coast route from 1 April 2012 until the start of the new franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the extension three new 600-seat Pendolino trains will be added to the line. This is in addition to the new Pendolino train which entered service in July of this year. Also, 31 of the existing Pendolino trains will be lengthened from 9 to 11 carriages, increasing the number of standard class seats on each train by almost 50%, from 320 to 470. In all, 106 new carriages are being introduced on the route making 28,000 extra seats available each day, an increase of 25%. This will relieve crowding on some of the busiest parts of the West Coast Main Line which is one the UK economy’s most important transport corridors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virgin will also be responsible for providing important services enabling people travel by train to the Olympic and Paralympic Games next summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/rail-passenger-franchises/"&gt;New franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20111027b"&gt;Press release: West Coast passengers in line for 28,000 extra seats as franchise extension signed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15793</id>
    <published>2012-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--13"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 15 August 2012 the Department for Transport announced to the London Stock Exchange that it intended to award the InterCity West Coast franchise to First West Coast Limited, a subsidiary of First Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bids were received from Abellio InterCity West Coast Limited - NV Nederlandse Spoorwegen, First West Coast Limited - FirstGroup plc, Keolis/SNCF West Coast Limited - Keolis SA and SNCF, Virgin Trains Limited - Virgin Group Holdings Limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise is planned to begin operation on Sunday 9 December 2012. The franchise will operate for a core term of 13 years and 4 months, with an option to be extended to operate for up to 15 years. The winning bid from First West Coast Limited provides for a premium of £5.5 billion &lt;abbr title="net present value"&gt;NPV&lt;/abbr&gt; over the core franchise term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Coast Main Line is one of the most important intercity rail passenger routes in the country and it is also a valuable public asset. Over the last decade and more, taxpayers have invested £9 billion to upgrade the infrastructure. It is a profitable franchise for the current operator and after significant public investment in the line the government is rightly seeking to get a substantial return for passengers and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The First West Coast bid provides: more trains on the route, with 12,000 extra seats per day provided by 11 new 6 carriage electric trains from December 2016 (in addition to the 106 extra Pendolino carriages currently being introduced); refurbishing the existing Pendolino and Voyager train fleets, more capacity on services between Birmingham and Scotland, and faster journey times between London Euston and Glasgow; new services to Blackpool, Bolton and Shrewsbury, subject to approval of the &lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;; lower standard anytime fares over the first two years; £22 million in station improvements; Oyster-style smart ticketing; and, for the first time in an intercity franchise, better customer satisfaction as measured by the national passenger survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a new franchise begins, employees of the current franchise operator, including drivers, guards and back office staff will be transferred to the new operator, protected by TUPE regulations. All of the rolling stock used by the incumbent operator will also transfer across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, I believe that the commitments in First West Coast’s bid represent significant improvements for passengers and will provide a good return for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of a legal challenge, which the government intends to defend robustly, we have not yet signed the contract with First West Coast, and consequently the competition remains live. I cannot give the full commercial details of the winning bid, or indeed of the other bids. Nor is it usual or appropriate - once litigation proceedings have commenced - for the government to comment on the detail of that, other than to say that our legal advisers are fully engaged in addressing and responding to those proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to keep the House updated, subject to the constraints of legal or commercial privilege.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14873</id>
    <published>2012-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-operator-for-west-coast-rail-passengers"/>
    <title>New operator for West Coast rail passengers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers from London to Scotland will benefit from a package of improvements including more trains and more seats, as Rail Minister Theresa Villiers unveiled First West Coast Limited as the new operator for the ‘InterCity West Coast’ franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the deal First West Coast Limited will introduce 11 new six-car electric trains which will enable more seats to be provided across the franchise, including greater capacity on the Birmingham to Scotland route. New services are planned from Blackpool, Telford, Shrewsbury and Bolton to London. First West Coast Limited has also committed to cut the cost of its ‘Standard Anytime’ fares by an average of 15% within the first two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The franchise stretches from London to Glasgow, connecting many of the UK’s major cities including Manchester, Liverpool, Birmingham, Wolverhampton, Edinburgh, Lancaster and Chester. The franchise deal is worth £5.5 billion (net present value) over the lifetime of the contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This new franchise will deliver big improvements for passengers, with more seats and plans for more services. Targets to meet on passenger satisfaction will be introduced for the first time in an InterCity rail franchise and passengers will also benefit from smart ticketing and from investment in stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The West Coast is the first of the new longer franchises to be let by the Coalition which has helped us secure real benefits for passengers by encouraging First West Coast Limited to invest in the future of the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits the new franchise will offer passengers include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;More Seats&lt;/strong&gt;: The new 11 six-car electric trains will deliver circa 12,000 extra seats a day, from December 2016 with the cascade of existing rolling stock to bolster capacity on West Coast routes. This is in addition to the 106 extra ‘Pendolino’ carriages which are currently being introduced into operation on to the franchise, which will deliver over 28,000 extra daily seats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;More Services&lt;/strong&gt;: Initially First West Coast Limited will operate the timetable they will inherit from the current franchise but are seeking to introduce a number of new services including a London Euston to Blackpool service from 2013 and from 2016 services from London to Telford Central, Shrewsbury and Bolton.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Improved Services&lt;/strong&gt;: Journey time improvements between London and Glasgow are planned, as well as additional services from London to Preston.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Fares&lt;/strong&gt;: First West Coast Limited is changing its Standard Anytime fares and reducing them by an average of 15% over the first two years of the franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Improved Stations&lt;/strong&gt;: First West Coast Limited is taking over responsibility for maintenance at 17 of their stations and will spend at least £22m on a station investment programme.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart ticketing technology: First West Coast Limited will introduce ITSO based smart ticketing. This will offer speed and convenience as well as new ticket types more tailored to individual needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bids were received from; 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abellio InterCity West Coast Limited - NV Nederlandse Spoorwegen),&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First West Coast Limited - FirstGroup plc,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Keolis / SNCF West Coast Limited - Keolis SA and SNCF,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Virgin Trains Limited - Virgin Group Holdings Limited.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virgin Trains has operated the franchise since 1997 and the existing contract expires on 9 December 2012. The new franchise will begin operation on Sunday 9 December 2012. The franchise will operate for a core term of 13 years and 4 months, with an option to be extended to operate for up to 15 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Train Service Specification for new Inter City West Coast represents a relaxation from the rigid timetable specification of the past, while retaining obligations that protect the key elements of service, such as principal first and last trains and minimum numbers of station stops per week and per day. This marks a significant shift from the highly detailed specification which featured in previous franchise specifications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To support its bid, First West Coast Limited has provided £10m of Shareholder Capital, a £45m Performance bond agreement and a subordinated loan of £190m. This is in addition to the requirement to provide a Season Ticket bond of circa £5m and a £15m Parent Company Guarantee to ensure the new Station Facilities maintenance obligations are met.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This longer franchise length encouraged investment in assets such as stations by extending the period over which commercially attractive schemes can pay back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anytime fares allow the use of any train, including at weekday peak times. Anytime tickets are not the only ones available to walk-on passengers. Off-peak fares are also available on the day and - as their name implies - are generally valid on all but peak services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new services are subject to obtaining the necessary permissions and access rights from the Office of Rail Regulation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ITSO is a government-backed common technical standard for smart travel which means that transport operators throughout Britain can link up so passengers only have to use one secure payment ‘smart’ card no matter what bus, train or route they are using.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14867</id>
    <published>2012-07-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-great-western-franchise-to-deliver-new-express-trains"/>
    <title>New Great Western franchise to deliver new express trains</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new 15 year Great Western franchise will see passengers benefit from new express trains, additional capacity, smart card ticketing and passenger satisfaction targets as part of proposals being put forward today by Rail Minister Theresa Villiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of train services required by the new franchise will be based broadly on the current timetable, rather than the contracted minimum in the existing franchise. The popular sleeper service to Penzance will be retained. An extra early, fast train from London to Plymouth will be introduced. This will achieve aspirations for a ‘there and back in a day’ service to Plymouth from the capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful extra local services such as those on the Truro to Falmouth, Par to Newquay and the Severn Beach Lines, including those which are locally funded at present, are being added to the base specification of the franchise. This recognises the valuable work and track record of investment made by local stakeholders. Full responsibility for funding these local schemes is expected to pass to the Department for Transport from 2015, securing their future and freeing up local resources for other transport priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passengers using the Great Western Line will benefit from major infrastructure improvements and new rolling stock over the next few years, as a result of the government’s ambitious programme of rail improvements, including extensive electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the first time on the Great Western franchise, we will be introducing requirements on passenger satisfaction for the train operator to meet which will mean they have to focus strongly on the issues that matter the most to passengers. Extending smart card ticketing across the franchise will provide many more passengers across the West and South West with the kind of convenience Oyster has brought to Londoners. The Sleeper train is being retained, Plymouth gets the new early train from London they asked for and the future of popular extra local services such as the Severn Beach Line and Truro to Falmouth has been secured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This new franchise will see additional capacity delivered to benefit passengers. A more efficient and flexible franchise will encourage private sector investment, for example in improving stations and investing in rolling stock. It will promote greater efficiency and also enable the train operator to react to more effectively to changing passenger demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise will run for 15 years from July 2013 to July 2028. It will require broadly the same number of trains to run between end-to-end destinations as is the case today, while giving the new operator greater flexibility with regard to timetabling and calling patterns and, in certain instances, use of connecting trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flexibility will help ensure the line is used in the most efficient way for passengers and potentially allow faster journey times and improved services. It will also encourage private sector investment in the franchise, including stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final decision has not yet been taken on the exact number of through services between Paddington and Penzance. The Invitation to Tender requires the continuation of 9 journey opportunities between London and Penzance each day (in addition to the Sleeper) with at least 6 being provided by through trains. After discussions with local &lt;abbr title="Member of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; and Cornwall Council, the government is asking the bidders to explore with stakeholders how rail services in Cornwall might be improved to ensure the right balance between long distance and regional services is achieved. The &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt; therefore requires bidders to provide a price for additional through journeys above the minimum and also for a half hourly regional service on the Cornish main line. Decisions on whether these options are affordable and can go ahead will be taken prior to the new franchise being agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of other options which could help to further improve local services have been included which potential operators are invited to consider and provide pricing for so that they can be taken forward if a value for money solution is provided and local funding is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Details published of the new franchise that will begin from 21 July 2013, are set out by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/great-western-franchise-2013/"&gt;Department in the Invitation to Tender (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Invitation to Tender follows a consultation designed to give the public and stakeholders a chance to have their say on what they wanted from the new franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Train Service Requirement for the operation of the Great Western franchise represents a change from the rigid timetable specification of the past, while retaining obligations that protect the key outcomes for passengers and taxpayers, such as principal first and last trains and minimum numbers of station stops per week and per day. This marks a significant shift from the micro-management that has prevented operators from maximising capacity and optimising timetables to react to the changing demands of their passengers in the past.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The four shortlisted bidders from run the franchise from July 2013 are: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First Great Western Trains Limited (FirstGroup plc)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;GW Trains Limited (Arriva UK Trains Limited - DB (UK) Investments Limited)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NXGW Trains Limited (National Express Group PLC)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stagecoach Great Western Trains Limited (Stagecoach Group plc)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bids for the franchise are expected to be received in October 2012 and the new operator will be announced in March 2013. The new Great Western franchise will run until July 2028, with an option for the department to extend for up to 7 reporting periods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the government set out its plans on franchise reform, it acknowledged that each franchise contract needs to reflect the different characteristics of the lines and services it covers. Therefore the requirements set out in the Great Western Franchise may not necessarily become standard terms in every subsequent rail franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt; for the Great Western Franchise follows the current agreed regulated fares policy as set out in the 2011 Comprehensive Spending Review - a rise in 2012 of &lt;abbr title="Retail Price Index"&gt;RPI&lt;/abbr&gt;+1% and &lt;abbr title="Retail Price Index"&gt;RPI&lt;/abbr&gt;+3% for 2013 and 2014, returning to &lt;abbr title="Retail Price Index"&gt;RPI&lt;/abbr&gt;+1% thereafter. Over the long term we are committed to reducing the cost of running the railways and the goal of ending the era of above-inflation fare increases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local services which are expected to move from local to national funding in 2015 include:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Service Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Funding Body&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bristol TM to Severn Beach (frequency increase)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bristol City Council&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bristol TM to Severn Beach (Sundays)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;South Gloucestershire Council&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Truro - Falmouth (all week frequency increase)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cornwall Council&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exeter - Barnstaple (additional M-F and additional Sundays)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Devon County Council&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Priced Options: The &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt; asks bidders to price the following improvements to services:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1) Services to Cornwall&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Continued operation of 9 through services. Provision of a half hourly, regular service between Plymouth and Penzance or Exeter, from May 2017 when cascaded rolling stock is anticipated to become available.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2) TransWilts Rail (Phase 1)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Additional weekday rail services and reinstatement of Sunday services from Salisbury to Swindon via Melksham&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3) Riviera Line (Exeter to Paignton) strengthening&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Introduction of an additional 1tph service on the Riviera line from Newton Abbot to Paignton&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4) Heart of Wessex Line Service Optimisation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A much strengthened service on the Heart of Wessex line between Bristol and Weymouth&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5) Bristol Metro Phase 1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;An advanced scheme developed by the West of England Partnership. Phase 1 will provide a half hourly service in the Greater Bristol Metropolitan Area including re-opening of the rail line to Portishead to passenger services&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6) Devon Metro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Devon Metro follows a similar concept to Bristol Metro for local services into Exeter, from Exmouth, Barnstaple, Newton Abbot and Paignton. It also proposes additional, new services on the SWT route to Axminster and to Okehampton&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7) Cornish Branch Line service enhancements&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;St Ives Trains extended to Penzance. Additional summer, Monday-Saturday Looe Valley Services&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8) Tavistock-Bere Alston re-opening&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Re-opening of the rail line from Bere Alston to Tavistock&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15532</id>
    <published>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/red-tape-challenge"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last November, the Department for Transport launched the rail transport theme of the Red Tape Challenge - part of the Cabinet Office’s project to review all of the outstanding regulations currently on the statute book. Following a rigorous process of challenge, stakeholder discussion and public consultation, I am now pleased to be able to announce the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department put forward every secondary regulation relating to rail transportation for public discussion under the rail transport Red Tape Challenge. 198 of these were judged still to be live with a further 23 being identified as already “lapsed or spent”. Of these 221, I propose to scrap, merge, simplify, amend or improve 88 (40 per cent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The detailed breakdown I propose is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Keep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Improve&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Scrap&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moved*&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Number&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Percentage&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;58%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;27%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved regulations predominantly relate to another Red Tape theme and will be resolved in a different part of the Challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amongst the measures being pursued, we intend to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;harmonise and simplify the process for obtaining an operating licence;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce regulatory burdens and costs on historic cableways;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;merge a number of instruments to make regulations easier to understand; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remove a significant number of lapsed or redundant instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120817142021/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/gov-20111110"&gt;full list of regulations, including further information on the actions we are intending to take&lt;/a&gt;, is available on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this represents an important step forward in removing unnecessary regulatory burdens. Some elements of this programme will mark a major shift in the way the Department does business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcomes also need to be viewed against the backdrop of the Government’s wider efforts to put an end to the micro-management that occurred under the last Government in relation to matters such as franchise management. Both our franchise reform programme and our command paper ‘Reforming our Railways: Putting the Customer First’ seek to transfer more decisions from Whitehall to the professionals who run our railways as part of our efforts to deliver a more financially sustainable and customer-focused railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is already implementing the results of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120819091700/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/gov-20110520"&gt;Roads Transport Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and Aviation Transportation, the final transport theme, is now open for public comment until 26 July.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13685</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/annual-update-on-crossrail"/>
    <title>Annual update on Crossrail</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crossrail is now moving firmly into its construction phase. A number of significant milestones have been achieved in the last twelve months. The purpose built Tunneling and Underground Construction Academy was opened in East London last year and welcomed its first students in September 2011. Tunneling began in May, with the first tunnel boring machine launched at the Royal Oak Portal in west London. Construction contracts for Paddington, Farringdon, Whitechapel, Tottenham Court Road and Liverpool Street stations have been awarded. The Canary Wharf station box structure is now complete. The Invitation to Negotiate for the Crossrail Rolling Stock and Depot contract was launched by Crossrail Limited on 28 February, with the first round of tenders due to be returned during late summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the number of lorry movements, excavated material from Crossrail’s western tunnels has started to be transported directly from Royal Oak to Northfleet in Kent by rail. A former freight line from the North Kent Line has been completely reconstructed to enable freight train movements from London. Two-thirds of excavated material generated by tunnel, station and shafts construction will be taken to Northfleet and transferred by ship to create a new 1,500 acre nature reserve at Wallasea Island in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail is responsible for delivering improvements on the existing surface sections of the Crossrail route. The overall target price for these works was approved in April 2012 and was within the £2.3bn funding envelope. Network Rail has also begun construction of the expanded Stockley Flyover in west London to enable higher frequency Crossrail trains to operate to Heathrow Airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crossrail services are on schedule to be operational from 2018 with full services operating from late 2019. The Crossrail Board continues to forecast that the costs of constructing Crossrail will be within the agreed funding limits. We expect Crossrail to cost no more than £14.5billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the passage of the Crossrail Bill through Parliament, a commitment was given that a statement would be published at least every 12 months until the completion of the construction of Crossrail, setting out information about the project’s funding and finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with this commitment, this statement comes within 12 months of my last one which was published on 13 July 2011. The relevant information is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total funding amounts provided to Crossrail Limited by the Department for Transport and Transport for London (TfL) in relation to the construction of Crossrail to the end of the period (22 July 2008 to 29 May 2012).
£2,751,624,360&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expenditure incurred (including committed land and property spend not yet paid out) by Crossrail Limited in relation to the construction of Crossrail in the period 30 May 2011 to 29 May 2012 (excluding recoverable VAT on Land and Property purchases).
£1,044,294,000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total expenditure incurred (including committed land and property spend not yet paid out) by Crossrail Limited in relation to the construction of Crossrail to the end of the period 22 July 2008 to 29 May 2012 (excluding recoverable VAT on Land and Property purchases).
£2,928,548,000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amounts realised by the disposal of any land or property for the purposes of the construction of Crossrail by the Secretary of State, TfL or Crossrail Limited in the period covered by the statement.
£nil&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers above are drawn from Crossrail Limited’s books of account and have been prepared on a consistent basis with the update provided last year. The figure for expenditure incurred includes monies already paid out in relevant periods, including committed land and property expenditure where this has not yet been paid. It does not include future expenditure on construction contracts that have been awarded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14891</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rail-franchise-to-deliver-smart-card-tickets-and-encourage-investment-in-better-stations"/>
    <title>New rail franchise to deliver smart card tickets and encourage investment in better stations </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new 15 year Essex Thameside franchise will see passengers benefit from the introduction of smart card ticketing and provide important opportunities for private sector investment in improving stations, under proposals being put forward by Rail Minister Theresa Villiers today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/essex-thameside-franchise/"&gt;Invitation to Tender (ITT) published today for the new franchise&lt;/a&gt;, will also give bidders much more flexibility to develop their own train timetable to better suit passenger demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A more flexible franchise will encourage private sector investment, for example in improving stations. It will promote greater efficiency to drive down costs and also enable the train operator to react more flexibly to changing passenger demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The introduction of new requirements on passenger satisfaction will mean the operator has to focus strongly on the issues that matter most to passengers. Across the franchise, the roll out of smart ticketing will provide many more passengers with greater convenience and the sort of advantages already enjoyed in the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise will run for 15 years from May 2013 to May 2028, with an option for the department to extend for up to 7 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full repairing responsibilities of the 25 stations, including Fenchurch Street, will be transferred from Network Rail to the new operator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The franchise agreement will ensure that a minimum number of stops at each station will be provided but gives bidders more flexibility to adapt timetables to cater for changes in demand. This should enable the future franchisee to run services in a more efficient way which is more responsive to the travelling priorities of passengers using the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New service quality targets have been set and based around stations, train services, train facilities and customer services. The indicators have been weighted to reflect local priorities and will be revised to capture any changes during the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Details published of the new franchise that will take over from 26 May 2013, are set out by the Department in an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/essex-thameside-franchise/"&gt;Invitation to Tender (ITT)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Invitation to Tender follows a consultation designed to give the public and stakeholders a chance to have their say on what they wanted from the new franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Train Service Specification for the operation of Essex Thameside represents a relaxation from the rigid timetable specification of the past, while retaining obligations that protect the key outcomes for passengers and taxpayers, such as principal first and last trains and minimum numbers of station stops per week and per day. This marks a significant shift from the micro-management that has prevented operators from maximising capacity and optimising timetables to react to the changing demands of their passengers in the past.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The four shortlisted bidders to run the franchise from May 2013 are Abellio, First Group, National Express and MTR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bids for the franchise are expected to be received by 27 September 2012 and the new operator will be announced in January 2013. The new Essex Thameside franchise will run until May 2028, with an option for the Department to extend up to 7 months.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the government set out its plans on franchise reform, it acknowledged that each franchise contract needs to reflect the different characteristics of the lines and services it covers. Therefore the requirements set out in the Essex Thameside Franchise may not necessarily become standard terms in every subsequent rail franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ITT for the Essex Thameside franchise follows the current agreed regulated fares policy as set out in the 2011 Comprehensive Spending Review - a rise in 2012 of RPI+1% and RPI+3% for 2013 and 2014, returning to RPI+1% thereafter. Over the long term we are committed to reducing the cost of running the railways and the goal of ending the era of above-inflation fare increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/essex-thameside-franchise/"&gt;Essex Thameside franchise: Invitation to tender, 2 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066  &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14961</id>
    <published>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/putting-aviation-red-tape-under-the-spotlight"/>
    <title>Putting aviation red tape under the spotlight</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers and the aviation industry are being given the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;chance to cut red tape to make life easier for passengers and boost business.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation Minister Theresa Villiers is putting the spotlight on around 90 aviation regulations that have been placed on the Red Tape Challenge website today. The exercise gives people the opportunity to say whether they think that a regulation is well designed and provides vital protection or is badly designed, badly implemented or simply a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulations under the spotlight include instances where UK rules go beyond the minimum required by EU or international legislation. The exercise also offers an opportunity to see if some of the UK’s more historic aviation legislation is still fit for purpose and suited to today’s aviation needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas for deregulatory consideration include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;getting rid of all non-essential regulatory burdens on the aviation sector in order to unlock private sector-led economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;replacing obsolete legislation and delivering a new system of regulation, more focused than the current regime (work on this is already underway through the Civil Aviation Bill)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removing redundant regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aviation Minister Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a chance for everyone to have their say, whether they are a passenger, the owner of an airline or a light aircraft or are just an aviation enthusiast. We are determined to scrap any regulations which are disproportionate or obsolete, getting rid of non-essential regulatory burdens on the aviation sector.
&amp;gt;There’s no doubt that good quality regulation can add real value to the competitiveness of the aviation industry while balancing genuine environmental, safety and security concerns. But reducing red tape by getting rid of regulations which are unnecessary means we can help UK businesses become more competitive and create more jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has recruited experienced ‘sector champions’ who will be providing expert knowledge during the Red Tape Challenge based on the issues they face in their fields. The sector champions for aviation are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simon Buck, Chief Executive, British Air Transport Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tim Johnson, Director, Aviation Environment Federation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rob Siddall, Policy Director, Airport Operators Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark Tanzer, Chief Executive, ABTA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Bishop, Managing Director, DHL Air UK&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Tannock, Chief Executive, Light Aircraft Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marc Bailey, Chief Executive, British Business and General Aviation Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simon Buck, Chief Executive at British Air Transport Association, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The airline industry faces regulation not just from UK authorities but also from European and global regulators. This why we welcome the Red Tape Challenge as a way of identifying and reducing national regulation that may have become unnecessary, burdensome or simply obsolete having been overlaid by international requirements and I am pleased to be involved with this initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Johnson, Director at Aviation Environment Federation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Regulation can both promote and impede effective environmental protection. Pausing to examine how legislation is working in practice is a valuable opportunity for us to identify if it is still relevant in terms of being practical to implement or promoting environmentally-beneficial outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob Siddall, Policy Director at Airport Operators Association, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Helping ensure that the UK’s airports operate in the right business climate to flourish is a core activity for The Airport Operators Association. The Red Tape Challenge operates right on that territory, by looking for regulation that’s no longer needed or can be done differently. We’re looking forward to playing our part in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Tanzer, Chief Executive at the Association of British Travel Agents (ABTA), said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aviation is the lifeblood connecting the UK to the world. Good aviation regulation is essential to a successful and thriving sector that could help to facilitate the growth desperately needed in the UK. Businesses within the aviation sector, and the many businesses dependent upon it, have a unique opportunity to identify to Government those pieces of regulation which are holding back growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall aim of the Red Tape Challenge, a government-wide initiative to reduce bureaucracy, is to remove barriers to economic growth and increase individual freedoms. The presumption is that regulations will go, unless their retention can be justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge was launched by the Prime Minister on 7 April 2011, giving the public a chance to have their say on the more than 10,000 regulations that affect their everyday lives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Aviation Theme will go live on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge website&lt;/a&gt; on 28 June 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 themes, totalling over 3700 regulations have been launched on the Red Tape Challenge website so far&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall, of the 1500 regulations (across 8 themes) where ministers have already made decisions, the government has committed to scrap or improve well over 50% - decisions that will bring real benefits to business, civil society organisations and individuals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge process does not include legislation falling within the responsibilities of the devolved administrations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For each sector theme, experienced ‘sector champions’ are appointed who will provide expert knowledge in their specialist field; the champion acts as an intermediary between the sector and government, including helping to direct the web-based debates and discussions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14828</id>
    <published>2012-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/intercity-east-coast-franchise-consultation-launched"/>
    <title>Intercity East Coast franchise consultation launched</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers who travel between London and Scotland via the North East and Yorkshire are on track to get a host of improvements to their services, including a fleet of brand new trains and better stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the InterCity East Coast franchise consultation today, Rail Minister Theresa Villiers invited passengers, local councils and anyone with an interest in improved services on the East Coast Main Line to send in their views on what they want from the next franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are exciting changes on the horizon for the East Coast Main Line. It is set to receive a brand new fleet of InterCity Express trains. The next franchise will be up to 12 years in length giving the operator greater opportunities to invest in improvements that will benefit passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The consultation outlines what we expect the next operator to deliver, including better service quality, improvements to stations, the roll out of smart-ticketing technology and good levels of punctuality. Bidders will need to share with us their plans to improve the passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The East Coast Main Line is a key part of our nation’s transport infrastructure providing heavily used and economically significant services between north and south. Before we let this franchise, we want to hear from the people who use East Coast and listen to their ideas on better services. This consultation will help us make decisions on how we get the most from the improvements planned for the line over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning bidder, which will operate services on the East Coast Main Line from 2013, will need to deliver a number of different improvements including in relation to service quality and provision of information to customers, particularly during times of planned engineering works and unplanned disruption. The new franchisee will be responsible for ensuring that overall passenger experience improves throughout the life of the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful bidder is expected to oversee the introduction of new InterCity Express trains on the route, providing more capacity than the High Speed Trains they are planned to replace on much of the franchise. We also want to hear bidders’ ideas on how they will improve stations and make them more attractive gateways to rail services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The InterCity East Coast Franchise Replacement consultation, which starts on Tuesday 26 June and closes on 18 September 2012. The Department for Transport will produce a summary of the consultation responses alongside the Invitation to Tender, which will be published in January 2013. The winning bidder will be announced in August 2013 with the new franchise planned to start in December 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new operator will be expected to manage the franchise alongside planned upgrades to infrastructure and services, including introduction of Intercity Express Programme trains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation document confirms the Coalition’s continuing support for through services between London and destinations north of Edinburgh.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new franchise will return the operation of ICEC services to the private sector, replacing operation by Directly Operated Railways on behalf of the Secretary of State for Transport following early termination of the previous franchise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A copy of the consultation document is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-24/"&gt;DfT website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h4 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-24/"&gt;InterCity East Coast franchise consultation, 26 June 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108  &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14372</id>
    <published>2012-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/warwick-parkway-extension-given-go-ahead"/>
    <title>Warwick Parkway extension given go ahead</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commuters are to benefit from extra car parking spaces at Warwick Parkway station thanks to a £1m government contribution to the investment to build a new multi-storey car park, Rail Minister Theresa Villiers announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The substantial car park extension will boost capacity for passengers, increasing the current number of spaces to 959, from its current capacity of 737 spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport will provide £1m, working in conjunction with Chiltern Railways, towards the total cost of the £2.5m project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work has already started on the new extension to the car park scheduled to be opened by December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Theresa Villiers said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that we are able to announce the investment for this considerable car park extension at Warwick Parkway. There is no doubt that this will encourage more people to travel by train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Adding additional car park capacity will mean more spaces for passengers, easing congestion and helping improve overall journey satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with funding from Chiltern, the government’s contribution will improve the passenger experience and bring new commuters to the station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiltern Railways became the first UK operator to own and build a new station when Warwick Parkway opened in October 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Development Director for Chiltern Railways, Graham Cross said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of our Mainline service between London Marylebone and the West Midlands has resulted in record growth levels and a dramatic increase in passengers travelling from Warwick Parkway. The new multi-storey car park will meet the rising demand and demonstrates our commitment to offering the best service to our customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new extended car park is scheduled to open in December 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The department will provide £1m towards the full scheme cost of £2.5m.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
