<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/vince-cable</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/vince-cable.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Dr Vince Cable MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60564</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:05:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consumers-given-more-copyright-freedom"/>
    <title>Consumers given more copyright freedom</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>People will be able to legally make digital copies of music, films and eBooks for personal use as goverment changes UK copyright law.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has previously been illegal in the UK to move copyrighted works from one device to another, such as from a CD to an MP3 player or an iPod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new measures announed by government are designed to create a modern, robust and flexible copyright framework, whilst also protect the interests of authors and right owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes could contribute at least £500m to the UK economy over 10 years, and perhaps much more from reduced costs, increased competition and by making copyright works more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also be easier to create parodies of copyrighted works and for the purposes of quotation. They will also bring up to date existing exceptions for education, research and the preservation of materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary, Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Making the intellectual property framework fit for the 21st century is not only common sense but good business sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bringing the law into line with ordinary people’s reasonable expectations will boost respect for copyright, on which our creative industries rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We feel we have struck the right balance between improving the way consumers benefit from copyright works they have legitimately paid for, boosting business opportunities and protecting the rights of creators.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-to-copyright-law"&gt;Changes to copyright law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his review of intellectual property and growth, Professor Hargreaves made the case for the UK making greater use of these exceptions, which are allowed under EU law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to a consultation earlier this year, the Government will make changes to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Private copying - to permit people to copy digital content they have bought onto any medium or device that they own, but strictly for their own personal use such as transferring their music collection or eBooks to their tablet, phone or to a private cloud&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Education - to simplify copyright licensing for the education sector and make it easier for teachers to use copyright materials on interactive whiteboards and similar technology in classrooms and provide access to copyright works over secure networks to support the growing demand for distance learning handouts for students&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quotation and news reporting - to create a more general permission for quotation of copyright works for any purpose, as long as the use of a particular quotation is “fair dealing” and its source is acknowledged&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parody, caricature and pastiche - to allow limited copying on a fair dealing basis which would allow genuine parody, but prohibit copying disguised as parody&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research and private study - to allow sound recordings, films and broadcasts to be copied for non-commercial research and private study purposes without permission from the copyright holder. This includes both user copying and library copying&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data analytics for non-commercial research - to allow non-commercial researchers to use computers to study published research results and other data without copyright law interfering&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access for people with disabilities - to allow people with disabilities the right to obtain copyright works in accessible formats where a suitable one is not already on the market&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Archiving and preservation - to allow museums, galleries, libraries and archives to preserve any type of copyright work that is in their permanent collection which cannot readily be replaced&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Public administration - to widen existing exceptions to enable more public bodies to share proactively third party information online, which would reflect the existing position in relation to the use of paper copies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/types/hargreaves/hargreaves-copyright.htm"&gt;Government response to the Hargreaves Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/home.htm"&gt;Intellectual property Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56696</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cable-announces-step-change-to-turn-ideas-into-growth"/>
    <title>Cable announces step change to turn ideas into growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Secretary Vince Cable, today set out new plans to make sure UK creativity and innovation supports growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at The Big Innovation Centre, Dr Cable launched a range of measures that will improve services to business, strengthen enforcement, and help consumers get the most out of creative products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plans, which will involve a step change in the way the Intellectual Property Office (IPO) delivers services, include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;launching a superfast patent processing service to deliver patents in just 90 days and a faster trade marks examination service which will deliver a full examination report in five days, instead of 10;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a campaign to educate smaller businesses about getting the best value from their creativity and innovation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;action to help consumers and young people understand the importance of respect for IP and the harm counterfeiting or illegal downloading can do; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with key partners, such as the City of London Police, to tackle IP  crime such  as counterfeiting and online piracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new measures, which will come into effect next year, aim to encourage and help businesses get the best value from their ideas and boost growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new measures, which will come into effect next year, aim to encourage and help businesses get the best value from their ideas and boost growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IPO will also expand the way it operates, moving beyond just granting rights and do more to support businesses in understanding the opportunities available to them at home and abroad. This will include piloting an IP advisory service for small and medium businesses with high-growth potential. The IPO will work more closely with organisations where businesses already go for advice such as trade associations, UKTI, chambers of commerce, banks and accountants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our creativity, our openness to and talent for innovation, is a key pillar of our return to robust growth. So it is right we work to create the environment in which creative, innovative businesses of all shapes and sizes flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A vital part of this is making sure the intellectual property landscape encourages and cements success and growth. The new vision for how we support businesses and consumers is central to achieving this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure consumers are protected from counterfeiters and better understand the use and value of intellectual property is also key. A new national consumer campaign will be launched in the Spring to help raise awareness about counterfeiting and piracy and ensure that the rights of creators and innovators are better enforced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activity will in particular focus on young people, reaching out to them in schools, theme parks and on the web, to educate them about their responsibilities in downloading materials and also protecting their own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be further strengthening of the IPO’s IP attaché network which places a business attaché in challenging overseas markets to help British businesses and encourage improvements to the nation’s IP environment. In 2013, a new attaché will be placed in Singapore to serve South Asian markets, supporting those already in place in China, India and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will host an enforcement summit next summer inviting countries from around the world to share best practice and work together to combat problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Business Secretary is seting out his vision for developing the UK’s intellectual property landscape to encourage growth and a renewed programme of action for the Intellectual Property Office. Dr Cable is speaking at The Big Innovation Space at 9.00am on Monday 17 December at The Big Innovation Centre, 21 Palmer Street, London SW1H 0AD.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Intellectual Property Office (IPO) is part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) and is responsible for the national framework of Intellectual Property rights, comprising patents, designs, trade marks and copyright.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The IPO’s role is to help manage an IP system that encourages innovation and creativity, balances the needs of consumers and users, promotes strong and competitive markets and is the foundation of the knowledge-based economy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The IPO operates in a national and an international environment and its work is governed by national and international law, including various international treaties relating to Intellectual Property (IP) to which the United Kingdom is a party.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55331</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:21:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boosting-skills-and-jobs-on-the-south-coast"/>
    <title>Boosting skills and jobs on the south coast</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Following the Autumn Statement, Vince Cable visited Southampton to launch two schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable was in Southampton to launch two key schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment, following on from new investment launched in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;Chancellor’s Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He visited Eastleigh College to announce a new £550 million Further Education Capital Investment Fund to help improve college facilities across the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That investment  will be targeted towards colleges in the greatest need of help to improve facilities, improve efficiency and save money in the long term. Colleges will be able to apply for funding through the Skills Funding Agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extra £310 million for the Regional Growth Fund to create and safeguard jobs was also announced in the Autumn Statement.  To date, £2.4 billion has been conditionally offered to businesses and intermediaries up and down the country – creating jobs and boosting the local economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south coast has benefited from a number of different Regional Growth Fund projects and programmes. The Solent LEP has been awarded £2m from the Regional Growth Fund to roll out the second phase of the successful Bridging the Gap Funding programme to Southampton and the Isle of Wight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other beneficiaries of Regional Growth Fund awards for the area include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southampton City Council has been awarded a further £5.3 million Regional Growth Fund in support of the ‘Platform for Prosperity’ project bringing the total to £10.9 million. The project entails the improvement and upgrade of the road infrastructure outside Eastern Docks and is expected to create or safeguard over 800 jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cobra Precision Engineering and Elite Care Homes are two of the first recipients of £100,000 of phase one of the Solent LEPs Bridging the Gap award. The grant will leverage close to £600,000 additional private investment and create and safeguard 12 jobs at the two firms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Solent Future’s project is a £13m Regional Growth Fund money investment from Round 3. Part of the funding will be utilised to ensure a sustainable future for the Advanced Manufacturing skills in the Solent workforce. This will bring together leading businesses, colleges and Universities at a world-class training centre on the Solent Enterprise Zone. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Portsmouth Naval Base Property Trust in Portsmouth secured £1.23 million of Regional Growth Fund to support two projects within the Historic Dockyard at Portsmouth. 
£750,000 will be used to develop the Cell Block Enterprise project which will support enterprise skills development and provide access to early stage funding with mentoring managed by the University of Portsmouth. The project aims to create over 440 jobs in the supply chain. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£475,000 will contribute to the development of the International Boatbuilding Training College (IBTC) which combines heritage conservation with apprenticeships and other training to develop transferrable skills. The project has also had initial support from the Heritage Lottery Fund which could result in a final grant of £3.9 million grant to help support the development of heritage skills for the future. Both projects will have a ten year economic life cycle. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;LINKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Dec/autumn-statement-2012"&gt;BIS: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Vince-Cable-launches-schemes-for-skills-and-jobs-on-South-Coast-68482.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Vince Cable launches schemes for skills and jobs on South Coast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-550m-capital-investment-programme-will-transform-FE-colleges-68485.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New £550m capital investment programme will transform FE colleges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55695</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:26:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/vince-cable-launches-schemes-for-skills-and-jobs-on-south-coast"/>
    <title>Vince Cable launches schemes for skills and jobs on South Coast</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable visited Eastleigh College to announce a new £550 million Further Education Capital Investment Fund which will help improve college facilities across the country. He also announced an additional £310 million for the Regional Growth Fund to create and safeguard jobs. Both schemes will support growth in the economy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capital investment will be targeted towards colleges in the greatest need of help to improve facilities, improve efficiency and save money in the long term. Colleges will be able to apply for funding through the Skills Funding Agency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, the Business Secretary toured the College’s Technology Skills Centre where he met apprentices learning a range of practical disciplines from plumbing to electrical installation. He also saw the Engage Recruitment unit which works with the local JobCentre Plus to help students of all ages develop their skills, qualifications and work experience in order to find employment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastleigh College is a member of the Ford Multi Agency Task Force which has been set up to address the impact of any job losses from Ford in Southampton. Dr Cable saw how the college is working with local business to help support the unemployed get back to work with different job opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Southampton is facing some serious challenges. The Ford van closure was undoubtedly a big blow. But there are some real strengths in the region including the universities and colleges. Eastleigh College plays an important role in the region and its economy. It is heavily involved in the Ford Multi Agency Task Force in Southampton and its’ strong relationship with local business will help produce the highly skilled people the economy needs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The quality of further education facilities should match the aspiration of the sector which is why the Government is stepping up capital spending, over the next two years £550 million is being invested in transforming colleges across the country, providing thousands of students with much better facilities.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastleigh College Chief Executive Tony Lau Walker said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One hundred per cent of Eastleigh College’s focus is working directly with employers to ensure a prosperous economic future for the region and enable local people to have the employment skills valued by employers for their business growth. New capital funds will ensure Eastleigh College can invest in new facilities and technologies to meet the needs of a growing economy.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further announcement from the Autumn Statement was that an additional £310 million will be added to the Government’s Regional Growth Fund. So far, £2.4 billion has been conditionally offered to businesses and intermediaries up and down the country - creating jobs and boosting the local economy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south coast has benefited from a number of different Regional Growth Fund projects and programmes. The Solent LEP has been awarded £2m from the Regional Growth Fund to roll out the second phase of the successful Bridging the Gap Funding programme to Southampton and the Isle of Wight.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is a partnership between Solent LEP, Southampton City Council and the local newspaper, The Daily Echo, to award grant funding to SMEs and startup businesses on a competitive basis. The programme is expected to create or safeguard 200 jobs over the next three years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bid was prioritised and moved through the RGF process quickly in light of the potential Ford closure. This will help workers at Ford who may be looking at self-employment as an option and those SMEs in the Ford supply chain that will require support recalibrating their business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other beneficiaries of Regional Growth Fund awards for the area include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southampton City Council has been awarded a further £5.3 million Regional Growth Fund in support of the ‘Platform for Prosperity’ project bringing the total to £10.9 million. The project entails the improvement and upgrade of the road infrastructure outside Eastern Docks and is expected to create or safeguard over 800 jobs. The investment outside of the port by the public sector, has given ABP Ports the confidence to invest over £200 million within the port estate over the next few years bringing significant benefits to local enterprises that use the port.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cobra Precision Engineering and Elite Care Homes are two of the first recipients of £100,000 of phase one of the Solent LEPs Bridging the Gap award. The grant will leverage close to £600,000 additional private investment and create and safeguard 12 jobs at the two firms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Solent Future’s project is a £13m Regional Growth Fund money investment from Round 3. Part of the funding will be utilised to ensure a sustainable future for the Advanced Manufacturing skills in the Solent workforce. This will bring together leading businesses and the further education sector at a world-class training centre on the Solent Enterprise Zone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Portsmouth Naval Base Property Trust in Portsmouth secured £1.23 million of Regional Growth Fund to support two projects within the Historic Dockyard at Portsmouth. 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£750,000 will be used to develop the Cell Block Enterprise project which will support enterprise skills development and provide access to early stage funding with mentoring managed by the University of Portsmouth. The project aims to create over 440 jobs in the supply chain. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;£475,000 will contribute to the development of the International Boatbuilding Training College (IBTC) which combines heritage conservation with apprenticeships and other training to develop transferrable skills. The project has also had initial support from the Heritage Lottery Fund which could result in a final grant of £3.9 million grant to help support the development of heritage skills for the future. Both projects will have a ten year economic life cycle. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Regional Growth Fund is helping to stimulate private sector investment and is having a beneficial effect in communities across the country. The additional £310 million of funding will help us support more projects and create more jobs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This reflects the success of the fund and the positive impact it is having on jobs - whether it is small SMEs such as Cobra Precision Engineering or larger infrastructure projects. The work of Solent LEP, Southampton Council and other stakeholders is crucial in linking up the public and private sectors to boost economic growth.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doug Morrison, Solent LEP Chairman, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Solent LEP have worked hard to ensure that national funding opportunities such as the Regional Growth Fund are accessible to entrepreneurs and SMEs locally in the Solent; and our work with The Daily Echo, The News, The University of Portsmouth and other organisations on Bridging the Gap is a fantastic example of this.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are finding that locally, we are able to administer funding extremely quickly and efficiently, and the first two funding recipients from Bridging the Gap announced by Dr Cable today highlight this. Of course this investment comes at a challenging time for the Solent economy; and the work we are doing with Eastleigh College on the Ford task force and the investment we have been able to secure for schemes like phase 2 of Bridging the Gap and Platform Road in Southampton will help our economy come through this difficult period.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Notes to Editors  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**1. Eastleigh College is one of the largest employer engaging colleges in the south east. In 2011/12 the college worked with 22,000 learners and 1,400 employers and was inspected by Ofsted as Grade 1 ‘Outstanding’ in July 2012.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FE Capital Investment Strategy can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/F/12-1340-further-education-college-capital-investment-strategy-plan"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/F/12-1340-further-education-college-capital-investment-strategy-plan&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Colleges are normally expected to contribute at least double the government grant contribution. On this basis a £550m government contribution is expected to enable college projects valued at in excess of ??1.65bn. The £550m capital funds are over 2 years - 2013-14 and 2014-15.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An evaluation of the impact of capital expenditure on FE college outcomes, used to inform the FE College Capital Investment Strategy is being published on the same day as the announcement of the Strategy. The evaluation can be found at (DN insert link)  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Regional Growth Fund (RGF) is a £2.6bn fund operating across England from 2011 to 2015. It supports projects and programmes that lever private sector investment to create economic growth and sustainable employment. It aims particularly to help those areas and communities which were dependent on the public sector to make the transition to sustainable private sector-led growth and prosperity.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first three rounds allocated £2.4 billion and will leverage over £13 billion of private sector investment - creating and safeguarding 540,000 jobs.   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement 2012 provided for an additional £310 million of Regional Growth Fund money. Government will confirm how applicants can apply for funding in due course.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information on the Regional Growth Fund can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/rgf"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/rgf&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Solent Local Enterprise Partnership (LEP) is a locally-owned partnership between businesses, local authorities and higher and further education, and plays a central role in determining local economic priorities and undertaking activities to drive economic growth and the creation of local jobs.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Solent LEP is led by the business community and supported by university partners, the further education sector, three unitary authorities, eight district councils, one county council and the voluntary and community sector - all working together to secure a more prosperous and sustainable future for the Solent area.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries.’ It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011: &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work is underway across Government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the Government wants the economy to travel.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BIS’s online newsroom contains the latest press notices, speeches, as well as video and images for download. It also features an up to date list of BIS press office contacts. See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/newsroom"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/newsroom&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer, George Osborne, has delivered his 2012 Autumn Statement to Parliament.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55457</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/responsible-capitalism"/>
    <title>Responsible capitalism</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Vince Cable discusses how capitalism can go wrong and states the government's aim for a market economy based on responsible capitalism.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning. It is no exaggeration to say the pensions industry is a lynchpin of the economy. Pension fund investments are a critical source of capital for UK companies, and potentially for infrastructure as well as savings vehicles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectively, you hold over £150bn of UK equities. That figure illustrates the scale of your influence, but it goes much further than merely delivering returns to fund tomorrow’s pensions for today’s workers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Careful husbandry over long timescales, a core duty for any pension fund, is an essential component in a system of responsible capitalism that encourages the pursuit of long-term value rather than short-run, sometimes illusory, returns.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like to focus today on the work we are doing in government to support such a system - because it is clear we have a long way to go before we can say it exists.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equity investment has become increasingly complex and intermediated, with more and more links in the chain. As a result, the different players are often working to their own agendas and timescales to the detriment of long-term value creation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often, traders go after a quick buck rather than looking for sustainable returns based on sound stewardship of companies. Holdings are bought and sold to turn a short-term profit with no thought given to the underlying fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phantom chase was at its most frantic in the financial markets, where banks took dross and sold it as gold. But that lack of responsibility - the failure to take calculated investment risks based on sound principles - is more widespread. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capitalism"&gt;Capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of so called short-termism is part of a wider debate about capitalism and whether it should be constrained by a wider sense of responsibility. So, what do I mean by responsible capitalism? Let me explain by quoting Adam Smith, who said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest. We address ourselves, not to their humanity, but to their self-love, and never talk to them of our own necessities, but of their advantages.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Adam Smith himself was scathing about some forms of business behaviour - particularly those that led to the suppression of competition. He wrote “people of the same trade seldom meet together even for merriment and diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise that there some irony in using this particular quote in a speech to a trade association conference. But Smith’s conception of self-interest is distinct from the crude, material, selfishness we have seen. Elsewhere in his writings he discusses the notion of sympathy, or fellow feeling, and emphasises its importance. So Smith’s butcher or baker cannot pursue their self-interest and obtain what they want without also meeting the needs of the customer. .   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pursuit of self-interest is not inherently irresponsible: the desire to trade and profit produced meat, beer and bread in Smith’s day, and today has given us iPads, foreign holidays and life-saving drugs. What connects these things is their reliance on individuals acting in their own interests to deliver goods and services that benefit us all.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to reconcile Smith’s butcher, brewer and baker with the complexity of today’s capitalism. Indeed the modern public company with dispersed shareholder ownership did not exist at that time. But they would have recognised the key role that trust and confidence play in effective markets. Without them, no economy can function effectively.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen too many examples of irresponsible capitalism recently. Companies not paying their taxes. Employees making up the numbers or gambling the future of the entire company. Customers being sold complex products they neither need nor want. Managers helping themselves to lavish remuneration packages at the expense of customers, their shareholders and their workforce.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Roger Carr, the CBI’s President, acknowledged the problem at its annual conference on Monday. He said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Standards have been variable, greed prevalent and fairness forgotten in a number of sectors - banking and media at the forefront - but others from all walks of life showing signs of bad behaviour.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who found myself labelled “anti-business” for criticising the excesses of banking and media barons I empathise totally with Sir Roger. He, like me, is of course pro-business.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like many in this room and in business we share a sense of dismay at some recent behaviour. I believe the majority of businesses play by the rules, pay their taxes and contribute to the economy. Where they don’t, Government has a duty to intervene. But as owners, institutional investors have a major role in challenging and correcting this behaviour.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our task together is to reform the system in order that trust is restored because, without it, the capitalist system cannot function effectively.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are fundamental questions about why parts of the capitalist system have gone awry. At least part of the industry’s problem is one of distorted perspective - a prevailing focus on the short term at the expense of the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-kay-review"&gt;The Kay Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the supposition which led me to invite John Kay to look at this problem in the round. And he has subjected the UK’s equity markets to rigorous independent review with support from Sir John Rose, formerly of Rolls Royce, Chris Hitchen of Railpen and James Anderson of Baillie Gifford   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His findings amount to a compelling argument that today’s transactional cultures and the pursuit of short-term gains in financial markets are undermining the core responsibility of company directors and institutional investors to act as effective stewards of the assets they control.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long-term pursuit of value creation has been crowded out by a focus on short-term gains.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company directors have a clear legal responsibility to make decisions with regard to the long-term. This is part of their duty to promote the success of the company. Engagement by investors needs to change to support directors to meet this responsibility. The focus should be aligned with the timescales of the company’s business model - which may be very long term.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the stewardship relationship must be based on an understanding of company fundamentals. That’s the best way to create an environment of trust and challenge, which enables those managing the company to take sound long-term decisions on investment and strategy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Kay found there is a particular problem in how the performance of active asset managers is currently measured. Faced with the need to deliver short-term performance, active asset managers will have an incentive to focus on what the market is doing - seeking to outperform other asset managers - rather than to engage with companies to understand and foster the creation of value.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So pension schemes and other asset holders need to issue clear mandates for active asset managers. They must set targets to achieve &lt;strong&gt;absolute&lt;/strong&gt; returns that meet the needs of savers rather than just chasing the market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That approach will send a strong signal that it’s time the short-termism ended and was replaced by a clear-sighted focus on long-term value creation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to John for his cogent analysis of the problems in the corporate sector. Today I am publishing the Government’s response to his review. It focuses on restoring relationships based on trust and confidence to the investment chain. The report has provoked constructive debate on many of the issues raised, and progress is being made on a number of the recommendations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Financial Reporting Council has revised the Stewardship Code to give a sharper emphasis on long-term company strategy, reinforcing the message that engagement has to be more than a box-ticking exercise. Instead, it requires genuine dialogue with companies about the long-term prospects for growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors are also recognising they need to engage collectively with companies. The review recommended an investor forum to maximise their influence, and there are encouraging signs that this will happen soon. I am happy to be a catalyst but it is not for government to create a new quango - a forum will only succeed if it is created and run by the investors it represents.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High on the to-do list for any forum is to tackle overly complex incentive schemes which encourage short-termism and tend to pay out asymmetrically. Some executives see spectacular rewards for good performance but there is no corresponding fall in pay when performance is poor.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Kay called on companies and asset managers to change their own practices. Our reforms to executive pay - including giving shareholders a binding vote on pay policy for the first time - will support this by empowering investors to engage more effectively with companies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come a long way in the last year. The shareholder spring has shown there is real appetite among shareholders to be much more challenging of unjustified pay awards.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial factor is ensuring investors have the information they need to make long-term decisions, on pay and a range of other issues. John Kay was scathing about the effect of quarterly reporting on long-term investment. I agree with his analysis, and the government will work with our European counterparts to change the law so it is no longer required.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a challenge here too for asset owners, including pension funds, who need to look beyond quarterly performance to judge their managers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our narrative reporting reforms, to encourage better quality annual reports that put the numbers into context, will help. The new rules, which come into force next year, will make reports simpler, more relevant and more focussed on forward looking strategy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust is also the product of behaviour - a commitment to act with integrity and expect integrity from each other.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Fiduciary duty’ is used a lot in the debate on these issues, but it means different things to different people. We need clarity, with consistent standards of behaviour required throughout the investment chain.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today we are making it clear that all intermediaries should act in good faith in the long-term interests of clients or beneficiaries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These standards should be universal and immutable. We need to achieve them by making sure that our regulatory framework supports them - but also by promoting them as behavioural norms in the investment industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will ask the Financial Conduct Authority to consider whether their regulatory rules and approach support these standards and, where necessary, we will argue for changes to regulatory requirements at EU level.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we are asking the Law Commission to conduct a review of the legal obligations on investment intermediaries seeking to act in their clients’ best interests - and to report back as soon as is practicable   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takeovers bring the discussion of duty and long-termism into particularly sharp focus. Company directors have a legal duty to promote the success of the company. A duty that requires that decisions be made with regard to the long-term consequences.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company directors must recommend that shareholders reject a bid if they believe that the transaction will destroy long-term value, or that the premium being offered does not reflect the fundamental value of the company. Directors must give their best advice to shareholders. Shareholders must then decide what to do.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owners and asset managers have a vital role here. In order to protect their long-term financial interests they must challenge management to explain the strategy and logic of large deals and provide robust, consistent push-back where they have concerns. Events continue to show it is as true for the shareholders in the bidding company as it is in the target.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the Takeover Panel are carrying out a review of the impacts of last year’s changes to the Takeover Code. I look forward to seeing their findings, and their assessment of the progress that has been made.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the light of the debate around takeovers in the wake of the Kraft acquisition of Cadbury, I was anxious to ensure that takeover activity should be subject to greater transparency over fee incomes, and that rules should not play into the hands of short-term speculative investors. I therefore welcomed the reforms by the Takeover Panel.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Government also has a wider role to play here - particularly in strategically important sectors. This is recognised by the current legal framework, and we are not proposing to change it. It is important that companies focus on creating sustainable competitive advantage, not on complex merger and acquisition strategies that destroy shareholder value.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takeovers are part of a wider context: the need to ensure that the bedrock of the capitalist system - the competitive market - functions as effectively as possible. The government is consequently strengthening the regulatory framework to create a single, powerful competition authority - the Competition and Markets Authority.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will have a duty to promote competition for the benefit of consumers and will observe the principle of supporting long-term growth. This objective will be formally embedded in its performance framework.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also ensure that the Competition and Markets Authority works closely with sector regulators to more vigorously tackle competition issues in regulated sectors.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the areas I’ve discussed depend on effective engagement between companies and their owners for progress to be made. So to fuel to the cultural change that’s required, we are endorsing John Kay’s ‘Principles for Equity Markets’ - and the directions for market practice which flow from these.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular we have challenged leading industry bodies - including the NAPF - to review the report’s Good Practice Statements. I am delighted the NAPF has accepted this challenge.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to measure the headway we are making on John Kay’s recommendations we will publish a progress check in eighteen months’ time, setting out how Government has taken forward the recommendations and how well companies and investors have stepped up to the plate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-strategy-and-financial-services"&gt;Industrial Strategy and Financial Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other major policies afoot which have at their heart an attempt to inject a more long term approach to business decision making. One is the industrial strategy in which we sit down with sectors like aerospace, life sciences, automobiles, energy supply chains, and others to plan the long term implications for skill development, technological change and innovation and procurement.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another is financial services. Tim Breedon’s recent review for me found the UK has one of the most sophisticated financial centres in the world. But UK businesses outside the financial sector aren’t getting the benefit from this. There is a kind of enclave development unconnected with the real economy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One specific example is that while the City can provide a range of sophisticated services to international business, British medium and small companies cannot get long-term, patient capital for love nor money.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we need to fundamentally change the system so the financial services industry serves businesses, and not the contrary.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking a number of steps to reform the banking industry, but we need to go further and reshape the business finance market. That is why I have announced the creation of a business bank that will have as its core mission to stimulate competition in the business finance markets and make them work for businesses.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a clean balance sheet, and £1bn worth of funding, this bank will be tasked with expanding lending and investment to the manufacturers, exporters and high growth companies that power our economy, in particular addressing the need for long-term, patient capital.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will shortly announce the appointment of an advisory group for the bank. Its task will be to help shape the design and its future activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="wider-work"&gt;Wider work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other areas that will help promote long termism, and truly responsible capitalism, such as greater diversity in workforces - especially in the boardroom, the growth of social enterprise and alternative models such as employee ownership and mutuals. I cannot hope to go into detail on all of these areas in this speech, but we are making good progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This then, is the government’s clear priority - ensuring we have a market economy rooted in a system of responsible capitalism. Expectations of the market system have changed since the financial crisis - after paying for its reconstruction, UK citizens must see and share in the benefits of recovery and growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far-reaching reforms I have discussed today will help, but they are the start of a much longer process. One that requires a change in attitude and behaviour among key players in the system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies are beginning to recognise this, and are investing in jobs, skills, supply chain development, and other areas that will help create long-term value.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only by responding to these concerns that we can restore trust in markets - and as major shareholders you are in a uniquely strong position to help achieve that. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47572</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/association-of-colleges-annual-conference-2012--2"/>
    <title>Association of Colleges annual conference 2012</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Vince Cable sets out how government will improve the status of FE colleges, provide funding to improve facilities and focus on apprenticeships and social mobility.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to begin, as I did this time last year, with a note of thanks. On that occasion, I took the opportunity to congratulate you for catering to the increasing numbers of adults taking basic skills courses - and, indeed, for the great strides you made in delivering apprenticeships. More on those in a moment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start with what’s been the main story of the year - the London Games - where the contribution of our FE sector was considerable. More than 8,000 students from 60 colleges were trained through the “Bridging the Gap” programme, coordinated by North Hertfordshire College, with over 4,000 finding work in security and stewarding roles. In the host boroughs, Hackney Community College led the effort to prepare unemployed residents for similar job opportunities. And on the field of play, someone has worked out that if the FE college and university graduates in Team GB were to constitute a separate country, they would have come seventh in both the Olympic and Paralympic medal tables.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I’m also very encouraged by further increases in adult participation - 15 per cent on Skills for Life courses in English, 20 per cent in maths. All told, provisional data for the 2011/12 academic year reveal over 3.1 million learners aged 19 or over in government-funded further education - including the almost 700,000 people who benefitted from a community learning course. Then we have strong apprenticeship numbers, with more than half a million apprenticeship starts in 2011/12.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These successes are testament to your efforts. I also realise that you are having to manage change, some of it difficult: Community Learning Trust pilots underway; the introduction of adult loans from the start of the 2013/14 academic year; the latest round of the employer ownership pilots for apprenticeships. I want to express my own appreciation to the AoC for the constructive comments we received on the 24+ loans scheme, which led us to introduce additional measures to help students on Access to HE courses and disadvantaged groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="perceptions"&gt;Perceptions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever visiting FE colleges I am always struck by the energy and entrepreneurial sprint of those who lead and work in them. Yet the feeling has remained that people in this country, and some politicians, regard further education as the poor relation to higher education. It explains why ministers and college principals have bandied around awkward phrases such as “parity of esteem” - almost willing school leavers, mature students and the general public to change their minds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are changing, though - and I believe it’s time to stop agonising about negative perceptions. In our popular culture today, the contestants on Masterchef or Great British Bake Off receive infinitely greater exposure than the teams on University Challenge. We rightly admire craft and skill as much as - if not more than - knowledge.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The educational landscape is changing. By the end of this Parliament, we aim to have transformed the status of apprenticeships in this country. My ambition is that by 2015 an 18-year-old leaving school and weighing up the choice of degree versus apprenticeship would do so without factoring in social stigma - seeing them as different but of equal value in terms of experience, job prospects, value for money and earnings potential.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make sure that skills provision in this country is of such quality that any lingering snobbery is removed from the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="improving-college-facilities"&gt;Improving college facilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of facilities in FE should match the aspiration of the sector. I am very aware of the of legacy problems from past underinvestment in the FE estate. As college principals know, we have just confirmed the recipients of the third tranche of renewal grants to 56 more colleges - with Government putting up £110 million in this round alongside over £300 million of investment from the colleges themselves. I regret that at present we are only able to fun half the bids - but there will be future rounds. This money will be put to creating specialist facilities and modernising existing ones - new laboratories at Stratford-Upon-Avon College; a new creative industries building at Kingston College; a new arts centre at Burton and South Derbyshire College.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme, supporting an injection of £1 billion into the FE estate, is producing learning environments in which our lecturers can deliver an excellent education to their students. Sprucing up campuses can give a lift to entire communities - not least through the jobs associated with the remodelling and building work. Over the past three years, we have ensured that all FE colleges in England have had the opportunity to apply for some degree of grant funding. Last year, 244 colleges across England were successful in securing Renewal Grant funding. And this year, a further 150 colleges received support, with 56 of them securing up to £3 million for important building projects. I am grateful for the active support and participation of the AoC throughout the process of setting criteria, assessing applications from colleges and allocating resources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FE, then is a sector that is expanding. Looking ahead, I see three main tasks in particular. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="apprenticeships"&gt;Apprenticeships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there must be no let-up in the drive to increase and improve apprenticeships.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the coming year, we’ll be focusing on making sure that all apprenticeships offer substantial new learning, and that the qualifications apprentices take are stretching and valued by employers. Doug Richard’s forthcoming recommendations will be important here. We’re going to continue increasing the number of higher level apprenticeships, to degree level and beyond, especially in priority sectors like engineering, construction and digital And we’re going to broaden the input of employers in all aspects of apprenticeships - with a special effort to get more SMEs involved.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is also doing more to practise what it preaches - like my own department, where around 30 members of staff, all aged over 25, have signed up for apprenticeships, half of which are at Level 4. In future, we want to expand the scheme to include profession-specific apprenticeships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="social-mobility"&gt;Social mobility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second task is improving social mobility. Here, much of the debate has concentrated on universities, which have increased overall participation of those from disadvantaged backgrounds, though not in the most selective institutions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, to promote meaningful social mobility we must also improve the life chances of those who have already reached adulthood. The UK today has nearly 5 million people of working age with no qualifications.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re doing what we can - including through the all-age National Careers Service - to spread the message that education and training are worthwhile at any point in life. There is a wage return of around 6 per cent just from achieving basic literacy and numeracy. So it is vital that people know about second chances - including those leaving state institutions - a care home, a prison, the Army. Indeed, one of our policies I’m proudest of is a prisons programme in collaboration with a local FE college boosting maths and English skills, based on Army experience.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to the continued funding of English and maths courses for adults without basic skills. We are now funding adults to get Maths and English GCSEs. These programmes are meat and drink for colleges - they always have been. It’s important that colleges are not only recognised for their role as agents of social mobility, but that you make yourselves heard in the wider debate.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same goes for the people in our communities who provide personal learning, family learning and neighbourhood learning courses. The value of what you do cannot be adequately conveyed in bald numbers - because they do not measure improved mental health or self-esteem, nor the boost children get from having parents able to help them read in the evenings or discuss their schoolwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-better-deal-for-young-people"&gt;A better deal for young people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final challenge also falls within the parameters of social mobility, and it’s about filling a gap in provision for young people not in education or employment. Policy formulation remains at an early stage, but I want to give you sense of what we’re considering.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is this: the Government has a clear vision for 16- to 18-year-olds, where we are raising the participation age and increasing support for English and maths. But for young people over 18, the offer is much less clear. There’s generous educational support for some - despite fees higher education is still substantially subsidised - but, for others, financial support through the benefits system can actually prevent them from learning.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we should be keeping this age group as far away from the benefits system as possible, unless there’s a really compelling need. For this group, then, we need a much simpler system, which supports and incentivises people to get the skills they need to secure sustainable employment, whether through HE, FE or an apprenticeship, or through more bespoke interventions to help them acquire the employability skills that too many companies tell me are lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, let me conclude on an optimistic note.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also happened to be in Birmingham last week, attending the Skills Show at the NEC. For the thousands of visitors, it was a terrific event showcasing competitions in 50 different skills, offering people hands-on experience and providing expert careers advice. It showed that preparations for WorldSkills 2013 are well on track - and that we’re providing young people with the skills and motivation to start a business of their own.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on my way here today, I stopped in at Dudley College to formally open their new vocational and sixth form centres. It was great to see how their plans for a learning quarter in the town centre are developing - and Dudley has just been awarded £2 million through the Enhanced Renewal Grants scheme to build specialist facilities to teach advanced manufacturing and engineering.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the FE and skills sector is in good hands and in good shape. I’m not blind to areas where we need to raise our game - declining take up of vocational qualifications is a concern, for example. Nevertheless, I’m confident that we’re doing the right things to achieve a bright future for FE - hacking away at bureaucracy, promoting our expertise abroad, treating education as a fundamental strand of the Government’s evolving industrial strategy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you again for your efforts, and for your support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47570</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/cbi-conference-2012"/>
    <title>CBI conference 2012</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Vince Cable tells the CBI conference what the UK's long-term plans for business will be and how this will create growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction-competitiveness"&gt;Introduction: competitiveness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have heard the PM speak about achieving economic growth and jobs in the UK in an environment where there is intensifying international competition. Global growth is undeniably good news. We should welcome the fact that the vast swathes of humanity who until recently were subsistence farmers are now clawing their way out of poverty. They will expand the markets into which we sell - as the Prime Minister pointed out, exports are growing fast to Brazil, Russia and China. And we need to do a lot more to offset years of neglect of emerging markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can’t forget that these countries also generate more commercial competitors. And every other developed country, including a recovering United States, is relying on these markets to grow and looking at how to be more competitive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t live in a zero sum world but it may not feel like that in countries that are struggling to grow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-trends"&gt;UK trends&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we have had a difficult time, but there are some reassuring figures on job creation, falling unemployment, and business start-ups. If the more upbeat mood in business is to be sustained, there has to be a clear pathway to resumed and then sustained growth out of the financial crisis.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth in the short run - the next year or two - depends largely on an expansion of overall demand. In the past two years the ongoing Euro crisis and the persistent challenge of dealing with the legacy of damaged banks and a collapsed property bubble has not been helped by a big rise in energy prices. It is little wonder that business confidence has been faltering.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is determined to do what it can to support demand. Our determination to put in place a credible plan for deficit has allowed the Government to pass on the benefits of a credible balance sheet to the wider economy. That, and our independent monetary policy, is why we have been able to announce innovative schemes like Funding for Lending. And we will not sit on our laurels till the economy is growing strongly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="investment-in-human-capital"&gt;Investment in human capital&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the longer term what matters for growth is the attractiveness of the investment climate, the quality of physical infrastructure and the supply of high quality human capital. Some government decisions have an immediate impact: movement on infrastructure projects and regulatory certainty for energy investors means activity and jobs in the near term. I recognise the frustration in the business world that these things are moving slowly.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human capital calls for substantial investment in training, further and higher education as well as schools and research leading to innovation. Where is this going to come from? Most of it, of course, takes place in companies. However, for wide swathes of training and education there are valuable spillovers which mean that the private sector needs support from the government. That is why I have been so determined to protect and grow apprenticeships and put higher education on a sustainable footing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recall that at the beginning of this government we were forced to make difficult cuts in pursuit of deficit reduction and we enjoyed the support of the CBI for that. But the CBI was critical of certain cuts in particular and argued for more spending on education and science. Now the government faces serious financial constraints on account of the large fiscal deficit: a problem which will continue beyond the middle of the decade. We cannot repeat what we did before when we replaced grant funding with student loans repayable from graduate incomes. Now the main areas of higher education that still enjoy considerable financial support from government are subjects like engineering and science and the research ringfence which is the basic minimum to protect Britain’s competitiveness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="growing-demands"&gt;Growing demands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed in the coming years I see a growing call on government in two areas in particular. The first is in post 18 vocational education. We have made a big step forward with partially funded apprenticeships which have increased to over 1 million in the last 2 and half years, a growth of over 60% - and we are shifting towards a more employer led system where the funding flows from the company to trainers. But apprenticeships cover only a modest proportion of the student leaver population and we badly need a system of training that deals better with the so-called NEETS. This means having real ambition for the further education sector.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second is in research and development before commercial innovation. I am delighted at the progress we have been able to make with the Technology Strategy Board and in introducing the Catapult centres - in advanced manufacturing, cell therapy, new offshore renewables and space, with the connected digital and transport technologies catapults to come. Even though we have managed to protect the science budget from serious cuts we must not be complacent. We have noted the criticisms of the CBI that the valuable Smart Awards and Knowledge Transfer Partnership have been squeezed and are giving priority to supporting innovation when we have opportunities to invest more.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to build on our excellence in science, and improve how we turn great ideas into great businesses - just last week the Chancellor laid out eight technologies where Britain could be a world leader. And you only need to look at the proposals coming out of NESTA and CASE to show that there is no lack of opportunities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has to be some prioritisation connecting public spending in areas which contribute to recovery and growth, not on the political soft options. And this is an issue I have spent a lot of time reflecting upon in recent months during the work I have done with colleagues across government to formulate a new long-term plan for UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-strategy"&gt;Industrial strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting Industrial Strategy, is underpinned by two principles. First, a recognition that is necessary to plan for the long-term, prioritise activities and allocate resources accordingly - just as any successful company does. And second, an understanding that government must work with industry to tackle genuine market failures where they occur.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this does not mean picking winners. We will be flexible in our approach, rigorously evaluating where we best use our resources, and open to new, disruptive industries as they develop. This is not about entrenching the old industries, but rather ensuring that the UK is ready to take advantage of new opportunities as they develop.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing fits these two principles as clearly as getting the skills system right. This task is long term: to have the skills we need in 2020 or 2030 we need to start acting now. And the benefit that the whole economy receives from talented people makes investment in skills a classic market failure, requiring permanent government support. It is also an area where working with business is utterly essential - too much failure in the past has come from the government ignoring the input of industry. That is why it is so welcome that the CBI chose this theme in its report “First steps: A new approach for our schools”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="engineering-skills-and-education"&gt;Engineering skills and education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to ensure long term success we have to plan, now, to ensure an adequate supply of skilled workers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many strands to this work. We need to remain open to the many talented and entrepreneurial people that throng to our shores to learn, work and invest - that is how over the years Britain has gained so much of its industrial and business expertise. Being open for business means being open to overseas talent as well as overseas investors.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means we need our schools system to produce people with the soft skills required by all employers, such as the ability to cope with the routines and demands of the workplace, as well as equipping them with the management and leadership skills they need to progress. I applaud the emphasis being placed by my colleague the Secretary of State for education on raising the standards of maths and English in school and on standards in general. But we also have to develop credible pathways of vocational education in schools including engineering, and to introduce school children to the importance of enterprise and entrepreneurship.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is a clear and growing demand in British companies for specialist technical skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and again, large manufacturing companies come to my department and tell me they are worried about looming shortages of skilled engineers. It is one of my major priorities as Business Secretary to address this problem.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Academy of Engineering has published estimates of long term demands for engineers, and there is no doubt that these are very challenging. My Department’s Chief Scientific Adviser, Professor John Perkins - himself an eminent engineer - is working closely with the Academy and others to see what more might be done, including areas such as diversity and redressing the pronounced gender bias, and helping people return to the profession. On this I’d like to commend Allan Cook, Chairman of Atkins, for picking up and running with the idea of the ‘Talent Retention Solution’ an industry group set up originally to match jobs with engineers leaving the defence sector, and now running with more than 500 companies registered - currently still free for SMEs. I’m very pleased to announce that the TRS which is now funded and managed entirely by business is being extended now and is working with Universities so that students can put up their profiles &amp;amp; search for jobs - effectively an ebay for talent. The industry group see this as an important move towards supporting young people into engineering and manufacturing jobs and will be progressively using TRS to source new and experienced talent in the years to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="perceptions-of-engineering"&gt;Perceptions of engineering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constraints on engineering supply are clearly complex and rooted in a number of factors, ranging from the influences of parents and teachers to the outdated perceptions of industry that are a world away from the well remunerated, rewarding and dynamic careers on offer in engineering today.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always astonished by how different engineering is from the stale image of repetitive badly paid metal bashing. Instead I’d point to recent visits such as one to a McLaren factory, which felt more like a space ship than the classical image of a factory floor. Equally on a modern car production line, like the ones I’ve seen in visiting Toyota and JLR over the past months, you are just as likely to see women as men.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even as we gradually turn this perception around, by the time young people reach the age where they might want to choose engineering, they may have failed to gain the educational and/or technical skills needed to take it forward.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the reason we are running a number of programmes designed to increase the numbers passing through every stage of the pipeline.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The See Inside Manufacturing campaign has been a successful way of opening young people’s eyes to the career opportunities available in engineering by showing them around some of the UK’s leading industrial companies. Complementing this, we have programmes such as STEM ambassadors, Apprenticeship ambassadors, Make It in Great Britain, and the very successful Big Bang Fair which inspires the very youngest and this year involved 170 organisations with 56,000 people at the main event in Birmingham. Last Wednesday, I opened the Skills Show in Birmingham which welcomed 100,000 young people over the next three days to competitions and talks built around high levels of skill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prestigious new award, the Queen Elizabeth Prize for Engineering, has also been launched. A range of private sector partners have contributed to the endowment of the prize fund, and the £1m prize will now be awarded bi-annually by the Royal Academy of Engineering. It has real potential to inspire future generations of engineers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many manufacturers and professional bodies are highly pro-active in reaching out to inspire and inform young people. It is gratifying also to see Engineering UK’s ‘Tomorrow’s Engineers’ programme take this to the next level, by helping companies and academies join forces to engineer a vital step change in perceptions for the long-term.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine has supported the move towards greater Business Engagement in the school curriculum. He is right, and we are working with the careers service to connect the businesses, LEPs and schools to make this happen.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once their interest has been engaged, we have to ensure that opportunities to develop the requisite skills are available. University Technical Colleges provide a model for meeting that need.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our UTC programme will establish at least 24 new colleges by 2014, offering around 20,000 14 to 19 year olds rigorous training in a number of engineering, science and technical disciplines. Details of the first 15 were announced in May and include partnerships with household names such as Jaguar Land Rover, British Airways and Virgin Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="access-to-jobs"&gt;Access to jobs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, following their technical education, would-be engineers need access to jobs and training so they can start and develop their careers. If an adequate pipeline of British Engineers is to be created it cannot be down to government and future engineering graduates - through their fees - to do the financial heavy lifting. I hope we can see a reciprocal number of industrial sandwich schemes, paid internships and individual sponsorship from the private sector.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One area where there is real progress is apprenticeships. The investment we have ploughed into apprenticeships over the past two years has led to record numbers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t pretend that apprenticeships can solve the skills supply issue at a stroke - but they are an important part of the solution. Specifically apprenticeships in engineering and manufacturing technologies have doubled in recent years to 49,000 starts in 2010/11. We recognise that in focusing on quality as well as quantity we need more advanced apprenticeships in engineering, construction and digital skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller employers may need some extra help to absorb the costs of taking on an apprentice, so we are offering grants of £1,500 to support those with fewer than 1,000 employees that have not hired an apprentice in the past 12 months, and we have recently streamlined the process to make it as easy as possible for employers to recruit apprentices.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is gratifying also to see that the bids for Employer Ownership Pilots that I announced on the 11th September have included a number of high-quality bids from employers seeking to meet their specific engineering needs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the development and delivery of higher level apprenticeships, equivalent to degree level, is being supported through a £25m fund that will build the engineering skills base in a range of disciplines, including environmental technologies, space, energy and utilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="engineering-in-he"&gt;Engineering in HE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to engineering is just as strong in the higher education system. Since 2009, the Higher Education Funding Council for England has invested in measures to increase the demand and sustain the supply of strategically important subjects within STEM. Engineering and technology are by far the largest of these subjects in terms of undergraduate numbers. This year, when we introduced the new student financing system, demand to study engineering held up better than for any other subject, as students have taken an increasingly hard-headed view about career options.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, earlier this year an extra £12m was invested by the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council in new doctoral training programmes in four of the EPSRC Centres - Emergent Macromolecular Therapies, Continuous Manufacturing and Crystallisation, Ultra Precision, and Composites. Each training programme will support three cohorts of doctoral researchers and will provide specialist research and technologists specifically for advanced manufacturing industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme will reinforce the £300m Research Partnership Investment Fund, which will be used to leverage over £1bn investment in science and R&amp;amp;D collaborations. The fund, run by HEFCE, will support the creation of more cutting-edge research facilities and help promote long-term strategic research partnerships between universities, businesses and charities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of innovative projects have already been given the green light. For example, a £60m partnership between the Birmingham University and Rolls-Royce to establish a casting and simulation research facility. And a £92m partnership between Warwick University, Jaguar Land Rover and Tata Motors European Technical Centre for a new National Automotive Innovation Campus.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these interventions are designed to stimulate innovation, reduce the risks associated with investment in new technologies and R&amp;amp;D, and bolster the skills pipeline all the way along. The ultimate aim is to nurture a thriving innovation ecosystem which attracts the most talented people to careers in engineering and science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am a realist and I recognise that the initiatives I have outlined will take time to bear fruit. I know, too, that more needs to be done to reverse the constraints on skills that have resulted from the historic lack of investment. It will also be necessary to win battles in Government to prioritise this agenda. Nevertheless, I am confident we will succeed in bolstering the skills base as we develop and implement our long-term plans for UK industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an ambitious agenda and we stand ready to work with the CBI and others as it is implemented in the months ahead. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
