<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/william-hague</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/william-hague.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon William Hague MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55967</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-to-contribute-funds-to-courts-in-sierra-leone-and-cambodia--2"/>
    <title>UK to contribute funds to Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on UK contributions to the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in a written ministerial statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce that in order to strengthen international justice and help secure accountability for some of the most horrific crimes against humanity in the last 50 years, the UK will make a voluntary contribution of £1,000,000 to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and a voluntary contribution of £600,000 to the international component of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s contribution will help ensure the Special Court for Sierra Leone is able to complete its work, and leave a lasting legacy for the people of Sierra Leone. On 30 May, the Court sentenced Charles Taylor, a former President of Liberia, to 50 years in jail for aiding and abetting war crimes. Taylor is the first former Head of State to be convicted by an international tribunal and the Court is currently hearing his appeal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia is delivering long awaited justice for millions of Cambodians through the trials of the most senior and responsible surviving members of the Pol Pot regime. The scale of the crimes committed and the number of victims makes it one of the most significant tribunals of its kind since Nuremberg. The Government’s contribution will help to prevent the collapse of the Court which has faced a significant shortfall in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International justice is central to foreign policy. It is essential for securing the rights of individuals and states, and for securing peace and reconciliation. Through the International Criminal Court, and the separate international tribunals, we are working to make clear that those responsible for the worst crimes will be held to account and that political leaders will not enjoy impunity. Our support to these institutions is an important element in our strategy to reduce conflict, promote stability and strengthen the rules based international system. In order to give Parliament a full accounting of this work we will, from this point forward, also provide an annual statement at the start of the financial year detailing our progress on this important issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55806</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representatives from over 130 countries and international organisations met in Marrakesh for the fourth Friends of Syria meeting to support the Syrian National Coalition and the Syrian People. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the meeting the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank the Government of Morocco and H.M. King Mohammed VI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Twenty-two months ago the people of Syria asked for change. Their government responded by pounding cities into rubble, plunging four million people into desperate humanitarian need, and sowing fear and insecurity across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Friends of the Syrian people, we have done much to seek a peaceful end to the conflict. But we remain deeply disappointed by the failure of the international community to put its full weight behind the agreement made in Geneva six months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But in the United Kingdom we do not rule out any option to save lives. In addition, the Assad regime should not doubt our resolve, or miscalculate how we would react to any use of chemical or biological weapons against the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the Friends of the Syrian people, we have four immediate responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, we must increase our political support for and recognition of the Syrian National Coalition. I encourage other nations to recognise them as we have done in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The people of Syria need to feel the solid ground of a unified political alternative to the Assad regime. The National Coalition has now begun to offer that hope, and it is only right that we give them the recognition they deserve, and the support they need to survive and to prevail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some countries have resisted the idea of a transition because they have seen no alternative to Assad’s leadership. Well now the world can see that there is an alternative, and I urge all countries including Russia and China to work with us to end the conflict. If they do, they will find us constructive partners, and I commend Special Envoy Brahimi for his efforts in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Second, I appeal to all countries here to give practical support to the Syrian National Coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom has given over £7 million of non-lethal support, including communication equipment and human rights training.  We will provide a further £1 million in communication support, and look to expand our assistance, through the leadership of the National Coalition, following the deployment of a UK Stabilisation Response Team to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the new Assistance Coordination Unit established in Cairo, which will be able to help co-ordinate  non-lethal assistance to the Syrian people including to the Local Coordination Committees inside Syria, and we call on all countries here to give it active support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we increase our support to the Syrian people we must also increase the pressure on Assad and his allies. I call again on all countries to implement sanctions, and to ensure that their territory is not used as a conduit for arms or assistance to the regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Third, we must ensure the international community is ready to provide rapid assistance to a future government in Syria in order to help a political transition succeed. We need to be ready to react to change on the ground, which could happen suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We look to the National Coalition to develop further detailed plans for achieving and implementing transition working with all Syria’s communities, and to uphold human rights and international law, including humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fourth and finally, we must do more to alleviate Syria’s humanitarian tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom has provided £53.5 million so far in humanitarian aid which is providing 100,000 people with food, blankets and warm clothing, and we have helped 30,000 sick and wounded people by funding hospitals, mobile clinics and training for health workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many other countries have given generously too, but it cannot be right that the UN appeal for Syria is still underfunded.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we gather in this beautiful city we should remember that 50% of all Syria’s refugees are children. The majority are not in school, are living in makeshift shelters in the depths of winter, and many have lost their families. They represent Syria’s future. Their safety, their education, and their ability to return to their home matter to Syria, and to the peace and security of the region. So I urge all countries to do more to help share the burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As part of our new initiative on preventing sexual violence in conflict, the UK has deployed experts to the region to provide training on documentation of sexual violence which we hope will support future prosecutions and care for survivors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We do not know how long the conflict in Syria will last. But uniting the international community around these efforts, helping the National Coalition to win the confidence of the Syrian people, planning for a peaceful future for the country and protecting the victims of the violence on whom that future will rest, is surely the right way to seek to end the conflict and stop the appalling loss of life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Friends of Syria meeting" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4802/friends-of-Syria-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/unog/website/news_media.nsf/%28httpNewsByYear_en%29/18F70DBC923963B1C1257A2D0060696B?OpenDocument" title="Final communiqué of the Action Group for Syria"&gt;Geneva Declaration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative" title="Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict Initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54865</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/government-publishes-afghanistan-progress-report"/>
    <title>Government publishes Afghanistan progress report </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a written statement to parliament the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform the House that the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, together with the Ministry of Defence and the Department for International Development, is today publishing the twenty second progress report on developments in Afghanistan since November 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 9 October the UN Security Council adopted resolution 2069 (2012) extending the authorisation of the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan (ISAF) by a further year. The resolution provided a 12 month roll-over of the Chapter VII authorisation, with an unqualified “all necessary measures” provision. It also incorporated NATO Chicago Summit commitments to support the training, equipping, financing and capability development of the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF) up to and beyond 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Afghanistan held the first meeting of the Afghanistan-UK Joint Commission chaired by Afghanistan’s Deputy Foreign Minister Jawed Ludin and Baroness Warsi to review implementation of the Enduring Strategic Partnership document signed by President Karzai and the Prime Minister in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 25 October the International Development Committee (IDC) published its Afghanistan: Progress and Prospects after 2014 report. The Government welcomes this report. The Department for International Development will shortly publish a formal response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 31 October the Afghan Independent Election Commission (IEC) publicly announced that 5 April 2014 would be the date for the next Presidential Election in Afghanistan. The Provincial Council elections, postponed from 2013, will also take place on 5 April. As part of this announcement, the IEC published an ambitious timeline for the full electoral processes. Although the timeline as it stands does not cover the Parliamentary elections due in 2015, it effectively meets the Afghan commitment at the Tokyo Development Conference to produce a timeline by early 2013. An implementation plan is set to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October typically marks the end of the so called Afghan Summer fighting season. This time is used by insurgents to recuperate and plan. Overall the levels of violence are likely to decline, and in accordance with seasonal norms, we can expect the character of operations to change during the winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four members of UK Armed Forces lost their lives while deployed on operations in Afghanistan in October. The two separate incidents that caused these deaths were assessed to be the result of insider attacks. We take these attacks and their causes extremely seriously and we continue to work at the highest level to reduce the risk of insider attacks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of Afghanistan continued to progress plans for the privatisation of the New Kabul Bank. The first in a series of investor road shows took place in October. A road show in Dubai is planned for November. Tenders are being managed by the Afghan Ministry of Finance, Central Bank, and the Cabinet. The process aims to attract high quality investors. The New Kabul Bank is a commercially viable bank, with 550 million USD of deposits and over 100 branches across Afghanistan. As one of the largest banks in Afghanistan, its survival is important for economic development and jobs. The UK is supporting the Afghan Government with the sale of the Bank, thus promoting a transparent and effective process.&lt;br&gt;
I am placing the report in the Library of the House. It will also be published on the Foreign and Commonwealth Office website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-progress-reports" title="Afghanistan Progress Reports"&gt;Monthly progress reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British Embassy in Afghanistan &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinafghanistan.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Afghanistan"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56671</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns Democratic People’s Republic of Korea satellite launch</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I strongly condemn the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s (DPRK) satellite launch today. This launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 as it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. This provocative act will increase tensions in the region. I deplore the fact that the DPRK has chosen to prioritise this launch over improving the livelihood of its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be summoning the DPRK Ambassador to the UK to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the UK will urgently consult partners in the United Nations Security Council on our response to this development. It is essential that the DPRK refrain from further provocative action and take constructive steps towards denuclearisation and lasting peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54862</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T17:02:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-to-attend-friends-of-syria-meeting-in-marrakesh"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary to attend Friends of Syria meeting in Marrakesh</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 December the Friends of Syria will meet to support the Syrian National Coalition and the Syrian People &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 22 month conflict over 40,000 people have been killed and 2 million people have been displaced inside Syria. There are daily reports of more deaths and atrocities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the fourth meeting of the Friends of Syria and follows the formation of the Syrian National Coalition in Doha on 11 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s objective in Marrakesh is to provide support to the Syrian National Coalition as they establish themselves as a credible alternative to the Assad regime. We believe that the Friends of Syria should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send a clear message to Assad that his position and regime are no longer sustainable by giving more political support to the National Coalition;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Provide practical support to the Syrian National Coalition in pursuit of a political transition, while also helping local councils in Syria provide essential services;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Re-establish a sense of urgency around planning for a political transition and Syria’s long term future, reinforcing the message that Assad cannot be part of any transition and offering reassurance that fears of a post-Assad vacuum are unfounded.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increase efforts to alleviate the horrendous humanitarian suffering as winter approaches. Syria’s neighbours have shown extraordinary generosity, but UN appeals remain critically underfunded. The UK has committed £53.5 million in humanitarian assistance and we are asking for others to contribute to the fund.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syria desperately needs a political transition based on the Geneva Declaration. The UK continues to believe that Russia and China should recognise that President Assad can never recover legitimacy in the eyes of the Syrian people and that they should back UN Arab League Special Envoy Brahimi in bringing about a diplomatic solution to the crisis. We therefore welcome his on-going discussions with the US and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this happens, the UK will continue to do all we can to avoid a drawn-out military conflict by;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;backing the Syrian National Coalition in pursuit of a genuine transition process and supporting them in preparing for political transition;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;increasing pressure on the Syrian regime through the effective implementation and enforcement of sanctions to stop funds used to finance the killing;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ensuring we have maximum flexibility to act in the future following the decision to limit the rollover of the EU arms embargo to three months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the UK special representative to the Syrian Opposition &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/JonWilksFCO" title="@JonWilksFCO"&gt;@JonWilksFCO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the Foreign Secretary &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/WilliamJHague" title="@WilliamJHague"&gt;@WilliamJHague&lt;/a&gt; and the Foreign Office &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;@foreignoffice&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/unog/website/news_media.nsf/%28httpNewsByYear_en%29/18F70DBC923963B1C1257A2D0060696B?OpenDocument" title="Final communiqué of the Action Group for Syria"&gt;Geneva Declaration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusions from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=785484582" title="Friends of Syrian People: Chairman's conclusions"&gt;Friends of Syria meeting in July&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54859</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Jordan and the UK are longstanding friends and allies and it was a pleasure to welcome King Abdullah to London today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ahead of the meeting of the Friends of Syria in Morocco tomorrow we discussed the growing crisis in that country. I paid tribute to the generosity of the Jordanian people in hosting the significant and growing number of Syrian refugees. And we welcomed the formation of the Syrian National Coalition and its efforts to provide a credible and inclusive alternative to the Assad regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We agreed on the need for a new initiative to achieve peace between the Israelis and Palestinians, led by the US and supported by the wider international community. This is needed as a matter of urgency, before the window closes on the two state solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“King Abdullah described his efforts to institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. I welcomed these and emphasised the importance of delivering an inclusive political process led by King Abdullah that provides substantive democratic reforms. The UK stands ready to support this work, in particular through the Arab Partnership. We discussed the difficult economic situation in Jordan and what the UK and EU can do to help Jordan carry through difficult but necessary economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I also expressed appreciation for the assistance provided by the Jordanian Government in our efforts to return Abu Qatada.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54856</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/championing-britain-through-commercial-and-economic-diplomacy"/>
    <title>Championing Britain through commercial and economic diplomacy </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, more than at any moment in modern history, British diplomacy must play a central role in supporting jobs and growth in our economy. We need commercial diplomacy and economic expertise to run through the bloodstream of the Foreign Office, and it really is starting to do so. Western economies are facing significant economic and fiscal challenges. There is simply no option to generate growth through increased government expenditure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that as well as using diplomacy to tackle threats in the world and to advance human rights and freedom, all the things the Foreign Office does so well, we also need to build up our influence where it counts, in new trading hubs and high-growth economies of the 21st century as well as our vitally important markets in Europe and the United States. You are on the front line helping us to do this, making the contacts, speaking to business leaders and building the influence that will enable British companies to remain competitive in a global market. We need your local knowledge and understanding to spot both opportunities and barriers to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were important changes to make and I want to thank you personally for responding so readily and energetically in making them happen, which is something that I can see and feel wherever I go. British business also appreciates it, as the results of a recent survey clearly show. But that survey also highlighted that we must sustain this effort over the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to build on these successes, increase our ambition, and reach even further; because if we don’t then others will in our place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is you who is making clear that Britain is open for business and has an abundance to offer. I have been immensely impressed by your efforts so far. The skills that you display in getting under the skins of your local cultures, building relationships with business, lobbying officials, and reporting economic and political developments, are the skills that will allow us to give British business the competitive edge that it needs. Whether it be championing the UK’s contribution to the green economy, or influencing trade negotiations in Brussels, it is you, our network, which is connecting opportunities abroad to jobs at home. I want you to know that the work you are doing is vitally important. It is important to us in the FCO. It is important to the Prime Minister. And it is important to the whole country. So, I will champion you and the work you do and I want you to champion Britain. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39681</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-attends-manama-dialogue"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary attends Manama Dialogue</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today arrived in Bahrain to take part in the Manama Dialogue. The Dialogue, hosted by the think tank International Institute for Strategic Studies, is a leading forum for governments and non-government experts to discuss regional security issues in the Middle East. These issues are a top priority for the UK and the event provides an important opportunity to discuss shared concerns with representatives from the region and key members of the international community. The Foreign Secretary is leading a UK delegation, which also includes Lord Astor of Hever, MOD Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State and Government Spokesperson, and General Sir David Richards, the Chief of the Defence Staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will meet members of the Government of Bahrain during his visit. As a close friend and ally, the UK has consistently encouraged the Government to take further steps to implement promised reforms and urged all sides to enter into an inclusive and constructive dialogue.  While progress is being made in some areas, we believe there is still more to be done to achieve long term stability and prosperity in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to attend the Manama Dialogue, which brings together key figures from a variety of backgrounds to discuss events and regional security in the Middle East. I will lead discussions in a session on the influence of sectarian politics in the region, highlighting the importance of universal human rights and access to justice as the most effective ways to tackle the tensions that sectarianism inflames.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will also meet representatives of the Government of Bahrain to continue our discussions on the need for full and timely implementation of their reform programme, and the UK’s offer of support.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
