<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/william-hague</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/william-hague.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon  William Hague MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39681</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-attends-manama-dialogue"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary attends Manama Dialogue</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today arrived in Bahrain to take part in the Manama Dialogue. The Dialogue, hosted by the think tank International Institute for Strategic Studies, is a leading forum for governments and non-government experts to discuss regional security issues in the Middle East. These issues are a top priority for the UK and the event provides an important opportunity to discuss shared concerns with representatives from the region and key members of the international community. The Foreign Secretary is leading a UK delegation, which also includes Lord Astor of Hever, MOD Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State and Government Spokesperson, and General Sir David Richards, the Chief of the Defence Staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will meet members of the Government of Bahrain during his visit. As a close friend and ally, the UK has consistently encouraged the Government to take further steps to implement promised reforms and urged all sides to enter into an inclusive and constructive dialogue.  While progress is being made in some areas, we believe there is still more to be done to achieve long term stability and prosperity in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to attend the Manama Dialogue, which brings together key figures from a variety of backgrounds to discuss events and regional security in the Middle East. I will lead discussions in a session on the influence of sectarian politics in the region, highlighting the importance of universal human rights and access to justice as the most effective ways to tackle the tensions that sectarianism inflames.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will also meet representatives of the Government of Bahrain to continue our discussions on the need for full and timely implementation of their reform programme, and the UK’s offer of support.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18782</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T16:42:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T16:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-holds-trilateral-talks-with-foreign-ministers-of-pakistan-and-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary holds trilateral talks with Foreign Ministers of Pakistan and Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague, Foreign Minister of the Islamic Republic of Pakistan Hina Rabbani Khar and Foreign Minister of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan Dr Zalmai Rassoul, today held a trilateral meeting to discuss the Afghan-led peace and reconciliation process, and how to strengthen their joint efforts to address extremism and advance regional peace and stability.  They were joined by Masoom Stanekzai, Head of the Joint Secretariat to the High Peace Council.  This meeting was the third in a series of trilateral discussions that have taken place this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the meeting Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Supporting the security and prosperity of Afghanistan and Pakistan is one of the most important priorities in UK foreign policy. I congratulate both Foreign Ministers for the real progress that their countries have made in recent weeks in helping advance the Afghan-led peace and reconciliation process, notably through the visit of the High Peace Council to Pakistan, led by Chairman Rabbani, on 12-15 November. And I welcome their agreement today to continuing to develop a Strategic Partnership between Pakistan and Afghanistan. Both countries will have the unwavering support of the British government in these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18771</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T13:38:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T13:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-expresses-concern-about-reports-of-violence-in-cairo--2"/>
    <title> Foreign Secretary expresses concern about reports of violence in Cairo</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am concerned by reports of violent clashes following earlier peaceful protests in Cairo. I urge all sides to show restraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK remains committed to supporting Egypt’s political transition and strengthening democracy. We are in close contact with both the Egyptian authorities and leaders of the opposition.  We call on the Egyptian authorities to make progress on transition in an inclusive manner which allows for a constructive exchange of views. We urge all parties to resolve their differences through a process of dialogue which allows all voices to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17810</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T12:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T12:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-kuwait-joint-steering-group-communique"/>
    <title>UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group Communiqué</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inaugural meeting of the UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group took place at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office in London on 28 November 2012, and formed part of the State Visit to the UK of His Highness Sheikh Sabah Al Ahmad Al Jaber, the Amir of Kuwait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Steering Group was launched by The Rt Hon William Hague, British Foreign Secretary, and His Excellency Sheikh Sabah Al Khalid Al Sabah, the Kuwaiti Minister of Foreign Affairs and Deputy Prime Minister, with the aim of further strengthening the ties between the two countries, across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group agreed to meet every six months under the leadership of Alistair Burt MP, Minister for the Middle East and South Asia, and His Excellency Khaled Sulaiman al Jarallah, Undersecretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting the breadth of the bilateral relationship, the group discussed a range of issues, including trade and investment; migration; defence and foreign policy; and international development:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On trade and investment, Ministers committed to seek out opportunities to strengthen commercial links between the UK and Kuwait and stressed the importance of encouraging the growth of business between the two countries. The Ministers welcomed the appointment of Baroness Morris as UK Trade Envoy to Kuwait, applauded Kuwait’s ambitious National Development Plan and agreed that UK companies had a vital role to play in supporting it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On defence and security, Ministers pointed to the close cooperation between the two countries, enshrined in a shared military history and a strong tradition of military officer exchanges, and committed to strengthening this partnership further in support of shared regional objectives. They agreed to build a strategic dialogue going forward, discuss cooperation on defence equipment and to increase training in the military field. It has been agreed that the UK will refurbish Kuwait’s Hawk trainer aircraft.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On regional issues, Ministers discussed Israel/Palestine and the need for both sides to return to negotiations. Ministers agreed to work together to improve stability in the region, urging reconciliation in Syria and committing to coordinate closely to support political progress in Yemen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On international development, Alan Duncan MP, UK Minister for Development, held a separate bilateral meeting with the Kuwaiti Minister for Foreign Affairs. Recognising the role both countries already play, and committing to learn from each other’s experiences, they agreed to work together as partners on this globally important area.
Ministers also discussed prospective cooperation on migration, education and healthcare, and agreed to follow up progress across the board at their next meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17577</id>
    <published>2012-12-02T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-02T10:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict Initiative </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman, presenter: New efforts to deal with one of the most horrific consequences of that conflict – mass sexual violence against women.  Britain is about to dispatch a team of doctors, detectives and other experts to the Syrian region to investigate allegations that rape is being used repeatedly and deliberately as a weapon of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brutality in Syria has, according to the United Nations, reached “appalling heights”.  The opposition now fears the uprising has claimed more than 40,000 lives, but as well as the lives lost, there are many thousands of lives ruined too – not by bombs or bullets, but by another weapon of war: rape.  After meeting his team of experts, the Foreign Secretary told this programme that within weeks the Government will be taking the unprecedented step of deploying doctors, investigators, psychologists and lawyers to the Syrian region to gather evidence to bring the perpetrators of rape to justice, evidence likely to be gathered too in the Democratic Republic of Congo.  Last week, the M23 rebels marched on the city of Goma.  Both sides are accused of appalling abuses.  Rape has become a fact of life here for 15 years now.  This woman was raped in 2002 by the Hutu militia.  A decade on, she still fears her attackers will return, so her identity has been concealed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unnamed woman, victim of military rape [translated]: I don’t know those people, and I don’t know where they are now, and I couldn’t follow up, because if I tried to investigate, those people would come back and they’d kill me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: It’s thought 12% of women in the Congo have been raped at least once, and the figures elsewhere in the world are just as shocking. Up to 50,000 women were raped during the Bosnian conflict in the 1990s; 64,000 women and girls were sexually assaulted in Sierra Leone between 1992 and 2002, and 400,000 were raped during the hundred-day genocide in Rwanda in 1994. Justice for the victims remains elusive, though – only 30 men have been convicted of rape committed during the Bosnian War, and a sense of outrage about that was what persuaded Angelina Jolie, the actress turned UN envoy, to make a film about the Bosnian rape camps, In The Land of Blood and Honey. The Foreign Secretary happened to see it, and says today it inspired him to launch a global campaign to tackle war zone rape, and forge an alliance with one of Hollywood’s biggest stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, William Hague and Angelina Jolie plan to join the experts gathering evidence in the field next year, and earlier I went to speak to both the Foreign Secretary and the Hollywood star at Mr Hague’s official country residence in Chevening in Kent. I began by asking the Foreign Secretary about the deployment to the Syrian region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague (Foreign Secretary): Well, one of the things we will be doing is deploying the team that we’ve now assembled. We’ve assembled a team of 70 doctors, lawyers, forensic experts, psychologists who can be deployed in the field; in the case of Syria, helping Syrian refugees – they’re going to be training local health professionals to gather the medical evidence, to get the forensic evidence and documentation that can be used in prosecutions in the future. So this is a practical example of what we can do, and we’ll be having other deployments over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Well, you’ve been to many war zones. Do you think it’s realistic, in a war zone, in a war situation, to deploy a team in this way and actually gather evidence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie (Special Envoy, United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees): Absolutely. I think it’s… I think it must be done. I think it’s a… it… you know, I work a lot with refugees, people who are internally displaced, people who have just fled from conflict. I was in the Syria conflict particularly recently, on four different borders, and you meet the people the moment they cross – and they immediately want to start talking. They want to know what’s happening to their future, they want to participate. They want to put on record what’s going on in the country; they want things not to be missed, and they want to know that one day, they’ll be able to go home, and there will be accountability. And so it matters to them emotionally, and it matters to the future of their country on a legal level that they will be able to find some justice and impunity, move forward, and have their basic human rights protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Talking about where this is happening now, it’s really a, kind of, cruel coincidence of timing, isn’t it, that the trouble in the Congo has, sort of, flared up, at just the moment you’re really stepping up this campaign. Is there a sense, do you think, that the M23 rebels, when they marched on Goma, that the UN really stood by and failed in its duty to protect those civilians – some of whom were being raped?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: It’s a very, very complex situation, and I know in particular I reached out to UNHCR, and we talk often about – daily – on reports what’s happening, and I know that the team there on… for UNHCR is extremely frustrated that they can’t access the people, they can’t get to the internally-displaced people because of… because of the violence, until there’s a ceasefire, until there’s a… they actually can’t reach them. That’s a particular part of the UN, that brings aid relief and is able to be present, and they can’t get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Is that your understanding? That it was the practicalities of the issue that meant that the troops weren’t there in sufficient numbers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: Of course, the area we’re talking about, enormous, the numbers of troops very small, the support from neighbouring states – not there; so all of these problems are present there, and the leadership has to come from within the region to sort this out, but the pressure to do that and, if necessary, the resources to help to do that have to come from the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: You’ve been to many war zones – Darfur, Iraq, Afghanistan; I’ve missed many, I’m sure – what did you witness there on this particular issue, of rape in the war zone, that really, sort of, inspired you to back this campaign?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: For me, this campaign came about with… we came together on a film I’d worked on that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: The Land of Blood and Honey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: …The Land of Blood and Honey – which came from these years in the field where I’d continued to meet victims of sexual violence who… you know, had just seen no justice, and had felt isolated and abused, and abuse upon abuse because they had felt ignored. But you start to… I started to lean very much towards the law, and to understand that when people don’t know their rights and they don’t know they can fight for it and they don’t have… any rape, any kind of sexual violence that would happen to anybody in this room, the perpetrator would be arrested, we would see justice. Millions and millions of people around the world don’t have that. It’s a shame, and it’s something that… how dare we not do something? So it was helping to give them a voice, and trying to understand myself what more needs to be done to assist them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: And this film is one of the inspirations behind the British Government’s campaign, you know – it’s so good, it’s so clear, it’s so horrifying. It brings to life the statistics. But I think what Angelina achieved with the film was really to bring that to life, to… so that it’s not just something that’s out of mind and out of sight. It removes anybody’s excuse for not doing anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: And, I mean, there’s so much talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: There’s a lot of bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: There’s a lot of bureaucracy, and there’s a lot of talking, and it just… and when we first started to speak about this, and I learned about the initiative, it was… it wasn’t about, you know, how we can go there together and talk; it was something very practical that had to be done – it was a… ‘there will be an absolute’… you know, ‘there’s people on the ground, there are things being done, there will be results, it will move forward’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Some people might be a little bit cynical, seeing you sat there next to a major Hollywood star. What do you think Angelina Jolie brings to your campaign?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: Well, Angelina was instrumental in the campaign, because – as I mentioned a moment ago – her film about what happened in Bosnia was certainly, to me, one of the main motivating factors in getting this campaign going; but of course she… Angelina brings her experience as an envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees, having visited so many countries, and the ability to mobilise opinion and to attract attention to these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: To get it talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: And that’s one of the things that we have to do. This has been a subject that for too long has been not talked about – it’s taboo in some countries to talk about it. It’s not been the main focus of attention, even in countries like our own, in international affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: And when you hear people’s stories repeatedly over the years, as you have done – obviously their world is so far removed from, you know, the world that we all inhabit. Do you… how do you empathise with what you’re hearing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: How can we live in a world where people are abused in such fashions, where young, you know, girls and boys are being raped so violently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Well, you nod at that – I mean, you’re famously, you know, unemotional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: Are you famously unemotional? That’s so interesting.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: The Foreign Secretary has to be, yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: I as… am I famously emotional and you’re famously unemotional?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: It’s quite a combination, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: I wasn’t saying you’re famously emotional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: That’s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: It’s quite a combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: That’s why we’re a combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: But, I mean, even you have been… “even you”, I say – OK. You’ve been moved by what you’ve heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague: This is one of the worst things happening in the world today, and a world that has mounted campaigns against a slave trade, that is on the edge of agreeing an Arms Trade Treaty ought… is a world which ought to be able to do something about this.  So yes, even the unemotional Foreign Secretary feels very, very strongly about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Do you ever think that what you’re doing on a humanitarian basis is so much more, sort of, time-consuming and more rewarding, potentially, than what you do in your acting, and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: Oh, of course. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: All the time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: Yeah. Yeah, of course. I mean, I wouldn’t…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Does that ever make you think you’ll give up the acting and focus purely on the…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: I think I’m going to have to give up the acting as the kids hit the teenage years anyway, because… you know.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: Too [unclear].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: There’s going to be too much to manage at home. But…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: That’s [unclear].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: You know, I… you know, I’ve enjoyed being an actress, and I’m so grateful for the job, and I’ve had great experiences, and I’ve even been able to tell stories and be a part of stories that mattered. And I’ve also done really just things for fun and, you know, hopefully… but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cathy Newman: But you’re speaking in the past tense there, as if from now on…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie: I’ll do some films, and I am so fortunate to have the job, you know. It’s a really… it’s a very lucky profession to be a part of, and I enjoy it. But if it went away tomorrow, I’d be very happy to just be home with my children, and I would… you know, I wake up in the morning as a mom, and I turn on the news like everybody else, and I see what’s happening in the world, and I want to be a part of the world in a positive way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17576</id>
    <published>2012-12-01T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-01T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-north-koreas-proposed-satellite-launch"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns North Korea's proposed satellite launch </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on North Korea’s plans to launch a satellite, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We condemn the announcement by North Korea’s Central News Agency that North Korea intends to launch a satellite between 10-22 December. The United Nations Security Council made clear in April that any attempts by North Korea to launch a satellite using ballistic missile technology would be a serious violation of UN Security Council resolution 1874. We therefore call on the North Korean authorities to abandon this plan. Failure to do so must lead to a further response by the international community, and will damage the prospects for peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17277</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T12:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-meets-kuwaiti-minister-of-foreign-affairs"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary meets Kuwaiti Minister of Foreign Affairs </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was delighted to welcome His Excellency Sheikh Sabah Khaled Al-Hamad Al-Sabah, Kuwait’s Minister of Foreign Affairs and Deputy Prime Minister, to the Foreign Office today. The United Kingdom and Kuwait enjoy a historic relationship whose foundations date back to the eighteenth century. As long-standing friends we have been through much together, including the liberation of Kuwait from Saddam Hussein’s forces in 1991.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kuwait is a key ally in a region with significant implications for the security and prosperity of the United Kingdom On coming to office I was clear that we needed to do more to enhance our relationship and today I am pleased to announce the inauguration of a new UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group. This will meet regularly to deepen the strong ties between our countries and provide a forum to develop our partnership on trade, foreign and security policy – including the UK’s decision to help Kuwait with its security infrastructure to help counter the threat from terrorism - and development where Kuwait has a strong record as a generous donor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today we discussed our bilateral relations and reiterated our commitment to build on progress and increase trade to £4 billion by 2015. We also spoke about the political situation in Kuwait and I made clear the UK’s continued support for Kuwait’s deep-seated democratic tradition and its fully elected Parliament and vibrant media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally we discussed the current situation in Middle East, including the Palestinian resolution at the UN General Assembly, Iraq, Syria and Iran. In particular I made clear that I believe it is time for a huge effort on the Middle East peace process and that we continue to urge the United States to give a decisive lead in the coming months before a two state solution slips away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35632</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretary-william-hague-met-the-dutch-foreign-minister-frans-timmermans"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Dutch Foreign Minister Frans Timmermans</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was Mr Timmermans’ first visit to London since becoming Foreign Minister on 5 November.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the Ministers’ agenda was the situation in Gaza and the broader Middle East Peace Process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary highlighted the need for strong international action to help build on the ceasefire agreed last week. The Foreign Secretary also raised the importance of international recognition of the Syrian opposition and welcomed Dutch input to European External Action Service work on supporting Syrian Civil Society.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministers welcomed continued bilateral activity on the UK-Netherlands Strategic Business Dialogue, helping to identify commercial opportunities for UK businesses and tackling barriers to trade.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit Mr Timmermans also met the Minister for Europe, David Lidington.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35625</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-un-international-day-for-the-elimination-of-violence-against-women"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary marks UN International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Preventing and addressing sexual violence is essential to resolving conflicts and building sustainable peace. In our lifetimes millions of women, children and men have endured this horror.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must shatter the culture of impunity for those who use rape and sexual violence as a weapon of war and shift the balance of shame away from survivors to the perpetrators of this crime. This is a cause whose time has come, and it will be a major theme of the UK’s Presidency of the G8 next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By standing shoulder to shoulder with civil society, communities and international organisations I truly believe that we can confront and one day even end the use of sexual violence as a weapon of war.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
