<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/william-hague</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/william-hague.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon William Hague MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61173</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Ministers urge progress between Sudan and South Sudan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK, US and Norway say that Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan must seize the opportunity for peace now.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January. In a joint statement, Foreign Ministers from the ‘Sudan Troika’ are calling for the two countries to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint statement by Norwegian Foreign Minister Espen Barth Eide, United Kingdom Foreign Secretary William Hague and U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the news that the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January in a further effort to resolve outstanding issues between the two countries. We applaud the progress made at their Presidential Summit held in Addis Ababa at the end of September 2012, which demonstrated that a durable and equitable settlement is within reach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We commend the continuing valuable role of the African Union High-Level Implementation Panel led by former President Thabo Mbeki and the efforts of Ethiopian Prime Minister Hailemariam Desalegn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We regret that progress in implementing the Agreements signed on 27 September has stalled and in particular that the agreed security arrangements at the border are not yet in place. We call on the two leaders now to address concretely all outstanding issues and ensure that the armed forces of the two countries immediately withdraw from the demilitarised zone and deploy the Joint Border and Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM), in line with what has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We stress the importance of making progress in parallel on other parts of the relationship between the two countries. Full implementation of all agreements on their own terms and without preconditions or linkages between them, will help build confidence and benefit the people of the two countries. The restart of oil production and export will be particularly valuable for both economies and should not be held up by negotiation on other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We underline our support for the approach taken by the African Union to the question of Abyei. The proposal made by former President Mbeki is based on the Comprehensive Peace Agreement, including the Abyei Protocol. The proposal, adopted by AUPSC on October 24, sets out a clear path towards determining Abyei’s final status in accordance with agreements already signed by both parties, while protecting the rights of all communities and ensuring Abyei can become a model for cross-border cooperation and coexistence. We note in particular that the proposal provides for Abyei’s continuing special status as a bridge between the two countries with guaranteed political and economic rights for both the Ngok Dinka and Misseriya, whatever the outcome of the referendum. We urge the two countries to meet to elaborate on these rights and to move toward agreement on Abyei’s final status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision. We strongly urge them to seize the opportunity of the Summit meeting on 4 January to demonstrate their commitment to implement what they have agreed and make peaceful co-existence a reality.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60961</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:14:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"/>
    <title>G8 events</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During the UK G8 Presidency 2013 there will be events in addition to the leaders' summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="g8-foreign-ministers-meeting"&gt;G8 foreign ministers’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 and 11 April 2013, the Foreign Secretary William Hague will host his counterparts from the G8 countries. They will meet for the G8 foreign ministers’ meeting at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to the UK’s G8 Presidency making headway on the serious challenges facing our global community today. Today the Prime Minister explained that by supporting the development of open economies, open governments and open societies we can harness the power of the private sector for everyone’s benefit. Our G8 priorities of advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency can only take place in an environment of political stability and peaceful international relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With my G8 foreign minister partners, I look forward to discussing and taking decisions on some of the most pressing foreign and security policy issues that we face. In particular I will be focusing on the Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative, a personal priority for me during the UK’s G8 Presidency and beyond, and ensuring that the G8’s Deauville Partnership provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g7-finance-ministers-and-central-bank-governors-meeting"&gt;G7 finance ministers’ and Central Bank governors’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 to 11 May 2013, the Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne and the Governor of the Bank of England Sir Mervyn King will host a spring meeting of the G7 finance ministers and Central Bank governors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Chancellor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to hosting colleagues from the G7 to Britain in the spring. This group remains an important institution and a key forum in which to grapple with the challenges that face the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This meeting will be a significant opportunity for the UK and our partners to take on these challenges and to show leadership in the fight to tackle the ongoing ramifications of the global financial and debt crisis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g8-leaders-summit"&gt;G8 leaders’ summit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G8 leaders’ summit will take place on 17 to 18 June 2013 at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue" title="Lough Erne Venue"&gt;Lough Erne in County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17291</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:34:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:34:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-personnel-attend-funeral-of-sir-rex-hunt"/>
    <title>RAF personnel attend funeral of Sir Rex Hunt</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Air Force personnel have attended the funeral of Sir Rex Hunt, former Governor of the Falkland Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personnel from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/34squadron.cfm" title="34 Squadron RAF Regiment"&gt;34 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/609squadron.cfm" title="609 (West Riding) Squadron"&gt;No 609 (West Riding) Squadron Royal Auxiliary Air Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) have attended the funeral of Sir Rex Hunt, former Governor of the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others attending included Air Commodore (Ret’d) Dempster Anderson representing &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment veterans and Group Captain Gary Bunkell, Inspector &lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, representing the Honorary Inspector General.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment formed part of the coffin-bearing party and assisted both in the church and at the graveside. Falklands veterans, ex-&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; and members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23304.aspx" title="The Parachute Regiment"&gt;Parachute Regiment&lt;/a&gt; donned their green and maroon berets to form a guard of honour for the coffin as it entered the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coffin left the church to the tune of the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; March and Sir Rex was buried with the Falkland Islands flag on his coffin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Jeff Metcalfe, Officer Commanding No 609 (West Riding) Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/2fphome.cfm%202%20Force%20Protection%20Wing%20Headquarters"&gt;No 2 Force Protection Wing&lt;/a&gt; were honoured to be asked to perform this solemn duty for Sir Rex Hunt and his family. The personnel were drawn from 34 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment and 609 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt; and were proud to support this sad occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I served on 2729 Squadron 20 years ago when Sir Rex was my Honorary Air Commodore. I had met him personally and I am proud that I have been involved in laying him to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF personnel in formation " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1256/rexhunt2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; personnel in formation at the church where Sir Rex Hunt was laid to rest [Picture: Ian McIntyre, gazettelive.co.uk, 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many within the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment, still serving or associated with the Corps, who remember Sir Rex with some affection from the earliest days of the Falklands conflict in 1982 when &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/squadrons/63_sqn_history.cfm" title="63   Squadron RAF Regiment"&gt;63 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment&lt;/a&gt; deployed with 5 Brigade and manned the Rapier air defence systems around San Carlos Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within days of the Argentinean surrender, 63 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment redeployed from there to defend the new air base established at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Stanley, which was to be their home - and for those of the other &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Germany-based Rapier roulement squadrons involved - for another five years before the resident Rapier squadrons redeployed to the new Mount Pleasant Airbase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at Stanley, Sir Rex visited the remote Rapier site on many an occasion and he always took an intense interest in the men and what they were doing in defence of the Islands. The &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment was to be deployed permanently in the Falklands until 2006, a total of 24 unbroken years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the news of the death of Sir Rex Hunt, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was very sorry to hear of the death of Sir Rex Hunt. As Governor of the Falkland Islands he served his country and the Falkland Islanders with great distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60215</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens"/>
    <title>Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has reaffirmed UK support for imprisoned Human Rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the United Nations vote on the human right situation in Iran, the Foreign Secretary has released a video. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic freedoms of ordinary Iranians are being denied. Many citizens live in constant fear of arbitrary arrest, false imprisonment and, in some cases, death. There is undeniable evidence of abuse: the recent death in custody of blogger Sattar Beheshti is one tragic example. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also spoke about Nasrin Sotoudeh, who recently ended a 49-day hunger strike in protest against the harassment of her family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have sacrificed your own freedom, family life and health in order to help others. I want you to know that we are following your case closely. And that I echo the many calls upon Iran for your immediate release. Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regime hopes to silence those who call for basic human rights in Iran. I want to make clear that the promotion and protection of human rights is at the heart of UK foreign policy. And we are committed to supporting and protecting those who defend human rights and work tirelessly to advance personal freedoms, often at great personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OHQkieCYSZg"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/ukiniran/punishing-a-human-rights-defender-nasrin-sotoudehs" title="Nasrin Sotoudehs story"&gt;Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family" title="UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60181</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-court-of-human-rights-decision-on-chagossian-case"/>
    <title>European Court of Human Rights’ decision on Chagossian Case</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary has commented on the European Court of Human Rights’ decision on the Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom case. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case concerns complaints made by the Chagos Islanders arising from the evacuation of the British Indian Ocean Territory between 1967 and 1973.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the end of this legal process, which has taken many years. We have made clear our regret for the wrongs done to the Chagossian people over forty years ago. Nevertheless, it was right for the Government to defend itself against this action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that this litigation is concluded, the Government will take stock of our policy towards the resettlement of the British Indian Ocean Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;), as we have always said we would. There are fundamental difficulties with resettlement in &lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;, but we will be as positive as possible in our engagement with Chagossian groups and all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Human Rights decision on application 35622/04: Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.echr.coe.int/ECHR/Homepage_EN" title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60102</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T10:30:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T10:30:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary sends his best wishes to all for a Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0MNVdzOKLbM&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s Christmas message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2012 has been a remarkable year. Britain and the Commonwealth have celebrated the Diamond Jubilee of Her Majesty The Queen who today visited the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, her last engagement of this jubilee year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK also welcomed the world during the Olympic and Paralympic Games, the legacy of which will live on for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year has been a celebration of Britain’s diversity, innovation and creativity. 2013 presents us with many challenges but we’ll continue to work towards making the world safer, fairer, and more prosperous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to our presidency of the G8 and the ambitious agenda the Prime Minister has set for us and our partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And at this time of year we remember especially all those who will be spending this festive season in places of conflict. The suffering of the Syrian people and the prolonged misery that they have faced has saddened us all. The UK will continue to search for a peaceful solution. I’d like to thank all those who’ve worked so hard to protect others around the world including our servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wish you and your families wherever you are in the world a Merry Christmas and a peaceful and Happy New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe Ministerial Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
