<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56873</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:23:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/private-security-companies"/>
    <title>Private Security Companies</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the development of a regulatory system for private security companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aims to raise the global standards of private security companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) working in complex and high risk environments overseas. To this end, we have been working closely with interested partners, including industry and civil society, to establish a voluntary, independently audited and internationally recognised regulatory system that is practicable, effective and affordable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification to professional standards is the next step towards effective voluntary regulation. First the Government endorsed the Montreux Document in 2008, in which States commit to observe existing international legal obligations relevant to the operations of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in areas of armed conflict. Secondly, in 2010, an International Code of Conduct for Private Security Providers (&lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt;) was created. This provides a set of principles to guide companies. The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been signed by over 500 &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;, around a third of them British. We have reviewed options on setting new professional standards to make the Code effective. We now intend to issue an HMG publication specifying that ASIS PSC 1-2012 is the applicable standard for UK-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments on land overseas. I will place a copy of the publication in the libraries of both Houses. Companies, independent auditors and the UK Accreditation Service (&lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) will then take the further steps to enable auditing against these standards to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; mandated the development of auditable standards to ensure that signatory companies are implementing their commitments under the code. In response to this requirement, the international security trade association, ASIS, was funded by the Department of Defense to develop the standard – ‘PSC1’ – for the regulation of private security companies operating on land in complex environments overseas. This standard was drafted in a multinational and multi-stakeholder forum in which UK Government, UK industry and UK civil society fully participated.  It was published in March 2012 as an approved American National Standard and is the only standard currently available for companies operating in this field. &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; seeking certification in the UK to this new standard will have to be audited by independent third party auditors accredited by &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our trade association partners, the Security in Complex Environments Group, will, in consultation with Government, develop guidance to help British &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; meet the requirements of the new standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ambition is to have a single, internationally agreed standard and we therefore welcome the fact that PSC1 was recently submitted to the International Standards Organisation (ISO) to be considered for adoption as an international standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments. This process may take some time. We will review the need for a separate HMG publication of this standard once the ISO process has been completed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working with other States, industry and civil society internationally to ensure that there should be globally recognised standards and that UK companies are not unfairly disadvantaged by raising their standards. We expect that the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; governing board, when established, will advise that certification to the PSC 1 standard by suitably accredited independent auditors will meet the Code’s requirements for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to have auditable professional standards. We are still consulting with industry and civil society partners on what additional steps &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; might need to take to obtain full certification by the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; that they are meeting the Code’s principles but I can confirm that there will be no need for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to go through duplicate auditing procedures to become certified.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; was drafted with land-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in mind. However, since 2010 there has been a rapid rise in the number of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on anti-piracy operations at sea. Although many of the principles relating to &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on land and at sea are similar, there are important legal and practical differences. The Government is therefore also contributing to an international drafting process under the ISO for an equivalent professional standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in the maritime sector. A draft maritime standard was introduced at the International Maritime Organisation in late November. If and when this standard is adopted, &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will start the process of accrediting suitably qualified independent third party auditors to certify UK-based maritime &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity on the standards against which &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; should be audited is an important step forward in the drive to raise standards in this industry through voluntary action, but independently audited. It is also a practical illustration of the Government’s commitment to human rights and to working with business and civil society to find effective ways to implement our commitments even in the most challenging environments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56617</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:06:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/list-of-certified-companies"/>
    <title>List of certified companies </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Exporters need to always consult this listing if they intend to register for the OGEL (certified companies) published by the Export Control Organisation </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This list is published by the Export Control Organisation (ECO) in conjunction with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/military-goods-ogels#ogel-certified-companies"&gt;Open general export licence (certified companies)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular OGEL permits, subject to certain conditions, the export or transfer of items specified in Schedule 1 of the licence to those companies referred to in Schedule 2. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should always consult this list first before registering to use the licence via &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;, ECO’s export licensing database. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should also be aware that the Euopean Commission also publishes a publically available database called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/sectors/defence/certider/"&gt;CERTIDER&lt;/a&gt;. This Euopean database contains more information about the certification of defence-related companies across Europe. Access You can also &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/sectors/defence/certider/help/CERTIDER_Europa%20Manual_EN.pdf"&gt;download guidance on consulting the CERTIDER database on the Europa website (PDF, 1.81MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/52540</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:40:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/exchange-of-notes-uk-note-concerning-itar-rule-change-dated-11-august-2011"/>
    <title>Exchange of notes (UK Note) concerning ITAR rule change dated 11 August 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Document issued in conjunction with the International Trade in Arms Regulations (ITAR) rule change dated 11 August 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This note was issued in conjunction with an equivalent US Note. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For related guidance please refer to our guide &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/exporting-military-goods-to-the-united-states"&gt;exporting military goods to the United States&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/51396</id>
    <published>2012-08-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:40:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/exchange-of-notes-us-note-concerning-itar-rule-change-dated-11-august-2011"/>
    <title>Exchange of notes (US Note) concerning ITAR rule change dated 11 August 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Document issued in conjunction with the International Trade in Arms Regulations (ITAR) rule change dated 11 August 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This note was issued in conjunction with an equivalent UK Note. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For related guidance please refer to our guide &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/exporting-military-goods-to-the-united-states"&gt;exporting military goods to the United States&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/47242</id>
    <published>2012-06-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/strategic-export-controls"/>
    <title>Strategic export controls</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office’s Strategic Export Controls Reports demonstrate the Government’s 
commitment to transparent and responsible controls on British arms 
exports.The quarterly and annual reports give details by destination, of physical exports and equipment licensed for export.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
