<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Increasing investment in research, development and innovation for growth"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48312</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/annual-innovation-report-2012-innovation-research-and-growth"/>
    <title>Annual innovation report 2012: innovation, research and growth</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fourth annual innovation report that gives the latest available evidence on UK innovation performance and the contribution of business, government, higher education and research organisations to UK innovation activities. Presents key measures of innovatio&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48270</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-innovation-survey-2011-statistical-annex-revised"/>
    <title>UK innovation survey 2011: statistical annex [revised]</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statistical annex for data from the 2011 UK innovation survey (12/P107). It includes an overview of the methodology, details of response rates and weighting, and reference tables with the survey results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48185</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-a-synthetic-biology-roadmap-for-the-uk-letter-from-david-willetts-mp-to-dr-lionel-clarke"/>
    <title>Response to 'A synthetic biology roadmap for the UK': letter from David Willetts MP to Dr Lionel Clarke</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government’s response to the UK Synthetic Biology Roadmap Coordination Group_s recommendations for the future development of synthetic biology in the UK. Synthetic biology aims to design, engineer or replicate biological systems, for example biosynthetic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47148</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/vince-cable-promotes-uk-advanced-manufacturing"/>
    <title>Vince Cable promotes UK advanced manufacturing</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;8 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="mira-technology-park"&gt;MIRA Technology Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIRA Technology Park (MTP) was granted &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;Enterprise Zone&lt;/a&gt; status by the government in August 2011. This has enabled MIRA to become Europe’s most advance independent transport technology facility. It is the first milestone in MIRA’s aim to become Europe’s most advance independent transport technology facility. Vince Cable opened the Technology Park’s new £6 million Control Centre, with the help of a MIRA unmanned vehicle to cut the ribbon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIRA provides state-of-the-art secure research facilities where high-tech companies can develop products that will make the world’s vehicles cleaner, smarter and safer. With companies like Bosch, Ashok Leyland, Triumph Motorcycles, Norgren and Lockheed Martin, the MTP cluster will help the UK to benefit from advanced automotive manufacturing, through deep rooted research and development.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was created the Technology Park has created 188 jobs, and a further 145 will be created in 2013. These are steps towards the goal of creating 2,000 jobs at MIRA over the next 10 years, and will contribute to the growth of advanced manufacturing in the Midlands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-for-low-carbon-automotive-research-and-development-challenge"&gt;Funding for low carbon automotive research and development challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary also announced £16.5m of funding for the next low carbon automotive research and development challenge from the Technology Strategy Board (TSB), the Office of Low Emission Vehicles (OLEV) and the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC). This will support R&amp;amp;D into four key areas: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internal combustion engines &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy storage and management &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lightweight vehicle and powertrain structures, and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electric machines and power electronics. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="toyota"&gt;Toyota&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the day at Toyota in Burnaston, Vince Cable witnessed the launch of production of the new Auris model - this time in all its hybrid, petrol and diesel guises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary acknowledged Toyota’s critical part in the success story of the UK automotive manufacturing industry. Toyota has &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;made the technology to reduce carbon dioxide from cars a mainstream proposition, as the first company to manufacture a volume hybrid vehicle in Europe &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;boosted UK automotive manufacturing by investing in Burnaston, including £185 million in Auris for its European markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable met Toyota workers who were initially recruited as temporary contractors and were then offered production apprenticeships. Toyota now offers all new production workers a Level 2 apprenticeship. A high percentage have taken up this apprenticeship offer, with some going on to become direct Toyota employees. This supports the government’s aim to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/holt-review-new-measures-to-improve-apprenticeships-for-smes"&gt;promote apprenticeships and make them more widely available&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-growth-funding-for-derby"&gt;Regional Growth Funding for Derby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable also confirmed that Derby City Council will receive £40 million for its programme bid under Round 2 of the Regional Growth Fund (RGF), supporting growth and sustainable employment in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Programme will provide funds to support local business investment. This is expected to create around 3,000 new private sector jobs in the area in 2020, and develop local transport infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;Enterprise Zones&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/g/12-1010-growing-uk-automotive-supply-chain-2012-update.pdf"&gt;Growing the automotive supply chain: the road forward - 2012 update (PDF, 257 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/holt-review-new-measures-to-improve-apprenticeships-for-smes"&gt;Support for small businesses in taking on apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Employers/The-Benefits.aspx"&gt;Business benefits of apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48180</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/e-science-and-e-infrastructure-needs-of-the-uk-life-sciences-industry"/>
    <title>E-science and e-infrastructure needs of the UK life sciences industry</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Report for the E-Infrastructure Leadership Council (ELC) on the e-science and e-infrastructure requirements of the UK life sciences industry. Focuses on several scientific disiplines and makes recommendations for each, including investing in the UK skills&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48181</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/developing-e-infrastructure-in-the-uks-engineering-and-manufacturing-industries"/>
    <title>Developing e-infrastructure in the UK's engineering and manufacturing industries</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the progress made by the UK engineering and manufacturing industries in the adoption, utilisation and exploitation of UK e-infrastructure. Highlights a number of significant barriers to that progress and makes recommendations to enable the remova&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47153</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-billion-investment-for-uk-science-and-research"/>
    <title>£1 billion investment for UK Science and Research</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash boost comes from the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (UK RPIF), which will deliver over £1 billion to support the development of new facilities and projects in areas including life sciences, energy and advanced manufacturing. The projects announced today are:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A £48 million partnership between Manchester University, Christie Hospital and Cancer Research UK to develop the Institute for Cancer Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An £85 million partnership between UCL (University College London) and the Great Ormond Street Hospital for The Centre for Children’s Rare Disease Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £32 million partnership between Queen’s University Belfast, The Atlantic Philanthropies and a Wellcome-Wolfson Capital Award to deliver the next phase of the Institute of Health Sciences. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £34 million partnership between the University of Nottingham and GlaxoSmithKline to support the Centre of Excellence in Sustainable Chemistry. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £38 million partnership between Swansea University, British Petroleum (BP), and TATA Steel Europe for the development of the Energy Safety Research Institute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £60 million partnership between Brunel University, TWI and other companies to develop a National Research Centre for Structural Integrity. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £150 million partnership between Imperial College London and Voreda to contribute to the development of a major new campus adjacent to the White City regeneration area.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This takes the  total number of projects supported by the fund to 14.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities will shortly be able to bid for the remaining £80 million of public investment from the fund. This must be matched by at least double from private sources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is fantastic that our top businesses and top charities are queuing up to collaborate with our world-class universities. They want to work together to deliver innovation, commercialisation and growth, which will help make sure the UK competes and thrives in the global race.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The winning projects will tackle the key issues we face - like fighting disease, ensuring energy efficiency and improving infrastructure - for the benefit of all.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK RPIF was first launched with £100 million of public finance in May 2012 and, in response to the large number of high-quality bids, the Government recently tripled the public support to £300 million. All projects have to include private funding from industry or the charitable sector worth a minimum of double the public contribution - making more than £1 billion of investment in total.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UKRPIF is managed and allocated by Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE), working in collaboration with devolved counterparts.  All proposals are assessed by an independent assessment panel.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/whatwedo/rsrch/howfundr/ukresearchpartnershipinvestmentfund20122015/#d.en.72999."&gt;HEFCE’s fund details&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/More-than-1-billion-to-be-invested-in-UK-science-and-research-68276.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: More than £1 billion to be invested in UK science and research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/science"&gt;BIS Science &lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47192</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/shaping-a-uk-agri-tech-strategy-call-for-evidence"/>
    <title>Shaping a UK agri-tech strategy: call for evidence</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK has the potential to be at the forefront of developing innovative solutions, and to make fuller use of its agri-science base. Translating fundamental and applied scientific research into innovative technologies, practices and information could enable countries worldwide to meet the food and environmental challenges ahead while also contributing significantly to UK economic growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its world class plant, animal and environmental research base, the UK is well placed to contribute to the global effort needed to improve the sustainable intensification of agriculture both at home and overseas. This would raise yields without using more land while adapting to climate change, reducing emissions, and maintaining biodiversity and other ecosystem services. It will involve engaging a very wide range of disciplines including natural (plant, animal, agronomy) and social scientists, engineers, and experts in risk management, economics and modelling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is developing a long-term agri-tech strategy focused on knowledge transfer and the application of technology to the agricultural sector. This is part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/speeches/vince-cable-industrial-strategy-september-2012"&gt;UK Industrial Strategy&lt;/a&gt; announced by the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills in September 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This call for evidence seeks to establish a strong evidence base from the existing knowledge in the agricultural sector. It will inform our understanding of role of agricultural technology, its strengths and weaknesses and the potential benefits to global food production. We aim to gain better understanding of potential opportunities for UK businesses including growth in exports of products, technology and know-how, and inward investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/agri-tech-strategy-call-for-evidence-Oct-2012"&gt;Respond to the online survey&lt;/a&gt; **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/s/12-1174-strategy-for-agri-tech-call-for-evidence.pdf"&gt;Shaping a strategy for agri-tech: call for evidence (PDF, 127 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48228</id>
    <published>2012-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/science-engineering-and-technology-set-statistics-2012"/>
    <title>Science, engineering and technology (SET) statistics 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A summary of key science, engineering and technology indicators, prepared in collaboration with the Office for National Statistics. Includes analysis of the Government financing of SET activities in the UK, describes the relationship between the funders a&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48102</id>
    <published>2012-08-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/life-sciences-strategy-update-august-2012"/>
    <title>Life sciences strategy update: August 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Letter from David Willetts to stakeholders about progress in implementing the ‘Strategy for UK life sciences’ (URN 11/1429). Focuses on and highlights progress for the following themes: research clusters and collaborations, data, improving the environment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
