<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Helping people to buy a home"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17053</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T15:57:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-empty-homes-conference-2012"/>
    <title>National Empty Homes conference 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Rachel Whiteread won international recognition for her cast of an empty room. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a striking piece. Conveying the sadness, the sheer tragedy of an unoccupied place - a place with no one to call it home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significantly, the artist’s name for that work was ‘Ghost’ and that really is the point. Homes are not pieces of sculpture. They are made to be occupied. An &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes"&gt;empty home&lt;/a&gt; is a phantom. A hole in the heart of a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know homes fall empty for all sorts of reasons. Some are renovated, some in probate, some are even second homes. But, wherever you find these haunted houses you’ll find blighted communities and lost neighbourhoods. Ambition abandoned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen how it happens. The empty edifice becomes an eyesore. The eyesore becomes a magnet for rats, vandals, drug dealing, squatters and prostitution. Neighbours are inconvenienced. Communities are damaged. Council and local emergency services stretched to breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics prove the point. Research by The Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors suggests properties adjoining poorly maintained empty properties can drop by almost 20% in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in part we were reaping the whirlwind of the failed policies of the past. The destructive Pathfinder programme undermined once vibrant communities. Marooning people in appalling homes surrounded by a sea of derelict streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the legacy we’ve inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A legacy of almost three quarters of a million empty homes abandoned to the winds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re determined to say never again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to inhabit the absences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plug the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring ghost homes back from the brink to the land of the living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we afford not to do it? It’s a moral and financial imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 1.7 million families on housing waiting lists. Of those some are homeless forced to live in overcrowded B&amp;amp;Bs. And the country’s population is growing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, house building is really important, vital, as the Deputy Prime Minister’s recent housing announcement made clear. But, as George Clarke would say, it would be “a crying shame” if we couldn’t occupy these wastes of space. Make use of what we’ve already got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the government’s approach has been threefold. First, we’re making more funds available for bringing homes back into use. And we’ve committed £160 million to bring over 11,000 empty houses back into use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t about throwing money at a problem but making sure the money goes to the right places. Everyone who understands this area, knows there is no one-size fits all solution. Behind every empty home lies a myriad of social, historic and economic issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our approach must be to create local answers to local issues. Giving local communities the right incentives to take the lead. So they will no longer turn a blind eye. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than talk you through which fund comes from which pot, let me focus on the difference the money can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Habitat for Humanity in Dagenham, received financial aid to bring 35 houses back into use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redcar &amp;amp; Cleveland Borough Council used its cash to renovate 20 homes and help unemployed residents to learn new skills for employment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing Health Independence, out in my constituency in Bath, is bringing 18 properties back from the brink&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kingston upon Hull City Council has written to 500 owners of empty homes offering to resuscitate their property - more than three quarters have already said yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These organisations deserve all the praise they get. What can be better than giving someone a home?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our approach is not all about money. It’s about keeping empty homes on the agenda. That’s the second point I’d like to make today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be a case of out of sight out of mind. Often there are people who care passionately about the areas they live in but they haven’t a clue about what to do next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But thanks to George - the fastidious work of the Charity Empty Homes, the grass roots activities of local authorities and registered providers, the passion of community groups - ghost homes now have nowhere to hide. We’re stopping the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we’re taking the carrot and stick approach. There are now powerful incentives for all local authorities to tackle empty homes such as the New Homes Bonus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means local authorities can earn the same financial reward for bringing an empty home back into use as building a new one. And it has provided an income of £26 million to local authorities for bringing empty homes back into use over the past year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when advice and support isn’t enough? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those circumstances we’ll get tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to take action against individuals who just can’t be bothered, who refuse to see the problem, who feel it’s ok to abandon their homes to the elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve given local authorities the power to reduce or remove Council Tax relief for empty and unfurnished homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve allowed them local discretion to introduce a Council Tax premium on homes empty and unfurnished for more than 2 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next April, billing authorities will be able to charge up to 150% of Council Tax on such property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the Empty Dwelling Management Orders. These force owners to bring their properties back into use. And, last but not least, as a last resort, there is the compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point about these things is not how many times they are used but the fact they are there at all. They are a deterrent against those who refuse to take responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our efforts these silent shells are vanishing before our eyes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we came to power the number of long term empty homes has fallen by 50,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This downward trend is continuing. The latest figures show a further decrease 20,000 in long term empty homes to 259,000 in 2012. And every house back in circulation, means a roof over the head of a working family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there is still a very long way to go. Yet what we’ve demonstrated emphatically is the power of collaborations. That it’s coalitions of organisations - registered social landlords and community groups, house builders and local authorities - that together will make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These collaborations ensured the house in Oldham that stood empty for 14 years will soon be occupied. Oldham Borough Council and Aksa Homes brushed aside the cobwebs, hovered up the tumbleweed, rebuilt the pathways and put in new gates and fitted a new kitchen. A new home awakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s absolutely vital we harness the wealth of skill, experience, knowledge and application that these partnerships bring. So today I am inviting councils, housing associations, community and voluntary groups, and high street regeneration groups, prioritising our 27 Portas pilots to step forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In exchange for a share of £300 million I want them to tell me their plans to scatter the shadow of empty homes and bring thousands more back into the light. You’re the experts and it’s your innovative ideas I’m after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final thing. I’m keen to take our empty homes policy in a new direction. This shouldn’t just be about turning disused residential properties, those ageing apparitions, into inviting homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not turn empty offices into homes? Why not use the spaces above shops for housing? People who need a place to live don’t mind where it comes from. We’re making this easier to do. We’ve already introduced a whole host of policies to get rid of the red tape that gets in the way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know this type of project can be more challenging than a residential refurbishment. Typically, there are obstacles such as access and security to overcome. But they mustn’t stand in our way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minute you occupy an empty home, you start of an amazing chain reaction of events. You don’t just bring homes back to life, but neighbourhoods and communities. And businesses and jobs follow in their wake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re determined to exorcise ghost homes from the collective psyche. We’re straining every sinew to make them a myth not the reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up and down the country, there are people who dream of one day seeing neighbourhoods revive and redundant homes come back to life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have little doubt, that working together, we will grant them their wish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16804</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T12:41:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T12:41:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-visits-hidden-homes-in-wandsworth"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles visits ‘Hidden Homes’ in Wandsworth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles visited the Rollo housing estate in the London Borough of Wandsworth today (22 November 2012) to see how £3.6 million of government funding is helping the council provide more affordable homes for local families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the final 38 affordable new homes of the Hidden Homes initiative that celebrates its 10th anniversary this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles with Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1168/Rollo2-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wandsworth Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis welcome Eric Pickles to the borough to officially unveil the new Hidden Homes&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Offering excellent value-for-money, the cutting-edge programme converts vacant and disused spaces on housing estates - from boiler rooms to storage areas - into modern and attractive affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme has delivered 238 homes in Wandsworth over the past decade. These have been allocated to local families and first time buyers, often on a shared ownership basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hidden Homes approach has provided more affordable homes, and at the same time prevented these redundant spaces from becoming eyesores or potential havens for anti-social behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles praised the borough for boosting housing delivery that, in the 12 month period to March 2012, was the highest in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Wandsworth scheme was a lesson to other councils for delivering more affordable housing, despite the tough economic circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects like Hidden Homes also provide valuable economic regeneration, creating jobs and boosting the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is committed to delivering more affordable homes that families need. Our £19.5 billion investment is delivering 170,000 affordable homes, and our FirstBuy and NewBuy schemes are helping families take the next step on the property ladder with just a fraction of the normal deposit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we also want more councils to do more, and adopt innovative solutions like those being pioneered in Wandsworth. Using government and council funding, these Hidden Homes are making a fantastic contribution to the affordable housing landscape and giving families and first time buyers the chance to have their own home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabinet Member for Housing at Wandsworth Council, Councillor Paul Ellis said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Hidden Homes scheme has played a really major role in increasing the supply of affordable housing over the past decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well as proving incredibly cost effective, it has also helped create jobs in the construction sector and been the key to regenerating redundant land on housing estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the secretary of state will today unveil its biggest single scheme, and that as a result, 3 dozen families in housing need will be able to move into brand new high quality homes”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding for Hidden Homes builds on the options available for aspiring homeowners who want to get onto and up the housing ladder. This includes the NewBuy Guarantee and the reinvigorated Right to Buy, which will give thousands of council tenants the opportunity to buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632071654509/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16489</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T15:01:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/right-to-buy-notice-in-reply-to-a-tenants-claim-rtb2"/>
    <title>Right to Buy: notice in reply to a tenant's claim (RTB2)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a council tenant applies to buy their home through the Right to Buy scheme, the council will send a notice (RTB2) within 4 weeks of receiving the completed application form (RTB1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will confirm if the tenant has the Right to Buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16254</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:29:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/social-housing-sales-in-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Social housing sales in England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents official statistics on the number of sales of existing social housing stock in England for 2011 to 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social housing sales include sales under right to buy, preserved right to buy, right to acquire, social homebuy, other outright or shared equity sales to tenants, and sales of existing stock to the private sector. The figures exclude sales through low cost home ownership schemes where these do not relate to existing social stock, i.e. sales of newly built homes for shared ownership or acquisitions of private sector homes for affordable home ownership. Intra-tenure transfers between social housing providers are also excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were an estimated 9,670 total social housing sales in England in 2011-12. This is an increase of 15% on 2010-11 but continues the low level of sales seen since 2008-09. The increase was entirely due to an increase in private registered provider sales; local authority sales were virtually unchanged.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were an estimated 3,720 right to buy sales in England in 2011-12 (38% of all sales), a 1% increase from 2010-11. Most (70%) right to buy sales were of local authority properties. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The average market value of a local authority property purchased through right to buy in 2011-12 was £100,040. Average capital receipts were £73,350 and the average discount was £26,690 per property. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registered provider sales in 2011-12 included 140 properties sold through the right to acquire scheme (compared to 200 in 2010-11) and 40 through social homebuy (compared to 110 in 2010-11).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A further 3,320 sales (34% of total sales) were disposals of registered provider properties to the private sector. Other shared equity and outright sales of existing stock accounted for the remaining sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These statistics relate to right to buy sales by local authorities and registered providers. The statistics include sales under the right to buy and preserved right to buy schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16258</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:29:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/right-to-buy-sales-in-england-2012-to-2013-quarters-1-and-2"/>
    <title>Right to buy sales in England: 2012 to 2013 - quarters 1 and 2</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents official statistics on the number of sales of dwellings under the right to buy scheme, as well as providing statistics on receipts resulting from those sales, and starts on site as part of the one-for-one replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local authorities sold an estimated 444 dwellings under the right to buy scheme in 2012-13 quarter 1. In this quarter local authorities received £24 million from right to buy sales, while 14 dwellings were started on site or acquired.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local authorities sold an estimated 1,043 dwellings under the right to buy scheme in 2012-13 quarter 2. In this quarter local authorities received £62 million from right to buy sales, while 234 dwellings were started on site or acquired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These statistics relate only to sales by local authorities under the right to buy scheme, excluding sales by registered providers under preserved right to buy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14720</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/multi-million-pound-boost-will-help-buyers-onto-the-housing-ladder"/>
    <title>Multi-million pound boost will help buyers onto the housing ladder</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First time buyers will from today benefit from a multi-million pound boost to help them onto the housing ladder said Housing Minister Mark Prisk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister announced the first allocations from a £280million pot to help a further 16,500 first time buyers benefit from the FirstBuy scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk confirmed that £40million will go to 41 developers to help 2,500 first-time buyers this year - and called on them to go further, and bid for a share of £240million to help deliver thousands more new homes under the scheme next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="home-ownership-hope-for-thousands"&gt;Home ownership hope for thousands&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hugely popular FirstBuy scheme reduces the amount of deposit first-time buyers have to find by offering an equity loan of up to 20 per cent provided by the Government and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister said that the extension of FirstBuy would provide help to thousands more first time buyers across the country, offering an alternative to the Bank of Mum and Dad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme has already helped thousands of buyers across the country, with 3,000 sales made by March this year and developers reporting more than 8,000 FirstBuy reservations by the end of August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £280million boost to FirstBuy forms part of the Housing and Growth Package announced by the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister in September, one of a range of measures designed to get Britain building and kickstart the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This package builds on the suite of options available for aspiring homeowners who want to get onto and up the housing ladder. This includes the NewBuy Guarantee and the reinvigorated Right to Buy, which will give thousands of council tenants the opportunity to buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Firstbuy has already proved hugely successful, providing a practical alternative to the Bank of Mum and Dad for thousands of first-time buyers across the country.
&amp;gt; “The scheme has become a major player in helping people onto the property ladder and getting Britain building again - and I’m determined to maintain that momentum.
&amp;gt; “That’s why today just a month after the Prime Minister confirmed this funding boost, I’m asking developers to start putting this money to good use - and giving them the chance to start planning for how they can help first-time buyers in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homes and Communities Agency chief executive Pat Ritchie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the additional £280million of FirstBuy funding, which will make a major difference to the lives of prospective homebuyers and keep momentum for affordable home ownership going, not only for this financial year but for the year after.
&amp;gt; “We are pleased to be able to allocate some of the funding for this financial year, and anticipate a strong bid response to the remaining £240million, and we look forward to working with our developer partners to bring these homes forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FirstBuy provides first time buyers with an equity loan of up to 20 per cent of a new build property from a participating developer. The loan, which is jointly funded by Government and housebuilder, can reduce the deposit requirement to just 5 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Budget 2011 the Chancellor announced the FirstBuy scheme which will see Government and housebuilders providing £400million to help around 10,500 first time buyers purchase a home.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency published official statistics on 12 June that showed there had been 2,994 sales by the end of March 2012 (sales starting in September 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 6 September the Prime Minister announced a further £280million for the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency has today announced initial allocations of £40million and published a prospectus inviting housebuilders to submit proposals for the remaining £240million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13385</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:35:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/housing-and-growth--5"/>
    <title>Housing and growth</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission, Mr Speaker, I would like to make a statement on housing and planning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the coalition government inherited a legacy where house building had fallen to its lowest rates since the 1920s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a top-down planning system that built nothing but resentment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a regime of regional planning quangos that created paralysis and confrontation -  after 6 years of preparation, by the general election, less than 60 councils had completed local plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result was no development. No regeneration. No community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government wants to get the economy growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remove unnecessary red tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support locally led sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November, the government published a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; to support a thriving, active and stable housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, we published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to condense 1,000 pages of central planning guidance to just 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housebuilding is up: 29% higher in 2011 than in 2009. But there is more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, my department is announcing a further series of common sense measures to promote house building and support locally-led economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technical details are laid out in a written statement which has been laid before the House. I will summarise the key points for Hon Members:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;following on from &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/11300/2204242.pdf" title="Review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes"&gt;Sir Adrian Montague’s independent report (PDF 272 KB)&lt;/a&gt; on supporting the private rented sector, we are providing £200 million of new funding to support institutional investment in high-quality rented homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thanks to the action we have taken to tackle the last government’s deficit, we are passing on the lower costs of borrowing. We will be issuing a debt guarantee for up to £10 billion to support private investment in the private rented sector and in new affordable housing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will support up to an additional 15,000 affordable homes through the use of loan guarantees, flexibilities and capital funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we also intend to extend our successful refurbishment programme to bring an additional 5,000 existing empty homes back into use. The last government wanted to demolish Victorian terraces with John Prescott’s Pathfinder programme. By contrast, we are getting homes back into productive use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in total we will invest another £300 million in these measures to support new affordable homes and bring empty homes into use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we actively want to support home ownership, which fell under the last Parliament despite a Labour pledge to increase it by a million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are extending our successful FirstBuy scheme for first time buyers, with an additional £280 million of funding, helping up to 16,500 additional first-time buyers to purchase a home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to free up more brownfield land for development and regeneration, we will accelerate the release of surplus public sector land and empty offices through a targeted programme of transfers from other government bodies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will work with local authorities and developers to unlock locally supported large sites. Just last week, we were back to unblock the Eastern Quarry in the Ebbsfleet Valley - a major ex-industrial site that had stalled for a decade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are working with local communities and councils. But some councils need to raise their game, by failing to make planning decisions in a timely way. Planning delays create uncertainty both for local residents and local firms. So we will introduce a series of practical measures to help speed up planning decisions and appeals, and major infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some complex developments take time to assemble. So we are allowing for developers to extend the duration of existing planning permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are making it easier for developers to change unrealistic Section 106 agreements. A development which isn’t built means no Section 106 payments. Common sense reforms will result in more regeneration, more housing and more community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable development should go hand in hand with environmental safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can confirm that we have protected the Green Belt, in line with our commitment in the coalition agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always the case that councils can amend local Green Belt boundaries should they wish - and we will support councils which choose to. This can include introducing new Green Belt protection around new large developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is considerable previously developed land in many Green Belt areas. We encourage councils to make best use of this land, whilst protecting the openness of the Green Belt in line with the requirements of the National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to protect our countryside, we need to focus more growth in our town centres. So we are introducing measures to make it easier to turn empty commercial buildings into housing. Our high streets will benefit from a greater resident population, increasing footfall and supporting local shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nation, we have great pride in our homes. We want to make it easier for families to undertake home improvements - such as building a new conservatory. So we will be seeking to simplify and increase permitted development rights for householders. Cutting back municipal red tape in this way could provide a particular boost for small traders and small builders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, these practical measures build on the housing, local government finance and planning reforms already in play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving more power to individuals, to communities, to councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing new incentives to support local shops, local firms and local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering sustainable development and getting Britain building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16670</id>
    <published>2012-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dealing-with-squatters-in-your-home"/>
    <title>Dealing with squatters in your home</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 1 September 2012, a person squatting in a residential building is committing a crime. The offence covers squatting in all residential buildings. It protects homeowners and lawful occupiers who discover squatters have occupied their homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is jointly produced by the Department for Communities and Local Government and the Ministry of Justice. It is aimed at informing property owners about the new offence and the procedures for regaining possession of their properties from squatters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It updates the version published on 21 March 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11583</id>
    <published>2012-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:33:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/mortgage-arrears-and-possessions-forecasts"/>
    <title>Mortgage arrears and possessions: forecasts</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In January 2012 DCLG commissioned Professor Muellbauer, of Oxford University, to update his model which forecasts repossessions and loans in arrears in the UK and to produce updated forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research report sets out the changes to the model since the last report and the revised forecasts. This update led to the inclusion of an extra eight observations, together with a number of data revisions. The update also means that the forecast of loans in arrears and repossession now draws upon a range of economic forecast scenarios based mainly on underlying forecast data from the Office for Budget Responsibility but also from Oxford Economics for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new forecasts represent an improved outlook for both repossessions and arrears compared to the previous forecast. The main reason being the change in interest rate expectations; interest rates are now expected to rise much later; in mid 2013, instead of early 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
