<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting the Falkland Islanders’ right to self-determination"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47019</id>
    <published>2012-06-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-honours-sacrifice-of-falklands-fallen-thirty-years-on"/>
    <title>UK honours sacrifice of Falklands fallen thirty years on</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne has spoken of his admiration for the Falkland Islands people on the thirtieth anniversary of the conclusion of the Falklands conflict.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representing the UK Government at commemoration services in the capital, Stanley, Mr Browne has also met members of the Falkland Islands Assembly and heard how they are building their economy and developing their communities to improve local facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of those living on the islands can trace their family back nine generations, and all believe the area’s improving fortunes are testament to the self-determination in which they passionately believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Browne’s visit also marks a time to reflect on the sacrifice of those who gave their lives for freedom. Speaking ahead of the Liberation Day Service at Christ Church Cathedral, he said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am honoured to be here to remember the members of the UK Armed Forces who fought, and the many who died, in the Falklands conflict. Their sacrifice will not be forgotten. It is the reason that the people of the Falkland Islands are able to choose their own future today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The people living here now either remember the conflict themselves or know somebody who does. It is very much alive in the collective memory. We should not forget the reasons for our presence here or the right of the Falkland Islanders to decide their own destiny. This is a fundamental right. Thirty years on, the principle of self-determination for the Falkland Islands people remains as important as it ever has.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the service the Minister will attend the Liberation Day Parade, involving both members of the Armed Forces and local residents. The parade will include a ‘freedom march’, stressing the rights of all peoples to liberty and justice. This right was emphasised on Tuesday when the Falkland Islands Government announced a referendum on their political future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, Mr Browne also remembered the Argentine dead during a visit to the Argentine cemetery at Darwin, where he laid a wreath to the fallen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his wider programme, on Tuesday the Minister opened a new fisheries building, highlighting the importance the region puts on this industry. He also visited the Community School in Stanley, talking to the people who will be the future of the Falkland Islands, and whose decisions will affect the islands’ developments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47022</id>
    <published>2012-06-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-welcome-falkland-islands-government-referendum-announcement"/>
    <title>Ministers welcome Falkland Islands Government referendum announcement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague and Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne today welcomed the announcement by the Falklands Islands government of a referendum on the islands' political future.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The British Government has been consistent in its view that the future of the Falklands can only be determined by the people who live there.  So the Prime Minister and I support this initiative to demonstrate - without doubt - the definitive view of the Falkland Islands people.  In a region that rightly prizes democracy and human rights, it is entirely appropriate that the Islanders can express this fundamental right.  The principle of self-determination is a key part of the United Nations charter.  The voice of the Falkland Islands people should be heard.  I hope very much that Argentina, and indeed the whole of the international community, joins the UK in listening carefully to what they have to say.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking, today, from Stanley, Falklands Islands, Jeremy Browne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a privilege and a pleasure to be here with the Falkland Islands people, as they commemorate the thirtieth anniversary of their liberation.  The sacrifices made by the British armed forces in the 1982 conflict were significant.  We will never forget them.  But the British Government believed then, as we do today, that the protection of the Falkland Islanders’ political liberty - of their right to determine their own future - is a principle worth defending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Only the Falkland Islands people can determine how they wish to be governed.  So I very much support this initiative by the Falkland Islands Government.  Indeed, I believe this referendum is a truly significant moment.  It will give the Falkland Islands people the opportunity to send a clear message - not just to Argentina, but to the whole of the international community - that the Islanders, and they alone, are masters of their fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the next few months the Falklands will give their definitive verdict on their political status.  The British Government will respect their decision, in line with the principles of the United Nations Charter.  And I call on all governments who prize democracy and human rights to do likewise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whilst it is for the Islanders to choose, let me be clear: the British government greatly values the links between the UK and the Falkland Islands.  We believe these should continue and deepen, long into the future.  And if this proves to be the will of the Falkland Islands people, then we in the UK will not just respect it, but will continue actively to defend this act of self-determination from those who seek to challenge it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, the Falkland Islands Government announced its attention to hold a referendum.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Chairman of the Legislative Assembly, Gavin Short, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have no doubt that the people of the Falklands wish for the Islands to remain a self-governing Overseas Territory of the United Kingdom.  We certainly have no desire to be ruled by the Government in Buenos Aires, a fact that is immediately obvious to anyone who has visited the Islands and heard our views.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we are aware that not everyone is able to come to these beautiful Islands and to see this reality for themselves. And the Argentine Government deploys misleading rhetoric that wrongly implies that we have no strong views or even that we are being held hostage by the UK military. This is simply absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have thought carefully about how to convey a strong message to the outside world that expresses the views of the Falklands people in a clear, democratic and incontestable way. So we have decided, with the full support of the British Government, to hold a referendum on the Falkland Islands to eliminate any possible doubt about our wishes. This referendum will be organised by the Falkland Islands Government and will take place in the first half of 2013.  We will invite independent, international observers to observe the process and verify its outcome.  Exact timings, the specific wording of the question, and other details will be announced in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are holding this referendum not because we have any doubts about who we are and what future we want, but to show the world just how very certain we are about that.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47021</id>
    <published>2012-04-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/why-we-still-want-to-work-with-argentina--2"/>
    <title>Why we still want to work with Argentina</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague wrote about areas where the Falklands, UK and Argentina can work together in an article for the Telegraph.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have apparently reliable evidence that an Argentine task force will gather off Cape Pembroke [East Falkland] early tomorrow morning, 2 April. You will wish to make your dispositions accordingly.” So read the characteristically understated telegram from the Foreign Office to the Falkland Islands’ Governor, Rex Hunt, dispatched 30 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it came to pass: in less than 24 hours, Argentina’s armed forces had invaded the islands. Thus began a 10-week occupation, ended only by a British task force sent to restore the Falkland islanders’ liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s anniversary of the start of that conflict marks a day for commemoration and reflection, especially for those families - on both sides - whose loved ones were lost to its battles, including many Argentine soldiers who also rest in peace on the islands. In the UK, we will remember those 255 service personnel who made the ultimate sacrifice for an inviolable principle: to restore the Falkland islanders’ right to determine by whom they wished to be governed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look back on those events, we should remind the world that in the years since their liberation the Falkland islanders have repeated - without qualification or equivocation - their wish to keep their constitutional status, their national identity, and to live peacefully with their neighbours in Latin America. As long as the people of the Falklands continue to express that view, the UK will defend and support their right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 30 years, much has changed. Despite the challenges of relative geographic isolation, the Falklands have grown and prospered. The population has almost doubled to about 3,000. GDP rose from £5 million in 1980 to more than £100 million in recent years. And in the face of a sustained Argentine effort to prevent them from doing so, the Falkland islanders have developed a thriving local economy, with a responsibly managed fishery, growing tourism based on their unique natural environment, and the beginnings of a commercial hydrocarbons industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation has coincided with significant wider change across Latin America as well. Democracies have blossomed, and trade between neighbours is driving socio-economic progress throughout the region. These are positive developments which I welcome warmly. As I said in a speech shortly after becoming Foreign Secretary, the UK has been too much absent from South America for too long. The increased potential of the partnerships between Britain and Latin American countries is beginning to show since we’ve increased our diplomatic presence, with more staff and new posts, and dramatically increased the number of ministerial visits to the region since 2010. We are well on track to double our trade with Brazil, Mexico and Colombia by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the regional politics, the Falkland islanders are keen to play their part in this new regional reality. The trade, commercial and people-to-people links between the islands and South America are long-standing, but have even more promise today. As 21st-century mature democracies, we should all embrace the economic opportunities available to those willing to trade openly in an increasingly interconnected world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against this broader context, the Argentine government’s policy in recent months has been deeply regrettable and its statements have impressed few people, including in South America. In place of the dialogue and engagement we saw in the 1990s, Argentina has in recent years taken a range of measures to try to coerce the islands: from attempts to intimidate businesses involved in the hydrocarbons industry, to the harassment of Falkland fishing vessels by the Argentine coastguard; from threats to cut the one air link between the islands and South America, to actually closing its ports to cruise ships that have visited the Falklands. Such efforts to intensify a disagreement - which neither we nor the people of the Falkland Islands have ever sought to provoke - are out of step with international collaboration in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain will maintain an absolute commitment to preserve the right of the Falkland islanders, some of whom have lived there for nine generations, to determine their own political and economic destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while the British government will not negotiate over the sovereignty of the islands unless and until the people who live there wish it, there is much that all three of us - Falklands, UK and Argentina - can nevertheless discuss together. Fisheries, hydrocarbons, communications, trade and confidence-building measures have all been the subject of agreements in the past - albeit agreements that Argentina has subsequently resiled from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if anniversaries provide moments for reflection, it is surely time to reflect on how we can all work together in our common interest in the years ahead. It is relevant that many countries who have bilateral disagreements still collaborate on areas where there are mutual benefits such as economic and trade co-operation. That is our wish with Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47023</id>
    <published>2012-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/falkland-islanders-free-to-determine-their-own-future"/>
    <title>Falkland Islanders free to determine their own future</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A Foreign Office spokesperson has today spoken about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson said: “The people of the Falkland Islands are British out of choice. They are free to determine their own future, and there will be no negotiations with Argentina on sovereignty unless the Islanders wish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are not militarising the South Atlantic. Our defensive posture in the Falklands remains unchanged, though we remain firmly committed to the defence and security of the Falklands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“UN action is a matter for Argentina. The Falklands is already discussed annually in the C24 Committee. The UK has no doubt about our sovereignty over the Falklands, and the principle of self-determination, as set out in the UN Charter, underlies our position.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47020</id>
    <published>2012-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/falkland-islanders-must-be-masters-of-their-own-fate"/>
    <title>"Falkland Islanders must be masters of their own fate"</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>In an article published today the Foreign Secretary William Hague sets out why the future of the territory can only be decided by its people themselves.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday, the writer Simon Winchester and the Argentine Foreign Minister made the case for a negotiated handover of the Falklands. Here the Foreign Secretary sets out why the future of the territory can only be decided by its people themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The future of the Falkland Islands is about people: their freedom to determine their own future and to develop their own community and economy. Thirty years after the Argentine invasion, their right to self-determination remains, and will always remain, the cornerstone of our policy. This is in tune with the beliefs in human and political rights of the 21st century, but it is also rooted in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of the two months of occupation by Argentina in 1982, the Falklands have been continuously and peacefully inhabited and administered under British sovereignty since 1833.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Argentina alleges that Britain took the Falklands by force in 1833, expelling the civilian Argentine population and supplanting it with British subjects. The facts speak differently: Britain took formal possession of the islands in 1765, establishing various settlements over the next half century before the independent state of Argentina came into being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1832 Argentina dispatched a military garrison to the islands. Britain protested and sent forces to remove it. No civilians were expelled and historical evidence suggests that the majority of the 30 or so civilians chose to stay. British settlers arrived from 1833 onwards, and were joined by other nationalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1850 Britain and Argentina signed an agreement to settle their “existing differences”. And in the 90 years between 1850 and 1940 Argentina made only one formal diplomatic protest over the Falkland Islands, in 1888.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The islanders of today live in a diverse and democratic society. Many have lived there for generations - there are children on the islands whose Falklands ancestry can be traced back nine generations. As with Latin America, the population has grown through a natural flow of migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And although they retain their links to the UK as an overseas territory, the islanders elect their own leaders and make their own decisions about how to govern their own affairs. While they are justifiably proud of their links to Britain, many say that they are Falkland Islanders first and British second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only the islanders can be the masters of their future. We will never impose a different kind of political association, or agree to changes in sovereignty, unless and until the islanders themselves wish it. This has been the policy of successive British governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Argentine Government characterises its position as reasonable, saying that it wishes to negotiate peacefully a “resolution”. Britain has always been open to discussions with Argentina, and that, of course, remains the case. There are many areas on which we can co-operate: on joint management of fish stocks, on hydrocarbon exploration and on strengthening air and sea links between the Falklands and South America. We used to do this in the 1990s and ought to be able to do it again. But we will never negotiate sovereignty without the consent of the islanders. Self-determination is an established principle in international affairs, embedded in the UN Charter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are happy to talk, recent Argentine governments have taken a less constructive approach. They walked away from the South Atlantic Fisheries Commission, thus - as The Times recently reported - risking serious damage to fish stocks in the South Atlantic. Argentina has withdrawn from a 1995 agreement to co-operate on oil exploration and, in violation of the principles of global free trade, targets companies that operate in Falklands waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of working for a mutually beneficial solution for commercial air links, Argentina has banned charter flights and prevented most scheduled air services. At sea, Argentina has sought to impose restrictions on Falklands vessels travelling through the international Strait of Magellan or calling on other South American ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is genuinely interested in progress it should stop these attempts to intimidate a civilian population. It should agree to discuss how, as democracies, the Falklands, Britain and Argentina can work together in the South Atlantic neighbourhood in our common interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many aspects of our relationship with Argentina are positive, but they have the potential to be so much more productive. For our part, we stand ready to build on this potential for the benefit of all our citizens and of wider peace and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this would be welcome in the region too. This week I was in Brazil where, as part of a broad agenda, we discussed these South Atlantic issues. I know that the statement by the Latin American bloc Mercosur last month, apparently banning vessels that fly the Falkland Islands flag, troubled many people. In my view it had no legal or political justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in discussions with regional partners over the past few weeks it has become increasingly clear that this declaration will present no practical impediment to the ability of ships to travel between the Falklands and South America. Moreover, I see no regional appetite for joining Argentina in its attempts to damage the islands’ economy or target the livelihoods of islanders, and I welcome that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever political differences there may be between UK and South America on our sovereignty of the Falklands, we have with Brazil and other partners a relationship where we can discuss them honestly, and address them in the context of international law and respect for the human rights of the islanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also continue with our wider policy of deepening and broadening Britain’s engagement with Latin America as a whole, sending more diplomats, opening diplomatic missions and boosting trade and cultural ties. Mine was the fifteenth British ministerial visit to Brazil in the past year - testament to a change in our relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to us intensifying these efforts over the coming years, for there is great potential in this new relationship. As we take it forward, we will always ensure that the wishes of the Falkland islanders and their right to self-determination are never in doubt.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece first appeared in The Times newspaper&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/28313</id>
    <published>2012-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-statement-to-the-house-of-commons-on-the-falkland-islands"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary statement to the House of Commons on the Falkland Islands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague responds to statements made in South America regarding the Falkland Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I would like to update the House on the British Government’s response to statements made in South America regarding the Falkland Islands during the Christmas recess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 15th December the Government of Uruguay declared that they would deny access to their ports to ships flying the Falklands flag.  This was followed five days later by a statement from the summit of the Mercosur group of countries (Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay, with associate members including Chile) that echoed the Uruguayan announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our response has been justifiably robust.  The Uruguayan Ambassador was formally summoned to the FCO and I spoke twice to the Uruguayan Foreign Minister to underline how seriously we regard this development. Our Ambassadors in the region were instructed to call on their host governments to express our strong objection to the Mercosur statement and to assess the practical implications for vessels operating between the Falklands and South America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made clear that the decision to close ports to ships flying the Falklands flag has no legal basis, and that it would be unacceptable and unbecoming for any Latin American democracy to collaborate in Argentina’s attempts to economically blockade the Falkland Islands.  We reiterated our strong support for the rights of the Islanders to determine their political future, and also made clear that any attempts to coerce them through economic or other pressures would be resisted by the British Government.  Such actions are inconsistent with the principles of the United Nations Charter and the rights of the Falkland Islands people to trade openly and without hindrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we do not accept that the decision to refuse entry to vessels flying the Falklands flag has any basis in international law, our priority has been to ensure that the trade and commercial links between the Falklands and South America are not compromised by this political declaration.  We have had productive and honest discussions with Uruguay, Chile and Brazil.  All three countries have said that they have no intention of participating in an economic blockade of the Falkland Islands and that all Falklands-related commercial shipping will continue to enjoy access to their ports, in accordance with domestic and international law, if they are flying the Red Ensign or another national flag when docked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that others in the region will continue to recognise that differences of opinion over UK sovereignty of the Falkland Islands can not justify collusion in efforts to intimidate an innocent civilian population through economic pressure.  The British Government will always ensure that the Falkland Islanders’ right to determine their political future is respected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, we will continue to strengthen our engagement of Latin America, as I set out in my Canning House speech in November 2010. The UK has considerable political, economic and security interests in the region, with high potential for future economic growth through partnership with Latin America.  I am confident that this important agenda is consistent, and indeed mutually reinforcing, with our desire to ensure that the interests and wishes of the Falkland Islanders are protected.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47044</id>
    <published>2011-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-expresses-concern-over-mercosur-decision"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister expresses concern over Mercosur decision</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne has spoken after the Mercosur group of countries decided to prevent ships that fly the flag of the Falkland Islands from entering their ports.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am concerned by the decision of the Mercosur group of countries to prevent ships that fly the flag of the Falkland Islands from entering their ports. Falklands-flagged vessels have been regular visitors to South American ports for 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is not yet clear what the practical impact of the Mercosur statement might be as it reflects similar language used in the region previously. Some countries take a different view from us on our sovereignty of the Falkland Islands. It is for the people of the Falkland Islands to determine their future. It is unacceptable to engage in an economic blockade of the Falklands. Mercosur should take the responsible decision and not do this. There can be no justification - legal, moral or political - for efforts to intimidate the people of the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have instructed our Ambassadors in the region to raise this issue as a matter of urgency to clarify exactly whether or how Mercosur countries propose to implement this agreement. We will then consider our next steps in light of information we  receive. But no one should be in any doubt about the British Government’s commitment to support the Falkland Islanders’ right to determine their own political future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay make up the Mercosur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/25226</id>
    <published>2010-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:14:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/jeremy-browne-no-doubt-about-our-sovereignty-over-the-falkland-islands"/>
    <title>Jeremy Browne: “No doubt about our sovereignty over the Falkland Islands”</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne has said there “cannot be negotiation on sovereignty unless and until the Falkland Islanders so wish,” following a statement by the Argentinean President.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Argentinean President Cristina Kirchner today at the EU-Latin America and Caribbean summit asked the UK to open negotiations on the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister of State for Latin America, Jeremy Browne said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have no doubt about our sovereignty over the Falkland Islands. The principle of self determination as set out in the UN charter applies. There cannot be negotiation on sovereignty unless and until the Falkland Islanders so wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Lisbon Treaty clearly reaffirms the EU position that the Falkland Islands is an Overseas Territory of the United Kingdom.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“While we disagree with Argentina over the Falkland Islands, we have a close and productive relationship on a range of other issues, including on economic issues in the G20 and on climate change, sustainable development and counter-proliferation.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Catherine Ashton, High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy and Vice-President of the Commission, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Falkland Islands are associated with the European Union as an overseas territory of the UK in accordance with Articles 198/204 of Part Four of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
