<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16084</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report on the revocation of the North East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S5 from the Northumberland County and National Park Joint Structure Plan First Alteration relating to the green belt at Morpeth. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the Coalition Agreement to safeguard green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note:&lt;/strong&gt; Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13410</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-east-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East Midlands Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East Midlands Regional Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13408</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the South East Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South East Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices. This includes whether or not to retain the Oxfordshire structure plan policy H2, covering development at Upper Heyford, until a revised plan is adopted by the relevant local planning authority (Cherwell District Council).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13404</id>
    <published>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-yorkshire-and-the-humber-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the Yorkshire and the Humber regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11630</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/code-for-sustainable-homes-and-energy-performance-of-buildings-data-england-wales-and-northern-ireland-up-to-end-of-june-2012"/>
    <title>Code for sustainable homes and energy performance of buildings data: England, Wales and Northern Ireland up to end of June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest official statistics on the Code for Sustainable Homes and Average Energy Efficiency (SAP ratings) were released on 23 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics in this release relating to the Code for Sustainable Homes show the number of dwellings that have been certified to the standards set out in the Code Technical Guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11808</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/potential-funding-for-community-green-spaces"/>
    <title>Potential funding for community green spaces</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the potential funding available to community and voluntary organisations to start either a food growing or community orchards project. It identifies the different grant schemes open to local groups, green spaces, allotment organisations or trusts, and also where to go to get help when looking for funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in August 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11809</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/space-for-food-growing-a-guide"/>
    <title>Space for food growing: a guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide is aimed both at community groups that might be looking for land to start their food growing project or trying to find new ways to encourage people to get involved in their existing scheme and at individuals who might be interested in growing their own food but are not sure whether to wait for a local authority allotment or continue their search elsewhere. The guidance can also be used by voluntary groups trying to decide what activities might suit their client base or by individuals who have yet to be convinced that food growing is really for them. The guide provides links to sources of further advice and guidance and also to more detailed information on where to go to get funding or to learn from established projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12703</id>
    <published>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renegotiation-of-section-106-planning-obligations"/>
    <title>Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s Housing Strategy &lt;em&gt;Laying the Foundations: A Housing Strategy for England&lt;/em&gt; published on 21 November 2011 set out a proposal to allow reconsideration of planning obligations agreed in more buoyant market conditions. The aim of this consultation is set out the details of how the proposal will work and to seek views.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12704</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy"/>
    <title>Strategic Environmental Assessment of revoking the east of England regional strategy</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Environmental Report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the East of England Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy (which together form the regional strategy in force for the East of England).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East of England Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East of England Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11598</id>
    <published>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/investigation-into-overheating-in-homes"/>
    <title>Investigation into overheating in homes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report identifies the main gaps in the literature on overheating in homes, and recommends areas where further work might be of most value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis has been carried out on behalf of Government by a consortium led by AECOM, and supported by the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and University College London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the second project output; the first being a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/overheatingliterature"&gt;Literature Review&lt;/a&gt; covering whether overheating is occurring in new dwellings, in existing dwellings and whether or not retrofitting/refurbishing existing dwellings is likely to increase the risk of overheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
