<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16084</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report on the revocation of the North East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S5 from the Northumberland County and National Park Joint Structure Plan First Alteration relating to the green belt at Morpeth. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the Coalition Agreement to safeguard green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note:&lt;/strong&gt; Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13410</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-east-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East Midlands Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East Midlands Regional Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13408</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the South East Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South East Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices. This includes whether or not to retain the Oxfordshire structure plan policy H2, covering development at Upper Heyford, until a revised plan is adopted by the relevant local planning authority (Cherwell District Council).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13404</id>
    <published>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-yorkshire-and-the-humber-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the Yorkshire and the Humber regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11630</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/code-for-sustainable-homes-and-energy-performance-of-buildings-data-england-wales-and-northern-ireland-up-to-end-of-june-2012"/>
    <title>Code for sustainable homes and energy performance of buildings data: England, Wales and Northern Ireland up to end of June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest official statistics on the Code for Sustainable Homes and Average Energy Efficiency (SAP ratings) were released on 23 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics in this release relating to the Code for Sustainable Homes show the number of dwellings that have been certified to the standards set out in the Code Technical Guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11808</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/potential-funding-for-community-green-spaces"/>
    <title>Potential funding for community green spaces</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the potential funding available to community and voluntary organisations to start either a food growing or community orchards project. It identifies the different grant schemes open to local groups, green spaces, allotment organisations or trusts, and also where to go to get help when looking for funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in August 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11809</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/space-for-food-growing-a-guide"/>
    <title>Space for food growing: a guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide is aimed both at community groups that might be looking for land to start their food growing project or trying to find new ways to encourage people to get involved in their existing scheme and at individuals who might be interested in growing their own food but are not sure whether to wait for a local authority allotment or continue their search elsewhere. The guidance can also be used by voluntary groups trying to decide what activities might suit their client base or by individuals who have yet to be convinced that food growing is really for them. The guide provides links to sources of further advice and guidance and also to more detailed information on where to go to get funding or to learn from established projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12703</id>
    <published>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renegotiation-of-section-106-planning-obligations"/>
    <title>Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s Housing Strategy &lt;em&gt;Laying the Foundations: A Housing Strategy for England&lt;/em&gt; published on 21 November 2011 set out a proposal to allow reconsideration of planning obligations agreed in more buoyant market conditions. The aim of this consultation is set out the details of how the proposal will work and to seek views.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13382</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T11:21:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/abolition-of-regional-strategies"/>
    <title>Abolition of regional strategies</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is the Government’s policy to revoke existing regional strategies outside London, reflecting manifesto commitments made by both Coalition parties in the 2010 general election and subsequently incorporated into the Coalition Agreement. The Localism Act 2011 provides for the abolition of regional strategies in a two-stage process. The first stage, to remove the regional planning framework and prevent further strategies from being created, took effect when the Localism Act received Royal Assent on 15 November. The second stage would be to abolish the existing regional strategies by secondary legislation. However, any final decision on this must take account of assessments of, and consultation on, the possible environmental effects of revocation of each of the existing regional strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Environmental Assessment process is set out in an EU Directive (Directive 2001/42/EC). In March 2012, the European Court of Justice issued a significant ruling on the interpretation and application of the Directive (Inter-Environnement Bruxelles ASBL &amp;amp; Others v Government of the Brussels-Capital Region).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Strategic Environmental Assessment process, and before the decision of the European Court of Justice, there has already been consultation with the statutory consultation bodies on the scope and level of detail of the environmental reports. Public consultation took place between October 2011 and January 2012 on the basis of environmental reports published in October 2011. Detailed responses were provided in the course of this exercise.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the decision of the European Court of Justice, in the light of planning policy and legislation that have been put in place since January 2012, in light of the earlier consultation responses, and in order to be meticulous in observing the requirements of the Directive, the Government is now updating the environmental reports and undertaking additional consultation. We are publishing the first of the updated environmental reports: the report in respect of the proposed &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;revocation of the East of England Regional Strategy&lt;/a&gt; shortly and will place a copy in the Libraries of both Houses. This report builds on and is intended to supersede the previous report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period for consultation responses will remain open for eight weeks. We welcome and encourage all interested parties to respond. At the end of that period we will consider all consultation responses, including those already submitted during the October 2011 to January 2012 response period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks my Department will publish updated environmental reports relating to the proposals on each of the other regional strategies, so that those proposals too can be the subject of additional consultation. In each case there will be an 8 week period for consultation responses. All updated environmental reports will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses as they are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed revocation of the Regional Strategies may be regarded as a material consideration by decision makers when determining planning applications and appeals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In respect of plan-making, the National Planning Policy Framework implementation period provides councils with the incentive to get their plan policies up to date and in doing so they can have regard to the policy to revoke Regional Strategies and the new National Planning Policy Framework policies. A local plan document must be in general conformity with the regional strategy at the stage that the plan is submitted for examination but it is open to councils when preparing local plans to take account of the policy to revoke up to the time of submission. Local authorities can also bring forward proposals (for example on housing targets) which have a local interpretation to them in their plans, based on their own sound evidence base where that is justified by the local circumstances. That evidence base is likely to be more up to date than that included in the Regional Strategies. Each case will depend on its particular facts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12704</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy"/>
    <title>Strategic Environmental Assessment of revoking the east of England regional strategy</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Environmental Report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the East of England Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy (which together form the regional strategy in force for the East of England).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East of England Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East of England Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
