<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15804</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/development-rights-for-small-scale-renewable-and-low-carbon-energy-technologies-and-electric-vehicle-charging-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Development rights for small-scale renewable and low-carbon energy technologies and electric vehicle charging infrastructure</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sought views on government proposals to introduce permitted development rights for small scale renewable and low carbon technologies in domestic and non-domestic settings. It also sought views on introducing permitted development rights and deemed advertisement consent in relation to electric vehicle charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13410</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-east-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East Midlands Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East Midlands Regional Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13408</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the South East Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South East Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices. This includes whether or not to retain the Oxfordshire structure plan policy H2, covering development at Upper Heyford, until a revised plan is adopted by the relevant local planning authority (Cherwell District Council).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13404</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-yorkshire-and-the-humber-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the Yorkshire and the Humber regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12791</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-better-use-of-energy-performance-certificates-and-data"/>
    <title>Making better use of energy performance certificates and data</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Energy performance certificates (EPC) and display energy certificates (DEC) have an important role to play in supporting our carbon reduction aims by providing vital information about the energy efficiency of buildings in England and Wales and advice about measures to improve their energy performance. To enhance their contribution, we are consulting on a number of measures to help improve the effectiveness of EPCs and to make better use of energy performance data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12784</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-town-and-country-planning-environmental-impact-assessment-regulations-2010"/>
    <title>The town and country planning environmental impact assessment regulations 2010</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper covers the consolidation of the 1999 environmental impact assessment regulations, as amended, and explains amendments for screening changes and extensions. It also explains the requirement for the competent authority to provide reasons for screening decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12745</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/environmental-report-on-the-revocation-of-the-east-of-england-plan"/>
    <title>Environmental report on the revocation of the east of England plan</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its stated commitment to protecting the environment the government decided to carry out an environmental assessment of the revocation of the existing regional strategies, on a voluntary basis. It is the government’s clear policy intention to revoke existing regional strategies outside London, but this is subject to the outcome of environmental assessments and will not be undertaken until the Secretary of State and Parliament have had the opportunity to consider the findings of the assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional strategy whose revocation is proposed is the &lt;em&gt;East of England Plan&lt;/em&gt;, published in May 2008. The environmental report on the revocation of the East of England Plan is available below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12744</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/environmental-report-on-the-revocation-of-regional-planning-guidance-for-the-south-west"/>
    <title>Environmental report on the revocation of regional planning guidance for the south west</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its stated commitment to protecting the environment the government decided to carry out an environmental assessment of the revocation of the existing regional strategies, on a voluntary basis. It is the government’s clear policy intention to revoke existing regional strategies outside London, but this is subject to the outcome of environmental assessments and will not be undertaken until the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government and Parliament have had the opportunity to consider the findings of the assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional strategy whose revocation is proposed is the &lt;em&gt;Regional Planning Guidance for the South West (RPG 10)&lt;/em&gt;, published in September 2001. The environmental report on the revocation of the regional planning guidance for the south west (RPG 10) is available below. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12743</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/environmental-report-on-the-revocation-of-the-east-midlands-regional-plan"/>
    <title>Environmental report on the revocation of the East Midlands regional plan</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its stated commitment to protecting the environment the government decided to carry out an environmental assessment of the revocation of the existing regional strategies, on a voluntary basis. It is the government’s clear policy intention to revoke existing regional strategies outside London, but this is subject to the outcome of environmental assessments and will not be undertaken until the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government and Parliament have had the opportunity to consider the findings of the assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional strategy whose revocation is proposed is the &lt;em&gt;East Midlands Regional Plan (RRS8)&lt;/em&gt;, published in March 2009. The environmental report on the revocation of the East Midlands regional plan is available below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12741</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/environmental-report-on-the-revocation-of-the-north-west-of-england-plan"/>
    <title>Environmental report on the revocation of the north west of England plan</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its stated commitment to protecting the environment the government decided to carry out an environmental assessment of the revocation of the existing regional strategies, on a voluntary basis. It is the government’s clear policy intention to revoke existing regional strategies outside London, but this is subject to the outcome of environmental assessments and will not be undertaken until the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government and Parliament have had the opportunity to consider the findings of the assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional strategy whose revocation is proposed is the &lt;em&gt;North West of England Plan Regional Spatial Strategy to 2021&lt;/em&gt;, published in September 2008. The environmental report on the revocation of the north west of England plan is available below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
