<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-effective-regulation-of-freight-transport/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-regulation-of-freight-transport/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-regulation-of-freight-transport/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing effective regulation of freight transport"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-29T10:47:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17276</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T10:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T10:47:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-29-november-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 29 November 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has today published the following transport statistics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/driver-and-rider-tests-and-instructor-statistics-quarter-2-2012-13"&gt;Driver and rider tests and instructor statistics: quarter 2 2012/13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/road-freight-statistics-quarter-1-2011"&gt;Road freight statistics: quarter 1 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;statistics at DFT&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15323</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:07:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/cost-of-the-driver-cpc-recording-and-evidencing-database"/>
    <title>Cost of the Driver CPC recording and evidencing database</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information about the cost of the Driver CPC recording and evidencing database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14942</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T11:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:20:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plans-unveiled-to-increase-lorry-speeds-to-boost-growth"/>
    <title>Plans unveiled to increase lorry speeds to boost growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans to increase the speed limit for some heavy goods vehicles (&lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in a bid to boost economic growth have been announced today by Roads Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current speed limit on single carriageways for &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; over 7.5 tonnes is 40 mph. Under the proposals, this could be increased to 45 mph or 50 mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freight industry say this will help growth by improving journey times, cutting congestion and reducing costs to business and the cost of goods people buy. It could also reduce the number of collisions caused by other road users overtaking slower moving lorries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is committed to doing everything it can to improve conditions for economic growth. We are consulting on increasing the single carriage way speed limit for certain &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; after listening to industry experts who say that this will boost the UK economy and businesses of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While this is likely to lead to more than £30 million a year in benefits for businesses through quicker journeys and reduced congestion, I want to make sure we have carefully considered the evidence of all of the effects on the economy, environment and – of course – road safety before we make a decision. I welcome views from all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; statistics on monitored free-flow roads estimate that around 70% of &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; currently travel over 40 mph and it is argued that these &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; have an unfair competitive advantage over those who stick to the speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed limit for smaller &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; (those between 3.5 tonnes and 7.5 tonnes) is 50 mph. This will remain unchanged. This consultation does not cover any other speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch of the consultation follows a commitment published in ‘The logistics growth review’ in November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 1 February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation is now available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-34"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport estimates that around 280,000 &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; would be impacted by the changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The maximum speed limit for the road on single carriageways is 60 mph, (unless a local speed limit is in force)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066    &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292   &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/examining-the-speed-limit-for-heavy-goods-vehicles-over-7-5-tonnes-on-single-carriageway-roads"&gt;Consultation on examining the speed limit for heavy goods vehicles over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway roads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/heavy-goods-vehicle-speed-limit-increase-evaluation-final-report"&gt;Heavy goods vehicle speed limit increase evaluation: final report (PPR 576)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heavy-goods-vehicles"&gt;Heavy goods vehicles, written statement by Stephen Hammond, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13364</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:07:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heavy-goods-vehicles"/>
    <title>Heavy goods vehicles</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-34"&gt;consultation document which aims to examine whether the speed limit for heavy goods vehicles (&lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;) over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageways, is set at the right level&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This follows a commitment published in ‘The logistics growth review – connecting people with goods’ document in November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current speed limit on single carriageways for &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; over 7.5 tonnes is 40 mph. The speed limit for smaller &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; (those between 3.5 tonnes and 7.5 tonnes) is 50 mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders have told us that the 40 mph speed limit causes unnecessary costs to vehicle operators, congestion, avoidable overtaking collisions and creates an uneven playing field for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freight and logistics sector is an essential part of the economy, vital to businesses of all sizes and sectors. Raising &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; speed limits on single carriageway roads could lead to quicker journeys and lower costs for the sector, aiding economic growth as well as reducing frustration for the many drivers who find themselves stuck behind slower-moving lorries on busy roads unable to overtake. However there are other consequences of greater speed – both in terms of the environmental impacts and the potential effects on road safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are inviting responses from the trade associations, haulage companies, government enforcement bodies or police forces and organisations, road safety groups, local authorities and road users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 1 February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121109a"&gt;Plans unveiled to increase lorry speeds to boost growth press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/trl-ppr576"&gt;Heavy goods vehicle speed limit increase evaluation: final report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14755</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/examining-the-speed-limit-for-heavy-goods-vehicles-over-7-5-tonnes-on-single-carriageway-roads"/>
    <title>Examining the speed limit for heavy goods vehicles over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway roads</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximum speed limit for heavy goods vehicles (&lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;) over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway roads is prescribed in Schedule 6 of the Road Traffic Act 1984. The current speed limit on single carriageways for &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; over 7.5 tonnes is 40 miles per hour. The speed limit for smaller &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; (those between 3.5 tonnes and 7.5 tonnes) is 50 mph. The government made a commitment in ‘The logistics growth review – connecting people with goods’ document published in November 2011, to consult on this issue during 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders have said that the 40 mph speed limit causes unnecessary cost to vehicle operators, congestion, avoidable overtaking accidents and creates an uneven playing field for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freight and logistics sector is an essential part of the economy, vital to businesses of all sizes and sectors. Raising &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; speed limits on single carriageway roads could lead to quicker journeys and lower costs for the sector, aiding economic growth as well as reducing frustration for the many drivers who find themselves stuck behind slower-moving lorries on busy roads unable to overtake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there are other consequences of greater speed – both in terms of the environmental impacts and the potential effects on road safety. The department wants to make sure we have carefully considered the evidence of all of the effects on the economy, environment and road safety before any decision is made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/trl-ppr576"&gt;Heavy goods vehicle speed limit increase evaluation: final report (PPR 576)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20121109a"&gt;Heavy goods vehicles, written statement by Stephen Hammond, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121109a"&gt;Plans unveiled to increase lorry speeds to boost growth press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15329</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T10:56:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/heavy-goods-vehicle-speed-limit-increase-evaluation-final-report"/>
    <title>Heavy goods vehicle speed limit increase evaluation: final report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport commissioned the Transport Research Laboratory (TRL) to provide an evidence-base, analysis and reasoned opinion on whether or not there is likely to be any road safety risk involved in increasing the speed limit of heavy good vehicles exceeding 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway de-restricted roads from 40mph to 50mph (or possibly 45mph). This report gives detail on the findings of the research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-34"&gt;Consultation about examining the speed limit for heavy goods vehicles over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway roads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20121109a"&gt;Heavy goods vehicles, written statement by Stephen Hammond, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121109a"&gt;Plans unveiled to increase lorry speeds to boost growth press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13191</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T22:31:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/hgv-road-user-levy-bill"/>
    <title>HGV Road User Levy Bill</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today correcting the answer to a question that I provided during the Ways and Means Resolution debate on the &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; Road User Levy Bill, on Tuesday 23 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the question asked by Bob Stewart (Beckenham) (Con) on “whether vehicles leaving a port of entry will have a physical sign on their windows indicating that they have paid” [Official Report, 23 October 2012, Col 881], I should have clearly stated that there will be no physical sign of payment, through the display of a paper disc, sticker or similar item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payment of the levy will be recorded in a database using the vehicle registration as the unique identifier. We expect that enforcement of non payment will be carried out using Automatic Number Plate Recognition (ANPR) technology equipped cameras linked to this payment database, which will allow &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; to target and stop non-compliant vehicles. We expect that checks on vehicles will be made shortly after the heavy goods vehicles have left the port at which they have arrived, and are on the UK road network. Further checks will be carried out in other locations. Non-compliant vehicles will need to pay a penalty of £200 before they are allowed to proceed. Cases that are taken to court will be liable to a fine of up to £5,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of a physical indication of payment is impractical, as drivers could have to physically change stickers or discs daily, and it would create an enormous and costly burden, in terms of administration of the charge. It could also create problems if relied on for enforcement, as stickers or discs could be forged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s consultation on this subject was also based on a database linked enforcement method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13190</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T19:02:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/hgv-road-user-levy"/>
    <title>HGV Road User Levy</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of Members of the House, I am today setting out some details of the &lt;abbr title="heavy good vehicles"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; Road User Levy Bill which will be debated in the House of Commons on Tuesday 23rd October. The bill itself will be walked in after the debate on the Ways and Means resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="heavy good vehicles"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; Road User Levy Bill with introduce charges for all HGVs that weigh 12 tonnes and over for using the UK road network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government realises the importance of haulage services provided by both UK-registered and foreign-registered vehicles to our economy, ensuring that goods are brought in and efficiently moved around the country. The key aim of this bill is to ensure a fairer arrangement for UK-hauliers to help improve their competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation being introduced fulfils a commitment in the Coalition Agreement and is designed to remove an inequality, whereby UK hauliers pay to use many roads abroad, but foreign-hauliers do not pay to use roads in the UK. The levy is designed to be cost neutral for UK hauliers, through offsetting reductions in Vehicle Excise Duty (VED) payments. Changes to VED will be included in the Finance Bill 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The levy will be time based and will vary according to the vehicle type, weight and number of axles. This seeks to ensure that the charging scale is linked to the amount of damage a &lt;abbr title="heavy good vehicles"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; causes to a road. The levy will be a maximum of £1,000 per year or £10 per day for the largest vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK-registered HGVs will pay the levy for either a six-monthly or annual period. Foreign-registered vehicles can pay the levy either daily, weekly, monthly or annually. Rebates will be available under certain circumstances. Revenues will be paid into the Consolidated Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill makes it an offence to fail to pay the levy and, on summary conviction, a fine of up to level 5 on the standard scale (currently £5,000) will be payable. The bill also provides for the offence to be subject to a fixed penalty and it allows the Secretary of State to refuse to issue a vehicle licence if he is not satisfied that the appropriate levy has been paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will be administered by the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA) or the Driver and Vehicle Agency (DVA) in Northern Ireland. A private company will be contracted by the Department for Transport to administer the payment scheme for foreign-registered HGVs. The contractor will be required to maintain an electronic database of foreign-registered HGVs for which a levy has been paid. UK enforcement agencies will have access to the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will be enforced by the Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (VOSA) in Great Britain and the Driver and Vehicle Agency (DVA) in Northern Ireland. These agencies currently enforce UK and foreign hauliers’ compliance with regulations on vehicle roadworthiness, drivers’ hours and other road safety regulations. The Police also have enforcement powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-03"&gt;conducted a consultation exercise in early 2012, and the findings of this are also being published&lt;/a&gt; today, and will be available on the Department for Transport’s website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16423</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T21:11:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/security-requirements-for-moving-dangerous-goods-by-road-and-rail"/>
    <title>Security requirements for moving dangerous goods by road and rail</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses involved in the carriage of dangerous goods by road and rail for national and international journeys are required to take security measures to safeguard against acts of terrorism in accordance with chapter 1.10 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unece.org/trans/danger/publi/adr/adr_e.html"&gt;European Agreement concerning the International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Road (&lt;abbr title="European Agreement concerning the International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Road"&gt;ADR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; and of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.otif.org/en/publications/rid-2011.html"&gt;Appendix C of the Convention concerning International Carriage by Rail&lt;/a&gt;, Regulations concerning the International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Rail (&lt;abbr title="International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Rail"&gt;RID&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-requirements"&gt;The requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulation 5 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/1348/contents/made"&gt;Carriage of Dangerous Goods and Use of Transportable Pressure Equipment Regulations 2009&lt;/a&gt; (and as amended) apply the security provisions of &lt;abbr title="European Agreement concerning the International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Road"&gt;ADR&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Rail"&gt;RID&lt;/abbr&gt; for national journeys. Regulations 7 and 8 also contain additional security requirements for Great Britain. These regulations are subject to agreed derogations as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/cdg-approved-derogations-and-transitional-provisions/"&gt;Carriage of Dangerous Goods: Approved Derogations and Transitional Provisions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security requirements are split between two levels. A general level is applicable to all dangerous goods and requires that they shall only be offered to people, companies or organisations that have been appropriately identified, temporary storage sites shall be properly secured, drivers shall carry a means of photographic identification and security training awareness shall be provided. A higher level applies for high consequence dangerous goods and requires that a security plan is adopted, implemented and complied with. High consequence dangerous goods are defined as those which have the potential for misuse in a terrorist incident and which may, as a result, produce serious consequences such as mass casualties or mass destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirements do not apply to the carriage of civil nuclear material as defined by the Nuclear Industries Security Regulations 2003 (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Industries Security Regulations 2003"&gt;NISR&lt;/abbr&gt;). The transport of such material and non nuclear radioactive material is regulated by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/nuclear/transport/index.htm"&gt;Office for Nuclear Regulation&lt;/a&gt; in accordance with &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Industries Security Regulations 2003"&gt;NISR&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="road-and-rail-guidance-documents"&gt;Road and rail guidance documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) published guidance when the security requirements originally came into force in July 2005 to help you determine which measures you should apply in order to comply with the security requirements. This guidance is currently being reviewed and updated and will appear here in the near future. If in the mean time you have any enquiries regarding the security requirements please contact the department using the contact details below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supplementary-guidance"&gt;Supplementary guidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="carriage-by-road-and-rail"&gt;Carriage by road and rail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For advice on security training content, see our ‘Guidance for the design and delivery of security awareness training for the carriage of dangerous goods by rail &amp;amp; road’ publication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For information on personnel security see the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/personnel-security-resource-list/"&gt;CPNI Personnel security resource list&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nactso.gov.uk/hazardous-materials"&gt;UK National Counter Terrorism Security Office (NaCTSO)&lt;/a&gt; promotes an awareness raising scheme which encourages businesses and individuals to report suspicious activities and transactions involving chemicals, fertiliser and equipment of security concern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more information on the security of Class 1 Explosives: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/licensing/storage/storage-security.htm"&gt;HSE Security requirements for manufacture and storage of explosives&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You should consider the planning system when putting in new physical security measures - the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.planningportal.gov.uk/wps/portal/portalhome/unauthenticatedhome/!ut/p/c5/04_SB8K8xLLM9MSSzPy8xBz9CP0os3gjtxBnJydDRwMLbzdLA09nSw_zsKBAIwN3U_1wkA6zeHMXS4gKd29TRwNPI0s3b2e_AGMDAwOIvAEO4Gig7-eRn5uqX5CdneboqKgIAGUwqho!/dl3/d3/L2dBISEvZ0FBIS9nQSEh"&gt;planning portal&lt;/a&gt; website includes a planning guide for small businesses that will help you determine whether planning permission is required&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compliance with security requirements should be considered in conjunction with developing your &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/business-continuity"&gt;business continuity plan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physical site security guidance from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cpni.gov.uk/advice/Physical-security/"&gt;Centre for the protection of National Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="carriage-by-road-only"&gt;Carriage by road only&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; has produced a security training film for drivers of vehicles carrying dangerous goods; managers and employers of those drivers; and depot staff having responsibilities for communications with those drivers whilst on the road - please use our ‘Application form’  to apply for a copy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please also use our ‘Security film notes for trainers’  which support the dangerous goods road security training film&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Serious Organised Crime Agency and UK Border Agency have produced a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.soca.gov.uk/news/345-soca-a-uk-border-agency-joint-campaign-on-lorry-crime"&gt;Lorry Crime Prevention Booklet&lt;/a&gt; with a focus on preventing illegal immigration across the Channel but which reinforces &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s transport security messages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="enforcement-of-the-requirements"&gt;Enforcement of the requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Office for Nuclear Regulation enforce the security requirements of &lt;abbr title="European Agreement concerning the International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Road"&gt;ADR&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="International Carriage of Dangerous Goods by Rail"&gt;RID&lt;/abbr&gt; in Great Britain. For enquiries on legislation concerning Northern Ireland please contact the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hseni.gov.uk/guidance/topics/carriage_dangerous_goods_3_column.htm?ts=larger"&gt;Health and Safety Executive Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="enquiries"&gt;Enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enquiries regarding government policy and the regulatory requirements can be made via the following options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:dgsecurity@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;dgsecurity@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7944 2881&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fax: 020 7944 2174&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15833</id>
    <published>2012-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:45:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guide-to-mode-shift-revenue-support-msrs-scheme"/>
    <title>Guide to Mode Shift Revenue Support (MSRS) scheme</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide outlines the criteria and processes in place for applying for support from the Mode Shift Revenue Support scheme, also known as &lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Although information is correct at the time of publication, it is advisable that potential applicants contact the appropriate administrative body for the most up to date information before submitting a formal application for grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that there is no automatic entitlement to grant support and any offer of grant which may be made remains entirely at the discretion of the appropriate administrative body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-msrs"&gt;What is &lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; assists companies with the operating costs associated with running rail or inland water freight transport instead of road, where rail or inland waterway transport is more expensive. It is designed to facilitate and support modal shift, generating environmental and wider social benefits from reduced lorry journeys on Britain’s roads. The scheme operates in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; (Intermodal) for the purchase of intermodal container movements by rail; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; (Bulk and Waterways) for the purchase of other freight traffic movements by rail and all movements by inland waterway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; is a direct replacement for both the Rail Environmental benefit Procurement Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Rail Environmental benefit Procurement Scheme"&gt;REPS&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the Waterborne Freight Grant for inland waterways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on &lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; (Intermodal) can be found in section 2, &lt;abbr title="Mode Shift Revenue Support"&gt;MSRS&lt;/abbr&gt; (Bulk and Waterways) in section 3 and how to apply for both schemes in section 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
