<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state-minister-for-the-armed-forces</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state-minister-for-the-armed-forces.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for the Armed Forces</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18754</id>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-02-09-royal-navy-club-founders-day-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/02/09 - Royal Navy Club Founder's Day Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chairman, First Sea Lord, Gentlemen, it is an honour to be invited to address this year’s Founders’ Day dinner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the Admiralty Board, may I thank you Mr Chairman for your hospitality - and the Elder Brethren of Trinity House for allowing us to celebrate here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a busy year for the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the First Sea Lord intends to speak about operations, so let me express my appreciation, and that of the Government, for the incredible work that has been done by the Royal Navy since the last Founder’s Day Dinner: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On standing operations around the globe; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining our nuclear deterrent; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Royal Marines and others in Afghanistan; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the very substantial Naval contribution to Operation Ellamy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-state-of-the-nation"&gt;The State of the Nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by acknowledging, that as well as being a busy time for the Navy, it has been a great stretch, and this last 18 months has been particularly difficult as the reality of what the SDSR means settles in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing ships like Cumberland decommissioned - or Ark Royal - or aircraft like Harrier - all having given such good service to the Navy and the nation over many years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing gaps appear in naval capabilities like carrier strike;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not easy saying goodbye to colleagues you’ve served with for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redundancy programme, in particular, is a matter of great regret to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m sure everyone here recognises that the Government had to act to tackle the huge bow wave of unfunded liabilities that had built up in the Defence programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in itself, would have been a daunting effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not only this, I think, that has been so sobering over the last 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also been the realisation by many, particularly those of us concerned with the defence of the nation, of just how threatening the UK’s financial situation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The national debt has now topped a trillion pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are spending £50bn a year on the interest alone - the equivalent of a dozen Queen Elizabeth Aircraft Carriers or 33 Astute Class submarines - the scale of what we, as a nation, are facing becomes clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years ago, it was institutions like Northern Rock and the Royal Bank of Scotland that were being bailed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last year it’s been whole countries - Ireland, Greece, Italy, Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the United States has had its credit rating down-graded - and is cutting its defence budget by a staggering $500bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eurozone crisis has thrown a spotlight on just how exposed Britain’s economy is - and it has shown us just how isolated Britain could quickly become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nietzsche said - if you gaze for long into an abyss, the abyss gazes also into you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced, that in this era of great volatility, in this era of interconnectedness, in this era of economic exposure, Britain will continue to need all the benefits, all the influence and all the security that accrue from being a maritime power of significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is: how do we sustain that power in an age of austerity and competing demands - austerity and competing demands that are shared by our most dependable allies too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I try to answer that question, let me set out why Britain needs to remain a maritime power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-utility-of-maritime-power"&gt;The Utility of Maritime Power&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am of course preaching to the converted here so I will keep it brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an operational point of view, maritime power is essential in a world where we have to project power to protect our national security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we have to gain access to, and operate in, other domains in far flung parts of the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the littoral remains the focus of so much human activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea-basing provides choice and flexibility in deploying and sustaining force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides mobility, range and endurance and can help overcome a whole host of challenges associated with having a footprint on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are not abandoning carrier-strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we will maintain our amphibiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a vital part of the balanced capabilities that we have defined as Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maritime power, for Britain in particular, has never been solely about the application of military force in time of hot war - it is about a continuous national presence in other parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating slices of sovereign territory from which to operate and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea is a one of the most important global super-highways that Britain, as an island nation, depends upon for our prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on imports of goods and energy - the vast, vast majority coming by sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that dependence on the sea, especially for energy, is only going to increase in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only what comes and goes by sea - the trade which sustains our way of life - it is also about the resources the sea provides which need protecting - oil, minerals, fish, increasingly off-shore wind power too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe seas enable strong economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy has always played a part - sometimes alone, sometimes alongside our allies and friends - in making sure the vital sea arteries in the global commons are protected and that international law is observed - providing deterrence, reassurance, and influence - contributing to the nation’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="austerity-and-the-royal-navy"&gt;Austerity and the Royal Navy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, why more than any other institution in the country, you of the Royal Navy understand the inextricable link between economic power and the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is woven into much of your history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said an Army marches on its stomach - well it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Cicero said, finances are the sinews of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole of the Armed Forces march on the public purse - on the back of the taxes we all pay - and the size of the public purse depends ultimately on the health of the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, in my view, the coalition Government is right to focus its priority attention on getting the deficit under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right not only for the economy - but in the long-term it is right for national security too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only with healthy public coffers can we hope to sustain, in the long-term, the investment required for the high-tech, well equipped military forces we know we will need in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have had to act to both balance the Defence budget and bring the Defence Programme in line with the financial reality the country faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Budget took a hit - not nearly as much as some other departments - but a reduction in resources none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach the next General Election, and in preparation for the next Defence Review in 2015, the approach the political parties take to the Defence budget will be a measure of how committed they are to realising Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, thanks to cross-Government agreement, we now have the ability to plan on the budget allocated to defence equipment and support increasing by 1% a year in real terms between 2015 and 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been difficult but we are now close to achieving a sustainable budget for the first time in decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly confident that the end is in sight to the period of retrenchment and the period of growth will in time begin again with funds released for projects outside the core programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget that we are still spending considerable sums on Defence - over £150 billion over the next decade on defence equipment and support alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Royal Navy - we are already beginning to see the shape of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Daring, Dauntless and Diamond now part of the fleet, Dragon expected in the Spring, and Defender and Duncan coming on line - in the Type 45, Britain can boast one of the most advanced warships in the world - and the envy of our allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Astute is nearing the end of her sea trials to be followed over the next few years by Ambush, Artful, Audacious, Anson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2020, the Queen Elizabeth Class Carriers - the largest ships the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime thereafter, the Type 26 Global Combat Ship will begin to come on stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these will be leaders in their field and represent the most capable, high-technology platforms the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ship for ship this will be one of the most powerful fleets in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be smaller - yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be able to do everything, everywhere, every time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No - of course not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are entering an era in which all of Britain’s security requirements - and those of our dependent territories - can only be guaranteed through our alliances and through our partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in reality, it has always been thus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to turn a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need now to begin the hard work of putting the Fleet of 2020 together, bringing these platforms on line, making sure we retain the right skills, developing new recruits, maintaining the profile of the Navy in the public mind - all the while delivering on operations - keeping our citizens safe - protecting our interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me pay tribute to the way the First Sea Lord has set out his vision of a powerful, adaptable and vibrant Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you here are in attendance through your qualification for command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the moral component of leadership is one of the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are currently serving we need you to be focussed, positive, full of ideas, prepared to change yourself, willing to drive change in others, inspiring those around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are no longer serving we need your continued energy and experience, advocating in public for maritime power - even if it means - every now and then - holding people like me to account for the decisions we are taking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this Founder’s Day, together we celebrate the long and illustrious history of the Royal Navy - but let us today also look forward with confidence in the future too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18748</id>
    <published>2011-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-12-07-uk-norway-nuclear-disarmament-verification-initiative-workshop"/>
    <title>2011/12/07 - UK-Norway Nuclear Disarmament Verification Initiative Workshop</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, it is a great pleasure to welcome you to London today to this international workshop on nuclear disarmament verification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last five years the United Kingdom and Norway have been working together - one nuclear weapon state, one non-nuclear weapon state - looking at the challenges associated with verifying the dismantlement of nuclear warheads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop brings technical experts and policy officials from the UK and Norway together with those from 12 non-nuclear weapons states and the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next three days we will share with you the progress we have made and, hopefully, learn from you as we investigate avenues for further work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collaboration between Norway and the UK has been groundbreaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have built up a unique level of trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is about increasing awareness, understanding and trust between all of us here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about proving we can create partnerships that make an active contribution to nuclear disarmament and meaningful progress under the Non-Proliferation Treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-commitment"&gt;UK Commitment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite notable challenges over the last 40 years, the NPT has succeeded in limiting the spread of nuclear weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But large arsenals remain and nuclear proliferation continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to redouble our collective efforts and take tangible steps towards a safer more stable world in which countries with nuclear weapons feel able to relinquish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is committed to the long-term goal of a world without nuclear weapons, and we believe that the NPT is the best vehicle for creating the conditions to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress should be made not just on disarmament, but across the other pillars of the NPT too - non proliferation and peaceful access to nuclear power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, the Coalition Government has announced a series of unilateral measures to scale down our nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something Britain has done on a number of occasions since the end of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latest action includes reducing the number of warheads aboard each submarine to a maximum of 40; reducing the number of operational missiles in the VANGUARD class submarines to no more than eight and reducing the number of operational warheads to no more than 120. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme has commenced and we expect completion across the fleet by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On current plans, the subsequent reduction in our total stockpile of nuclear warheads to no more than 180 will be completed by the mid 2020’s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are meaningful reductions and confirm Britain’s place as the most forward leaning, progressive and transparent nuclear weapon state in the P5 and with the smallest declared arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sustainable-disarmament"&gt;Sustainable Disarmament&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we will do what we can on our own, we are clear that sustainable disarmament can only be achieved through a multilateral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the approach of both the Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties that make up the UK’s Coalition Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our focus now is on continuing to press for progress on multi-lateral disarmament and tackling the technical and practical challenges that disarmament poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable disarmament needs to be mutual, it needs to be balanced and it needs to be verifiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries will need to not only disarm, but also be seen to disarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, NPT Article VI calls for disarmament ‘under strict and effective international control’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any future disarmament process would need to be underpinned by a verification regime that can provide confidence that nuclear disarmament has taken place and that non-proliferation objectives have been met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must work now to ensure that the practical challenges are surmountable and we have the technical foundation necessary to make progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what this workshop is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="trust-and-verification"&gt;Trust And Verification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is very grateful to Norway for the commitment it has shown towards the work we are undertaking together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important and enduring lessons of our initiative is that building trust and confidence will be essential to implementing an effective verification regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, we have found, does not always come naturally in an area traditionally so shrouded in secrecy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course real non proliferation obligations and national security interests that both have to be protected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that shouldn’t hold us back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have worked hard at breaking down barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just about a technical understanding of the challenges of warhead dismantlement - it is about cultural understanding too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that I mean putting yourself in another’s shoes - a nuclear weapons state being sensitive to how a non-nuclear weapons state will approach issues - and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a non nuclear weapons state may want to see every last corner of a facility to ensure that there are no weapons being concealed, but without the understanding how this full access could give away proliferative information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment the UK Norway Initiative is unique - but it needn’t be, and it shouldn’t be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have proven that all States Parties to the NPT are able to make an active contribution to their Article VI disarmament obligations through verification research, whilst fulfilling their obligations to non-proliferation under Articles I and II. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop will demonstrate just how complex and how difficult it is to develop a credible regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to stress that the UK Norway Initiative does not yet have the ‘verification solution’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of work still to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true not only in the area of dismantlement verification that we have been concentrating on, but on the wider disarmament process too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other areas ripe for further collaborative and independent research and development and these represent opportunities for all states. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope this workshop will provide you with the ideas and understanding to help you identify some of these areas and to start your own projects perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Norway stand ready to offer guidance to states wishing to fulfil their NPT obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is the first time we have had the opportunity to elaborate on the whole project, and we are delighted each of you are here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are of course grateful to our colleagues at the Atomic Weapons Establishment for the role they are playing and look forward to the dinner they are hosting tonight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will be hosting a confidential expert-level meeting of the P5 early next year - this will be the first time that the P5 have met to focus on verification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is discussed here will be fed directly into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next few days will provide you with the opportunity to learn from our experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you the chance to challenge our conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it enables you to contribute to the international effort of disarmament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, we live in uncertain times - we live in an inter-connected and networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter which club you belong too, or how much you can afford to spend on your defences, no country, no matter how powerful, can hope to protect its national security by acting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to act together - not just to tackle existing threats, but to build for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the vision of the Non-Proliferation Treaty, and that has to be the vision that we seek to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what we are working towards here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the trust, understanding and know-how to ensure that when called upon we have the capability to achieve this vision for real.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18744</id>
    <published>2011-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-21-cyber-security-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>2011/11/21 - Cyber Security in the UK</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, thank you for inviting me here to talk about Cyber Security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to having a good discussion although I must admit to being a trifle nervous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded earlier of Don Bradman’s advice to his fellow countrymen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“don’t give the Englishmen an inch. Play it tough, all the way. Grind them into the dust”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I hope your approach to me here will be a little more gentle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before getting into the meat of the issue, let me start by setting out what I mean when I use the term cyber today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-cyber-domain"&gt;The Cyber Domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Ministry of Defence we are concerned with the environments in which Armed Forces can operate and defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally these have been physical geographic domains - land and sea for thousands of years - in twentieth century the air and space too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see cyber as new global domain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It consists of the interdependent network of information technology infrastructures computer systems, and embedded processors and controllers that power the internet and telecommunications networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure that creates the domain is physical - but the connections it creates are not bounded by geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberspace has revolutionised the way the world does business, educates, and entertains - the internet being the driving force of this revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our networked societies have come to rely on these connections - not only for information and social experience - but for the delivery of public services, for utilities like power and water, for economic growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure may be machine, but cyber space is a distinctly human environment - shaped by people - and abused by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaped by people because the human desire for information and access is driving the technology - not necessarily the desire for security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abused by people because cyber crime, cyber espionage, cyber terrorism, cyber vandalism - are all just human pursuits - simply crime, espionage, terrorism, vandalism and conflict by another means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about the suffix ‘crime’ - not the prefix ‘cyber’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference is the method - not the outcome or the intent -  stealing money or information is stealing - regardless of whether it is done by pick-pocketing or hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I do not agree with those who say we need a massive raft of new criminal offences relating to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we do need is to become smarter in preventing, detecting and prosecuting the use of cyber space for criminal or nefarious ends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will have to do this at an international level, because there are no geographic barriers in cyber-space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other area of security we will have to strike a very delicate balance in cyber-space between personal freedom, national sovereignty and international stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the London Conference set out earlier this month, we should focus on all the positive benefits of cyber-space - supporting economic growth and development, encouraging social freedom, providing choices - but doing so while ensuring safe and reliable access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because cyber is a methodology not an outcome, cyber policy and cyber security is difficult to place within the normal departmental system of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me set out how the UK is approaching this both domestically and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-growth-and-development"&gt;Economic Growth and Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, and most other nations for that matter, the economic well-being of our nation is increasingly reliant on the security and resilience of our inter-connected networks and systems operating in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These networks are not always clearly defined and working out exactly what to protect is difficult but ensuring that businesses are able to operate unmolested by criminals has to be a primary goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to be sure how much money is being lost to our economy as a result of cyber crime: most estimates come from online security companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A survey completed earlier this year by the UK company Detica was probably the most thorough ever conducted in the UK: it put the figure at £27bn which seems plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a big figure - and it is likely to continue growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we respond?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well first we have to recognise that this can’t be just government’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has to be a shared responsibility between government, business and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry has a responsibility to do more to prevent cyber crime, for example through more secure devices, systems and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector has to lead in the development of improved Internet security products, systems, services and standards in cyberspace, and to make the market easier to navigate for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a responsibility on users too to apply online the sort of basic commonsense behaviour they use in everyday life to keep themselves safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I call basic cyber-hygiene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your anti-virus software up to date;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regularly scan your computer for viruses;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t post sensitive personal information on open sites;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t open email attachments from senders you don’t recognise;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t download files you are unsure of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To illustrate how far people have yet to get the message, in the UK only around a quarter of all purchasers of a new PC ever activate their online virus protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a busy city you would never leave your front door unlocked when leaving the house, so why do that with your e-valuables?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course none of this is to say that Government has no role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does - particularly in law enforcement and the defence of critical national infrastructure - but its main function will be as a facilitator - encouraging the spread of fast networks, encouraging best practice in business and encouraging individual responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when it comes to tackling cyber crime, the efforts of users and businesses can only go so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only approach that can be effective will be a concerted and urgent international effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must ensure there are no safe havens for cyber criminals, what is unacceptable behaviour “offline” must also be unacceptable “online”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in the domestic arena, this does not mean that we need a new set of laws purely to police cyberspace, rather we should ensure that those international legislations and treaties that protect us are also enforced in the cyber domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-security"&gt;International Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this goes beyond crime, it should also apply to the other relations between states which are governed by treaties, including in conflict situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle must be that states should continue to comply with existing rules of international law and the traditional norms of behaviour that govern interstate relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any use of force and armed conflict, including that states must settle their international disputes by peaceful means in such a manner that international peace, security and justice are not endangered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is developing a range of cyber capabilities which would be used in accordance with the well understood Laws of Armed Conflict and more generally under Domestic and International Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of any UK military capability is subject to strict ministerial oversight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because cyberspace is a domain - a means to an end, it is not an end in itself - well understood concepts such as proportionality of action apply to cyberspace as much as they do to actions in the air, land or maritime domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes cyber so potent as a tool is a number of factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the all-pervasive nature of computers in our lives, in the Critical National Infrastructure, in our economy, in our financial services, in Defence, which creates huge vulnerabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the low technological threshold of entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our adversaries can exploit the same technology used by citizens going about their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That laptop that sits on the desk at home or in the office - used to do accounts, send email or catch up with television programmes - is the same instrument that could be used to launch an attack on our critical national infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, a single networked laptop in the hands of a sophisticated and informed attacker could be as effective a weapon as, say, a cruise missile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, there are no geographical barriers in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attack could be launched from any corner of the world with little warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a conventional military movement - which requires the kind of organisation, mobilisation and logistical support that is hard to hide - a cyber attack can essentially be covert until the moment it begins to do its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, attribution of both cause and effect will be difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know from the recent STUXNET worm, it can be very difficult to trace from where and by whom an attack was initiated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it may be unclear when a cyber event is taking place, what its exact purpose might be or the ultimate aims of the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifth - and perhaps most insidious - with cyber it is possible to rapidly create a mass effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the cyber attacks of Georgia in 2008 - hackers can be enlisted to ideological causes, equipped with the means to carry out mass attacks - so called botnets - and given the target information to direct and synchronise attacks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than a single attack on a target - this can result in hundreds of thousands of computers worldwide being hijacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that cyber is a powerful asymmetric tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen how terrorists can attack symbolic rather than military targets - the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Centre being an obvious example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can only be a matter of time before terrorists begin to use cyber space more systematically, not just as a tool for their own organisation, but as a method of attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So - is cyber a perfect storm for those of us concerned with security?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me offer two considerations that might encourage us to see some light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to quote a well known law of Physics, every action has an equal and opposite reaction - defence seeks to nullify attack ad infinitum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite what the technological reaction to cyber will be is as yet unclear but a response will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, what we present as vulnerabilities to ourselves are also vulnerabilities for our allies too - this is a great opportunity to pool our resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we should not forget the same vulnerabilities may apply to our enemies as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot guarantee our security in cyber space without international action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think and act internationally because cyber space is international space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of work being done bi-laterally and multilaterally to develop common understanding and common positions with other countries and international organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department has been working closely to develop enhanced Cyber relationships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the importance of cyber has been reflected in recent discussions we have had with Australia as well as with other allies such as the US and France amongst others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyber needs to be considered alongside Land, Air and Maritime in our campaign planning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end we are engaging with our trusted military partners to ensure that ‘Cyber’ is fully integrated into our preparations for future coalition operations and we are identifying opportunities for both information and burden sharing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion ladies and gentlemen, the cyber challenge is genuinely everyone’s problem, because the solution requires action at all levels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application of basic cyber hygiene by all citizens both at home and at work;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnership at a national and international level between governments and industry to protect critical infrastructure and ensure network resilience;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And broad engagement with allies and friends abroad to establish the principles of international action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let me finish with one final thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1860, the Pony Express fast mail system was set up in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It revolutionised cross-continental communication - reducing time it took messages to travel from the Atlantic to the Pacific to about 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pony Express has since been mythologised in print and film - the bravery of the riders, the romance of the Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you know how long this iconic system actually lasted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 months - 18 months before the ponies were replaced by the telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is this - technology moves quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how we protect ourselves today - we cannot stop thinking about how we protect ourselves tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of cloud computing where there is an app for every occasion - where we can’t always predict what the next big thing will be - we will need to be adaptable, flexible and fast off the mark to protect national security &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to be open to new opportunities, but ever aware of the dangers we will continue to face.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18734</id>
    <published>2011-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-10-14-supporting-civilian-authority-what-role-for-the-military--2"/>
    <title>2011/10/14 - Supporting Civilian Authority: What Role for the Military?</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the night of August 6th, and for three further nights, a small minority took to the streets in some of our urban centres looting, vandalising, burning, terrorising the law abiding majority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think everyone was taken by surprise by the manner in which the violence spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed as if copy cat opportunism fuelled by digital communications had resulted in mobs gathering in places tens, sometimes hundreds, of miles apart, but bent on the same criminal end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, the police adjusted their tactics and order was reasserted - but not before the cry went up from some quarters to put the Army on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared the feelings of frustration and disgust that must have been behind such calls. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also believe that in situations of such gravity there is merit in keeping all options available to you on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides decisions makers with the ability to escalate response if necessary - which in itself can have a deterrent effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the suggestion was not necessarily unhelpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Prime Minister told the House of Commons, the Acting Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police said he would have all his management team out on the streets before he asked for the Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much that Defence can do to help facilitate the work of the police and other authorities - providing niche capabilities or aiding capacity - even freeing up police in certain circumstances to enable more to take to the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But putting military forces on the streets themselves in a public order role should only happen as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to set out why that is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to set out how much our Armed Forces do, often unseen, often unsung, to defend the homeland and to make sure that, whenever they are needed, they can mobilise to save lives, protect people and safeguard our way of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-last-resort"&gt;THE LAST RESORT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this let me set out a little of the historical background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the formation across Europe of standing armies in the 17th century, and the advent of modern police forces in the 19th, the maintenance of order remained a primary role of national armed forces, whether regular or militia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, the regional footprint of the Army meant that when the local judiciary read the Riot Act, it was often the local regiment that responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy too operated in a law enforcement role against smugglers and pirates in much the same way as they operated against the navies of other states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the dangers of using the same organisation for national law enforcement as that trained and used for fighting wars against foreign armies were clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Peterloo Massacre of 1819 is an infamous example of why this system was wholly inappropriate for a country embracing modern liberal democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a body of men on horseback trained in the cavalry charge and the use of lethal force against foreign infantry, came face to face with the confusion, chaos and provocation of a domestic mob bent on venting anger, inevitably mistakes would be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those mistakes would likely be fatal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Richard Haldane, the reforming Secretary of War put it in 1908 “We want the Army to be a popular institution and not a menace to civil liberty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only when, during the General Strike of 1926, the Police proved themselves capable of maintaining order without assistance that the role of the Armed Forces in public order became that of last resort - the last defence against insurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, outside of Northern Ireland, the Armed Forces have not been used in the United Kingdom in a civil order role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-wrong-signal"&gt;THE WRONG SIGNAL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same reasons that led Haldane to resist the use of the military in law enforcement remain true today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who are trained in the use of lethal force - trained for battle, trained to impose their will by force on an enemy, trained for the express use of defending the territory and citizens of the country against external threats - they should not be regularly used as an instrument of force against the citizens of that same country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries continue to maintain gendarmerie type forces specifically to deal with major riots or insurrection often under the command of interior ministries rather than defence ministries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But crucially these gendarmeries - like our own riot police - are trained to deal with the circumstances they are likely to face -  mobs of civilians, maybe even lightly armed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are also - like our own riot police - fully aware of the legal underpinning of what they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not what our Armed Forces are trained for, not what they joined to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They would of course have done what was asked, and they would have acted professionally and with self-discipline - but it would not have been fair to ask them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the recent history in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that we need to prepare carefully for deliberate operations with thorough pre-deployment training, including an understanding of the social and legal context and very robust rules of engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would not have been the case if we had rushed the Army onto the streets to deal with rioters this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both the Home Secretary and the Prime Minister have pointed out, policing in this country is traditionally undertaken by consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces are built on an entirely different premise -  they exist to defend the people of this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen Armies set against citizens this year - in Libya -  in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So think about the signal that putting the Army on the street sends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means one of two things has happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either the police have been so overwhelmed by endemic disorder or factional unrest that emergency measures are required to protect people - in other words - a social collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the Government has lost its legitimacy, lost its popular support, lost its right to rule and rebellion even revolution is on the cards - in other words - a political collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither of these were the case in the riots this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t social protest, it wasn’t revolution, it was criminality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society and a government we have to learn the right lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security services too need to be sure they are better prepared for a new type of mob mentality enabled by digital communications that need not be geographically isolated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Government has to maintain both a sense of proportion and a sense of propriety when responding to situations like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In circumstances where the Police maintained the capacity to respond, putting the Army on the streets would have been wrong and an over-reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may well have been satisfying for some but it wouldn’t have been satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my second theme today - when the scale or nature of the problem is sufficient to require extraordinary military intervention on home territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standing tasks of Britain Armed Forces include a number of operations that could be described as homeland defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include the protection of our air space, the control of our national waters and the protection of our interests in nearby international waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the safety and security of citizens in the UK is primarily the responsibility of the Home Office, with the police the lead agency in most instances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is the correct role for the military in safeguarding the safety of citizens on home territory?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When should the Armed Forces provide, to use its technical term, Military Aid to the Civil Authority?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="military-aid-to-the-civil-authorities"&gt;MILITARY AID TO THE CIVIL AUTHORITIES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer falls into two broad categories - capability and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you will remember the harrowing scenes following the 2001 Foot and Mouth outbreak when the military took responsibility for command and control and many of the other tasks fell to them too - including disposal of animal carcasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country was not as prepared as it could have been to meet large scale events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Civil Contingencies Act 2004 placed a duty on a number of national, regional and local agencies to plan and prepare for all manner of emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the resilience model in which an incident is dealt with at the lowest level possible, building on tried and tested local multi-agency working arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Act, no statutory duty is placed on the MOD or the Armed Forces and, with a few exceptions, military personnel and other assets are not held at high readiness to provide support to the civil authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Armed Force are one of the only organisations in Britain that can provide, even at short notice, sufficient numbers of disciplined, organised and motivated personnel to carry out essential tasks, however distasteful, to save lives, to ensure the continuity of supplies and services, and to provide support when the civil authorities are stretched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear - the Armed Forces do not seek, and do not expect, to fill gaps that can and should more appropriately be filled by other government agencies or through the use of commercial operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces need to concentrate on core defence tasks -to plan for them, train for them, and generate forces against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the positive effects of the Civil Contingencies Act is that it is no longer the default reaction among emergency planners to consider the Armed Forces an easy way out of difficult situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are not cheap labour or simple brute strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are highly trained men and women - highly capable and highly expensive to mobilise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider search and rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy and Royal Air Force helicopters, aircraft and Mountain Rescue teams were called out over 1,900 times last year to respond to civilian incidents - an average of 5 times a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Military search and rescues teams do an amazing job in partnership with the Coast Guard and other agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we share this vital task at the moment is historic legacy and the lack of civilian capability to fill the role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is no intrinsic reason why search and rescue in the UK should be a defence task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why it is imperative that the principles behind Military Aid to the Civil Authorities are well understood by planners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capability-and-capacity"&gt;CAPABILITY AND CAPACITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Military posses specialised skills and equipment that are sometimes required in an emergency situation that it would be unreasonable or prohibitively expensive for them to be developed elsewhere in Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where these are required, particularly at short notice, it makes sense for the Armed Forces to provide them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be anything from expertise and specialised equipment to help in the search for missing people to engineering skills in an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 2009 floods in Cumbria, for example, when bridges over the Derwent were destroyed, 200 Army specialists, including from the Reserves, built what became known as ‘Barker’s Crossing’ to link the two halves of Workington that had been cut in two. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to specialist security capabilities, for obvious reasons I don’t want to go into specific details, but of course the Armed Forces are prepared to assist where necessary including in a counter-terror role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can say specifically that the Ministry of Defence provides the Bomb Disposal capability for the country outside London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this, the Armed Forces respond on average to about 7 call outs a day, although the majority are false alarms, hoaxes or remnant munitions from the 2nd World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces have the capacity to augment any emergency response, drawing on people and resources available at the time, if the scale or duration of any emergency threatens to overwhelm civil capabilities - particularly where the need is urgent and lives are in danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes responding to natural disasters or emergency situations created by extreme weather. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last December during the blizzards across the country to Armed Forces assisted in clearing snow so that help could be brought to vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All told, in 2010/11, the Ministry of Defence provided operational support to civil authorities on 75 different occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year for instance, the MOD undertook extensive planning and training for the provision of emergency support to the Ministry of Justice in the event of a Prison Officers strike -  not I hasten to add - to do the jobs of prison officers - but to help ensure that both prisons and prisoners remained safe and secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years servicemen and women have been used by Government to maintain essential services and supplies in the event of disruption, usually, but not always, as a result of an industrial dispute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the Fire Brigade strikes in 2002 when the Green Goddesses took to the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this I agree with Winston Churchill when he said in 1919 that “To use soldiers and sailors, kept up at the expense of the taxpayer, to take sides with the employer in an ordinary trade dispute…..would be a monstrous invasion of the liberty of the subject”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But” he added, “the case is different where vital services affecting the health, life or safety of large cities or great concentrations of people are concerned.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this caveat, alongside the principles of capacity and capability, which underpins our modern approach to the use of the Armed Forces at times of industrial dispute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, most operations under Military Aid to the Civil Power contain a requirement for both capacity and capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the Olympics in 2012 for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be one of the largest international events to take place in this country for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security challenge is significant and competitors and spectators alike will want to be sure confident of their safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world will be watching, our friends as well as our enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of other countries is that military assistance is required in a number of roles - including, but not restricted to, securing air space, maritime security, and contingency for rapid response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is no surprise that the Ministry of Defence is involved in the formation and execution of cross-Government plans for the Olympics and that the Armed Forces will be playing their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect to be in a position to set out details shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;THE FUTURE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I confident that, as a whole, we have the got the role of the Armed Forces in civil contingencies system right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should there be a more formalised role for the Armed Forces in UK resilience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am certainly confident in the capacity, professionalism and commitment of our Armed Forces to tackle any task thrown at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statutory duties set out under the Civil Contingencies Act continue to provide a sound foundation, but to believe that a system is perfect and cannot be improved is simple complacency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the cross-government approach undertaken by the National Security Council is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, as recommended by the Independent Review of the UK Reserve Forces, we are looking at how a greater contribution to UK resilience can be achieved by our Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, in this discussion we should not lose sight of the primary role of our Armed Forces - to maintain the capability to apply lethal force against those who would threaten the citizens of our nation and the interests of our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This primary role is correctly outward looking - just as that of the Home Office is inward looking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this inter-connected, inter-dependent world threats that originate in one part of the world can swiftly impact here at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to project power and protect our interests, often at distance, must be the driver for defence capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in August, when the crisis on the streets of Britain was the focus of our media, it was the streets of Nad-e-Ali and the skies over Tripoli that were correctly the focus of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These brave men and women truly represent Britain at its best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18719</id>
    <published>2011-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-07-05-cyber-security-an-all-of-society-approach"/>
    <title>2011/07/05 - Cyber Security: An all of Society Approach</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Careless Talk Cost Lives” - that was the mantra during the Second World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the nation’s war effort was a whole of society endeavour, this iconic information campaign sought to change people’s behaviour - to get them to think carefully about the information they possessed, and where and with whom they shared it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month the Ministry of Defence launched a new campaign to remind Armed Forces personnel, their families and friends about keeping a close hold on information - not just relating to work, but to personal lives too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 21st century this is not just about trying to change the behaviour of people having a conversation on the bus or in the pub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warning is this: You don’t know who could be watching you in cyber space so think before you tweet, blog, update, tag, comment, upload, text or share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information you put on the net can potentially be seen by anybody, at any time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this digital age, changing people’s behaviour online - wherever they happen to log on - is key to the pursuit of our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I don’t want to restrict myself to simply talking in my capacity as a Minister in the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I want to set the scene for this conference by talking about how this pursuit of national security needs to be a whole of society effort - not just a few academics who study these matters, not just a few departments in government, or a few parts of industry - but all of government, all of industry - and indeed the common sense application of cyber security at home too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about the need to redefine what we mean by the critical infrastructure of the nation and rethink how we protect it in the digital age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very nature of cyber space expands what we need to protect, deepens the need for partnership and broadens the pool of those who need to co-operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just dwell for a minute on the nature of the threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-anatomy-of-cyber-threats"&gt;THE ANATOMY OF CYBER THREATS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet and digital technology have an incredible capacity to increase the freedom and opportunity available to our citizens - to enhance people’s ability to control their own lives, make their own choices and expand their horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In government and business, it is leading to revolutionary ways of delivering services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report from McKinsey suggests that small and medium sized businesses who invest heavily in new web technologies grow and export twice as much as those who don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In countries with mature cyber societies, it is estimated that online businesses create more than 2 jobs for every traditional job lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for me, there is no question of the overall benefits to Britain of continuing to pursue these digitals models in government, business and more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But cyber space is a distinctly human environment - shaped by people - and abused by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaped by people because the human desire for information and access is driving the technology - not necessarily the desire for security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abused by people because cyber crime, cyber espionage, cyber terrorism, cyber vandalism - even the use of cyber in warfare - are all just human pursuits - simply crime, espionage, terrorism, vandalism and conflict by another means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference is the method - not the outcome or the intent -stealing money is stealing money regardless of whether it is done by pick-pocketing or hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I do not agree with those who say we need a massive raft of new criminal offences relating to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we do need is to become smarter in preventing, detecting and prosecuting the use of cyber space for criminal ends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we are investing in capabilities that enable law enforcement agencies to combat criminal activity in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear about what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t about acting like a ‘Big Cyber Brother’ - it isn’t about curtailing the joyously irreverent bottom up nature of cyber space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about catching and prosecuting real world criminals who are using the internet - paedophiles, fraudsters, thieves - and protecting the system which people now rely on against those who want to crash it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cyber-hygiene"&gt;CYBER HYGIENE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great deal of the current threat can be dealt with through the application of what I’d call basic ‘cyber hygiene’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the commonsense application of security measures that are simple to follow and easy to implement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your anti-virus software up to date &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regularly scan your computer for viruses &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t post sensitive personal information on open sites &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t open email attachments from senders you don’t recognise &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t download files you are unsure of&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cyber hygiene needs to be applied both at home and at work because what cyber space is doing is breaking down the barriers between someone’s job and their personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a member of the Armed Forces gossiping on MSN, posting on Facebook, or tweeting for the benefit of their family and friends needs to be aware that, because of their job, others may well be tuning in - opponents, adversaries, terrorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attack on your computer at home may well be designed to hack into your personal finances, but equally you might have been targeted because of what you do for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attacks known as ‘spear-phishing’ are on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criminals use personal information gathered on their targets - perhaps from social networking sites - to encourage victims to open an email attachment which allow the attackers to infect their computers with malicious software or viruses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victims of attacks like these may end up having their computers hijacked to take part in serious Denial of Service Attacks on government or business systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is often difficult to distinguish both the intent of the threat and against whom it is targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A potential adversary will go for the weakest link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD’s own networks are under daily attack as are networks across government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 2009 and 2010, cyber related security incidents more than doubled at the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD’s new Global Operations and Security Control Centre provides a state of the art facility in which we are able to bring together all the essential capabilities required to protect our own Defence systems, but we know we will need to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must accept that the security measures we are expected to adhere to at work apply equally, and just as importantly, at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the thrust behind the new campaign in my own department -changing behaviours, changing mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using the advice provided through government and industry initiatives to raise awareness of internet security, such as ‘Get Safe Online’, people can learn basic cyber hygiene. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needs to become second nature - just like ‘Careless Talk Costs Lives’ became, just like ‘Clunk-Click Every Trip’ encouraged the wearing of seatbelts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the 21st century and in cyber space, the responsibility for such education campaigns cannot lie with government alone -  ultimately it will be internet service providers, on-line retailers, businesses and everyone else with a stake in the integrity of the system who need to get the message across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="critical-national-infrastructure"&gt;CRITICAL NATIONAL INFRASTRUCTURE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these are sophisticated and evolving threats that cyber hygiene will inhibit, but not stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this does not absolve those of us with responsibility for national security from tackling the high-end threat or ensuring resilience and security in our critical national infrastructure (CNI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally when we talk of our CNI we are referring to the utility network, transport systems and the energy grids that power the country and keep us going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting this has been about physical sites and physical assets around the country - power stations, reservoirs, distribution centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the context has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think differently about what it is essential to protect and how we do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital networks which sustain our critical national infrastructure should be considered part of that infrastructure itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networked telecommunications underpin the UK business and banking system, they underpin the process of government, they underpin public access to everyday services and they underpin our security posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we have to be smart about what we are setting out to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t about ensuring that Lily Allen can tweet whenever she likes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is about making sure our emergency services can effectively respond to a serious disaster situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about making sure we consider the importance of digital networks to the financial system the country relies on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about making sure there is resilience in the digital networks that allow day to day governance to continue, in Westminster and across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way cyber security is a vital part of the protection of our critical national infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to security in the physical world and in cyber space needs to be seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Security Strategy has made a start in this process elevating cyber attack into the top rank of threats to national security and creating the new National Cyber Security Programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for the Cabinet Office, Francis Maude has responsibility for co-ordinating the programme across government and with business and academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has created the Defence Cyber Operations Group to ensure that our own departmental work is linked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new National Cyber Security Strategy currently being developed will take forward this comprehensive, cross-government approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its key themes - economic prosperity, increased national security and the protection and promotion of our way of life - embrace the kind of expanded concept that I outlined earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be careful we don’t overextend ourselves or lose focus on what is essential to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must do so with a new mindset, not just concentrating on protecting concrete and steel, but encompassing cyber space too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-together-at-home-and-abroad"&gt;WORKING TOGETHER AT HOME AND ABROAD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for the Protection of National Infrastructure is helping the Government and industry partners work together on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting critical national infrastructure, indeed national security as a whole, has always required partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many decades, much of what we have defined as critical has been in private ownership - such as the railways or the energy grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with certain business sectors has long been natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public too recognise their responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the current threat from terrorism which we face - reporting abandoned bags or being more alert to suspicious behaviour is, sadly, now part of every responsible commuter’s routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because the cyber challenge has further blurred security boundaries, it means we have to break out of our silos, break down barriers and break new ground in the creation of a new security partnership between government, business, academia and private citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent high profile cyber attacks on Google, Lockheed Martin, the IMF, Sega and Sony have shown that we cannot rely on one sector to take up the security slack for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that all parts of government when placing public contracts will increasingly take account of how seriously suppliers take cyber security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a wide range of capabilities across the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas such as defence, telecoms and banking have been in general more aware of the threats from cyber crime and have developed their own expertise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do not believe that a complete picture exists, either in Government or in the private sector, of both the threats and the capabilities available to tackle them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to improving national cyber security will be to get organisations properly sharing information on common threats so that combined responses can be made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the theme of the meeting that the Prime Minister held in February with a cross section of Chief Executive Officers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful this project must cover as many sectors of the UK economy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that a number of companies represented here today are deeply involved in this process and are determined to make it work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government will help support this initiative, but to be successful it must be industry-led, so thank you for your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even this national partnership I have talked about today -  between government, industry, academia and private citizens - will be insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National borders in cyberspace are virtually non-existent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a national Maginot line will not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as with the physical original - a way around it will be found. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot guarantee our national security in cyber space without international action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think and act internationally because cyber space is international space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of work being done bi-laterally and multilaterally to develop common understanding and common positions with other countries and international organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the importance of cyber has been reflected in recent discussions we have had with the US, Australia and France amongst others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department has been working closely with allies to develop enhanced Cyber relationships and there will be important announcements in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has also now ratified the Budapest Convention on Cyber Crime which is a good example of a multilateral organisation making a real contribution in the way in which we can work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all this work needs to be guided by discussion of how states should act in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international cyber conference which the Foreign Secretary announced the UK will host later this year will be an important first step in beginning the process of establishing principles that all nations should adhere to in cyberspace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion ladies and gentlemen, the cyber challenge is genuinely everyone’s problem. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect our national security and our critical national infrastructure we need to think differently and act differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a new whole of society endeavour:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application of basic cyber hygiene by all citizens both at home and at work. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new national partnership between government and industry to protect our critical national infrastructure which needs to be more widely defined in the digital age &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broad engagement with allies and friends abroad to establish the principles of international action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The digital age should be seen as an opportunity for Britain - an opportunity to lead in the development of new technology - to lead in developing systems that both empower and protect - to show how we can be both connected and safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me finish with one final thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1860, the Pony Express fast mail system was set up in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It revolutionised cross-continental communication - reducing time it took messages to travel from the Atlantic to the Pacific to about 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pony Express has since been mythologised in print and film - the bravery of the riders, the romance of the Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you know how long this iconic system actually lasted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 months - 18 months before the ponies were replaced by the telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is this - technology moves quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how we protect ourselves today - we cannot stop thinking about how we protect ourselves tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of cloud computing where there is an app for every occasion - where we can’t always predict what the next big thing will be - we will need to be adaptable, flexible and fast off the mark to protect national security &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to be open to new opportunities, but ever aware of the dangers we will continue to face.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18715</id>
    <published>2011-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-06-25-armed-forces-day--2"/>
    <title>2011/06/25 - Armed Forces Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s an honour to be here in Plymouth to celebrate Armed Forces Day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With members of our Armed Forces who represent the very best that this country stands for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With their friends and family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with veterans whose service we will never forget and always honour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the day when the rest of us can show our patriotic support for all these heroes, and their outstanding contribution to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because in this country, the respect we have for our Armed Forces is deeply embedded in our national make-up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Devon MP with long-standing ties to Defence, I’ve been privileged to witness the professionalism and courage of our Armed Forces at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there are few families who are not touched in some way by our Armed Forces - even simply by taking pride in the work they do to defend us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what all of us recognise - and what links the generations - is that those who serve stand for honour and sacrifice; they put themselves after others; their country before self. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plymouth has a proud military and maritime tradition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Drake to the Civil War; from the ‘Glorious Revolution’ through two World Wars, the sons and daughters of Plymouth have been at the heart of our nation’s history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Plymouth men and women are serving on the front-line once more - in operational theatres worldwide, often in difficult and dangerous conditions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Marines from Headquarters 3 Commando Brigade and 42 Commando are in Afghanistan in force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So too are their colleagues from 30 Commando Information Exploitation Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Gunners from 29 Commando Regiment Royal Artillery are providing their usual formidable support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So behind the flags, parades, and other events up and down the country to mark Armed Forces Day, we should remember that, as we speak, in this country and overseas, these brave people are putting their lives on the line - on the ground, in the air, and on the oceans - to keep us safe and to build a better world for our children. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also remember that each one of our soldiers, sailors, and airmen is also a wife or a husband; a father; a mother; a son or a daughter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do not choose this vocation for an easy life, and the pressure on their families is considerable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to thank all those who support their loved ones in the Armed Forces - through good times and bad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget that 15% of today’s Armed Forces are Reservists who, time after time, have come to Britain’s aid by supporting the Regulars, and remain integral to the future of Britain’s Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor should we forget the Cadets, or the adult volunteers who can show them the virtue of commitment and the rewards of success as our youngsters prepare for life as responsible citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, those serving in our Armed Forces will one day move into the larger family of veterans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Day is a celebration of our veterans’ community too, whatever their age.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means everyone from the 20 and 30 year-olds who have returned from operations in Afghanistan in their prime of life and are seeking new challenges on civvy street, to the older veterans who are part of our nation’s living history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They all have so much to offer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are a constant reminder to younger generations that preserving our way of life and the things we hold most dear is sometimes hard won, and never guaranteed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I mentioned Plymouth’s proud military tradition earlier. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warmth and hospitality the city has shown our Armed Forces, our veterans, cadets, and their families over the years, has been outstanding, and truly demonstrates the historic link between the military, the city, and the nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am delighted to announce that the City of Plymouth will host the fourth Armed Forces Day national event on Saturday 30 June 2012!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Day is coming home, and it’s richly deserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no doubt that - with its superb maritime location and historic ties; and with full support from local authorities, the local veterans’ community, serving military personnel, and you the public - Plymouth will put on a tremendous show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish you every success in hosting the 2012 national event.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, one of the marks of any civilised nation is the way it supports and respects those who fight for their country, and their families. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are an integral part of who we are as a nation, and an inspiration to us all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us honour that commitment by showing our support in Plymouth today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18708</id>
    <published>2011-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-03-31-natural-partners-necessary-partners-uk-france-defence-co-operation--2"/>
    <title>2011/03/31 - Natural Partners, Necessary Partners, UK-France Defence Co-operation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for giving me the opportunity to speak here today at the first annual defence co-operation conference organised by the Franco-British Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I speak, as part of a broad and growing coalition which includes Arab countries, British and French forces are operating to enforce UN Security Council resolution 1973.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both our countries agree that the action in Libya is necessary and right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we chose not to stand aside as the Gaddafi regime brutalised its own people and threatened to return Libya to the status of a pariah state on Europe’s southern borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took clear and decisive action to avert a humanitarian disaster in Benghazi and protect the people of Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working together we can help realise the legitimate demands of the Libyan people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often in the past we have allowed the small differences between us to preclude action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these past two weeks, although the path has not always been easy, France and the UK have provided leadership at the UN, in the EU and in NATO, with our friends and allies, to bring a wide coalition together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is testament to the determination of both our governments to act in concert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to security and defence in this globalised world, the real interests of our citizens are not in competition, but in partnership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about why the Franco-British partnership is important to the national interests of both countries, and how this partnership supports rather than replaces or undermines the multi-lateral organisations to which we both belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-new-era-of-partnership"&gt;A NEW ERA OF PARTNERSHIP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new era of partnership is needed for three distinct reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - in this globalised, volatile world the diverse and evolving risks to national security, are risks shared in common with our neighbours, our allies in Europe and further afield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a shared exposure to strategic risk and therefore a convergence of strategic interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - no country can hope to resolve threats to national security and international stability acting in isolation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture is too complex and the potential threats too widespread for unilateral action on all fronts to be effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting with partners provides the legitimacy, reach and resources that unilateral action cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - maintaining a strong military is becoming more expensive and budgets are under growing pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, we have had to make difficult decisions, not only to contribute to national deficit reduction which is the Government’s priority, but also to deal with the legacy of over commitment in our Defence budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries across Europe and indeed across the Atlantic, are seeking greater efficiency in defence budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships can help provide economies of scale through collaboration or burden sharing where appropriate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against these criteria, the Prime Minister and President Sarkozy’s initiative for enhanced UK/France bilateral defence and security co-operation is a responsible and necessary course of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ukfrance-defence-co-operation"&gt;UK/FRANCE DEFENCE CO-OPERATION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, each country has unique national interests but we share significant strategic interests in this new era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are near neighbours with similar sized economies linked through the single-market and through thousands of years of exchange of people, goods and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and France are parliamentary democracies with outward looking cultures, engaged in world affairs as permanent members of the UN Security Council, and both as leading members of the EU, NATO, the G8 and G20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are of course nuclear powers with similar sized high-tech militaries and with the capability and, perhaps importantly, the willingness to project power to meet our global responsibilities towards international peace and security as well to our own national security when threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we account for half of all spending on Defence in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new era, a closer Franco-British partnership is as natural as it is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are not starting from square one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusions of both the French Livre Blanc and the UK’s National Security Strategy and SDSR are strikingly similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are able to build on a solid base of bilateral co-operation forged over many years and enhanced recently by our operations in Afghanistan and elsewhere, including now in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been made easier by the UK’s recognition that the European Union has a role to play in the field of security and defence and by French reintegration into NATO’s Command Structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two treaties that Prime Minister Cameron and President Sarkozy signed in November set out a comprehensive programme of defence and security co-operation to be taken forward over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These treaties mark a step change in our partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nuclear-co-operation"&gt;NUCLEAR CO-OPERATION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to spell out the details of these treaties to this audience, so let me dwell, today, on one aspect that goes to the heart of the step change - nuclear co-operation under the Teutates project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will know, the two parties in the UK coalition Government have a different approach to the renewal of the current Trident system, but we are jointly pledged to maintain Britain’s nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsible stewardship of our existing nuclear weapons stockpile is vital work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this new and groundbreaking arrangement, the UK and France will share facilities to maintain the safety of our independent nuclear deterrents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of building duplicate national facilities, we have agreed jointly to construct and operate a new Hydrodynamics Facility at Valduc in France and a new Technology Development Centre at Aldermaston in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have moved quickly on this work - the facilities will be operational by 2015, with the first UK experiment time-tabled for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combining our scientific and engineering talent and in sharing expensive equipment, we can sustain the expertise and capabilities required as responsible nuclear powers and potentially save considerable sums of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will enable us to maintain the safety of our existing nuclear stockpile without breaching the conditions of the international treaties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me stress that this does not threaten the independence of each country’s operational nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This co-operation does not involve the sharing of any nuclear deterrent capability such as submarine patrols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it does mark a willingness to co-operate in depth in an area that has traditionally been taboo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Liberal Democrat Minister in this UK Coalition Government, I have the freedom to explore and argue the case for an alternative successor to the planned replacement of Trident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not Government policy, but I and my party colleagues would certainly be willing to explore the options for the UK and France to plan our successor programmes in closer co-ordination including, in the longer-term, the case for deeper co-operation on operational nuclear deterrence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="multi-layered-security"&gt;MULTI-LAYERED SECURITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has of course a extraordinarily close relationship with the United States on this and other defence matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This enhanced partnership with France does not diminish the close bilateral relationships we have with other partners in Europe and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-UK Mutual Defence Agreement is unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our close defence co-operation with other allies, for example the UK-Netherlands Amphibious Force, is unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the commitment of both France and Britain to the United Nations, to NATO and to the EU is undiminished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we need multilayered security so that we can respond using the right means for the right occasion - through multilateral organisations wherever possible - but also through coalitions, through bilateral relationships - and of course we must reserve the right to act unilaterally where required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me set out why we have chosen at this time to drive Franco-British defence co-operation through a bilateral relationship, in a way that is complimentary to NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alain Juppe said recently, NATO is “currently the only credible military alliance in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been the bedrock of our collective security for over 60 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is inevitable in the years to come that a significant proportion of US attention will be turned towards the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we are to retain the vitality of NATO, Europeans must up their game when it comes to the military capability that they are able to deploy and the political willingness to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will have the joint effect of continuing US willingness to invest in NATO, and provide independent means to act, including through the EU, should NATO choose not to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU has made progress in developing the institutional arrangements that increase its ability to react to an international crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the twelve years since Saint-Malo has seen disappointing progress in generating the kind of deployable forces that we will collectively need in the future if Europe is to match its economic role in world affairs, with influence on defence and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drive to improve European capability through NATO has been similarly slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 5 of the 28 NATO member states, 2 of those 5 being France and Britain, meet the NATO criteria of 2% of GDP being spent on defence spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I am proud of the UK Coalition Government’s efforts to meet it’s international responsibilities when it comes to the UN target on aid, so I am determined that we continue to meet our responsibilities to NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When national budgets across Europe are being squeezed, our taxpayers rightly expect the money we spend on defence and security to achieve real effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have the luxury of unlimited political energy or finances to indulge in duplication or institutional empire building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to prioritise to achieve better interoperability, capability and efficiency to ensure that we get more benefit out of our limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and France have similar levels of investment, similar levels of capability and a similar willingness to deploy that is not matched, at present, by most other European partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are not alone in Europe in seeking new building blocks to strengthen our Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nordic Grouping’s co-operation through NORDEFCO shares the ambition to grow capability and spend money more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrinsically, defence co-operation agreements among members of NATO or the EU have the prospect of improving the military capabilities available to both those organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the UK-France partnership can provide a roadmap for others to strengthen their capability by working with each other in similar ways it will be to the benefit of both NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may even kick-start the growth of greater military capability and co-operation in Europe in a way that St Malo and subsequent initiatives have yet to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drive of Britain and France to strengthen bilateral defence co-operation need not be exclusive in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should not, and does not, stop us working with others who are ready to invest in the same kind of deployable capability that the UK and France possess - but let me stress that willingness to deploy is the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is this - those who spend the money control the process and those who have the political will take the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we move forward in this way we may see the emergence of a core of European countries acting in concert with the will and the way to drive the process of capability improvement and efficiency in European Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally am relaxed about whether this happens through coalitions of the willing or through enhanced co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read with interest a recent report by Ben Jones published through the EUISS on Franco-British defence co-operation, and I agree with much of his analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I disagree with the conclusion that the relationship between the new UK/France Treaties and the EU’s CSDP is ‘enigmatic’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not - we have been clear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not St Malo 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bilateral agreement between the sovereign nations of Britain and France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I am a Liberal Democrat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pro-European, and I support Defence co-operation through the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not share the ideological aversion that some of my Conservative colleagues in Parliament have when it comes to CSDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I am a pragmatist and a realist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in what works and what is shown to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For pro-Europeans this new partnership with France is win-win, win-win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Win for the tax payers of both Britain and France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Win for the military capabilities of our respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Win for the capabilities available to NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And win for the capabilities available to the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way bilateral co-operation must surely enhance multilateral co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion Ladies and Gentlemen, we live in a world in which isolation is neither splendid, nor optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have no choice but to look outward, and to look to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To adapt Antoine de Saint-Exupery: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amitie, ce n’est pas se regarder l’un a l’autre, c’est regarder ensemble dans la meme direction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Sarkozy and Prime Minister Cameron have been leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will need to embed cultural and behavioural change in the defence and security apparatus of both countries, because reticence, and dare I say suspicion, still sometimes remains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This requires leadership from the top, clear direction through the chain of command, and above all familiarity through joint working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is said in the Ministry of Defence that ‘everyone has a friend in Washington’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move to a position where everyone has un amis in Paris too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the national interests of both Britain and France demand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because the benefits of our partnership will be felt in NATO and Europe too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18698</id>
    <published>2011-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-01-10-transforming-defence--2"/>
    <title>2011/01/10 - Transforming Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, this year will be special for the Royal United Services Institute as it celebrates the 180th anniversary of its establishment by the Duke of Wellington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take this opportunity to thank the Institute for the positive role it has played over many decades - but particularly over the last year, helping to prepare the ground for the Defence review we all knew was coming - and indeed we all knew was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Duke of Wellington famously said that “all the business of war, and indeed all the business of life, is to endeavour to find out what you don’t know by what you do” - what Wellington called “guessing what was at the other side of the hill.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Security Strategy and the Strategic Defence and Security Review could certainly be said to have been such an exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-defence---setting-the-blueprint"&gt;Transforming defence - setting the blueprint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did we need to ensure, that in every decision we made, success of the mission in Afghanistan was given priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, also after 12 years without a full scale defence review, we needed to look ahead - to the other side of the hill - and lay out a blueprint for the transformation of Defence so that our Armed Forces, and all who provide them with support, are fit and structured to face the challenges of the decades ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis in the National Security Strategy points to a world in which the threats to the United Kingdom are diverse and unpredictable and the character of conflict evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Adaptable Posture set out in the SDSR, rather than the alternatives we considered, was chosen as the best strategic response to the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task ahead of us to 2015 and beyond is driving the transformation of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a once in a generation opportunity, not only on the back of SDSR, but also through the root and branch reform of the entire Ministry of Defence led by the Defence Reform Unit under Lord Levene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your conference calls this the ‘unfinished business’ of the SDSR - so let me be clear for one moment about the finished business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Security Strategy and the SDSR provide the baseline, the parameters, the direction for everything in Defence from this point on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy, operations, force structure, resource - all are framed by the vision set out in SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR is the agreed blueprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do need to take our time to work through the decisions required to implement the vision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are not straightforward and they are not easy - the devil, as they say, is in the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure the growth of capability is coherent and compatible with current operations - to make sure that where we reduce we do so without creating undue pressure elsewhere - and where we strengthen capability we do so with new efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that our people are looked after through the process and that they understand what it is we are asking them to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a political challenge as well as an organisational challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the implementation decisions, such as on the future of the Reserves, will impact on much cherished institutions with powerful and persuasive supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others, such as on basing, could impact on communities across the UK whose representatives will continue to fight hard for them, inside and outside Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course we face the challenge of reducing numbers across all three forces and the civil service in a manner which honours the committed service of those who will be leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coalition Government has already proven that it has the courage to make the unpalatable decisions that were ducked for so many years by our predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must now show that we have the courage to see it through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do not - we will fail to create the balanced Armed Forces the country will need for the future and the cost-effective support structure that taxpayers demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be clear about the challenge ahead in the next few years, particularly that challenge of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-defence---the-challenge-of-resources"&gt;Transforming defence - the challenge of resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition Government is acting to reduce the huge fiscal deficit that we inherited from Labour - it will be hard, but it is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in Defence cannot pretend that deficit reduction is somebody else’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a strategic objective for the Government, and Defence must make a contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic stability and growth must come first, because this underpins everything that Government can hope to achieve for the people it serves - including defending them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any country that does not keep its economy under control will find it near impossible to preserve its national security in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same difficult decisions are being made by many of our allies - including the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron and Nick Clegg have both made clear recently - this year will be a difficult year - as the tough decisions we have taken in the Budget and the Comprehensive Spending Review become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a Liberal Democrat - and I am determined that this coalition Government is a reforming Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have opportunity in adversity to make radical change a reality - to make this country fairer, more sustainable and more secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of cutting isn’t radical in itself - being radical is the act of building something different, better and lasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that should be what the transformation of Defence is about - not just creating a coherent Defence capability for the future, but making that capability sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the rest of Government, Defence must learn to live within its means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the reform agenda is not just about the big ticket items decided taken in the SDSR, it’s about driving through new systems and processes - of accountability, transparency, cost control, realistic planning, firm and controlled project management - to bring the efficiency required to keep Defence within the funding envelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the relatively generous financial settlement the Defence budget has received compared with most other Departments, the budget has still been reduced and we have to face up to very tough circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are we fighting in Afghanistan and in the midst of the biggest fiscal crisis in a generation, but we also inherited an overheated and inflexible forward equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the 12 years since the last review, the previous Government allowed a massive unfunded liability in Defence to build up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crippling and has to be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR took some very difficult decisions to help rebalance the defence programme and has significantly reduced the underfunding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the act of implementation will require us to continue to develop and refine our plans to live within our means - because we are not there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, Future Force 2020 now provides us with a realistic aiming point, consistent with the financial envelope set for us by the Government’s challenging Comprehensive Spending Review over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I recognise that we haven’t been able to put absolutely everything right in one go but that is also why the commitment to 5 yearly Defence Reviews creates the ability to continue the transformation process .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach the next General Election, and as we prepare for the next Defence Review in 2015, the key debate will be around how we meet the financial challenges of Future Force 2020 and the vision of a Britain active on the world stage and protected at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, rather than cover the ground that the Chief of the Defence Staff did in his lecture here last month when he set out much of the strategic background to the decisions we have made, let me instead talk about how we make transforming Defence a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first it is worth setting out the vision of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-defence---the-baseline"&gt;Transforming defence - the baseline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the next few years, the mission in Afghanistan remains our Main Effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having made this commitment in the SDSR, this shaped many of our other decisions: the proposed changes to the Army, for example; and the preference for Tornado over Harrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we transform Defence we will have to ensure that the decisions we make do not have unintended consequences for operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may slow the process down as each implication is worked through - but it is the right thing to do - right for national security and right for the men and women on the ground in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the hardship and sacrifice shared with our international partners and the Afghans themselves, we are now operating from a position of strategic strength and there is cause for cautious optimism despite the significant challenges ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficult job our Forces are doing there is being done with the determination, skill and professionalism we have come to expect and so too often take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made it clear that there will not be British troops in a combat role or in the numbers they are now in Afghanistan by 2015 and depending on progress we may be able to start reducing our footprint earlier as we transition to more of a support role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in transforming Defence we need also to think beyond Operation Herrick and ensure equally that each decision we make is in line with the Adaptable Posture set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future Force 2020 isn’t a specific package for a specific operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides a menu of force elements from which we will be able to draw in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides a force structure which will enable us to react rapidly to crises, to conduct operations similar to Afghanistan, but also to respond with flexibility and agility to a range of threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have taken the difficult decisions on the equipment platforms necessary to focus of the challenges of future warfare rather than of the Cold War, such as reducing tanks and heavy artillery, and in order to begin to balance the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most painfully, we are reducing the size of the armed forces by 17,000, and the size of our civilian workforce by 25,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be difficult for the individuals concerned many of whom have served their country with great professionalism and dedication over many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as painful as this is, we know that it just has to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But SDSR was not just about cuts:  it was about change -  transforming to meet the challenges of the future with coherent and sustainable capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will now deliver carrier strike in a way that is more compatible with operations with our closest allies and with a more capable aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of the Army will be based on the more modular, more flexible, more effective, deployable Multi-Role Brigade structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Air Force will be based on fewer, more capable aircraft types, making for greater ease of maintenance and hence cost-effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the challenges ahead in achieving this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-defence---the-key-challenges"&gt;Transforming defence - the key challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the force structure changes are being implemented, including the retirement of platforms as set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other implementation issues are more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take basing for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, force structure changes mean that the RAF no longer has a use for several bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other, we will bring home our Forces from Germany progressively over the next decade with all the attendant issues that raises, including finding suitable accommodation and training areas in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take time to ensure we are making the best decisions possible, not only for the Armed Forces and our people - but taking into account the impact on the areas concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we need to maximise receipts for the tax payer from disposals of those parts of the estate we no longer need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a massively complex jigsaw which we will take some time to assemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that people want clarity as soon as possible - but I would prefer to get these things right rather than rush them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-defence---a-more-effective-department"&gt;Transforming defence - a more effective department&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is equally important that we transform how we do things as well as what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful, transformed Armed Forces require a transformed Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has taken some justifiable flak over the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In opposition, I was one of the leading critics - and, to be fair, almost everyone I have encountered in the Department has been quick to point out where things have gone wrong - and what could be done better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise how immensely complex and wide-ranging the business of Defence is - and while the MoD knows it needs to change - it is worth reflecting on the vast amount of work that the Department carries out quietly and effectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD undertakes a huge and diverse set of tasks - from military operations to estate management - from medical services to postal services - from meteorology to coastal protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it difficult to bring unified strategic direction to all parts of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has improved in the last few years, but much more needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the leadership of Lord Levene, the Defence Reform Unit, is working through how to create an MOD that is simpler, more effective better-led and, quite frankly, less wasteful of time and resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is in its scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking at the whole system, the ‘operating model’ of Defence - the internal structure and processes, the senior rank structure, and how people are to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking at how to incentivise staff so that the behaviours we want to see are encouraged - leadership, personal accountability, creative thinking and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking at how we generate and sustain forces, as well as at tour lengths and harmony guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in all of this we are working to reduce significantly the running costs of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquisition reform is a key element of this agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointment of Bernard Gray as Chief of Defence Materiel is an important step for the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a recognition of the need for radical and lasting change and the intent to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes a new relationship with industry, one that recognises our mutual interests, but one that demands value for tax-payers money as the bottom line - not just jobs and profit for shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Green Paper recently published by my ministerial colleague Peter Luff is a stepping stone to a new, no-nonsense approach to acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme to transform Defence cannot be done overnight; it will take time to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But taken all together - the force structure set out in the SDSR and the remodelling of the MOD by the Defence Reform Unit - this will be the most significant reform programme for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all of this, as the Chief of the Defence Staff said last month, what gives our Armed Forces their edge is the quality of the people who serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know the forthcoming period of transition will be difficult for many in both the Armed Forces and the civil service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will look after those leaving, preferably by voluntary release, by giving them the fairest terms and conditions we are able to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will be looking after those staying, by developing a new employment model for the Armed Forces, by reinforcing the Military Covenant and by creating an organisation that we are all proud to be part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have new leadership in the form of the new Government, a new Chief of the Defence Staff, General Richards, and the new Permanent Secretary, Ursula Brennan along with Jon Day and Bernard Gray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success will be collective - as must be the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be the energy and determination of military, civil service and indeed the wider Defence community, including yourselves, that will make the transformation in Defence happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is truly a joint endeavour and I hope today’s conference goes some way to highlighting what together we need to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18697</id>
    <published>2010-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2010-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2010-12-14-denmark-uk-defence-co-operation"/>
    <title>2010/12/14 - Denmark-UK Defence Co-operation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an old Danish proverb:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No one is rich enough to do without a neighbour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English poet John Donne put the same sentiment this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No man is an island, entire of itself.  Every man is a piece of the continent”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, in the globalised world we live in, this is true now, more than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No nation - no matter how large, no matter how powerful, no matter how rich in resources - can hope to secure its national interests acting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no nation can expect to hide from change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-together"&gt;WORKING TOGETHER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in Europe have recognised and acted on this proverbial wisdom for many decades - and for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the carnage of the Second World War, there has arisen in Europe a habit of co-operation where nations work in partnership, rather than through the kind of aggressive competition that proved so destructive in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between Denmark and Britain is amongst the strongest bilateral relationships in Europe - particularly on matters of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We train together, we fight together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closeness of our relationship is being played out on the ground in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I would like to talk about the progress we are making together in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first I want to address the wider UK-Danish partnership, because Afghanistan is not the be all and end all of our relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="northern-europe"&gt;NORTHERN EUROPE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peoples of the United Kingdom and Denmark have bonds that have endured for well over a thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share much culture, we share much blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even the best friendships need to be supported by mutual self-interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Denmark and the UK have global interests in this multi-polar world, but we cannot forget that geographically we are Northern European countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have argued that the information revolution has made geography irrelevant - and in some ways it has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course we must act in those areas, such as in cyber security, where physical space does not dominate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course we should seek to project our power beyond our neighbourhood because tackling threats at source is better than letting them come home to roost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even in this era of globalisation, the cold, hard realities of geography must remain central to defence and security planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Northern Europe it makes sense to work together to secure our own region, to keep our trade routes open, to exploit together new opportunities and to face together threats as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to deepen defence co-operation with Denmark -  recognising and respecting the sovereignty of our parliaments and the wishes of our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO will continue to be the bedrock of our collective defence, but of course we should seek opportunities to enhance our mutual security wherever we can achieve more by combining our resources. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Europe, membership of the different regional and security organisations is not uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we want to create a new and wider framework that makes it easier for both NATO and non-NATO members, EU and non-EU members to have a closer relationship in the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Northern Grouping, which had its inaugural meeting in Oslo this November, is an example of that, and we are grateful to have Denmark’s help and support in pursuing this initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As supply routes open through the Arctic, it is in our mutual interest to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it be in energy security, protecting resources or maintaining the freedom of the seas, where we identify a shared threat to the region, this Group has the potential to act as a clearing house for the capabilities which might be marshalled to address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="denmark-uk-defence-co-operation"&gt;DENMARK-UK DEFENCE CO-OPERATION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and Denmark have an excellent record on making Defence co-operation work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a common vision in NATO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very comfortable deploying together and operating together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gitte Lillelund Bech made it clear to us at the recent Northern Group meeting that over the last few decades there has been a transformation of Danish defence thinking - from defence of the motherland to being prepared to fight beyond your borders to protect Danish values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is reflected in the fact that over that period Britain and Denmark have been joined at the hip and the bonds created between our service men and women, forged on the battlefield, are the strongest possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the British Prime Minister David Cameron said in his meeting with Lars Lokke Rasmussen in August: “our troops have fought together, have suffered together and sometimes, tragically, have died together.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last 20 years this has taken place first in the Balkans, then in Iraq and now in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are also side by side fighting piracy off the Horn of Africa, under the NATO operation Ocean Shield. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a strong and active training, exercise and exchange programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We train together for Afghanistan and Denmark has air crew embedded in Joint Helicopter Command - and at the UK’s Permanent Joint Headquarters co-ordinating the Afghan mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conduct together a series of planned activity such as the annual JOINT WARRIOR exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British personnel are embedded in your Defence Ministry, Army Operations Command, and Royal Navy and Royal Air Force pilots fly your Lynx, Merlin and F16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, we want to continue to deepen the combined effectiveness of our armed forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the UK Government stands ready to assist Denmark in meeting its evolving Maritime Helicopter requirement in order to maintain the excellent interoperability between our navies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, closer collaboration with our Merlin fleets should help realise your ambition to use Merlin in the Tactical Troop Transport role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-strategic-security-and-defence-review"&gt;UK STRATEGIC SECURITY AND DEFENCE REVIEW&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, we have just completed the first review of our defence and security requirements for over a decade and we are now implementing the vision for our Future Force 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we are territorially more secure than at many times in our history, the threats we face are diverse and evolving - terrorism, cyber warfare, fragile or failed states, competition for resources, the effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This range of diverse threats is why Britain has concluded that an Adaptable Posture is required - one able to address the needs of today - such as our national security requirement to succeed in Afghanistan - yet able to be rebalanced swiftly for the threats of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means our Armed Forces will become in the future more flexible and agile, retaining global reach, and capable of providing nuclear and conventional deterrence, containment, coercion and intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we will be investing in new technology and capabilities more suited to the likely character of future conflict, such as cyber security, UAVs and Special Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also divesting ourselves of capabilities that have less utility in the post-Cold War world but with the ability to regenerate if threats change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central to this vision is an increased ability to operate interdependently with our allies in all areas of security and defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We undertook this review at a difficult time for the country as the coalition Government acts to tackle the fiscal deficit we inherited from our predecessors - so money is tight - as it is for Defence budgets across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the outcome means that we will maintain our position as a leading military power, with the 4th largest defence budget in the world and our Defence spending will remain above NATO’s minimum of 2% of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless we have had to take some tough decisions to live within our means, but this recognises the inextricable linkage between economic health and national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the process, when making these decisions, we have prioritised success in the ongoing mission in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="afghanistan"&gt;AFGHANISTAN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British and Danish Armed Forces are part of a NATO-led, 48 nation coalition acting to protect our citizens by ensuring that trans-national terrorists cannot find safe and unhindered sanctuary there as they did before 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to pay tribute to the bravery and commitment of the Danish forces operating under UK command in Helmand - and indeed to the Danish civilians working in the Provincial Reconstruction Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danish troops operate with no caveats, conducting the full spectrum of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their contribution is invaluable and greatly appreciated by the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the Battle Groups in Task Force Helmand they have played a key role in delivering the significant improvements in security we have seen in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ISAF surge now at its peak at 131,000 this corresponds with an increase in military operations, particularly in those areas where insurgent activity is still strong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this year has been particularly tough and I would like to send my condolences to the families and friends of those who have been killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thoughts are also with those who have been wounded, physically or mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a heavy price, a price being shared too by the British people and others across the coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is cause for cautious optimism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be clear about what we are seeking to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-security"&gt;NATIONAL SECURITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not seek a perfect Afghanistan, but one able to maintain its own security and prevent the return of Al-Qaeda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is primarily a mission of national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are neither colonisers nor occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are there under United Nations Security Council endorsement and at the invitation of the Afghan Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not in Afghanistan to create a carbon copy of a western democracy, and we are not there to convert the people to western ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We seek the government of Afghanistan by the Afghans for the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We insist only that it does not pose a threat to our security, our interests or those of our allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a reasonable critique to say that up to the reinvigoration of strategy and the surge of the last year, our collective ambition was not complemented by a collective willingness to commit the necessary military, political and civilian effect to achieve our aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, we should rue the lost opportunities between 2002 and 2006 to build up the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF) so that there were indigenous forces alongside ISAF strong enough to confront the gathering strength of the Taliban, particularly in the South.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a tough few years for our forces operating in Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are now operating from a position of increasing strength while the strategic position of the insurgency has begun to deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="increasing-strength"&gt;INCREASING STRENGTH&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ISAF coalition has increased its commitment to the mission, in manpower and equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan too is taking the threat seriously, and the safe havens in Pakistan are being squeezed by their Security Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insurgency has lost significant ground in the southern heartlands, including the key population centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been targeting their bomb-making networks and their leadership and command structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their network is under significant pressure, with the senior leadership isolated, training deficient, and supplies limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Security Forces are growing in competence, confidence and capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have expanded by over a third this year, in line with the targets set, and are increasingly leading operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s contribution to training and mentoring is in the top tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish Police Operational Mentor and Liaison Team is highly rated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is Denmark mentoring units from the 3rd Kandak of the Afghan National Army but they also mentor the ANA in running the Shorabak Garrison Headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increasing effectiveness of the ANSF brings closer the potential collapse of the strategic position of the insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only realistic hope for the insurgency is that international resolve will collapse before the Afghan Government itself is effective enough to stand on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message we must send as an international community is that this hope is an empty one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transition"&gt;TRANSITION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the NATO Lisbon Summit, extremely well marshalled by Anders Fogh Rasmussen, we all reaffirmed our enduring commitment to Afghanistan’s security and stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO and Afghanistan also agreed the framework of a long-term partnership that looks beyond the end of ISAF’s current mission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit set out that transition of lead responsibility for security from international to Afghan forces will begin in early 2011, with the objective of Afghans leading on security operations in all provinces by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transition to Afghan lead security responsibility will be dependent on the conditions in each district and province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some areas of Afghanistan will transition sooner than others, which will give nations the opportunity to redeploy their combat troops to areas where they are still required, or to rebalance their force contribution towards capacity building, training and mentoring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody should mistake the strategy for transition as a strategy of abandonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan will require the support of the international community, including military support for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is clear that we will no longer have troops in a combat role by 2015, but we foresee an enduring role in the country as part of a wide relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is of course for each individual nation to make their own decisions on their force contributions and the role they undertake and I recognise that each of us has unique pressures to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are democracies, it comes with the territory and it is healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But equally, while all of us want our troops home as quickly as possible, we must accept that to achieve this goal the gradual drawdown in ISAF force levels must be done in a coherent way and in line with conditions on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went in together, we should come out together - properly planned and executed as part of the combined effort we have committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, in the UK, we have the first coalition Government for many decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conservatives and Liberal Democrats are co-operating in Government, in the national interest, at this particularly testing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a Liberal Democrat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the most internationalist and pragmatically pro-European party in Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We instinctively understand the need to work together with other nations - and we embrace interdependence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new British Government will look outwards and forwards, not inwards and backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You in Denmark have many years of experience in making coalition government work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can learn from your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to issues of Foreign Affairs and Defence, a nation is more influential when it speaks with one voice abroad, based on consensus at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are lucky in the UK that there is a broad consensus on most Defence issues and all parties support the mission in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot be complacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our public, just like the public here in Denmark, want clarity about why we are in Afghanistan, what we are achieving, and what success will look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denmark and Britain are working together in one of the most difficult parts of Afghanistan to achieve our shared goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This builds on many years of close co-operation, which continues to prove its worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish physicist Niels Bohr is said to have remarked that “prediction is very difficult, especially about the future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I can go so far as to predict, as future threats emerge, and as new missions of national security present themselves, Denmark and Britain will face them together, confident in our ability to operate together, with determination to protect the interests we share, and with faith our enduring friendship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18691</id>
    <published>2010-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2010-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2010-11-09-meeting-the-cyber-challenge"/>
    <title>2010/11/09 - Meeting the Cyber Challenge</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to start by thanking Chatham House for giving me this opportunity to speak here today, and to commend Paul Cornish and his colleagues for their report launched this week “On Cyber Warfare”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It challenges us to think in different ways about our approach to cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It challenges us to bring the debate out of the technical realm and into the political.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-challenge-of-cyber-space"&gt;The Challenge of Cyber Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a liberal, I am excited about the capacity of the internet and digital technology to increase the freedom and opportunity available to our citizens - to enhance people’s ability to control their own lives and make their own choices - and to expand their horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also recognise that when it comes to cyber space, the old adage that man is wolf to his fellow man has sadly proved itself correct once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever he expands his dominance, whether it be on land, sea or air, or whether it be in cyber space, mankind carries his essential nature with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for the Armed Forces, I am concerned with how we should defend ourselves against those who would use cyber space to do harm, and how we best use the new technologies to further our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this is about protecting people’s privacy and livelihood not diminishing them - this is about protecting the freedom and opportunity cyber space brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to do that we must recognise that the threats in cyber space do not just come from malicious mischief makers or organised criminality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is it just our privacy and money that is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most societies, including Britain, have come to rely on digital networks for many of the things which allow normal life to function smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is at the heart of our transport system, our power and telecommunications, our health service and our economy as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take these technologies for granted, and we have come to depend on the services they provide every second of every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of a well planned, well executed attack against our critical networks could be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that cyber security has been identified as one of the top national security threats for the UK over the next five years indicates both the likelihood of such an attack and the level of impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without doubt, man has brought the capacity for war to cyber space too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect ourselves we need to understand how cyber space might be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must apply the same kind of logic Clausewitz applied to the conditions of his age, when looking to formulate approaches to the conditions of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Clausewitz showed, while the essential nature of conflict is unchanging, its character moves with the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like to look at the changing character of conflict and how this might manifest itself in the cyber domain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-changing-character-of-conflict"&gt;The Changing Character of Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the coalition Government’s new National Security Strategy demonstrates clearly, Britain is today both more secure and more vulnerable than in most of our long history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are more secure in the sense that we do not face, as we have so often in the past, a conventional threat of attack on our territory by a hostile power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are more globally interdependent, more networked and more reliant on digital technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are sources of economic strength - but also of vulnerability - and this reliance may be our soft underbelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who would mean us harm - be they states trying to gain an advantage - or those driven by ideology or straightforward greed - may not have the capability to challenge us using conventional military means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead they will seek to attack or undermine us in indirect ways - striking where we are most vulnerable - seeking to coerce us, to disrupt our society and do damage to infrastructure and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years we have seen civilian aircraft used as suicide bombs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen naval vessels attacked from inflatable dinghies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen the rapid evolution in the technology and tactical use of improvised explosive devices - against our armed forces in places like Afghanistan -  against our citizens on the London tube - placed on planes, driven into airports - designed to cause as much death and destruction as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is asymmetry in warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It avoids direct military confrontation; it avoids striking at strength and seeks to exploit perceived weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-asymmetrical-power-of-cyber-space"&gt;The Asymmetrical Power of Cyber Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domain of cyber space lends itself directly to this form of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give four reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there is a low threshold of entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our adversaries can exploit the same technology used by citizens going about their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That laptop that sits on the desk at home or in the office - used to do accounts, send email or catch up with television programmes - is the same instrument that could be used to launch an attack on our critical national infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the tools that would be used, the malware or viruses, are traded on the net - a black economy of rapidly growing size and sophistication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, a single networked laptop in the hands of a sophisticated and informed attacker could be as effective a weapon as, say, a cruise missile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there are no geographical barriers in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attack could be launched from any corner of the world with little warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a conventional military movement - which requires the kind of organisation, mobilisation and logistical support that is hard to hide - a cyber attack can essentially be covert until the moment it begins to do its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, attribution of both cause and effect will be difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know from the recent STUXNET worm, it can be very difficult to trace from where and by whom an attack was initiated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it may be unclear when a cyber event is taking place, what its exact purpose might be or the ultimate aims of the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth - and perhaps most insidious - with cyber it is possible to rapidly create a mass effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the cyber attacks of Georgia in 2008 - hackers can be enlisted to ideological causes, equipped with the means to carry out mass attacks - so called botnets - and given the target information to direct and synchronise attacks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than a single attack on a target - this can result in hundreds of thousands of computers worldwide being hijacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, last week Burma experienced a mass denial of service attack which effectively severed its internet connectivity with the rest of the world - just days before its first election in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that cyber is a powerful asymmetric tool for warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen how terrorists can attack symbolic rather than military targets - the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Centre being an obvious example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can only be a matter of time before terrorists begin to use cyber space more systematically, not just as a tool for their own organisation, but as a method of attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="on-cyber-warfare"&gt;On Cyber Warfare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But cyber is also a powerful tool in the hands of those traditionally able to engage in conflict - states themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Iain Lobban, the Director of GCHQ, said recently: we have seen the use of cyber techniques by one nation on another to bring diplomatic or economic pressure to bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital age has also enhanced the effectiveness of our military operations - providing secure communication networks, accurate navigation, and the ability to synchronise and deliver precise effects at a time and place of our choosing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is inevitable that we have seen the blending of conventional and asymmetric means to support the attainment of objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, as I mentioned before, such attacks can be conducted from a ‘safe’ distance and makes the attribution of attacks more difficult.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyber attacks on Georgian infrastructure in 2008 by supporters of South Ossetian separatism coincided with the Russian military offensive.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These attacks created a “fog of war” in which the Georgian government was unable to communicate with the international community to rally support to its cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cyber attack had both a tactical and strategic effect on the Georgian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integration of cyber and physical attack would seem to be the most likely use of cyber in the military sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must therefore win the battle in cyber space, as well as the battle on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing we should recognise is that actions in cyber space form part of the future battlefield, rather than being separate from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It adds a new and modern dimension to conflict, but what it seeks to achieve should be subject to the same strategic and tactical thought as a conventional military operation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will encounter the same adversaries with the same motivations in cyberspace as we do in the real world - albeit in a new environment which has its own unique characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Clausewitz believed, war is an expression of politics by other means. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we should also be able to prevent, deter, coerce or even intervene in cyber space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not be easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are those who argue that in countering cyber threats, conventional concepts will be rendered obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some sympathy with that view and we will need to adapt our analysis to the architecture of cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I do not believe we should just concede that because it will be difficult to apply concepts like deterrence to cyber space, that it will be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, cyber space is a new domain, but it is still a human domain with all the actions there driven by human behaviour and motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we should not jettison centuries of proven learning in awe of the complexities - we should reapply them to the new circumstances and supplement them where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn now to how we are doing this and the work of the coalition Government and others to integrate cyber space into our thinking on national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cyber-security"&gt;Cyber Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Security Strategy recognises that the response cannot, and must not, be for government alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no on-off button that government can use for our national networks and there is no defined perimeter in cyberspace which government can defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must draw more effectively on the knowledge, experience and resources of the private sector who own and operate large parts of the critical networks that deliver our essential services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our national approach to cyber security must be sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires us to keep pace with new technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But reducing vulnerability requires an understanding of people’s behaviours as much as it does network topology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means understanding what is critical to protect and managing the risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need dynamic defences that are able to - first, identify and assess risks - but second trace events to their source and stop them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While government must lead - cyber security can only be delivered as a partnership between government, industry and academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Strategic Defence and Security Review has launched a transformative National Cyber Security Programme supported by £650m of new investment over the next four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will overhaul not only our approach to tackling cyber crime, but also the UK’s ability to defend itself from cyber attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will seize the opportunities which cyber space provides for our future prosperity and for advancing our security interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, as I have suggested, we have strong capabilities on which we must build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include protecting our critical national infrastructure, protecting the operations of our armed forces at home and abroad, and exploiting cyberspace to enhance our defence -  including the capability to exploit the weaknesses of our opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyber capabilities may provide the kind of precise and tailored effects which a conventional attack cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, for example, we were able to switch off the lights for a window of opportunity, then this would provide decision makers with greater options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we should not underestimate the investment required to develop such capabilities; the intelligence, understanding and overall resource may be significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also the case that cyber cannot put boots on the ground, dominate the sea lanes or control the air - all of which remain critical to preserving national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still live in a physical world - so physical capabilities will never be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they should be supplemented by cyber capabilities which will give protection where necessary and greater flexibility where required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Cyber Operations Group&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the SDSR, we are creating a new UK Defence Cyber Operations Group which will integrate our activities in both cyber and physical space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Group will provide a cadre of experts from across Defence to support our own and allied cyber operations, to secure our vital networks and guide the development of our cyber capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also be responsible for developing, testing and validating cyber techniques as a complement to traditional military capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much to learn and develop in this area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take time to understand fully the threats and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Group will work closely with other Government departments, industry and other experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-action-and-the-law"&gt;International Action and the Law&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, there are no geographical barriers in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our partnerships need to be international.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to forge strong international alliances to increase resilience and joint operational capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As NATO is the cornerstone of the UK’s Defence, so addressing cyber in the NATO context will be important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with our NATO allies, we will need to establish a common understanding on how best to defend ourselves against cyber attack, and the role of NATO in our collective defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much discussion on the legal frameworks which apply to acts of aggression in cyberspace and those that apply during armed conflict itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the established laws governing the use of force and the conduct of hostilities are equally applicable to cyberspace as they are to traditional domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When applying the law, one of the difficult issues will be determining if an event constitutes an armed attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For traditional domains, we assess the act, its effects, and the whole context to determine whether it constitutes a breach of international law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then judge what the necessary and proportionate response should be, applying well established legal principles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should assessing and responding to a cyber attack be different? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the issue of attribution in cyber space will be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As will the issue of intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I said earlier, just because it will be difficult, doesn’t mean it will be impossible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I believe that the issues around NATO Article V may not be as difficult as some suggest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But certainly Article IV and the recognition of threats beyond Alliance borders will be an important approach at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion ladies and gentlemen when it comes to conflict, I believe we must recognise that actions in cyberspace should be governed by the same principles of international law which already act to check the worst extremes of state actions in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the last Government, I believe too often, we sought to use international law to justify what had already been decided, rather than using international law to guide our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have more respect than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to recognise how vulnerable Britain would be in a system of international anarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We therefore, I believe, need to apply the principles of international law to cyber space as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be difficult to achieve but the rule of law brings better security and better predictability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not extinguish threats but it helps manage them, helps to define what is accepted and what is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I believe is required if we are to protect the enhanced freedom of opportunity that the digital age can provide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
