<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state-minister-for-the-armed-forces</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state-minister-for-the-armed-forces.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for the Armed Forces</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56112</id>
    <published>2012-09-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-mod-ministerial-team-announced"/>
    <title>New MOD ministerial team announced</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Following the recent government reshuffle the Prime Minister's Office has announced a change to the ministerial team at the Ministry of Defence.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new ministerial team is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Secretary of State for Defence - The Rt Hon Philip Hammond MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Minister of State for the Armed Forces - The Rt Hon Andrew Robathan MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans - The Rt Hon Mark Francois MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology (including Defence Exports) - Philip Dunne MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and Minister for International Security Strategy - Dr Andrew Murrison MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and the Lords spokesman on Defence - Lord Astor of Hever&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45356</id>
    <published>2012-06-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:35:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-21-political-will-military-capacity-maritime-security-in-the-middle-east"/>
    <title>2012/06/21 - Political Will, Military Capacity: Maritime Security in the Middle East</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at the Rand Europe Rights of Passage Conference, London on 
Thursday 21 June 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, good morning and thank you for inviting me to speak today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provides me with the opportunity to set out the UK’s approach to an issue of critical national importance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One in which Defence, and particularly the maritime element of it, plays a vital part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one in which there is a great deal of international consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my comments are made on behalf of the UK, our position reflects thinking across a wide and very capable set of international friends and partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that context, I want to talk about two facets of maritime security - international law and military capacity to enforce it -and, in doing so, address the following key issues: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we mean when we talk about a right of passage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this apply to the Middle East with its unique geography and politics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What force structures exist to respond to maritime insecurity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what contribution does the UK make to maritime security in the Middle East? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="political-will"&gt;POLITICAL WILL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the Right of Passage - what is it and why is it important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great majority of world trade moves by sea; it underpins the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an island nation, 95% of UK trade in goods transits by sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our prosperity and security is dependant upon energy, raw materials and other trading markets that we access through the sea lanes and maritime trade routes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dependency will increase in the years to come as the UK becomes more reliant on imported energy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore vital that the free-flow of shipping is maintained so that the import and export of goods on which the nation depends can continue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept - the freedom to use the seas - is not new; indeed the maritime regime has been based on it for the past 500 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of the ‘Mare Librum’ or The Free Sea is the basis upon which the modern UN Conventions are built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Grotius, one of the founding fathers of international law, put it in the 16th century :’by the law of nations, navigation is free for any to whomsoever’ and that the ‘liberty of trading it leads to ‘hath a natural and perpetual cause and therefore cannot be taken away’.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a position that the UK Government fully supports today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Convention on the Law of the Sea recognises the importance of the key strategic maritime chokepoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hormuz, Bab el Mandeb, Malacca, Gibraltar and Dover - all of which exist within the territorial waters of coastal states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To challenge the right of transit for all vessels in these Straits -the right of passage through them - is to challenge the international system itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact would be felt on the global economy and the national security of any state that regularly trades through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="middle-east"&gt;MIDDLE EAST&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly so in the Gulf region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the UK’s national interest we have a confluence of a number of factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets and energy supplies vital to the UK, and many other nations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friendly and partner nations who we wish to support; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a particular maritime trading route - the Strait of Hormuz - that is vital to the stability of both the region and the global economy more generally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and other major maritime powers have long had a permanent presence in the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy has had a constant patrol in this area since 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of naval assets form a routine part of our commitment to the free movement of international shipping in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment serves three key purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, to protect the essential arteries of international trade;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, to reassure our international partners;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, to deter aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the UK is committed to the security of this region and will maintain a naval presence in the long term.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a range of priorities in the region, the most acute of which is the Strait of Hormuz. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Naval presence in the Gulf long pre-dates some of the current difficult issues facing the region and the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on a belief that the free movement of international maritime traffic is fundamental to regional prosperity, fundamental to international prosperity, fundamental to the regional security and fundamental to international security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strait-of-hormuz"&gt;STRAIT OF HORMUZ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, focussing in on the Strait of Hormuz, what are the UK’s principles for defining an international strait and therefore determining where a right of passage exists?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I outlined earlier, the Law of the Sea is designed to ensure freedom of navigation within international waters, and in international straits as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boundaries of a Strait are defined by the practicality of making a passage through it - the need of the mariner to use a particular route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is safety, shiphandling, navigation and seamanship, not necessarily proximity to land, that is at issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the right of passage starts at the first point from where such free passage is required, and finishes at the final point at which it is not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the basic calculus against which the UK will make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, and based on all that I have outlined before, we take all threats to undermine peace and stability in the region seriously. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threats or attempts to block the Strait of Hormuz show a contempt for international law as it is seen by the majority of the states in the region, if not the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of our will to ensure that this does not happen, I will paraphrase the Defence Secretary’s statement of 5th January this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in the interest of all nations that the arteries of global trade are kept free, open and running. Disruption to the flow of oil through the Strait of Hormuz would threaten regional and global economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any attempt by Iran to do this would be illegal and [ultimately] unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="military-capacity"&gt;MILITARY CAPACITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me now turn to the military capabilities that underpin the right of passage, because there is little point in having the legal basis with which to protect our national interests and those of our friends and partners, without the ability to enforce it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Professor Colin Gray put it: “strategy is a practical business.  If troops cannot do it, policy is a mere vanity”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining the broad capacity to protect our national maritime interests was a key component of the UK’s recent Strategic Defence and Security Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The naval forces we are building will be some of the most powerful, flexible and capable units afloat.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protecting and projecting UK influence is a key role for the frigate and destroyer force within it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our world-leading niche capabilities can also do this, particularly our oceanic survey and mine clearance capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This force will provide an enduring presence within priority regions of the world - of which the Gulf is clearly one.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are and will continue to be additional and powerful intervention capabilities available - ships, submarines, helicopters and amphibious forces ready to support this enduring presence if needs be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR created a High Readiness Force which is available to allow us to respond to protect our own national security interests, or to form a potential UK contribution to a multinational operation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maritime component of which is delivered by the Royal Navy’s Response Force Task Group, which is able to bring a range of capabilities to bear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has its own afloat Headquarters staff and commander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can plan and execute the full range of maritime operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be forward deployed in parts or as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its ships, submarines, aircraft and commandos are all trained and ready to work together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not geographically constrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can move forward and deliver force anywhere on the high seas -travelling over a 300 miles per day without any need for additional sea-based and more importantly land based support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can project power ashore through firepower, Apache Attack helicopters and the insertion of Special Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is agile and flexible, able to fight, deter, contain, project power, stabilise, reassure, and deliver training to our friends and allies without any need to reconfigure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a smart power tool, with a hard power capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-force-laydown"&gt;CURRENT FORCE LAYDOWN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to our current military presence in the region, the UK has maintained at least two Frigates or Destroyers in the Gulf and Indian Ocean region since 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They now contribute to the Coalition Maritime Force based in Bahrain and comprised of sailors and ships from 25 nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its mission is to conduct counter-piracy and counter-terrorism patrols and ensure the safety of the internationally important arteries of global trade in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a UK naval staff in Bahrain, co-located with the multinational maritime headquarters and we provide the Deputy Maritime Component Commander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek to provide this key leadership position and for as long as the coalition mission is needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2003, the UK has maintained a presence of Mine Counter Measure Vessels in the Gulf to support operations, conduct historic ordnance disposal and maintain freedom of navigation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These vessels initially cleared the routes into Iraqi ports after the war in 2003 and have subsequently cleared hazards left over from the Iran/Iraq war of the 1980s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are very capable units, highly regarded, regularly practised and fully acclimatised to the unique operating conditions found in Gulf waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with those of other like-minded nations, the UK naval presence forms part of a powerful force that is in place now, and can be called upon to ensure the peaceable use of the seas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the Royal Navy’s Response Force Task Group could quickly deploy to the region if required.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to conclude, I believe the answer to the question posed by this conference - do politicians have the will and legitimacy to act in defence of the shipping industry - has to be yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our will is based on a clear understanding of the vital importance of the flow of trade and energy to and from the Middle East &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists an economic necessity to preserve the free and legal use of the seas and access to critical strategic areas such as the Straits of Bab-el-Mandeb and Hormuz and key maritime trade hubs such as Dubai and Singapore. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legitimacy is based on the universal ideal of the freedom of navigation, a right under the maritime regime for the past 500 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our presence in the region safeguards our legitimate interests and acts as a deterrent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We retain formidable Armed Forces; equipped with some of the best and most advanced technology available; and able to project significant power to almost any part of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Defence is as much about preventing conflicts as it is about winning them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the maritime security role the UK plays in the Gulf is part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the gunboat diplomacy of the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can, and will, use all our unique assets - economic, diplomatic, military, political, legal, and cultural - to ensure that our citizens are secure and prosperous in this new era. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45350</id>
    <published>2012-05-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T18:31:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-22-address-to-15th-chemical-weapons-demilitarisation-conference"/>
    <title>2012/05/22 - Address to 15th Chemical Weapons Demilitarisation Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at the Marriott Hotel, Glasgow on Tuesday 22 May 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director-General, Your Excellency, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to welcome you all today to the 15th and final Chemical Weapons Demilitarisation Conference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the Chemical Weapons Convention entered into force in 1997, the United Kingdom hosted the first of this series of annual conferences, so it is perhaps appropriate that the final conference should also be held here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory for the efforts that they have made, year after year, to arrange and manage these Conferences. I must also thank their partners, the United States Army; the Abandoned Chemical Weapons Office, Japan; and our contractors; Battelle Memorial Institute; Bechtel Corporation; Bowhead Systems Management, Inc; Kobe Steel; Parsons Infrastructure and Technology Group;&lt;br&gt;
Science Applications International Corporation; and URS Corporation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a particular pleasure to welcome Ambassador Üzumcu the Director General of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He and his predecessor, Rogelio Pfirter, have been key supporters of these Conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom has sought the widest participation from all countries which are faced with the problems of destroying chemical weapons, including Old and Abandoned chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important traditional partners such as the US, Japan, and Germany have given sustained support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also newer partners such as the representatives from China, Iraq and Libya who are attending this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can each contribute our own experience and learn from each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no fewer than 15 countries in total at this Conference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a measure of the success of these Conferences that you, the participants, continue to attach such importance to attending, even at a time when increasing budgetary pressures limit the scope for travel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chemical-weapon-destruction"&gt;Chemical Weapon Destruction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 is of course an enormously important year for chemical weapon destruction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 29th of April was the final deadline provided for by the Chemical Weapons Convention for the destruction of all chemical weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destruction is a central obligation under the Convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it has been clear for some time that the deadline would not be met by the two major possessors of chemical weapons - US and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, understandably has dominated the agenda of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons for the past year or more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What view should we take of this?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, we cannot be satisfied that the deadline has been missed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that there have been insufficient funding and technical failures in some cases, and schedules which have frequently proved to be over-optimistic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also clear that the original deadlines were essentially political, not based on real experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main aim, when the deadlines were agreed in 1993, was to set target dates which would be sufficiently challenging to ensure that political and financial priority was given to meeting destruction obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, at that stage, no-one had substantial experience of chemical weapons destruction, and the practical, safety, environmental, regulatory or financial challenges involved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These have all proved much more demanding than originally realised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test of any organisation is how it deals with difficult problems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handling the 2012 deadline has been a real test for the OPCW, and it has taken long and painful efforts to reach a conclusion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend the States Parties for succeeding in resolving the issue, as well as the important related question of Abandoned Chemical Weapons in China, and I commend the Director General for his personal role in helping to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let us also celebrate the successes we have had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 73% of all declared stockpiles have been destroyed - around 51,000 tonnes of chemical agent put permanently beyond use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three countries have completed destruction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has now destroyed nearly 90% of its stockpile, Russia has passed the 60% mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya had destroyed over 50% of its small stockpile before operations were interrupted; and Japan has started destruction of Abandoned Chemical Weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those holding chemical weapons have clearly demonstrated their political commitment to destroying their stockpiles at the earliest practicable date, and have provided unprecedented transparency of their efforts in an area that was previously highly secretive because of national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must never forget both the technical complexity of the task, and the enormously dangerous nature of these toxic chemicals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destruction must be both effective and safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is truly a great achievement that destruction has been carried out with such an outstanding safety record, and many of you here are personally responsible for this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-contribution--chemical-weapons-demilitarisation-conferenece"&gt;UK Contribution &amp;amp; Chemical Weapons Demilitarisation Conferenece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has contributed to this process over the past 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, starting at home, we destroyed all our initial holdings of old chemical weapons - some 4,000 - by April 2007. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disposing of these old munitions, often in a heavily corroded state after being buried for 60 years or more, was difficult and dangerous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pay tribute to the staff of the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory  Porton Down, who did this successfully, without accidents or injuries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, during the past decade, in very close cooperation with the US and Canada, the UK led a £90M international programme of assistance to Russia with its chemical weapon destruction programme, managing projects at the Shchuch’ye destruction facility on behalf of 12 other donors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the facility started operations in March 2009, these projects have helped to destroy well over a million individual munitions and nearly 3000 tonnes of nerve agent. Just to illustrate what this means, just 1kg of Sarin could potentially cause up to 1000 fatalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also pleased to be planning to provide training for Iraq in dealing with its uniquely challenging chemical weapon legacy, and we have offered technical advice to Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, the UK has also sponsored this series of Conferences which have provided a unique opportunity for a wide range of experts from Governments and industry to engage and exchange ideas and lessons about the shared challenges that we have faced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continued support shown for these conferences is clear evidence of the value attached to them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you all know, this will be the final Conference in this series - a valuable opportunity to reflect on the shared challenges we have faced over the past 15 years - and successfully overcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chemical-weapons-convention---the-future"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention - The Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expertise that you have developed and shared at these Conferences will continue to be vital as we face new challenges in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I very much hope that the strong informal networks of experts that the Conferences have helped to encourage will be robust enough to survive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there are still major challenges ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still significant quantities of chemical weapons to be destroyed, mainly in Russia and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must remain a priority and be done safely, transparently and as soon as practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not doubt the commitment or ability to achieve this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot assume that there are no other threats from chemical weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Convention has not yet achieved full universal membership and full compliance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must also remain ready and prepared to admit new members, including ones who possess chemical weapons stockpiles. Current events in the Middle East highlight the difficulties here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must retain the necessary skilled personnel, and stand ready to carry out the necessary verification tasks, including challenge inspections and investigations of alleged use of chemical weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even when chemical weapon destruction is complete, the OPCW and the Convention will have to continue to adapt to new threats, challenges and priorities, to prevent the re-emergence of chemical weapons any time in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will have to respond to developments in science and technology, and maintain the effectiveness of industry verification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, I commend the Director General for the work which has already been undertaken on the future of the OPCW - the report of the Advisory Panel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Review Conference next April will of course provide an excellent opportunity for the OPCW to start to focus on the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will play a full part in these discussions, and we look forward to a constructive outcome which will further strengthen the Convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion ladies and gentlemen, enormous progress has been made, for which many of you can claim personal credit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must continue to share information, experience and expertise, so that we can complete the job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must prepare for the new challenges which lie ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that the UK will continue to engage actively and constructively on all these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemical weapons were developed over decades of international suspicion, rivalry and conflict, in conditions of the greatest secrecy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But together we are putting all this into the past, and with unprecedented international cooperation, are destroying these horrific weapons, so that this shadow will no longer hover over our citizens.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Brussels in 2007, the members of this Conference laid a wreath at the Menin Gate in Ypres to commemorate the soldiers who died there with no known grave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know it was at Ypres, on 22 April, 1915, that chemical weapons were first used on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One survivor, Anthony Hossack, a British Soldier wrote this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We could see in the failing light…. a low cloud of yellow-grey smoke or vapour, and, underlying everything, a dull confused murmuring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Suddenly down the road … came a galloping team of horses, the riders goading on their mounts in a frenzied way; then another and another, till the road became a seething mass with a pall of dust over all”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Plainly something terrible was happening…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last 15 years we have acted to see that this terror is banished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Conference series will come to an end, but our shared mission will continue - to ensure that chemical weapons are never produced or used again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are all here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55729</id>
    <published>2012-03-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:51:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-driving-efforts-on-global-nuclear-security--2"/>
    <title>UK 'driving efforts' on global nuclear security</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As the Deputy Prime Minister attends a summit on nuclear security in Seoul, Minister of State for the Armed Forces Nick Harvey has released a statement on the issue.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Harvey writes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of international terrorism has made the struggle to keep nuclear material out of the wrong hands more acute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Barack Obama hosted a landmark summit in Washington, two years ago, where the UK and other countries joined the campaign to ‘lock down’ nuclear material. Today [27 March 2012], the Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, will be returning from the second of these nuclear security summits in Seoul, South Korea, where he announced for the first time the groundbreaking work the UK, US and France are doing in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we are driving efforts to secure not just nuclear material but also the know-how that terrorists would need to turn those materials into an improvised device and threaten our people. This means preventing access to nuclear devices, materials and expertise by those who would seek to do us harm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of Clyde Marine Police Unit escorting Royal Navy nuclear deterrent submarine HMS Vanguard back to HM Naval Base Clyde in Scotland (stock image) " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5293/UK__driving_efforts__on_global_nuclear_security-03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of Clyde Marine Police Unit escorting Royal Navy nuclear deterrent submarine HMS Vanguard back to HM Naval Base Clyde in Scotland (stock image) [Picture: Chief Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Thomas McDonald, Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It means having a technical response force capable of detecting, making safe, diagnosing and disposing of an improvised radiological or nuclear device. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means having the forensic ability to trace the source of nuclear and radiological materials that could be used in such devices by utilising their unique chemical and physical ‘fingerprints’. In doing so, we can encourage states to keep effective control over their nuclear material. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has also announced that the UK is continuing to build on its world-class capabilities by opening a new nuclear forensics laboratory. One of only a handful in the world, the facility will enable the UK to carry out conventional forensics techniques - such as fingerprinting and DNA recovery - on radiologically-contaminated evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having remained silent on this issue for decades, I want the public to be reassured that the Government, Atomic Weapons Establishment and emergency services have been working tirelessly to protect us from this threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By announcing this capability we hope to help other nations secure their nuclear material and information and join us in combating - and deterring - nuclear terrorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a nuclear weapons state comes with the most solemn of responsibilities and that is why we must work together with our allies to make sure the secrets of these weapons stay safe and out of the hands of terrorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear terrorism is a real and global threat. A successful attack would be catastrophic with far-reaching human, economic, political and environmental consequences. We have a responsibility to make sure that does not happen and I am proud that the UK is leading the world in living up to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/41604</id>
    <published>2012-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T12:13:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tongan-pm-visits-the-mod-as-part-of-three-day-visit"/>
    <title>Tongan PM visits the MOD as part of three-day visit</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Tongan Prime Minister, Lord Tu'ivakano, and the Commander of the Tonga Defence Services, Brigadier General 'Uta'atu, were welcomed to the Ministry of Defence in London today with a ceremonial guard from the Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s visit is the first by the Tongan Prime Minister and is part of a three-day programme which includes a visit to the Royal Military Academy Sandhurst as well as meetings at MOD Main Building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit a range of topics will be discussed, including Tongan support in Afghanistan and training opportunities for the Tongan Defence Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has plans to arrange for trainers from the Royal Military Academy Sandhurst to travel to Tonga to conduct separate leadership and physical training courses. The Tongan Defence Force currently has an Officer Cadet at Britannia Royal Naval College Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister of State for the Armed Forces, Nick Harvey, who hosted the delegation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would like to express my gratitude to the Tongan Government for allowing the deployment of 55 Tongan troops serving alongside UK Armed Forces in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Their deployment has been nothing but positive. They have provided great utility and are conducting a variety of force protection tasks in partnership with British forces, significantly mitigating threats to internal security at Camp Bastion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK welcomes the opportunity to discuss the potential for extending the current Tongan deployment in Afghanistan as well as training opportunities in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18754</id>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:20:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-02-09-royal-navy-club-founders-day-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/02/09 - Royal Navy Club Founder's Day Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at Trinity House, London on Thursday 9 February 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chairman, First Sea Lord, Gentlemen, it is an honour to be invited to address this year’s Founders’ Day dinner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the Admiralty Board, may I thank you Mr Chairman for your hospitality - and the Elder Brethren of Trinity House for allowing us to celebrate here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a busy year for the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the First Sea Lord intends to speak about operations, so let me express my appreciation, and that of the Government, for the incredible work that has been done by the Royal Navy since the last Founder’s Day Dinner: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On standing operations around the globe; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining our nuclear deterrent; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Royal Marines and others in Afghanistan; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the very substantial Naval contribution to Operation Ellamy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-state-of-the-nation"&gt;The State of the Nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by acknowledging, that as well as being a busy time for the Navy, it has been a great stretch, and this last 18 months has been particularly difficult as the reality of what the SDSR means settles in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing ships like Cumberland decommissioned - or Ark Royal - or aircraft like Harrier - all having given such good service to the Navy and the nation over many years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing gaps appear in naval capabilities like carrier strike;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not easy saying goodbye to colleagues you’ve served with for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redundancy programme, in particular, is a matter of great regret to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m sure everyone here recognises that the Government had to act to tackle the huge bow wave of unfunded liabilities that had built up in the Defence programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in itself, would have been a daunting effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not only this, I think, that has been so sobering over the last 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also been the realisation by many, particularly those of us concerned with the defence of the nation, of just how threatening the UK’s financial situation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The national debt has now topped a trillion pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are spending £50bn a year on the interest alone - the equivalent of a dozen Queen Elizabeth Aircraft Carriers or 33 Astute Class submarines - the scale of what we, as a nation, are facing becomes clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years ago, it was institutions like Northern Rock and the Royal Bank of Scotland that were being bailed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last year it’s been whole countries - Ireland, Greece, Italy, Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the United States has had its credit rating down-graded - and is cutting its defence budget by a staggering $500bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eurozone crisis has thrown a spotlight on just how exposed Britain’s economy is - and it has shown us just how isolated Britain could quickly become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nietzsche said - if you gaze for long into an abyss, the abyss gazes also into you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced, that in this era of great volatility, in this era of interconnectedness, in this era of economic exposure, Britain will continue to need all the benefits, all the influence and all the security that accrue from being a maritime power of significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is: how do we sustain that power in an age of austerity and competing demands - austerity and competing demands that are shared by our most dependable allies too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I try to answer that question, let me set out why Britain needs to remain a maritime power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-utility-of-maritime-power"&gt;The Utility of Maritime Power&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am of course preaching to the converted here so I will keep it brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an operational point of view, maritime power is essential in a world where we have to project power to protect our national security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we have to gain access to, and operate in, other domains in far flung parts of the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the littoral remains the focus of so much human activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea-basing provides choice and flexibility in deploying and sustaining force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides mobility, range and endurance and can help overcome a whole host of challenges associated with having a footprint on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are not abandoning carrier-strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we will maintain our amphibiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a vital part of the balanced capabilities that we have defined as Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maritime power, for Britain in particular, has never been solely about the application of military force in time of hot war - it is about a continuous national presence in other parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating slices of sovereign territory from which to operate and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea is a one of the most important global super-highways that Britain, as an island nation, depends upon for our prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on imports of goods and energy - the vast, vast majority coming by sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that dependence on the sea, especially for energy, is only going to increase in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only what comes and goes by sea - the trade which sustains our way of life - it is also about the resources the sea provides which need protecting - oil, minerals, fish, increasingly off-shore wind power too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe seas enable strong economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy has always played a part - sometimes alone, sometimes alongside our allies and friends - in making sure the vital sea arteries in the global commons are protected and that international law is observed - providing deterrence, reassurance, and influence - contributing to the nation’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="austerity-and-the-royal-navy"&gt;Austerity and the Royal Navy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, why more than any other institution in the country, you of the Royal Navy understand the inextricable link between economic power and the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is woven into much of your history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said an Army marches on its stomach - well it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Cicero said, finances are the sinews of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole of the Armed Forces march on the public purse - on the back of the taxes we all pay - and the size of the public purse depends ultimately on the health of the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, in my view, the coalition Government is right to focus its priority attention on getting the deficit under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right not only for the economy - but in the long-term it is right for national security too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only with healthy public coffers can we hope to sustain, in the long-term, the investment required for the high-tech, well equipped military forces we know we will need in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have had to act to both balance the Defence budget and bring the Defence Programme in line with the financial reality the country faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Budget took a hit - not nearly as much as some other departments - but a reduction in resources none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach the next General Election, and in preparation for the next Defence Review in 2015, the approach the political parties take to the Defence budget will be a measure of how committed they are to realising Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, thanks to cross-Government agreement, we now have the ability to plan on the budget allocated to defence equipment and support increasing by 1% a year in real terms between 2015 and 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been difficult but we are now close to achieving a sustainable budget for the first time in decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly confident that the end is in sight to the period of retrenchment and the period of growth will in time begin again with funds released for projects outside the core programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget that we are still spending considerable sums on Defence - over £150 billion over the next decade on defence equipment and support alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Royal Navy - we are already beginning to see the shape of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Daring, Dauntless and Diamond now part of the fleet, Dragon expected in the Spring, and Defender and Duncan coming on line - in the Type 45, Britain can boast one of the most advanced warships in the world - and the envy of our allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Astute is nearing the end of her sea trials to be followed over the next few years by Ambush, Artful, Audacious, Anson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2020, the Queen Elizabeth Class Carriers - the largest ships the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime thereafter, the Type 26 Global Combat Ship will begin to come on stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these will be leaders in their field and represent the most capable, high-technology platforms the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ship for ship this will be one of the most powerful fleets in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be smaller - yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be able to do everything, everywhere, every time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No - of course not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are entering an era in which all of Britain’s security requirements - and those of our dependent territories - can only be guaranteed through our alliances and through our partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in reality, it has always been thus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to turn a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need now to begin the hard work of putting the Fleet of 2020 together, bringing these platforms on line, making sure we retain the right skills, developing new recruits, maintaining the profile of the Navy in the public mind - all the while delivering on operations - keeping our citizens safe - protecting our interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me pay tribute to the way the First Sea Lord has set out his vision of a powerful, adaptable and vibrant Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you here are in attendance through your qualification for command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the moral component of leadership is one of the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are currently serving we need you to be focussed, positive, full of ideas, prepared to change yourself, willing to drive change in others, inspiring those around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are no longer serving we need your continued energy and experience, advocating in public for maritime power - even if it means - every now and then - holding people like me to account for the decisions we are taking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this Founder’s Day, together we celebrate the long and illustrious history of the Royal Navy - but let us today also look forward with confidence in the future too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39865</id>
    <published>2011-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:03:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/extra-talk-time-to-those-back-home-for-troops-in-afghanistan-this-christmas"/>
    <title>Extra talk-time to those back home for troops in Afghanistan this Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK servicemen and women in Afghanistan will enjoy an extra 1 hour and 15 minutes of talk-time to keep in touch with family and friends this Christmas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All troops on deployed operations this festive season are being gifted an additional 30 minutes of call time funded by the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as an extra Christmas bonus, communications provider Paradigm will gift an extra 45 minutes to every UK serviceman and woman deployed in Afghanistan, meaning that they can now talk to family and friends for even longer over the festive season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Service personnel on operations already get an allowance of 30 minutes talk-time each week, which they can use to make phone calls home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troops on operations are also entitled to internet access as well as WiFi, giving personnel access to their emails from the privacy of their accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Minister Nick Harvey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have the utmost respect for our Armed Forces, who willingly endure the hardship of being separated from their families and loved ones over the festive period to protect our national security. I am delighted that we can offer those deployed on operations this extra talk-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Andy Wilson, who is responsible for managing welfare communications for Defence, Equipment and Support, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas can be a difficult time for troops and their families and we are pleased that we have been able to offer this extra talk-time so that our boys and girls on the front line can keep in touch with loved ones when it matters the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing Director of Paradigm, Keith Norton, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our WelComE service means that serving men and women, wherever they are in the world, can always keep in touch with their families and friends. Paradigm is proud to support British troops over the festive period and we are thankful to Cable and Wireless, who have joined us this year in giving our serving men and women additional talk-time over the Christmas period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk-time is part of WelComE (Welfare Communications Everywhere) project, which is run in partnership with communications company Paradigm under the current WelComE service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year the cost of calls made from Afghanistan to a UK landline were reduced from 11 pence to 6.5 pence per minute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18748</id>
    <published>2011-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:57:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-12-07-uk-norway-nuclear-disarmament-verification-initiative-workshop"/>
    <title>2011/12/07 - UK-Norway Nuclear Disarmament Verification Initiative Workshop</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at Prospero House, London on Wednesday 7 December 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, it is a great pleasure to welcome you to London today to this international workshop on nuclear disarmament verification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last five years the United Kingdom and Norway have been working together - one nuclear weapon state, one non-nuclear weapon state - looking at the challenges associated with verifying the dismantlement of nuclear warheads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop brings technical experts and policy officials from the UK and Norway together with those from 12 non-nuclear weapons states and the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next three days we will share with you the progress we have made and, hopefully, learn from you as we investigate avenues for further work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collaboration between Norway and the UK has been groundbreaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have built up a unique level of trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is about increasing awareness, understanding and trust between all of us here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about proving we can create partnerships that make an active contribution to nuclear disarmament and meaningful progress under the Non-Proliferation Treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-commitment"&gt;UK Commitment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite notable challenges over the last 40 years, the NPT has succeeded in limiting the spread of nuclear weapons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But large arsenals remain and nuclear proliferation continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to redouble our collective efforts and take tangible steps towards a safer more stable world in which countries with nuclear weapons feel able to relinquish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is committed to the long-term goal of a world without nuclear weapons, and we believe that the NPT is the best vehicle for creating the conditions to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress should be made not just on disarmament, but across the other pillars of the NPT too - non proliferation and peaceful access to nuclear power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, the Coalition Government has announced a series of unilateral measures to scale down our nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something Britain has done on a number of occasions since the end of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latest action includes reducing the number of warheads aboard each submarine to a maximum of 40; reducing the number of operational missiles in the VANGUARD class submarines to no more than eight and reducing the number of operational warheads to no more than 120. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme has commenced and we expect completion across the fleet by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On current plans, the subsequent reduction in our total stockpile of nuclear warheads to no more than 180 will be completed by the mid 2020’s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are meaningful reductions and confirm Britain’s place as the most forward leaning, progressive and transparent nuclear weapon state in the P5 and with the smallest declared arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sustainable-disarmament"&gt;Sustainable Disarmament&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we will do what we can on our own, we are clear that sustainable disarmament can only be achieved through a multilateral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the approach of both the Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties that make up the UK’s Coalition Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our focus now is on continuing to press for progress on multi-lateral disarmament and tackling the technical and practical challenges that disarmament poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable disarmament needs to be mutual, it needs to be balanced and it needs to be verifiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries will need to not only disarm, but also be seen to disarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, NPT Article VI calls for disarmament ‘under strict and effective international control’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any future disarmament process would need to be underpinned by a verification regime that can provide confidence that nuclear disarmament has taken place and that non-proliferation objectives have been met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must work now to ensure that the practical challenges are surmountable and we have the technical foundation necessary to make progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what this workshop is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="trust-and-verification"&gt;Trust And Verification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is very grateful to Norway for the commitment it has shown towards the work we are undertaking together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important and enduring lessons of our initiative is that building trust and confidence will be essential to implementing an effective verification regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, we have found, does not always come naturally in an area traditionally so shrouded in secrecy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course real non proliferation obligations and national security interests that both have to be protected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that shouldn’t hold us back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have worked hard at breaking down barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just about a technical understanding of the challenges of warhead dismantlement - it is about cultural understanding too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that I mean putting yourself in another’s shoes - a nuclear weapons state being sensitive to how a non-nuclear weapons state will approach issues - and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a non nuclear weapons state may want to see every last corner of a facility to ensure that there are no weapons being concealed, but without the understanding how this full access could give away proliferative information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment the UK Norway Initiative is unique - but it needn’t be, and it shouldn’t be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have proven that all States Parties to the NPT are able to make an active contribution to their Article VI disarmament obligations through verification research, whilst fulfilling their obligations to non-proliferation under Articles I and II. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop will demonstrate just how complex and how difficult it is to develop a credible regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to stress that the UK Norway Initiative does not yet have the ‘verification solution’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of work still to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true not only in the area of dismantlement verification that we have been concentrating on, but on the wider disarmament process too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other areas ripe for further collaborative and independent research and development and these represent opportunities for all states. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope this workshop will provide you with the ideas and understanding to help you identify some of these areas and to start your own projects perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Norway stand ready to offer guidance to states wishing to fulfil their NPT obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is the first time we have had the opportunity to elaborate on the whole project, and we are delighted each of you are here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are of course grateful to our colleagues at the Atomic Weapons Establishment for the role they are playing and look forward to the dinner they are hosting tonight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will be hosting a confidential expert-level meeting of the P5 early next year - this will be the first time that the P5 have met to focus on verification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is discussed here will be fed directly into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next few days will provide you with the opportunity to learn from our experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you the chance to challenge our conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it enables you to contribute to the international effort of disarmament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, we live in uncertain times - we live in an inter-connected and networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter which club you belong too, or how much you can afford to spend on your defences, no country, no matter how powerful, can hope to protect its national security by acting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to act together - not just to tackle existing threats, but to build for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the vision of the Non-Proliferation Treaty, and that has to be the vision that we seek to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what we are working towards here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the trust, understanding and know-how to ensure that when called upon we have the capability to achieve this vision for real.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18744</id>
    <published>2011-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:49:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-21-cyber-security-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>2011/11/21 - Cyber Security in the UK</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at the KOKODA Foundation Young Strategic Leaders Forum, Canberra, Australia on Monday 21 November 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, thank you for inviting me here to talk about Cyber Security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to having a good discussion although I must admit to being a trifle nervous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded earlier of Don Bradman’s advice to his fellow countrymen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“don’t give the Englishmen an inch. Play it tough, all the way. Grind them into the dust”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I hope your approach to me here will be a little more gentle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before getting into the meat of the issue, let me start by setting out what I mean when I use the term cyber today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-cyber-domain"&gt;The Cyber Domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Ministry of Defence we are concerned with the environments in which Armed Forces can operate and defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally these have been physical geographic domains - land and sea for thousands of years - in twentieth century the air and space too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see cyber as new global domain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It consists of the interdependent network of information technology infrastructures computer systems, and embedded processors and controllers that power the internet and telecommunications networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure that creates the domain is physical - but the connections it creates are not bounded by geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberspace has revolutionised the way the world does business, educates, and entertains - the internet being the driving force of this revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our networked societies have come to rely on these connections - not only for information and social experience - but for the delivery of public services, for utilities like power and water, for economic growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure may be machine, but cyber space is a distinctly human environment - shaped by people - and abused by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaped by people because the human desire for information and access is driving the technology - not necessarily the desire for security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abused by people because cyber crime, cyber espionage, cyber terrorism, cyber vandalism - are all just human pursuits - simply crime, espionage, terrorism, vandalism and conflict by another means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about the suffix ‘crime’ - not the prefix ‘cyber’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference is the method - not the outcome or the intent -  stealing money or information is stealing - regardless of whether it is done by pick-pocketing or hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I do not agree with those who say we need a massive raft of new criminal offences relating to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we do need is to become smarter in preventing, detecting and prosecuting the use of cyber space for criminal or nefarious ends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will have to do this at an international level, because there are no geographic barriers in cyber-space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other area of security we will have to strike a very delicate balance in cyber-space between personal freedom, national sovereignty and international stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the London Conference set out earlier this month, we should focus on all the positive benefits of cyber-space - supporting economic growth and development, encouraging social freedom, providing choices - but doing so while ensuring safe and reliable access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because cyber is a methodology not an outcome, cyber policy and cyber security is difficult to place within the normal departmental system of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me set out how the UK is approaching this both domestically and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-growth-and-development"&gt;Economic Growth and Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, and most other nations for that matter, the economic well-being of our nation is increasingly reliant on the security and resilience of our inter-connected networks and systems operating in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These networks are not always clearly defined and working out exactly what to protect is difficult but ensuring that businesses are able to operate unmolested by criminals has to be a primary goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to be sure how much money is being lost to our economy as a result of cyber crime: most estimates come from online security companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A survey completed earlier this year by the UK company Detica was probably the most thorough ever conducted in the UK: it put the figure at £27bn which seems plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a big figure - and it is likely to continue growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we respond?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well first we have to recognise that this can’t be just government’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has to be a shared responsibility between government, business and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry has a responsibility to do more to prevent cyber crime, for example through more secure devices, systems and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector has to lead in the development of improved Internet security products, systems, services and standards in cyberspace, and to make the market easier to navigate for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a responsibility on users too to apply online the sort of basic commonsense behaviour they use in everyday life to keep themselves safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I call basic cyber-hygiene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your anti-virus software up to date;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regularly scan your computer for viruses;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t post sensitive personal information on open sites;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t open email attachments from senders you don’t recognise;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t download files you are unsure of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To illustrate how far people have yet to get the message, in the UK only around a quarter of all purchasers of a new PC ever activate their online virus protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a busy city you would never leave your front door unlocked when leaving the house, so why do that with your e-valuables?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course none of this is to say that Government has no role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does - particularly in law enforcement and the defence of critical national infrastructure - but its main function will be as a facilitator - encouraging the spread of fast networks, encouraging best practice in business and encouraging individual responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when it comes to tackling cyber crime, the efforts of users and businesses can only go so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only approach that can be effective will be a concerted and urgent international effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must ensure there are no safe havens for cyber criminals, what is unacceptable behaviour “offline” must also be unacceptable “online”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in the domestic arena, this does not mean that we need a new set of laws purely to police cyberspace, rather we should ensure that those international legislations and treaties that protect us are also enforced in the cyber domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-security"&gt;International Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this goes beyond crime, it should also apply to the other relations between states which are governed by treaties, including in conflict situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle must be that states should continue to comply with existing rules of international law and the traditional norms of behaviour that govern interstate relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any use of force and armed conflict, including that states must settle their international disputes by peaceful means in such a manner that international peace, security and justice are not endangered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is developing a range of cyber capabilities which would be used in accordance with the well understood Laws of Armed Conflict and more generally under Domestic and International Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of any UK military capability is subject to strict ministerial oversight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because cyberspace is a domain - a means to an end, it is not an end in itself - well understood concepts such as proportionality of action apply to cyberspace as much as they do to actions in the air, land or maritime domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes cyber so potent as a tool is a number of factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the all-pervasive nature of computers in our lives, in the Critical National Infrastructure, in our economy, in our financial services, in Defence, which creates huge vulnerabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the low technological threshold of entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our adversaries can exploit the same technology used by citizens going about their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That laptop that sits on the desk at home or in the office - used to do accounts, send email or catch up with television programmes - is the same instrument that could be used to launch an attack on our critical national infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, a single networked laptop in the hands of a sophisticated and informed attacker could be as effective a weapon as, say, a cruise missile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, there are no geographical barriers in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attack could be launched from any corner of the world with little warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a conventional military movement - which requires the kind of organisation, mobilisation and logistical support that is hard to hide - a cyber attack can essentially be covert until the moment it begins to do its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, attribution of both cause and effect will be difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know from the recent STUXNET worm, it can be very difficult to trace from where and by whom an attack was initiated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it may be unclear when a cyber event is taking place, what its exact purpose might be or the ultimate aims of the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifth - and perhaps most insidious - with cyber it is possible to rapidly create a mass effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the cyber attacks of Georgia in 2008 - hackers can be enlisted to ideological causes, equipped with the means to carry out mass attacks - so called botnets - and given the target information to direct and synchronise attacks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than a single attack on a target - this can result in hundreds of thousands of computers worldwide being hijacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that cyber is a powerful asymmetric tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen how terrorists can attack symbolic rather than military targets - the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Centre being an obvious example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can only be a matter of time before terrorists begin to use cyber space more systematically, not just as a tool for their own organisation, but as a method of attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So - is cyber a perfect storm for those of us concerned with security?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me offer two considerations that might encourage us to see some light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to quote a well known law of Physics, every action has an equal and opposite reaction - defence seeks to nullify attack ad infinitum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite what the technological reaction to cyber will be is as yet unclear but a response will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, what we present as vulnerabilities to ourselves are also vulnerabilities for our allies too - this is a great opportunity to pool our resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we should not forget the same vulnerabilities may apply to our enemies as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot guarantee our security in cyber space without international action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think and act internationally because cyber space is international space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of work being done bi-laterally and multilaterally to develop common understanding and common positions with other countries and international organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department has been working closely to develop enhanced Cyber relationships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the importance of cyber has been reflected in recent discussions we have had with Australia as well as with other allies such as the US and France amongst others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyber needs to be considered alongside Land, Air and Maritime in our campaign planning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end we are engaging with our trusted military partners to ensure that ‘Cyber’ is fully integrated into our preparations for future coalition operations and we are identifying opportunities for both information and burden sharing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion ladies and gentlemen, the cyber challenge is genuinely everyone’s problem, because the solution requires action at all levels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application of basic cyber hygiene by all citizens both at home and at work;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnership at a national and international level between governments and industry to protect critical infrastructure and ensure network resilience;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And broad engagement with allies and friends abroad to establish the principles of international action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let me finish with one final thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1860, the Pony Express fast mail system was set up in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It revolutionised cross-continental communication - reducing time it took messages to travel from the Atlantic to the Pacific to about 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pony Express has since been mythologised in print and film - the bravery of the riders, the romance of the Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you know how long this iconic system actually lasted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 months - 18 months before the ponies were replaced by the telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is this - technology moves quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how we protect ourselves today - we cannot stop thinking about how we protect ourselves tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of cloud computing where there is an app for every occasion - where we can’t always predict what the next big thing will be - we will need to be adaptable, flexible and fast off the mark to protect national security &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to be open to new opportunities, but ever aware of the dangers we will continue to face.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
