<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state-further-education-skills-and-lifelong-learning</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state-further-education-skills-and-lifelong-learning.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for Further Education, Skills and Lifelong Learning</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47093</id>
    <published>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/skills-minister-unveils-new-investment-in-skills-in-key-industries"/>
    <title>Skills Minister unveils new investment in skills in key industries</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Skills Minister John Hayes has announced funds over £2.4m from the Growth Innovation Fund (GIF) to the nuclear and creative and cultural sectors.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GIF was set up to help employers overcome barriers to growth within their sectors and industries. So far the government has committed over £15 million to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boost innovation and productivity &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enable industries to set new professional standards &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support new or extended national skills academies. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="support-for-nuclear-skills"&gt;Support for nuclear skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclear.nsacademy.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy (NSA) for Nuclear Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; will receive government investment of more than £920,000. This will enable the Academy expand its activities into nuclear manufacturing to help UK manufacturers take advantage of the opportunities offered by the new nuclear build programme. It will also collaborate with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.semta.org.uk/"&gt;Sector Skills Council for Science, Engineering and Manufacturing Technologies (SEMTA)&lt;/a&gt; and the Sheffield-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://namrc.co.uk/"&gt;Nuclear Advanced Manufacturing Research Centre&lt;/a&gt; to create a focal point to boost companies’ capability to develop skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within its first three years the expansion aims to deliver a more skilled workforce, with an increase of 3,500 learners taking up programmes, including more than 500 apprenticeships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="support-for-creative-and-cultural-skills"&gt;Support for creative and cultural skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nsa-ccskills.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural&lt;/a&gt; will receive around £1.5 million. This will enable it to expand and open up opportunities for more than 1,200 new apprenticeships and craft training for young people across the jewellery, design and cultural heritage sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NSA Creative and Cultural also plans to reach around 1.2 million young people through their careers information, advice and guidance material over the next 5 years. It will work with a number of leading organisations and employers, for example the Goldsmiths’ Company, Holts Academy and the British Jewellers’ Association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is businesses themselves that are best-placed to identify the skills they need to drive growth. This investment is very good news for the UK nuclear and creative industries and will help them to overcome the skills gaps that stand in the way of them meeting their full potential. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new centre for excellence for nuclear manufacturing will increase the number of opportunities for technicians and skilled workers and ensure that UK firms can source the skills they need to grow their market share in an expanding market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural has already demonstrated its success in working with more than 200 employers in the theatre and live entertainment business. I am delighted that investment will allow them to increase opportunities in the design, cultural heritage and jewellery sectors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both nuclear manufacturing and for creative and cultural, government funding will be matched by business and delivered over three years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Skills-Minister-unveils-new-investment-in-skills-for-key-industries-67af8.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Skills Minister unveils new investment in skills for key industries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/gif"&gt;About the Growth Innovation Fund from the UK Commission for Employment and Skills (UKCES)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclear.nsacademy.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Nuclear Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nsa-ccskills.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further education and skills at BIS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18371</id>
    <published>2012-04-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-national-careers-service-launched"/>
    <title>New National Careers Service launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The new National Careers Service launched on 5th April 2012.  It will offer independent and impartial information and advice on learning and work.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Hayes also hosted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Apr/Ask%20John%20Hayes%20-%20Tweet%20your%20skills%20and%20careers%20questions"&gt;Twitter chat at 10.30am this morning&lt;/a&gt;, answering questions on the new service. Follow the conversation using #askhayes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-careers-service"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining face to face to face local advice with a new interactive website, the new &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt; will: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide information and advice for approximately 370,000 young people through the use of the helpline and website. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer face to face advice to 700,000 adults each year in a range of locations in local communities. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide detailed sector by sector labour market information so people can discover which industries are growing in their area. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide tools such as a CV builder and a Skills Health Check on the website to help people identify their skills strengths and gaps. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow people to open a Lifelong Learning Account, which gives them clear information and advice on skills, careers and financial support in a single, personalised online space. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Hayes said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Careers Service, universally available to people at all stages of their careers, has the very best interactive tools on its website and the highest-quality advisers, committed to the noble cause of helping others fulfil their aspirations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Making available the right advice at the right time and in the right places is to strike a blow for social mobility, social cohesion and social justice - a society that encourages people from wherever they start to journey to the destination of their dreams.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model turned Chef, Lorraine Pascale is an Ambassador for the service. Speaking from the launch she said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“After modelling, choosing my next career move was a big decision. I knew I wanted to find something that I was really passionate about, but I tried courses in hypnotherapy, auto repair and interior design before I found the thing that really makes me tick: cooking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having independent careers advice can really help you find the thing you want to do. I’d encourage everyone to make the most of the National Careers Service to find out how to take their career forward, and realise their ambitions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her view was echoed by Record Producer Pete Waterman. He said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I know from my own experience that it’s never too late to learn a new skill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I learnt to read and write much later in life than many people, but this opened up a whole new world for me.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s one of the reasons why I’m so passionate about helping people to get the skills they need to fulfil their ambitions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the National Careers Service: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/12-677-national-careers-service-right-advice-right-time.pdf"&gt;The right advice at the right time (PDF, 2.2 Mb) &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18372</id>
    <published>2012-04-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-standards-for-apprenticeships"/>
    <title>Better standards for Apprenticeships</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Tougher standards introduced by Skills Minister to drive up quality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes has announced that Apprenticeships will last for a minimum of 12 months, guaranteeing improvements in training and workplace learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new standards will come into force for all age groups from August 2012, subject to consultation with providers and employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those aged 19 and over, apprenticeships will last between one to four years unless prior learning or attainment has been undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the new measures, Mr Hayes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The momentum we have created by building the apprenticeship brand has brought about unprecedented success for the apprenticeship programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The majority of apprenticeships are the gold standard in vocational training. They boost individuals’ life chances and build the skills that drive growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They also provide a great return on public money. This has been independently recognised with the National Audit Office finding that apprenticeships generating £18 for the economy for every £1 spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we must be relentless in our drive to ensure all apprenticeships are as good as the best, to identify and root out any instances of poor quality provision, and to raise the bar on standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are taking strong and decisive action to tackle short duration so all apprentices receive high quality training and workplace learning setting them on the road to a long, rewarding career.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="grants-for-small-businesses-employing-their-first-apprentice"&gt;Grants for Small Businesses Employing Their First Apprentice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Monday 2 April small businesses (employing less than 250 employees) &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/News-Media/Latest-News/Article135.aspx"&gt;will be able to apply for a grant, up to a value of £1,500,&lt;/a&gt; when they recruit their first apprentice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service &lt;/a&gt;(NAS) is offering up to 40,000 Apprenticeship Grants to businesses who take on an apprentice aged 16 to 24 years old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those businesses interested in employing their first apprentice can contact one of the quality assured training providers or colleges approved to deliver Apprenticeship training by visiting the National Apprenticeship Service, or if they are ready to recruit, can call 08000 150 600 to speak to a NAS Apprenticeship Adviser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-minimum-12-month-duration-for-all-apprenticeships-6782c.aspx"&gt;Press Notice - New minimum 12 month duration for all apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/News-Media/Latest-News/Article135.aspx"&gt;Press Notice - Grants for Small Businesses Employing Their First Apprentice - Now Available!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18345</id>
    <published>2012-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/banks-boost-uk-jobs-with-new-apprenticeships--2"/>
    <title>Banks boost UK jobs with new apprenticeships</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>High street banks will create new apprenticeship schemes and offer more places to young people.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcements were made at a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.newsroom.hsbc.co.uk/articles/apprenticeship_week_-_hsbc_hos"&gt;financial services sector roundtable, held at HSBC&lt;/a&gt; in Canary Wharf, as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Feb/apprenticeships-week-2012"&gt;National Apprenticeship Week&lt;/a&gt;. The focus was on the creation of new apprenticeship routes into employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks taking part include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Barclays - 1000 new apprenticeships across England and Wales with a major programme in April.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HSBC - an extra 688 apprentices bringing the total number of employees within its apprenticeship scheme to 1,000 by the end of 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Santander to launch an apprenticeship scheme that will see up to 50 people offered places at the bank. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the event, Skills Minister John Hayes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that these banks are investing in apprenticeships which will help them secure the high-quality skills they need to create economic growth and provide new pathways to excellence for the brightest and best young people.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Creating a highly skilled workforce that can take on the best in the world means seeing apprenticeships as an access route to the professions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=423209&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On February 7 the Prime Minister announced &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Feb/apprenticeships-government-funding"&gt;round two of the Higher Apprenticeship Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//sitecore/service/notfound.aspx?item=web%3a%7b6604A760-C720-42F1-AD9A-6100618CD4EF%7d%40en"&gt;Apprenticeships at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18331</id>
    <published>2011-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/building-engagement-building-futures"/>
    <title>Building Engagement, Building Futures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Government has published plans to increase the participation of 16-24 year olds in education, training and work.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills/youth-participation"&gt;Building Engagement, Building Futures&lt;/a&gt; sets out the Government’s strategy to improve the opportunities for young people so they gain the skills they need to secure an Apprenticeship or employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes radical reforms to schools, vocational education, skills and welfare provision, and has five priorities for action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raising attainment in school so that young people have the skills to compete in the global economy. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping local partners provide services that support all young people, putting us on track to achieve full participation for 16-17 year olds by 2015. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging employers to offer more high quality Apprenticeships and work experience places. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensuring that work pays and giving young people the personalised support they need to find it, through Universal Credit, the Work Programme and the Get Britain Working measures. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Putting in place a new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/1-billion-package-tackle-youth-unemployment"&gt;Youth Contract &lt;/a&gt;worth almost £1 billion over the next three years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re taking action to get our young people into education, training and work, helping them get on the path to a fulfilling life, providing the right advice and guidance through a new National Careers Service and restoring a sense of responsibility and purposeful pride in our communities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having built the largest apprenticeships programme our country has ever seen we are now incentivising employers to offer more high-quality apprenticeships. We are also aligning welfare and skills reforms to better support young people without basic skills get up to speed and progress on to jobs and apprenticeships.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building Engagement, Building Futures has been published jointly by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/a00200853/building-engagement-building-futures"&gt;DfE&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://dwp.gov.uk/publications/policy-publications/building-engagement.shtml"&gt;DWP&lt;/a&gt; - more detail on those Department’s policies as outlined in the strategy can be found on those websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Participation Strategy follows the recent publication by BIS of key reforms to Further Education in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/fe-and-skills-new-challenges-new-chances"&gt;New Challenges, New Chances&lt;/a&gt; on 1 December 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="priorities-for-action"&gt;Priorities for action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt;, the Chancellor set out how the Government will create the conditions for economic growth and recovery. Building Engagement, Building Futures sets out the Government’s offer for young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the priorities for action, the Government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing £4.5 million over the next two years to give more 16-19 year olds access to work experience. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging employers to take on an 18-24 year-old from the Work Programme by making available 160,000 job subsidies worth up to £2,275 for each business. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reforming the Apprenticeships programme and, as part of the Youth Contract, ensuring funding for at least 40,000 incentive payments for small firms to take on 18-24 year old apprentices. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing an extra 250,000 work experience places over the next three years for young unemployed people across the UK as part of the Youth Contract. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funding charities and businesses to help the most disengaged 16-17 year olds get skills and jobs. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transforming vocational education following Professor Wolf’s review, with new 16-19 programmes of study, including meaningful work-experience and a focus on English and maths. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joining up the welfare and skills systems. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching a National Careers Service in April 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=422504&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further Education and Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://dwp.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Work and Pensions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18621</id>
    <published>2011-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/association-of-colleges-annual-conference--3"/>
    <title>Association of Colleges Annual Conference</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kirsty [Wark] and good afternoon everyone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always pleasant when I’m able to begin a speech with congratulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’ll all want to join me in congratulating Kirsty Wark on the impressively high levels of skill in the kitchen she displayed recently by reaching the final of the BBC Celebrity Masterchef competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was quite an achievement. The daytime television enthusiasts among you who have seen the show will know that its catchphrase is &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cooking doesn’t get tougher than this”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of great achievements, a second helping of congratulations must go to the UK team that competed at last month’s WorldSkills competition who are here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure most of you know how fiercely competitive WorldSkills is. Yet our team, over half of whom were apprentices or former apprentices, won 5 Gold medals, 2 silvers, and 6 bronzes, plus 12 Medallions for Excellence. That placed us 5th out of 51in the competition, ahead of Germany, France, our best-ever finish. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our gold medals was for cookery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I can say with all due deference to Kirsty that cooking really doesn’t get tougher than that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the members of the team would like to stand up. I’m sure that everyone here would like to take a closer look at the best of the best our skills system can produce and people who represent the level of achievement to which all our learners should be able to aspire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m sure we’d all like to show them our appreciation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the fall from the state of grace with which we’ve all been struggling almost since the beginning of time, I understand why few human beings see as many reasons to be cheerful as I do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can all be cheerful about the progress the further education sector has made; is making. Progress through the changes we’ve made since coming to Government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to remember just how much needed to change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For how long FE was neglected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to forget just how far we’ve travelled together over the last 18 months. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just how many petty restrictions we have swept away, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just how many pointless quangos are no longer around to interfere with your work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just how many more apprentices are there gaining the skills and experience upon which they can build good careers and fulfilled lives? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, anyone who has still to be convinced of the importance of Apprenticeships could do worse than read the Institute for Public Policy Research’s new pamphlet Rethinking Apprenticeships, which is being published today and to which Vince Cable, Martin Doel and I all have contributed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is always more we can do. But a record 442,700 apprenticeships starts is an achievement of which you can be proud and the Government can be proud too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, when I spoke to you, I set out our vision of a free sector supporting growth and social renewal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to describe not only the journey we have been on together since then. But also the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I know that in the FE sector new beginnings have never been in short supply. Over the last 10 years we’ve had &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four skills strategies, two FE strategies and the Leitch Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three Acts of Parliament, the old LSC agenda for change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And countless Secretaries of State, and even more FE Ministers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you agree that since we came to power the message has been clear. And it’s not all down to me, despite the compliments from the Secretary of State for Education; he deserves so much credit for all he is doing. FE - no longer the neglected middle child between schools and HE, but the prodigal son. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the strategy I formed with you, for you, at the outset holds firm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the simple truth at its heart holds true; it is this: If we want skills provision sufficiently responsive to meet dynamic economic and social needs, power must rest in your hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In framing our plans, having listened to you over the years, I had no doubt about your capacity to respond to the most radical change in the assumptions about FE in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is systemic change. A paradigm shift; a sector that moves quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so proud of what you have achieved. Thank you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am especially pleased with the way you have delivered on apprenticeships - the biggest growth in apprenticeship numbers ever. There are now 267,200 apprenticeship starts for 16-24 year olds; and 175,500 for 25+. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s growing the skills of our workforce by building people’s prospects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, we gave you yet another document. New Challenges, New Chances. It cements the strategy by responding again to what you have said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the consultation to which so many of you responded - and thank again you for that - we’re now on the verge of another package of reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never again a signpost to a future that will never happen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t anticipate the changes and challenges that will face our successors when our time is done, but I know that by building our strategy on time honoured principles we’ll be fit to face the journey to the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A future of lives changed for the better because of the difference your work makes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now “we have longer ways to go. But no matter, the road is life. “&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My direction of travel has been plotted on the roadmap you can help to draw. We have not only sought your views at every stage, we have taken them seriously. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is because only you can ensure that the sector’s teaching and learning is what’s right; what is needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll do all I can to see that you get the funding you need, but each of you, all of you are uniquely sighted about how best to spend it to meet the needs of your local areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view matters, but I’m certain yours matter more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to abolish as much uncertainty for FE as I can. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the New Challenges, New Chances reforms will be designed to help you plan for years - at least until the end of this Parliament - and to do so the ephemera of spin and soft soap must be washed away, replaced by a cleansing long term vision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No different strategy on my watch. This plan will last. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I can assure you that these plans will not be a lurch in an entirely new direction. On the contrary, they will follow the direction of travel that Skills for Sustainable Growth set a year ago and to which you contributed so much. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk mainly about that perspective during the rest of my time today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the new relationship between colleges, our economy, and the kind of civil society the coming generations deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relationship in which colleges will be trusted not only to manage their own affairs, but to play a key part in designing the whole framework within which they operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new relationship that challenges all of us, but which is fundamentally true to the legacy of the founders of adult education in England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe, like them, that further education should exist for the benefit of local people and their communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that it should feed the local economies that sustain them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially - that it should help ensure that every parent’s wish comes true; that their children enjoy the best chances and better prospects that earlier generations enjoyed, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vision is a sector freed from Governments that predict and provide. Free to reflect and respond to what it sees around it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you see from the window of the principal’s office? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it make you cry out, like Miranda, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“O wonder! How many goodly creatures are there here! How beauteous mankind is! O brave new world that has such people in it!”? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shops, offices, factories, open or closed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groups of mainly young people talking or speaking into mobiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People on foot, in cars or on buses going about their business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your communities. Your people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ll tell you what you don’t see. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t see me. Though I do know that some of you have my photo on your desks (some even on bedside tables or in wallets, I am told) and that’s perfectly understandable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t see Vince Cable’s nor Michael Gove’s. (no photos in wallets there) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not Geoff Russell’s face nor Simon Waugh’s nor Sir Michael Wilshaw’s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see is where your interest lies, where your passion for learning lives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People write and talk a lot about localism but a lot less about what it ought to mean. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Localism is being aware of your community’s needs, sensitive to its roots, careful about its future; feeling for the people around you, their prospects and their welfare, knowing that your fulfilment is bound to their well being; understanding that we are all part of an organic whole, each of us stronger because the whole is stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of our endeavours, achievements nurturing the common good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are stronger for me not telling you how to relate to the people you serve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past tendency in parts of Government was to see running an FE college like running a sweet shop - that is finally at an end. I know what you do - run multi-million pound organisations, which, in business terms, are large employers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that what it takes to be a successful college leader is not so different from what it takes to run any successful business and retain the support of your board of directors while drawing on their expertise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College governors are typically busy successful people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why ask them to give up their time unless we actually allow them to govern? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are shaping the skills Britain needs to prosper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to the future of your communities, colleges can help to fashion Britain’s future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we must have the courage to set you free to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want the sector to be rule-bound. I want you to establish best practice yourself through collective action like this week’s publication of the Foundation Code of Governance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That process of liberation began when I spoke at City &amp;amp; Islington College 18 month ago and continued with Skills for Sustainable Growth last November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of our New Challenges, New Chances consultation will map how much further we will travel by the end of this Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can give you just a taste of what’s to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it’s clear that you must have the ability to innovate to meet new demands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Margaret Sharp and her colleagues have stressed the need for an innovative code. And I thank Margaret for her presentation this morning and for the work she has led in producing the Colleges in the Communities report. I think we’re only just beginning to understand quite how important this work and its follow-up will be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I will ask my officials to organise with the AoC a series of workshops to put into practice Margaret’s proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we must allow you to accelerate the speed of change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t afford to prevaricate when employers have needs and there are unemployed adults ready to meet them, its no use waiting for the system to catch up. You need to get started with twin track qualifications and I’m pleased to tell you that Geoff Russell has found an easy way to do it - funding new start-up programmes through a simple mechanism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will bring forward further plans to make real the changes heralded by Education Bill. That means more deregulation more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff may say more on that when he speaks to you on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, there are over 2.5m people unemployed - a million of them young people - in this country at present. So I have also asked Geoff to use the normal process of reallocating funding to good performers, funding for those NEETs most in need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because of the urgency of this issue we are making up to £25 million available this academic year to increase capacity to improve the skills and employment prospects of the most disengaged young people using the in-year flexibilities in the skills funding system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, all organisations need stability in order to plan, to innovate and to build relationships. That is why I will continue to argue for colleges to be given three-year budgets, including for capital, of the sort that universities have enjoyed for decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifth, I want our changes to HE to have colleges at their heart. We will deliver more higher education in colleges - the 20,000 places is a beginning, not an end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will redefine higher learning through the accelerated development of level 4 and 5 apprenticeship frameworks. I will shortly announce the first round successful bids for funding for this step change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth, on apprenticeships: we will make the growth in numbers sustainable by further cuts in bureaucracy; by marketing apprenticeships to businesses that don’t yet enjoy their benefit with fresh verve and vehemence; a renewed emphasis on quality; and ensuring good fit between welfare reform and our skills offer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventh, to ensure that our teachers are the best in the world and have access to HE I can announce today that we will introduce a bursary for initial teacher training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighth, because Further Education must think increasingly broadly, looking to international opportunities I’ve asked the AoC to develop, with my department, a global strategy for FE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, I can confirm that an independent review of professionalism in FE will be undertaken by David Sherlock CBE and Dawn Ward OBE, Burton and South Derbyshire College. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government can do much to empower the learner and we are doing so, through things like the new National Careers Service, Lifelong Learning Accounts and good information on where jobs will be in the future - linking advice to opportunities and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sort of empowerment is recognising a shared responsibility for supporting learning; the Government providing core financial support, some individuals paying fees supported by loans and employers contributing so supporting learning too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the essential relationship remains that between learner or employer and provider. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because first-class programmes of learning; quality of teaching; and students growing by gaining new skills. These are at the beating heart of further education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cynics claim that me declining to tell you what to do and how to do it will lead to chaos. They say you’re not ready for freedom. That by me trusting you “mere anarchy is loosed upon the world”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer another of Yeats’ memorable phrases, “a terrible beauty is born”. The beauty I envisage of is the beauty of imagination; the beauty of creative minds. And its only terror is the thrill of new. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some critics call me an old-fashioned Tory. And they are right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My approach is rooted in the Toryism of Wilberforce and Shaftesbury of Randolf Churchill and Rab Butler. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My approach to your sector, our sector, certainly echoes the approach of my party when Disraeli, said that &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“all power is a trust; that we are accountable for its exercise; that from the people and for the people all springs, and all must exist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes we propose - and will publish by the end of the month - are a radical shift of power, from me to you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to make clear that I am and will remain accountable to Parliament - to the elected representatives of the people you serve- for the justness of your decisions, the excellence of your leadership; and the quality of your services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after serving the people of my constituency, I see that as the greatest honour of my political life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for coming with us on this journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you for all you do, for all those whose lives you touch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further Education - once described as the neglected middle child of our education system - now favoured. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Favoured by me; by the Government of which I am part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further education grown tall. Grown strong. At last, treated as a grown up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Favoured Sons and Daughters, Further Education has come of age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18620</id>
    <published>2011-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/institute-for-careers-guidance-annual-conference-2011--2"/>
    <title>Institute for Careers Guidance Annual Conference 2011</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning everyone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very pleased to be here today in one of our most fashionable, creative and enterprising cities. Given that fashion is about here and now and I’m more interested in then and when, it is the other two adjectives - creative and enterprising - which are my main themes for today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Service will be launched next April, and builds on Next Step, introduced last Summer, which has been and continues to be a vital and successful Government service. Next Step has the capacity to provide guidance to 700,000 adults a year, and can handle up to 1 million telephone guidance sessions and 20 million website sessions. And over 80% of adults receiving guidance say that it influences their decision to learn or move on in employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are impressive figures. They are testament to the achievements of the careers sector, and the respect in which careers guidance is held by those who have benefitted from it. And Next Step is a landmark service, streets ahead of the provision for adults we have seen in the past. Establishing a fully integrated careers service for adults was my ambition in opposition, delivered in Government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as we plan the launch of the National Careers Service we approach a moment of immense significance. It marks the point at which the careers sector will step into the sunlight. It is the start of your renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to do that, the sector needs to be both creative and enterprising, just as the City of Brighton and Hove has been. From the prescribing of seawater in the 1740s to its current epithet of “Silicon Beach”, Brighton has flourished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change is always a challenge, and for some people too hard to face. Perhaps that’s why we’ve heard too much talk of a “golden age” in careers guidance which is at risk. I don’t want you to have any illusions that the past was better than the future. Although the Connexions service had an impact on the lives of many young people, it was a model that simply did not work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving professional careers guidance is a specialism, which requires expertise and experience. The Connexions model stretched professional careers advisers to breaking point, requiring of them that they give expert advice on health, housing, personal finance and other matters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was ineffective, and ultimately destructive: the product of a public service strategy which asked professionals to do everything at once, rather than doing what they know best. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not the right model for professional careers guidance, and it will not be the model for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch of the National Careers Service brings a clear focus on professional, independent guidance which springs from a deep knowledge of the labour market and the specialist skills and experience of the careers adviser. Empirical, up to date, and to the point. That is what you have all called for, and that is exactly what will be delivered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it depends on the commitment of every single person in this room; every professional in the sector; everyone like us who has a passion for careers guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sensitive to the scale of the challenge you face and know just how radical our ambitions are. But I want us to move on and up, and take bold strides forward. Yes,economic circumstances are difficult. But that must be a spur, an inspiration to even greater creativity, drive and ambition. As I said in Belfast, we simply have to do more with less; and that will be the project and the glory of the careers profession. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am passionate about guidance. It can set young people upon a path which will inspire and motivate them at every turn. It can help adults who have fallen on hard times turn around their lives. It deserves the highest and widest public recognition, and the prestige of a profession which is respected and admired. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a chance, a golden chance, to turn your passion for guidance into a reinvigoration of the sector’s aims and ambitions. But we must move with the times. The model of the past is not the model of the future, and I want you to develop, to innovate, to reinvent where you need to reinvent, and to rise to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said before, guidance is “the stuff of dreams”, because it clarifies and inspires. As Ruskin put it, “To see clearly is poetry, prophecy and religion, all in one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Service will bring online and helpline services for young people and adults together in one place. It will be required to hold the new, more rigorous matrix standard which I had the pleasure to launch earlier this month. It will have a redesigned website which makes information about careers and the labour market more accessible. It will provide high quality advice and guidance to adults in community locations. And it will be promoted at a national level, so that its profile and visibility are high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the National Careers Service to be the gold standard in careers guidance. It will not manage the market - the Government’s approach is to remove regulation, not increase it. But it will set a standard of quality and professionalism that all providers of guidance should seek to match. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside that, the Careers Profession Alliance is leading the renaissance of the guidance profession. Following the great work of the Careers Profession Task Force, the Alliance has set itself the target of achieving chartered status for the careers profession inside three years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to share a platform today with Ruth Spellman, who is chair of the Alliance. This is not by chance, but by design. I want to stand shoulder to shoulder with the careers profession as it continues its journey, and I was pleased that Ruth spoke with authority about the steps which need to be taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applaud the ambition the Alliance have shown, and strongly support the work that Ruth and her colleagues are leading. Developing a set of professional standards which are respected and aspired to by all those providing careers advice - wherever they work and to whatever professional body they belong - is an undertaking of the utmost importance; and I urge all the parties involved onwards to success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I support the work on developing Higher Apprenticeships as a route for the professions, and I am sympathetic with the view that a quota of level 6 staff should be the aim. So the building blocks are in place. And we are working to a clear strategy, which will not change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The participation age for education and training will be raised to 18 in 2015. In line with that flagship policy, responsibility for careers guidance for young people will be devolved to the institutions of learning which know them best, and local authorities will be expected to work hard to re-engage those who have disengaged with the system. Schools will work with local authorities to identify young people who are at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Service will provide information, advice and guidance which supports growth and social mobility, and is in tune with the labour market. Its advisers will be expert, and its reputation will be second to none. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And underpinning this, the careers profession - and the market in high quality careers services - will continue to grow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must continue to look for new and better ways of measuring and recording the positive outcomes to which guidance can lead. Government will play its part in seeking new sources of evidence; but we will continue to be challenged to justify every penny we spend, and the best evidence of success is that which you yourselves provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Alliance, its constituent bodies, and every organisation and adviser in the sector, will need to champion the quality of professional standards to which guidance is delivered, so that there is demand for professional services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And everyone whose business it is to engage in this noble profession - not just the National Careers Service - will need to look for the opportunities and openings which allow them to demonstrate their skill and commitment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there has been debate about the importance of face to face careers guidance for young people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share the view that face to face guidance is of critical importance. Pupils and students can benefit enormously from support offered in person, which raises their aspirations and guides them onto a successful path. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true of those young people who do not have the social networks which can connect them to inspiring figures in different occupations; or those who come from families with a long history of unemployment; or those with learning difficulties or disabilities. You will have heard me speak before about the importance of wherewithal: many young people do not lack aspiration, but do lack the means to achieve their goals. Face to face guidance can help to move them onto the right path. This is the difference between information and advice, between data and understanding. It was Eliot after all who said “where is the knowledge lost in information.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you have stressed the importance of ensuring that schools are able to draw on careers guidance of the highest quality. I share that view. My friends in the teaching profession have left me in no doubt that headteachers are ready to respond to the new duty to secure independent, impartial careers guidance. But they have called for support to help them take advantage of opportunity, and help others do the same. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I am pleased to report that my right honourable friend Lord Hill of Oareford told the House of Lords last week that Government will bring forward statutory guidance for schools on the new legal duty. He also said that this statutory guidance will highlight to schools how they can be confident that the external support they are buying in is of the desired quality; and that the Government would consult on the guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Hill also confirmed that the Government will place a clear expectation on schools that they should secure face-to-face careers guidance where it is the most suitable support, in particular for disadvantaged children, those who have special needs and those with learning difficulties or disabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These important messages in statutory guidance will be underpinned by the sharing of effective practice and evidence of what works. Headteachers need to be able to spread the word about the best, most innovative and most cost effective providers of guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will not stop there. The matrix standard embodies the quality I expect of all careers guidance services. As a visible national standard, it will be promoted, and should serve to help schools decide what careers guidance to secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And providers in the National Careers Service will be encouraged to market their services to schools. This will provide an additional stimulus for the market in young people’s guidance to respond. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me reiterate. We are moving from a past in which specialist, professional careers guidance was submerged by a model which did not work, to a future in which high quality, dynamic and responsive careers services will flourish. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can create a long term environment for guidance which endures. But the sector needs to seize its opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Government, we will not rest on our laurels. On the contrary, we will continue to increase the reach and visibility of careers guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will encourage careers guidance providers in the community to establish networks with other public, private and voluntary sector services. Specialist services working in partnership can have a huge impact on outcomes for individual people. So I want to build on the level of co-location which the Next Step service has already developed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can confirm today that the number of Further Education colleges working with Next Step has now reached 139. Some, such as Southgate College, are exploring new models which bring together careers and job support. Here, in Brighton, Next Step South East is co-located with City College and the Whitehawk Inn community centre to deliver both support and training. We will work with the Association of Colleges, Jobcentre Plus and others to further develop those models. Following our launch in the spring, my ambition is for co-location with Job Centre Plus and colleges to exceed 250 sites across the UK by the end of next year. I can also announce that from April 2012, we will pilot new forms of co-location for the National Careers Service, including in places of worship, community centres, the charitable and voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will help providers in the service to expand their share of business in the market, so they can take the quality of the National Careers Service offer out as widely as possible, and I want to explore how a peripatetic service can be put in place to serve rural areas like the one I represent. The National Careers Service - in towns, cities and villages across the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will continue to explore how we make best use of available funding to support Growth and Social Mobility - for example, by reviewing the groups which are eligible for more than one session of face to face support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Service will be at the heart of the system. To play its role as part of the vision I have set out, it will need inspirational leadership, and a hotline to the profession. So I can announce today: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that we will establish a National Council for Careers made up of key figures from the profession, to advise on the management and direction of the service as it continues to develop; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and that in the New Year, we will publish a document confirming the policy and direction for careers guidance, which will reinforce everything I have said today. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Belfast, I issued a challenge, and called on you all to respond. My message has not changed. Indeed, it has got stronger, my conviction still more certain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the careers profession’s time. This is a renaissance. I love the past but I am not its captive. It will not take us forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone in this room, everyone out there in the sector is committed to inspiring and guiding the young people and adults of this country. We need to step up to the mark, as will the Government . In Kipling’s words “Gardens are not made by sitting in the shade.” We must continue the journey, and move into the bright sunshine. Moving forward, not holding back. Aiming high, not for ourselves, but for the lives we change through what we are and what we do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18616</id>
    <published>2011-10-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/launch-of-the-revised-matrix-standard"/>
    <title>Launch of the Revised Matrix Standard</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421556&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Read the press notice on the Matrix Standard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have heard me speak before will know that I have described careers guidance as “the stuff of dreams”. It promotes ambition, increases motivation and strengthens the desire to succeed. At its best, it can be inspirational. Today is about how we make those dreams come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that, guidance must be provided in a way which is of the highest professional standards, and free of the influence of any particular organisation. The new National Careers Service, which will be launched in April next year, will exemplify those principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, those whom the service inspires will need absolute confidence in its quality. I want careers guidance to be re-established as one of our most respected professions, with the same status in the public eye as doctors, lawyers and engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The careers sector is leading the development of new professional standards to which careers advisers can aspire. The Careers Profession Alliance is working to agree those standards by next year, and I continue to be immensely grateful for the hard work that they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is equally important that there is a visible, national quality standard for those organisations which provide careers guidance. It should act as a badge of the highest quality, carrying a level of prestige which the public recognises and which organisations are proud to embody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am delighted to be here today to endorse the launch of the revised matrix Standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we set out to review the existing matrix Standard, we wanted to design a badge of quality which would be fit for the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needed to be rigorous to ensure that it raised the bar on quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needed to work for organisations, by being compatible with other standards and frameworks which promote quality, so that information can be gathered once and used many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needed to reflect the changes in the careers guidance profession and it help organisations develop as their business needs changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, it needed to be flexible, so that it could be used right across the market in careers guidance which we are seeking to strengthen - from sole traders to large organisations, and from schools to Further Education colleges and universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very pleased to see that all this has been achieved.  The revised Standard now provides a more business focused structure which has been welcomed by those organisations that already use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been aligned to other measures of quality, such as the OFSTED common inspection framework.  It sets a clear expectation that careers sector organisations should ensure their staff are able to pursue the new professional standards that the public will increasingly ask for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, as someone who spends much of his working life reading official documents of wildly varying penetrability, I’m especially pleased to be able to say that the language used for the Standard has been simplified. This will make it more accessible to the widest possible range of organisations, so we can continue to encourage new providers with new ideas to enter the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like, therefore to extend my warmest thanks to all the organisations that have been involved in this important piece of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting that importance, we will expect all providers in the National Careers Service to achieve the revised Standard by April 2013. The Skills Funding Agency, which oversees the service contracts, will take a close interest in that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the proof of our success will lie in the hopes, dreams and ambitions of the countless young people and adults who are advised by careers professionals. The will expect an even higher quality of service, and it is our duty to ensure that these expectations are not only met, but exceeded. Dynamic provision to meet dynamic needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have, as I always do, spoken about careers guidance with - I hope - visible passion and enthusiasm. But you could be forgiven for asking why, with such pressure on the public finances and such a long list of public services in urgent need of reform, the Government is so keen to make further changes to the arrangements for careers guidance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s something about which my colleagues and I have thought a great deal. And, for me at least, a large part of the answer lies in the very instability of the concept of a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a time, and it ended rather less than a century or more ago, when poor people tended to have jobs, middle-class people tended to have careers and many richer people tended to be unemployed.  One of the major differences between now and then was that unemployment for a few could be viewed as a badge of honour. Gentlemen often described themselves in the census as “unemployed”, a sign that they could afford not to work rather than that they just couldn’t find work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the many, including my ancestors, unemployment meant misery and, in those far-off days, before the welfare state, a job was a sign that you and your family needed to earn enough money to feed, clothe and house yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “job” is of Anglo-Saxon origin. And for quite a lot of our history, it’s been true that a job could easily involve precisely the same thing on your first day in it as on your last maybe fifty years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, people with careers also needed to earn a wage in order to live. But the word also implied something more. Not just a certain level of education, but also a sense of progress, of upward mobility in social and material terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “career” derives from Norman French and ultimately from the Latin carrera, or “race”.  And indeed, some time after 1066, a job became what the conquered did while careers were reserved for the conquerors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even today, the question of whether a person is looking for a job or a career is essentially about how they see their place in society.  Do they see themselves as the modern equivalent of one of the Saxon swineherds who kept the pigs, or as one of the Norman barons who ate the pork?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But “career” carries other implications these days, too.  Among other things, it calls to mind the carriere, the very last and often fatal moment of a cavalry charge when the horses are given their head and devil take the hindmost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In similar vein, and, at least to those of us who remember the 1960s, the idea of a race in this context often has the word “rat” as a prefix. As good a description as any is Robert Frost’s observation that “By working faithfully eight hours a day you may eventually get to be boss and work twelve hours a day”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinction between jobs and careers is not just of historical significance.  When a young person leaves full-time education and steps out into adult life today, they have perhaps less idea of what awaits them than at any time for generations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most would no longer expect as a matter of course to follow their fathers through the factory gates, or down a coal mine or indeed into one of the professions.  Perhaps few would expect that their first job would still be what they will still be doing in a few years’ time.  Indeed, many wonder what the next fifty or sixty years will hold for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain today, nearly a million young people are unemployed - and not, in the vast majority of cases, out of choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they to find their own path as adults? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they to fill their active lives with worthwhile activity? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can they make a real contribution to making their communities and society at large better, as so many of those to whom I speak really want to? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how are they to gain that self-respect that comes from providing for your loved ones through your own efforts? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they to gain the purpose and pride that is the foundation of fulfilment? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to overstate the social, political and economic urgency of finding answers to these questions.  If we value our society, our democracy and our country, we must help people to see that they have a future within their grasp. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a boy, many old people still lived with the memory of the terror of the workhouse, where the comparative many working people ended up when they were no longer able to provide for themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workhouses had actually disappeared many years before, after Lloyd George introduced the Old Age Pensions Act in 1908. That, for the first time, offered a weekly income from the State to people aged over 70 who needed it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest anyone here marvel at the generosity of the Edwardian era, I should add that, in part due to infant mortality, average male life-expectancy at the time was only 45. It did not exceed 70 even in the mid-1970s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone born in this country today can expect to live to be over 80. And that’s not all that has changed. So, too, has the sort of life they can expect to live, at work and at home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace of economic and technical development mean that a “job for life” is an increasingly rare commodity. Corporate career paths that were well trodden by earlier generations now branch off in unexpected directions increasingly frequently. And, not least important, ordinary people’s aspirations have grown. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are not things to be regretted, especially the last. On the contrary, we should all celebrate the fact that these days young people are not simply steered into ruts and that we want them to aspire. But if we want them to turn aspirations into a real chance of fulfilling employment, we must help them to prepare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what the new National Careers Service is for and that is why it is so central to the Government’s wider ambitions for Britain and its people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why the revised Matrix Standard will offer such vital underpinning to the quality of the Service’s work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing lives by changing life changes. A nation enlivened by purposeful pride feeding individual achievement and nourishing the common good. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18305</id>
    <published>2011-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-interactive-careers-and-learning-tool-launches--2"/>
    <title>New interactive careers and learning tool launches</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Lifelong Learning Accounts will empower adults to take more control over their learning with clear information and advice on skills, careers and financial support all in one place.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new free online service launched today, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/LifeLongLearningAccount/Pages/default.aspx"&gt;Lifelong Learning Accounts&lt;/a&gt;, will help people to get improved access to jobs and career development opportunities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Account holders will have free access to a number of online tools, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A skills diagnostic tool to identify their interests, strengths and needs. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Localised course and job searches. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A CV builder. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An ‘eligibility checker’ to identify Government funding available to them &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A facility to store all their personal learner information - CVs, skills tests, job and course searches - in one easily accessible place they can share with a careers adviser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Further Education, Skills and Lifelong Learning, John Hayes said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lifelong Learning Accounts will encourage individuals to learn, and keep on learning. I want the accounts to help build a national community with the desire to seek out knowledge and skills and invest in their own success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All young people and adults should have the chance to learn and to excel in their chosen skill, getting into work and progressing in their chosen career.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="lifelong-learning"&gt;Lifelong Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as improving access to careers information and personal data, the accounts will encourage users to link up with other learners to share knowledge and experiences. Account holders will be signposted to relevant learners’ forums and communities via social media such as Facebook and Twitter.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accounts will also enable training providers to respond better to what learners want and help careers advisers to deliver targeted advice and support based on an individual’s interests.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lifelong Learning Accounts offer will continue to develop in 2012 and beyond to provide account holders with the information they want in a way that best suits them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421453&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find Find careers, learning and skills advice at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/index.htm"&gt;Directgov &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt; [](http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18291</id>
    <published>2011-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-cuts-apprenticeship-red-tape"/>
    <title>Government cuts apprenticeship red tape</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Boost for employers as Government outlines new measures on cutting red tape deterring employers from taking on apprentices.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes has announced a package of new measures to make it easier for employers to take on large numbers of apprentices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payments will be simplified, contracts streamlined and a number of data returns and audit requirements will be eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hayes said that firms that contract directly with the Government to train apprentices will now benefit from simplified payment, reporting and assessment requirements.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also receive better guidance to help them manage the recruitment, training and assessment of apprentices more efficiently and cost effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Apprenticeships are proving an increasingly effective training route for young people and companies. They are a proven way to fill skills gaps in our economy. That’s why we are boosting the number of apprenticeships and putting them at the heart of our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/further-education-skills/skills-for-sustainable-growth"&gt;Skills for Growth strategy.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But for far too long too many businesses have been put off by overly complex procedures and unnecessary layers of paperwork. We’ve worked with business to cut bureaucracy and ensure the benefits for employers, learners and the economy are maximised”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="action-plan-for-cutting-red-tape"&gt;Action plan for cutting red tape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announcing the measures at a summit hosted by the CBI today, Mr Hayes said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m determined that more employers and learners than ever should have the opportunity to benefit from our unprecedented investment in apprenticeships. Where red tape and bureaucracy deters employers from taking on apprentices, we’ll sweep it away.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That will give more firms access to the skills they need to thrive, creating new jobs and new growth, and it will give many more individuals better prospects and the chance to gain a real stake in society.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for cutting red tape for employers include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pilot for over 20 large employers who have volunteered to trial “payment by outcomes” which will eliminate a number of data returns and audit requirements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing an online plain-English toolkit for employers that clearly explains the end-to-end processes employers need to undertake for apprenticeships. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streamlining contracting arrangements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A commitment to no “in year” changes to contracting arrangements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A more proportionate approach to audit and inspection - reducing preparation time for employers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater use of electronic information, thus reducing paperwork. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A more streamlined certification process. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These measures follow the recommendations of a review led by the Employer Reference Group, the Confederation of British Industry (CBI) and large companies, including BT and TUI Travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susan Anderson, the CBI’s director for education and skills policy, said: “Cutting bureaucracy will support even more businesses to become involved and these recommendations set out the right path for reform.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They recognise that employers are primarily concerned with the day-to-day running of their businesses, and that they are committed to offering high quality training as their reputation and business success depends on this.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421064&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further education and skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/fe-and-skills-new-challenges-new-chances"&gt;New Challenges, New Chances: Next Steps in Implementing the Further Education Reform Programme&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
