<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state--14</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state--14.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State at the Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50172</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-philippines-partners-for-prosperity"/>
    <title>Britain and the Philippines: Partners for Prosperity</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here today, and especially pleased that we are in the company of Foreign Secretary del Rosario. I would like to thank the Makati Business Club, the Management Association of the Philippines and the British Chamber of Commerce for inviting me to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real thrill to be in the Philippines, on my first official visit to this beautiful country. It is almost 30 years since I was last here, in a personal capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a busy two days ahead and have just come from a very productive meeting with President Aquino, during which we discussed how Britain and the Philippines can work together to tackle today’s global challenges and support each other’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on the latter that I will focus today. I will talk first about the United Kingdom’s role in today’s changing world, before setting out why I think Britain and the Philippines can be powerful partners for prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom, like the Philippines, is an island nation – a characteristic which, unsurprisingly, has shaped how we view ourselves and the world around us. Britain is a relatively small place. We had enough but not bountiful natural resources. Combine that with a predisposition towards adventure and discovery, and it led us to build truly global networks and trade links. One thinks of names like Drake, Raleigh and Shackleton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No market was too far or too difficult; no peak too high. Indeed, the globalisation that people tend to view today as a very modern phenomenon has roots that go much deeper. The world in which the Victorians lived was far more integrated in some ways, with Britain sitting at the heart of a global economic system, including a de facto single currency – the Gold Standard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this brought us to South-East Asia. Our ties to countries like Malaysia and Singapore are perhaps best known and are still extremely strong. However, Britain’s links to the Philippines stretch back just as far. The first British Consul arrived as early as 1844. And I am reminded of one of your most famous national heroes, José Rizal, who lived in London’s Primrose Hill in the 1880s. Visitors today will find a blue plaque on the house in which he lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, and particularly in the last couple of decades, I have heard some say that Britain lost sight of the importance of South-East Asia; that our attention was diverted elsewhere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that relationships changed. But while it may have felt to some as if Britain had lost focus, we never went away. The commercial figures alone bear this out. UK trade and investment with South-East Asia today is still far higher than it is with China, despite the exceptional levels of growth and development that China has seen over the past 15 years. That said, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office has under the current Government significantly strengthened this focus, placing an even greater emphasis on our engagement with South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have rebalanced our foreign policy and diplomatic network. On a practical level, that means opening new missions, sending more diplomats to places like the Philippines. We are creating around 50 new jobs across the region. And I am sure many of you will have taken note of last month’s visit to Laos by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, to reopen the British Embassy there. The UK is now represented in all ten ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking this new approach because we see the emergence and re-emergence of economies across the world – not least the growth and development in Asia – as an opportunity. I believe there is much that we can achieve if we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is a key element of my Government’s efforts to deliver sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from an unbalanced growth model, reliant on government spending, to one based on expanding trade, encouraging inward investment, increasing the share of our economy that comes from exports, and manufacturing the goods that today’s consumers want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to meet our ambitious target to double exports to £1 trillion a year by 2020, we need to grow our exports by eight percent a year. Some of these will go to traditional markets like the European Union, but we are looking increasingly to fast-growing economies in places like South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Europe, the UK is leading the efforts to open up the EU market to trade with other nations. Growth may be slow in Europe – the forecasts suggest we can expect only 0.4 per cent next year – but it is still the biggest marketplace in the world, doing £11 trillion of business every year and encompassing 500 million consumers and 21 million companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our prosperity agenda forward won’t be easy – the global economic environment clearly remains a challenge. But it is a challenge I am confident Britain can respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we are doing within the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to embed commercial thinking should help. We are now training our diplomats in commercial as well as foreign affairs, and deploying new commercial staff across our diplomatic network. Our Ambassadors increasingly undertake secondments to companies before taking up their postings to gain firsthand commercial experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the often bleak commentary from elements of the media, the British economy has real strengths. Just think of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games held earlier this year. The Games followed hot on the heels of Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, and showcased to the world Britain’s diversity, openness, creativity and dynamism – politically, culturally and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is renowned for its excellence in financial services, the creative industries and, of course, in education. But as anyone who visited the British Business Embassy at Lancaster House in London during the Olympics would have noticed, we also remain one of the world’s most important manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s car industry, currently undergoing a renaissance, is one such example. We are home to seven global car manufacturers.  Ford, General Motors, Jaguar Land Rover and Mini you will know, but we also have big investments from Honda, Toyota and Nissan too, who produced over 480,000 vehicles in Britain last year. In total, more than one million vehicles and two million engines are produced in the UK each year, and over three-quarters of the vehicles we manufacture are exported. And enthusiasts of faster cars will know that eight Formula One teams have their headquarters in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the UK’s expertise across this and many other sectors makes us a highly compatible partner for the Philippines. I would point, for instance, to finance, where our ICT specialists are helping the Philippine Stock Exchange expand their optic fibre network across the ASEAN region; and to healthcare, where our extensive experience in Public-Private Partnerships is helping the Philippines in their plans to develop a centre of excellence in orthopaedic medicine, modelled on the Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our sectoral expertise is certainly not the only reason. What makes Britain a particularly attractive partner is, I think, the openness of our economy, our transparency and adherence to the rule of law and our firm belief in the rules-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of economic uncertainty, some are inevitably tempted to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. But protectionism is a short-term measure with long-term consequences, and in Britain we are taking the opposite approach. History has taught us that more trade, more competitiveness and making the UK open for business and open for investment are what will steer us towards sustainable economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines is heading down the same path, and I would highlight four areas that point towards this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is corruption, which remains a scourge on the global economy. It adds as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries. Those who are hardest hit are often the poorest and most vulnerable in society. That is why we are proud to have introduced the Bribery Act in the UK to address this all-too-common problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Aquino’s anti-corruption efforts and business-friendly policies such as the Integrity Initiative and the decision to join the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative are exactly the right thing to be doing – particularly now, during this period of global economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area is building the infrastructure needed to provide the foundations for long-term prosperity. Modern economies need roads, digital and cellular communications, public transport, schools and hospitals. Without them, we cannot deliver the skilled and trained workforce required to compete in the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third area is ensuring peace and stability. This is perhaps the most crucial platform for prosperity. I am proud that the UK played a small but important role in the framework agreement in Mindanao as a member of the international contact group.  And I would like to take this opportunity to repeat our deepest condolences for the terrible devastation caused there by Typhoon Pablo. Successful implementation of the framework agreement will unlock the economic potential of that area. We are also working closely with Secretary del Rosario and his team to bring about a peaceful resolution of the claims in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connected to international peace and stability is the fourth area: shunning protectionism and embracing free trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ future will not be shaped by growth in the archipelago alone. Whether it is through its overseas workers, the foreign investment that can create jobs, or its export markets abroad, it is clear that future prosperity here will be based on partnerships. This agenda is moving in the right direction.  But I think we can go further and faster. Agreeing a free trade agreement between the EU and the Philippines would be a valuable step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this policy prescription is good for your economy. But it is also vital for your broader development. International trade and investment is not just the best route to development; history tells us it is the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am speaking to you here today because I think – in fact I am certain – that the relationship between Britain and the Philippines can play an important part in promoting our mutual prosperity. We have much in common, and economies that rely on a strong and open global economy. We are democracies, with a strong attachment to human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today Secretary del Rosario marked this growth by signing a joint plan of action that will take our relationship to a new level. This is a genuinely exciting proposition. Our partnership will help to shape the business environment – working together on issues like anti-corruption, competitiveness, economic reform, a low-carbon economy and building awareness about the opportunities for trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade between our countries currently stands at around £1.1 billion. That is impressive, but is I think a fraction of what it can be, particularly when you consider just how fast your country is growing. In this year’s third quarter, growth in the Philippines reached 7.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joint action plan should help us to realise this potential. But we as governments can only do so much. Ultimately, it is businesses that will drive growth. We need your help to generate interest, build awareness and deliver projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore pleased that we have with us today some excellent examples of successful companies operating here –like Standard Chartered Bank, Marks and Spencer and Debenhams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On visas – not always an easy subject – I know that we have a fast, fair and efficient service here, and that we are opening new services to facilitate quick and easy travel for business via Saturday openings, a premium service and a new visa application centre in Cebu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sign that we are indeed open to business is the large number of Filipino overseas workers that are employed in the UK, who are making a valuable contribution to our economy but also sending back remittances to family in the Philippines. Their contribution cuts across many sectors, but is particularly evident in health and care work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that our new visa services will lead to many more visitors travelling between our countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help bring this about, I will sign a new air services agreement later today with Secretary Abaya, and meet Ramon Ang and Philippines Airlines, who hope to start direct flights to London soon. And, incidentally, their passengers will probably be arriving on new aircraft made partly in Britain, following the announcement by Philippines Airlines in August of a $7 billion order from Airbus for over 50 new aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to share our policy experience in infrastructure development, energy and Public-Private Partnerships so you can learn from our experiences, our successes and, occasionally, our mistakes. When President Aquino visited London in the summer, he went to St Pancras Station, a successful example of how well Public-Private Partnerships can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope what you have heard today is a clear indication of the UK’s role in today’s global economy, of what is happening here in the Philippines and, most importantly, a compelling vision for how Britain and the Philippines can be partners for prosperity, looking to the future with confidence and optimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit is just one of what I am confident will be many high-level visits in the coming months. I know that my colleague, the Foreign Secretary William Hague, is keen to visit in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the rest of my programme, and – with your agreement – I will not leave it another 30 years before I return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18382</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-mongolia-round-table-discussions-held-in-london"/>
    <title>UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions held in London</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 28 November, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire hosted Damba Gankhuyag, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Mongolia for the tenth UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks focused on commercial relations, foreign policy issues and defence cooperation, with the UK and Mongolia ultimately signing a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to increase defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU is aimed at supporting Mongolian defence reform, in light of its peacekeeping activities in UN operations and its recently joining the OSCE. Through modernising equipment, Mongolia hopes to become even more efficient in supporting international operations in less stable regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global partner, Mongolia is becoming ever closer to the UK, with increasing trade and cultural links. The Minister discussed how best to share the UK’s experience of cultivating and managing investment in both directions to improve bilateral trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks saw the UK and Mongolia strengthen their relationship, on the eve of celebrating the fiftieth Anniversary of diplomatic relations next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI hosted a business session in the afternoon, which was attended by a large number of business representatives discussing Mongolia’s extractive industries, mutually beneficial opportunities and Stock Exchange collaboration. The talks were concluded by a session on education cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the tenth UK-Mongolia Round Table. Held every two years, the talks form a key part of the UK – Mongolia relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35447</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/anglo-korean-society-dinner"/>
    <title>Anglo-Korean Society Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Warwick for that introduction. I would also like to thank Baroness Perry, who is the reason we are able to meet here in Parliament.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to speak to you this evening, so soon after my visit to South Korea. It was a real thrill to set foot in Korea for the first time, and to do so as we prepare to mark 130 years of diplomatic relations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bonds between our two countries are longstanding-something I was reminded of recently when I heard of the Korean War Veterans Association’s campaign to commission a war memorial here in Britain, which I am sure everyone in this room would support.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few decades the Republic of Korea has transformed itself. You have become the world’s twelfth-largest economy and a member of the G20; the first nation to transition from aid recipient to membership of the OECD Donors Assistance Committee.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are an economic miracle, a thriving democracy and a growing voice for good in the world today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these characteristics that make it so important for Britain to build a strategic partnership with Korea - one in which we work together, across the board, to achieve our common goals.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are, of course, watching the build-up to the Presidential elections with interest. It seems it will be a close contest. But regardless of who wins on 19 December, we look forward to continuing our close relationship with the new Korean government.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few minutes I want to explain what we have done over the past year to consolidate and build our strategic partnership, but also to consider what more we need to do.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new chapter in relations  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last twelve months have seen an unprecedented stepping up of co-operation between the United Kingdom and Korea.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have deployed more diplomatic staff in Seoul, and British Ministers are visiting more frequently.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, visited Korea in March, with Jeremy Browne following two months later. The then-Defence Minister Peter Luff was in Seoul in June; Energy and Climate Change Minister Greg Barker in October; and Lord Howell, the Foreign Secretary’s personal adviser on energy and resource security, just last week.  Korea was the first Asian country that I visited as a Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have hosted several high-profile Korean visitors here in London, including Trade Minister Bark, Deputy Minister for Political Affairs Kim Kyou-hyun, your Six Party Talks representative Lim Sung Nam, and senior politicians Sohn Hak-kyu and KIM Moon Soo.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These expanded contacts have helped us to drive forward our relationship like never before.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Host-to-Host agreement we signed in March is increasing commercial co-operation ahead of the 2014 Asian Games in Incheon, the 2015 World Student Games in Gwangju, and the Pyeongchang Winter Olympics in 2018. British company Populous designed the main stadium for the Asian Games, and others such as Colt are plugged into the Incheon supply chain.  The success of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games has left us well-placed to share our experience and to win contracts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On defence, we announced in March that Korean Daewoo Ship and Maritime Engineering would build four new tankers for the Royal Navy, a deal worth £460 million. Shortly afterwards Korea announced that Rolls Royce would supply engines for the next generation of Korean frigates, worth $120 million. We hope to continue to expand this relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June we launched our joint Youth Mobility Scheme, an initiative which in 2013 will enable up to 1000 young people from Korea to live and work in the UK for up to two years.  It grants the same rights to British young people, an opportunity I sincerely hope many will take advantage of.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And during my visit, I met some new North Korean settlers benefitting from our ‘English for the Future’ programme, which is helping to develop the English language skills they need to compete in today’s jobs market.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe we can do more.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scope to do more on security  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to tackle pressing international problems should be a high priority.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month’s inaugural UK-Korea Strategic Dialogue, which I was pleased to attend the opening of, provided an excellent vehicle to begin this. It was also very timely, as Korea prepares to take its seat on the UN Security Council next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central to our discussions were Security Council priorities such as the Middle East Peace Process, Syria, Iran and, of course, North Korea - on which I believe Britain can offer a valuable insight, given our presence in Pyongyang. Over the next year, I will be taking a personal interest in ensuring that the UK works closely with Korea to progress our common concerns.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to have a truly strategic relationship we need to look beyond these immediate priorities to the issues that will affect us in the longer-term.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is perhaps the most important of these. By spending two percent of GDP on green growth every year for the past four years; by putting in place domestically-binding emissions targets; and by becoming the first Asian country to pass emissions trading legislation, Korea is showing strong regional leadership  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to this your winning bid to host the Green Climate Fund, and the successful launch of Global Green Growth Institute, and it is clear that you are not just regional leaders on climate change - you are global leaders. New Song Do will be an excellent location for the Green Climate Fund, and I am delighted that Britain will take on the role of Vice President of the Global Green Growth Institute Assembly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are other issues to focus on too. I strongly believe that South Korea can be a powerful voice on human rights, for example - in its neighbourhood and beyond.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a shared commitment to international peacekeeping, having both contributed to efforts in Afghanistan, Lebanon, Haiti and the Horn of Africa. The Korean National Assembly’s recent decision to deploy a contingent of military engineers to South Sudan is welcome. I hope that Korea will continue to expand its efforts in this area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Korea are active international donors, so we have a shared interest in ensuring that aid is used effectively. Korea is uniquely placed, given its own experience of development, to play a key role in the dialogue between developing and donor countries to help us achieve this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should also work more closely on cyber security. It will not be easy to find an international consensus on rules of the road to guide future behaviour in cyberspace, and to combat the worst abuses of it. But the active engagement of countries like yours will help to take us a step closer. We are looking forward to the cyber conference in Korea next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer partners for prosperity  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the prosperity agenda, too, we have much to gain from closer co-operation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned from Korea last month fascinated by the sheer dynamism of its economy. I am keen to make more British companies excited by the opportunities this dynamism creates - especially new exporters and SMEs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I am pleased that next February, UK Trade and Investment will run a week-long series of events across Britain, ‘Opportunity Korea’, aiming to do just that. British companies are already coming on board and I am personally keen to play a part in ensuring its success.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we need your help to spread the message that Korea is a place with opportunities worth exploring. I would encourage businesses here today with experience of Korea to get involved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU-Korea Free Trade Agreement could also provide a significant boost to our commercial relationship. Of course, it needs to be implemented in a way that does not harm business, but if we get it right it could add £49 billion to EU Korea bilateral trade over the next 20 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common understanding  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we work more together, our countries are also developing a greater common understanding. That is important because, like any relationship, you work best together when you know each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of this year, our Embassy in Seoul commissioned a survey of Korean views of the UK. There were some hugely positive messages to come out of this - not least that participants between the ages of 18 and 30 identified Britain as their favourite overseas country. The enthusiasm for the UK - a genuine warmth I felt when I visited - was clear to see.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the survey also brought out traditional themes. People identified Britain as a “nation of gentlemen” - with grand architecture, a Royal Family and dreary weather.  English football’s Premier League also made an appearance, as did Harry Potter.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the stereotype extended into slightly more unhelpful territory. That behind our castle walls, we Brits are technophobes lacking in creativity and ideas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London 2012 started to challenge these perceptions, showing what today’s Britain is really like: diverse, open, connected, creative, dynamic. I know that message was not lost on our Korean friends.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shortly after the international spotlight had been fixed on the UK, it shifted quickly East - to Korea, to Seoul, and, ultimately, to Gangnam.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am talking, of course, about K-pop sensation ‘Psy’, whose “Gangnam Style” has taken the world, and Britain, by storm.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People across the globe - from members of our Royal Family to the UN Secretary General - have been embracing the rapper’s equestrian dance moves. You will be relieved to hear that I will not be inflicting my own rendition upon you this evening.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being serious for a moment, I think that Psy’s music has given the world, and people here in Britain, a glimpse of the dynamism and vibrancy of modern Korea. It has shown a nation of colour, creativity and confidence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I would like to end today by saying that I see Psy’s success as representing just one small fragment of today’s Global Korea.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are already a world leader in the business world, with companies like Hyundai, Kia, LG and Samsung, household names. As “Gangnam Style” has demonstrated, your music is global too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it should not stop there, and I don’t think it will. With your membership of the G20, your forthcoming role on the UN Security Council and your leadership on issues like climate change - you are becoming a truly global nation in the political sphere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you look to the years ahead, I hope you will view Britain as one of your closest partners. I am sure that the Anglo-Korean Society will help to ensure that you do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35446</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/constituent-parts-of-the-uk-and-membership-of-the-european-union"/>
    <title>Constituent parts of the UK and membership of the European Union</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May I firstly congratulate the Honourable Member for Glasgow North for securing this debate today and the Honourable Members from both sides of the House for their contributions to it and for the insight it has provided on this critical issue.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need not remind Honourable Members that the United Kingdom’s membership of the European Union touches the lives of all our citizens.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of our trade is with the EU - total exports to the EU in 2011 were £234 billion. The single market underpins a large portion of our economy, allowing our businesses to trade freely across a market of some half a billion people.  It facilitates collective action on issues that are too big for any one nation to tackle on its own. It magnifies our voice in the world on pressing international questions, such as the current situation in the Middle East or our concerns over Iran’s nuclear ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the United Kingdom, of course, that is the Member State: it is named in the European Union’s fundamental treaties as such. And it is the Government of the United Kingdom that must therefore negotiate in the EU’s various formations in the best interests of all its citizens.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we take into account the interests of the devolved administrations when formulating the UK’s position in EU negotiations which touch on the areas of policy that fall to the Scottish and Welsh Governments and the Northern Ireland Executive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits of devolution in EU negotiations  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good for people and businesses in Northern Ireland, Scotland and Wales, as well as England. It means that they all have a strong voice in the formulation of policy that matters to them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the voting weight and the capability and credibility of the UK’s negotiations in the EU are mobilised in the service of all UK citizens. But that does not mean the devolved administrations are only involved in EU policy when we are coming up with an agreed negotiating position for the UK. This Government has been open to having Ministers from the Devolved Administrations in the room, where appropriate, during the negotiations themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current devolution arrangements allow the special circumstances of Northern Ireland, Scotland and Wales to be championed by one of the largest and most influential Member States. Scottish independence, with a complex accession negotiation and no guarantee of favourable terms of membership at the end of it, would inevitably put a stop to that. Those advocating splitting off from the UK need to be clear about what that means in practice and use evidence to set out their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independence and EU accession  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have heard this morning, some advocate a fundamental reworking of the existing constitutional settlement that so benefits the people of the UK.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who argue for an independent Scotland suggest that only independence will give their nation a voice in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their argument is underpinned by the assertion - and it is only an assertion - that an independent Scotland would simply continue in membership of the EU, automatically inheriting the same arrangements that pertain to the UK now. We learnt only a few weeks ago, as we have also heard this morning - as the SNP was forced to reveal following a Freedom of Information request - that it had not previously commissioned any legal advice on an independent Scotland’s place in the EU. Yet the SNP has been making these assertions for several years while in Government. Many will find it absolutely astonishing that while seeking to make their case for splitting Scotland from the UK the SNP have been basing their facts on unfounded assertions rather than cold facts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not need to remind honourable members that the UK has managed to negotiate, over the years, exemptions from membership of the euro and from the Schengen common visa area, ensuring that the UK can maintain control over its own monetary and border policies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition honourable members will be only too aware of the importance of the UK’s rebate, negotiated with great skill and determination over twenty-five years ago. The rebate continues to ensure that the UK taxpayer is relieved of some of the burden of supporting some of the most imbalanced parts of the EU budget, which at the moment is of great concern to us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the UK has a permanent opt out from the euro, from the Schengen border free zone, a permanent rebate on our net contributions to the EU budget, a choice whether to join new EU laws in justice and home affairs and a protocol on how the Charter of Fundamental Rights applies to the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if Scotland left the UK and applied to join the EU all of these would be subject to negotiation, and there is no guarantee whatsoever that Scotland would obtain any of these special rights that the UK currently enjoys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is precisely the UK’s weight and influence, as one of the largest Member States that has helped us to succeed in negotiating such arrangements. And Scotland, like England, Northern Ireland and Wales, derives enormous advantage from them.  So I can see why the SNP is so keen to suggest to those voting in the referendum before the end of 2014 that they would simply continue in the event of independence, as if nothing had changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fact is that if Scotland became independent, everything would change. Independence is not simply an extension of the devolution arrangements that have worked so well. It is not merely a further point on the constitutional continuum. It is a fundamental change - a definitive split from the rest of the UK, an irreversible step. Independence would bring devolution to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As set out in the FCO’s Memorandum to the Foreign Affairs Committee inquiry into a separate Scotland, independence would create a new state - one that would have to take its place on an already crowded international stage. England, Northern Ireland and Wales would continue the international legal personality of the UK; Scotland, having decided to leave the UK, would start afresh. The overwhelming weight of international legal precedent underscores this point. There are many examples of this: one is India and Pakistan - where following independence India continued the UN membership and Pakistan joined as a new state. Another is the USSR where Russia continued the legal personality of the USSR and the other Former Soviet Union states were treated as new states. There is Ethiopia and Eritrea; and there is Sudan and South Sudan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That new state would need to decide which international organisations it wanted to belong to, in the context of its overall foreign policy. Obviously, it could not simply assert its membership of any of those organisations. The most likely scenario by far is that an independent Scotland would have to apply to join the EU as a new state, involving negotiation with the rest of the UK and other Member States, the outcome of which cannot be predicted. Scotland would no longer be represented with a permanent seat on the UN Security Council. Nor would a separate Scotland qualify for the G8 or the G20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Government is not alone in taking a factual and legally based approach to the issue. Jose Manuel Barroso, President of the European Commission made clear that “a new state, if it wants to join the European Union, has to apply to become a member like any state.” Recent correspondence between the Spanish Government and Commissioner Reding on this issue also supported this interpretation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In simple terms, an independent Scotland could not just assert that it would be a member of the club - the other members would need to agree as well. The comments of the Spanish Foreign Minister, Jose Manuel Garcia-Margallo, to the Spanish Parliament on the 23rd of October must be noted: “in the hypothetical case of independence, Scotland would have to join the queue and ask to be admitted, needing the unanimous approval of all Member States to obtain the status of a candidate country.” What the Spanish Foreign Minister was referring to was the list of candidate countries wanting to join the EU - Macedonia, Iceland, Serbia, Montenegro and Turkey.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the remarks of a Foreign Minister of a major EU Member State with an obvious interest in this issue. The Scottish Government must be prepared to respond and be upfront about the uncertainties surrounding their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an independent Scotland would not simply ‘continue’ automatically in membership of the EU. The EU Treaties would have to be amended to allow Scotland to join; and that would involve a negotiation. What terms would it secure? Would Scotland be able to avoid the commitment to join the euro or the Schengen area that every new Member State since 1992 has taken on? The simple answer is: we do not know. None of this is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the SNP, the UK Government is taking a transparent approach to analyzing the legal issues, including by engaging with eminent legal experts. On 2 October this year, the Advocate General for Scotland - one of the UK Government’s three Law Officers - delivered a speech at the Edinburgh Centre for Constitutional Law, setting out the Government’s initial view on the legal questions. The Government has also made clear that we will provide detailed evidence and analysis so that people in Scotland can make an informed decision about whether to stay in the UK and the implications in leaving it. We will publish this analysis over the course of 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the clear position of the UK Government that Scotland is better off in the UK, and the UK is better off with Scotland in it. We are backing up that position with a robust programme of analysis and evidence. Those advocating independence for Scotland are making assertions that suit their argument, with no solid foundation in fact.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35589</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-affairs-committee-report-on-the-role-of-the-commonwealth"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Committee report on the role of the Commonwealth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire, has commented on the publication, today, of the Foreign Affairs Committee’s report on the role and future of the Commonwealth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome today’s report by the Foreign Affairs Committee into the role and future of the Commonwealth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government is committed to strengthening our engagement with, and role within, the Commonwealth. We believe a strong Commonwealth is important to our future prosperity and the national interests of all its member states. We are committed to efforts to strengthen and reform the organisation so that it remains relevant into the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Committee’s interest in the Commonwealth and this report are therefore timely. We will study the recommendations, which should help inform our policy as we implement the Commonwealth modernisation and reform agenda, and as we look ahead to the next Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting a year from today. We will provide a full departmental response to the report in the New Year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35445</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-in-latin-and-central-america"/>
    <title>Britain in Latin and Central America</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my first visit to El Salvador. It is a pleasure to be here, and a privilege to address the IEESFORD diplomatic academy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would first like to repeat my message of last week and express my deepest condolences to the families and friends of those who lost their lives, or were injured, as a result of the earthquake in Guatemala. I know the tremors were felt here too.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake has been a tragic reminder of the very real threat this region faces day-to-day. The brave response of those on the ground, and the offer of support from countries across the region, has been an example to us all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, the British Foreign Secretary, William Hague, gave a speech at Canning House in London, on the United Kingdom’s relations with Latin America. His speech marked the opening of a new chapter in Britain’s approach to this region; that, and I quote, “the UK’s retreat from Latin America is over”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come here today to reaffirm this message, and to set out what this new chapter means for the United Kingdom and the countries of Central America.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historic partners   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has enjoyed a long and very special bond with Latin America.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Canning, the nineteenth-century Foreign Secretary and Prime Minister after whom Canning House was named, remains perhaps the most striking example. Under his leadership, Britain was among the very first countries to recognise newly independent Argentina, Colombia, Mexico, and, of course, Brazil, whose independence Canning himself helped to negotiate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Canning was certainly not the only Englishman to see the huge potential of Latin America. Weetman Pearson, one of the great Victorian entrepreneurs and an early proponent of globalisation, built railroads and harbours in Colombia, Mexico and Chile.  He also had ventures in oil and energy, illuminating Mexico and Chile with energy generated by the countries’ first hydroelectric plants.  Visitors to Veracruz can see a statue of Pearson, which was unveiled ten years ago to mark the centenary of its port.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearson’s endeavours reflected our strong trade links: by the time of the First World War, 50 percent of foreign investment in Latin America came from Britain, and 20 percent of its trade was with Britain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European and Central American economies had been closely linked since the Industrial Revolution. When we started importing jute from India, for example, the blue indigo dye used to colour textiles - particularly shirts - came from Central America, principally El Salvador. The term “blue collar workers”, which originated at that time, is still used in English to this day.&lt;br&gt;
By the late twentieth century, however, Britain had lost sight of the importance of Latin America. We had shut Embassies, withdrawn diplomats, found other trading partners.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s return to Latin America   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when this Government came into office, we inherited a relationship with Latin America that was well short of its potential. That was bad for Britain and, I think, bad for Latin America.&lt;br&gt;
It meant that we in Britain were not making the most of our relations with one of the world’s leading engines of economic growth. Latin America has a combined GDP greater than that of India and Russia together, with growth rates forecast at around four to five percent for the next five years. The region’s middle class is already bigger than China’s and India’s combined.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its countries are also playing an increasing role in international affairs. Guatemala currently has a seat on the UN Security Council, and will be joined from January by Argentina - who will take over from Colombia. Eight Latin American states are currently members of the UN Human Rights Council. Countries like Brazil are increasing their development co-operation in Africa.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from a Latin American perspective, it meant losing out on all that Britain has to offer - whether making the most of British expertise in energy, education or financial services, or taking full advantage of the UK’s position as a springboard to the EU’s Single Market of over five hundred million customers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So over the past two years, the Foreign Secretary has led Britain’s most ambitious effort to strengthen our ties with Latin America since the days of Canning.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the difficult economic situation we face, we have opened a new Consulate General in Recife in Brazil, and we are on track to re-open our Embassy in Paraguay next year. We have sent more diplomats to Brazil, Mexico, Columbia, Chile and Peru - by creating, for instance, a new network of Prosperity Officers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we recognise that there is no substitute for high-level engagement. So we are visiting more.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been over forty Ministerial visits to Latin America since this Government came into office - including those by the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister to Mexico, and the Prime Minister’s visit to Brazil in September, with the largest ever trade and education delegation.  I joined him on that trip - my first as a Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, Ministers from no fewer than ten Whitehall Departments have touched down in Latin American countries so far this year. We have also hosted several major inward visits, President Santos of Colombia and the incoming President of Mexico among them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have increased co-operation at the highest levels with Brazil, for example through our Host-to-Host programme on the Olympics, and with Mexico during their very successful Presidency of the G20.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America has been crucial to our refocus too. We have, for example, strengthened our Embassy in Panama, and we are increasing our resources for engaging with Honduras. The Foreign Secretary visited Panama last year, as did my predecessor, Jeremy Browne, who also went to Costa Rica. Panamanian President Martinelli has visited the UK twice in the past year, and Ministerial contact with Guatemala has also increased.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is perhaps most evident right here: I am in El Salvador first and foremost to re-open the British Embassy, which I will do this afternoon.  Since it was closed nine years ago, El Salvador has been the largest economy in the world without a British Embassy. That is something we had to put right.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that in the short time we have been back, much has already been achieved. We have worked more closely on climate change and prison reform, and on preventing violence against women, which I know is a priority for the government here, including the First Lady.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, our Ambassador launched the GREAT campaign to spread the message that Britain is open for business. Shortly afterwards, the Embassy marked Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee. And we held a series of events around the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games, with more to follow to help build a lasting legacy here. Incidentally, I should offer my congratulations to El Salvador on the design of your Olympic uniform, which quite rightly won plaudits around the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These activities are only a sign of what is to come. I say this because I believe that it is strongly in the interests of the UK to work more closely with Central America across the bilateral agenda. That means engaging more on security, as well as prosperity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the security challenge   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we should not exaggerate the security challenge that Central America continues to face, nor should we downplay it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belize, Guatemala, El Salvador and Honduras have some of the highest homicide rates in the world, linked mainly to the activities of criminal gangs. Central America, situated as it is between drug producers to the south and major consumers to the north, clearly faces significant challenges. We recognise this, which is why co-operation between security authorities and Britain’s Serious Organised Crime Agency remains a crucial part of our work in the region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central American governments are taking positive steps to tackle organised crime and the drugs trade, and we want to support your efforts - not just because it is in the interests of Central America, but because your security problems affect Britain too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons we have stepped up our involvement with SICA, the Central American Integration System - which is, I know, based just down the road from here. Last November we committed an extra £250,000 in funding for SICA projects, ranging from training police in Belize to supplying equipment for counter-narcotics work in Costa Rica and Honduras.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be meeting SICA representatives tomorrow and am delighted to announce today that Britain, currently a “Friend of SICA”, has applied to become an Extra-Regional Observer. This demonstrates how seriously we take your efforts to tackle violence, organised crime and insecurity. If our application is agreed, I hope our strengthened commitment will enable us to work more closely with SICA, its Friends and Observers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time that Central America is underpinning its own security, it is playing an increasingly important role outside its neighbourhood.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costa Rica and Guatemala are providing a strong voice on human rights internationally in their roles as members of the UN Human Rights Council.  Central American countries have been strong supporters of the growing international consensus on Syria. It is important that your voices are heard, not least because you have a wealth of experience you can share with the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to hear that El Salvador is considering increasing its international peacekeeping contribution, partly as a way of thanking the United Nations for the role it played in helping to draw up the Peace Accords to end the civil war in 1992. This is an important and welcome step. I know that El Salvador already participates in nine peacekeeping missions, from MINUSTAH in Haiti to UNIMIT in East Timor.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central American governments are taking a constructive approach on a range of international issues. Many of you have shown a real willingness to listen to others’ views, including on issues like the Falkland Islands. We are grateful to those countries that allowed the Islanders’ representatives to visit recently and set out their case for determining their own political status and being allowed to live in peace.  We very much hope that Argentina too will one day listen to their views.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting our mutual prosperity   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the security situation in the region continues to improve, it will reinforce the conditions for trade and investment to flourish. British exports to Latin America as a whole increased by fourteen percent last year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America is already an important market for trade, and the figures bear this out.  It has a combined GDP of over $167 billion, and its countries represent a market of close to forty-two million people.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Panama, which is growing at an impressive rate. Its GDP is projected to grow by 9.5 percent this year, and according to the Latin Business Index it ranks second in Latin America for ease of doing business. Consider Nicaragua, whose investment agency, ProNicaragua, was named by a World Bank study earlier this year as the top investment facilitator globally.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive stories like these are helping to attract foreign investment to the region. And the opportunities, I know, are significant - particularly in infrastructure, energy, green technology, education and retail.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore unsurprising that British companies are already operating successfully - including familiar British names such as Lloyds Insurance, BT, BUPA, Unilever, GlaxoSmithKline and JCB. The UK is already the world’s biggest investor in Panama.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, UK exports of goods to SICA countries totalled just £355 million last year. I think there is scope to increase this significantly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why within the last year we arranged a trade mission to Guatemala and El Salvador, and brought a Costa Rican business delegation to the UK.  It is why we are negotiating a new Double Taxation Agreement with Panama, which we hope to conclude by the end of the year; and why we have signed a bilateral Memorandum of Understanding with the Dominican Republic, which covers trade and investment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is why we are supporting Central American countries as they address the underlying barriers to prosperity such as corruption - by, for example, funding training in Belize to tackle money laundering.  And it is why we will continue a busy programme of high-level visits, including a landmark visit by the Lord Mayor of London to Panama next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And countries across the region can take steps to drive growth in our trade too. Ratifying the EU-Central America Association Agreement, signed in June, would have a particularly significant impact.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once implemented, its trade pillar will reduce or eliminate tariffs that Central American countries pay when exporting goods to the European Union.  This will be hugely beneficial, with gains on exports such as coffee, sugar and spices, as well as textiles and vehicle parts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, Central American signatories are expected to experience gains in national income of around $3 billion as a result of the Agreement’s trade pillar coming into force. It will also diversify your trade markets, create jobs and, ultimately, help to reduce poverty.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it will liberalise sixty-nine percent of Central America’s existing trade with the EU, saving EU exporters an estimated £68 million annually in customs duties. And by introducing new safeguards such as better protection of Intellectual Property and Geographical Indications, the Agreement will make Central America a more attractive destination for investment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the very real benefits it will bring, I was pleased to hear that on 18 October Nicaragua became the first Central American country to ratify the Association Agreement.  I would strongly encourage others to follow.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canning Agenda launched by the Foreign Secretary is just two years old. It will take time for us to rebuild the sort of relationship between the United Kingdom and Latin America that Canning would be proud of.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I think the actions we have taken have put us on the right track. And we are starting to see the benefits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America will remain a crucial part of our re-engagement. I hope that when Foreign Minister Martinez and I cut the ribbon at the new British Embassy this afternoon, it will underline Britain’s commitment to this exciting and dynamic region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that as we tackle today’s global challenges; as we work closer together on trade, counter-narcotics, international crime, on climate change, human rights and the most pressing of international issues, we will go some way to supporting our mutual prosperity in the years to come.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there is a bright future ahead for Britain and Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35573</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-burma-welcomes-aung-san-suu-kyi-s-joint-statement-on-rakhine-state-with-burmese-parliamentarians"/>
    <title>Minister for Burma welcomes Aung San Suu Kyi’s joint statement on Rakhine state with Burmese parliamentarians</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following Aung San Suu Kyi’s joint statement on Rakhine state with Burmese parliamentarians, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister of State Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the joint statement on the situation in Rakhine State from Burma’s Parliamentary Committee on Rule of Law, chaired by Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and ethnic MPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I echo the statement’s calls for increased security, respect for human rights regardless of ethnic group or religion, accountability for crimes committed, and increased humanitarian support. I also welcome its call for the issue of citizenship to be looked at urgently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to stand beside those in Burma working for freedom and democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/jpg/News/711631982/October/human-trafficking-large1"&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35442</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/promoting-rules-based-systems-for-global-economic-growth"/>
    <title>Promoting rules-based systems for global economic growth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my first visit to Wilton Park, and I am particularly pleased to have been asked to open discussions on such an important subject: how international rules and standards can help to stimulate global economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the first time we have tackled this issue in this forum. And with such a distinguished group of people here, I am confident that discussions over the next day and a half will be productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure we are all agreed that we are sailing in unchartered economic waters. Few would have predicted at the onset of the global economic crisis in 2008 the long-term impact it would have on the global economy. How we navigate our way out of the current difficulties remains open to debate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, we do know that increased and freer trade plays a major part in driving global growth. But to be sustainable and responsive to the interests of even the most vulnerable, this must respect the core values that underpin prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few minutes I will argue that a shared set of rules and standards governing the global economy is crucial to achieving this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation we face is, in many respects, daunting. Economic uncertainty is eroding business confidence and dampening growth prospects, particularly in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses, SMEs in particular, are finding it harder to access finance. Confidence in the banking sector has ebbed. The Doha global trade deal has stalled, and many countries are struggling to reduce their deficits. Growing protectionism and falling demand are impacting on business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no easy solution. Different countries will - rightly - adopt different approaches, recognising the differences in our economies. But as these problems have global implications, we should all be concerned about how we respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IMF recently announced that growth in the volume of world trade was projected to slow this year to 3.2 percent, driven by lower demand, especially in the Eurozone. GDP growth expectations for advanced economies were downgraded from 1.6 to 1.3 percent. Last month Eurozone business activity contracted at its fastest pace for almost three and a half years due to austerity measures and continued uncertainty. Vulnerable Eurozone economies are at a critical stage: Greece’s growth this year is projected to slump to minus 6.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christine Lagarde has referred to the “ripple” effect that the crisis is having on the wider economy. It stands to reason that when growth in the world’s largest economic bloc - the European Union - is faltering, it will have a knock-on effect elsewhere. Indeed, this is one of the reasons why faster-growing developing economies are also predicted to slow this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big markets of China, India, Russia, and Brazil are all experiencing slower growth. In the second quarter of 2012 China’s growth hit a three-year low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And although the IMF projections are weak, the reality could be even weaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens on one side of the world should matter to the other. When demand weakens in one part of the chain, it is felt elsewhere. In that sense, economic uncertainty is contagious, and as we have seen through the latest growth projections, no-one is immune.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that we do not all have our own individual challenges to overcome. For many countries the biggest challenge is reducing harmful deficits. For others it is rapid population shifts, high food and energy prices, or slowing export demand. These will inevitably require their own unique solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing is clear: the choices we make individually in response to these economic challenges will, in one way or another, impact on others. So we also need a co-ordinated international response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what kind of response? We recently asked businesses in the UK what they saw as the greatest challenges facing them in the global market place. Their answer was unequivocal: protectionism and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain, with its history of mercantile adventurism, has long been a strong advocate of free trade - and we have had to learn lessons along the way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that at times of economic difficulty, it can be tempting to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. It is only natural for countries to want to secure jobs and livelihoods for their own people. So we should not be surprised to have seen a rise in protectionism in recent months. Between November 2011 and June 2012, at least 110 protectionist measures were implemented globally - 89 of which came from G20 members themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be in no doubt: protectionism is a short-term response that has long-term and often unintended consequences. The current impasse in the Doha trade round is thought to be costing the world around $180 billion a year. And protectionism can often lead to tit-for-tat measures that result in an inevitable race to the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we really want to support our domestic industries, we need to make them more efficient and more competitive, rather than choosing to build a protectionist wall which will ultimately undermine competitiveness. Securing international trade agreements that open access for our businesses is the way forward - and it is a sad fact that protectionism tends to make these harder to attain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also believe that corruption remains a scourge on the global economy. It is a corrosive element with long-term economic, social and political consequences. And by adding as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries, it inflicts damage on the most vulnerable in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this is a difficult subject. Some continue to downplay its potential to damage the global economy, classing it as a necessary evil in normal business behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should not fall into this trap. Make no mistake: corruption is global. In Europe, we have had to take tough measures to deter it. In developing economies, domestic concern about corruption is also rising, as a growing private sector tries to compete with state-run and protected assets. And in some of the world’s poorest countries, the lack of strong, transparent and accountable institutions means that citizens remain unable to share in the benefits of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report by the International Chamber of Commerce, Transparency International, the UN Global Compact and the World Economic Forum provides a stark reminder of the costs of corruption to business. The report states that corruption is the biggest single obstacle to economic and social development around the world. It put the price tag at around $2.6 trillion, or 5 percent of global GDP, each year. And it is not just a question of the direct cost: corruption damages business confidence, deters investment and distorts the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the domestic and international application of rules and standards as an essential part of building the confidence the market needs. Corruption is exactly the sort of threat they can help to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on this the UK is showing global leadership. Our Bribery Act, which sets out a framework for dealing with corrupt business practices, has been a brave step to take. Indeed, it was initially met with nervousness in some quarters. But a year on, British companies are telling us that they see it as a real reputational asset in securing trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister, David Cameron, made clear in an article in the Wall Street Journal recently, if we are to successfully tackle global poverty we need a radical new approach, supporting what he calls the “the golden thread” of conditions that enable open economies and open societies to thrive: the rule of law, the absence of conflict and corruption, and the presence of property rights and strong institutions. He will make this a key focus of his role as co-chair of the UN’s High Level Panel of Eminent Persons on the Post-2015 Development Agenda, as well as for the UK’s G8 Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to these two challenges - protectionism and corruption - is therefore crucial. And I think this is where the subject of this conference comes in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current framework of global economic rules and standards covers a broad range of activity, from corporate governance, anti-corruption to competition law and rules governing trade. But the coverage, breadth and depth of these rules is patchy. Crucially, most were drawn up at a different time, when there was a different global economic dynamic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global economy is even more interconnected today that it was 50 years ago, with a range of new and influential economic actors. So there needs to be an architecture within which we can maximise the benefits of trade - one in which everyone sees the imperative to engage. This was a clear recommendation of the Prime Minister’s report to the G20 last year on global governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if we all played a game according to different rules, it would not be much of a game. Business needs the assurance of a level playing field, underpinned by basic rules, to have the confidence to engage and export - no matter where in the world you are operating.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rules are not about constraining business, and we would not back them if they were. They are about ensuring that businesses remain flexible and responsive, yet resilient enough to build a solid foundation for future global trade and economic engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to show countries that are currently hesitant that these rules are relevant, and ensure that the process through which new and existing standards are updated and developed is transparent and open to all. The architecture needs to be fit for purpose. And it will be important for key players such as the OECD to continue adapting to the changing global dynamic, while recognising that different countries are at different stages of economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should also recognise that if we disagree we risk the system breaking down, with partners reneging on their commitments and others free-riding from the sidelines. During this period of global economic stagnation, we should all be pushing for partners to implement existing commitments. At the same time, we should encourage new partners to join the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic challenges we face today are complex and multifaceted. They will require individual solutions, but - I hope I have shown this afternoon - within a collective framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are beyond the point where we can credibly argue that economic progress can be best served through isolation and protectionist policies; globalisation remains our only option. Of course, we should recognise that there is no magic bullet, and I would certainly not argue that the current rules and standards are a perfect model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing I am sure about is that economies across the world need to complement each other if we are to meet our common objective of sustained, long-term growth, in which our businesses and peoples can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to finish today by posing some practical questions. Of the global rules and standards that already exist, which need fixing most urgently, and how? What more can we do to improve enforcement? Are there areas of economic activity that fall outside the current architecture, and if so, should - and how - do we bring these in? Are there rules that are out of date and no longer applicable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not expect you to find concrete answers to these questions in the next day and a half. But I hope that in your discussions you will be able to explore comprehensively the rationale behind the rules-based economic system and how it can contribute to the global recovery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing the report Wilton Park will produce after the conference. We will study it carefully as we review our responses to these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35545</id>
    <published>2012-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-raises-violence-in-rakhine-state-with-burmese-embassy"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister raises violence in Rakhine state with Burmese Embassy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom remains deeply troubled about the further outbreaks of violence in Rakhine State and continues to urge the Burmese government to put in place measures to bring the violence to an end. Minister for Burma Hugo Swire pledged the UK’s commitment to working closely with the Burmese government, parliament and civil society, and through our development assistance, to see Burma continue its transition to democracy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in Parliament, Mr Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday I called in the Burmese Charge d’Affaires to the Foreign Office to discuss our serious concerns about the violence in Rakhine State and the casualties and displacement among Rohingya people. This follows My Right Honourable Friend the Foreign Secretary’s meeting with Burma’s Foreign Minister in New York in September, and my own meetings during the UN General Assembly. There is an urgent need for an end to the violence, for the Burmese authorities to ensure security in the region, and for humanitarian access.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35437</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/human-trafficking-reception"/>
    <title>Human Trafficking reception</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Susannah for your kind introduction, and indeed to your whole team for organising this important event with the Home Office.  The problem of human trafficking is fresh in our minds following Anti-Slavery Day last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is an area on which I have been engaged for some time.  In my previous job in the Northern Ireland Office, I was proud to work with my old friends, Anthony Steen and Baroness Butler-Sloss, to promote the good work of the Human Trafficking Foundation on both sides of the Irish border.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, my new home - the Foreign and Commonwealth Office - has a rich history of fighting slavery, human trafficking and other international violations of basic human rights - the legacy of William Wilberforce and his brave colleagues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it would be remiss of me to pass up the opportunity to earn some ‘brownie points’ with my new boss, the Foreign Secretary, by drawing your attention to his excellent, well-researched and fascinating book - ‘William Wilberforce’ by William Hague - still available in all good bookstores!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am delighted that we have such a wide range of distinguished participants here this evening to discuss how we can all work more closely on combating this particularly pernicious crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my brief remarks, I want to focus on the big picture: the global nature of human trafficking and how the international community needs to work together to combat it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will then hand over to my colleague, Mark Harper to concentrate on this government’s strategy to tackle the problem and how it is being implemented here in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to know precisely how many people directly suffer from human trafficking.  However, according to some estimates, at any given time as many as 27 million men, women and children are captive to human traffickers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put the scale of this problem in its historical context: today more people are trafficked each year than the total number of those trafficked in the 350 years of the transatlantic slave trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People talk about the abolition of slavery.  But slavery has not been abolished.  It continues on an unprecedented scale and with unparalleled barbarity.  Today, human trafficking involves not only slavery, but blackmail, kidnap, rape and murder.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the fact that slavery is universally illegal is no reason for complacency.  Human trafficking is the second most lucrative organised criminal activity in the world, worth around $36 billion annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a phenomenon that is not restricted to any particular country, region or continent, and it is certainly not restricted by national boundaries.  Many victims find themselves in countries foreign to them where they are particularly vulnerable - they may not speak the language, may have no contact with any family or friends, and may fear the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="why-we-need-to-act"&gt;Why we need to act&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are two fundamental reasons why governments should take action, and take action together.  The first is that this crime is particularly abhorrent.  It ranks among the worst forms of human rights abuse.  There is surely nothing more degrading, demeaning or dehumanising than being sold into the sex trade or being forced into manual labour and criminal activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people are trafficked for spare parts - organs that extracted by their purchaser.  Many of the victims are children, abducted from their families to fight in wars, to suffer sexual abuse, and to have their chances of a normal life robbed of them.  I believe we have a moral duty to take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason for governments to work together to fight this scourge is that it does not only affect the direct victims.  Human trafficking is the lifeblood of many organised criminal groups.  The $36 billion that it generates could well feed terrorism and trade in drugs and arms.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the effects of human trafficking are broadly felt across societies.  As governments, we have a duty to protect our citizens from these threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot effectively tackle the problem in isolation.  It is a transnational crime, and it requires a transnational response.  That is why this we are here this evening in the Locarno Room of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.  Because while the Prime Minister has made clear that fighting human trafficking is a “Coalition priority”, in order to be effective, we need to be able to work closely with other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, we want to focus on how we can break each and every link in the human trafficking chain. Let me take you through each in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="prevention"&gt;Prevention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first link in the chain is the targeting of potential victims.  To break this link, we have to reduce the vulnerability of people to human traffickers.  I am sure that Mark will go into detail about the victims that we find here in the United Kingdom.  But the vast majority of those victims originate from outside Britain.  So we want to work with governments to prevent their citizens from falling prey to traffickers in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a very basic level, this involves alleviating the conditions of vulnerability - such as poverty, lack of education, and lack of employment opportunities - that lead people into the arms of traffickers.  This is central to much of the work of our Department for International Development.  But it also runs specific programmes in South Asia and West Africa which target communities in which human trafficking is particularly prevalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevention also requires educating potential victims about the threat of human trafficking.  I understand that the vast majority of victims are deceived into captivity, being unaware of the dangers inherent in migrating to find work.  So part of our preventative work is focussed on raising awareness among vulnerable groups.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embassies and High Commissions across our network have partnered with local NGOs to this end.  For example, our embassy in Prague has launched a project with La Strada and Diaconia, both local charities, which raises awareness of human trafficking in socially excluded groups across the Czech Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transit"&gt;Transit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next link in the chain which needs to be broken is the transit of victims across borders.  For those unfortunate enough to fall prey to human traffickers, it is important that police and border officials are able to work together to prevent victims from being removed from their own countries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Police run joint operations with their counterparts across Europe and beyond.  And we are eager to expand cooperation with other law enforcement agencies across the world.  Assistant Chief Constable Olivia Pinkney and Detective Chief Inspector Nick Sumner will tell you shortly more about this good work.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further cooperation will also help to break the next chain-link: identifying trafficked individuals and their captors, rescuing the former and prosecuting the latter.  Intelligence sharing is needed to capture and convict trans-national criminals.  So we are particularly proud of the Arrest Referral Programmes that we have developed with the State Police forces in India and hope that we can set up similar programmes with other partners.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="repatriation-and-reintegration"&gt;Repatriation and reintegration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But liberating the victims and apprehending the perpetrators is by no means ‘job done’.  I am horrified by some of the bureaucracy required for victims to be able to travel home after the terrible ordeals that they have endured.  It can take many months to obtain the requisite travel documentation, which seems like pouring salt into the wound.  I sincerely hope that we can find a way of expediting the safe return of victims desperate to get home to their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final link in the chain that needs to be broken is the one connecting rescued victims with the risk of further human trafficking.  Because those returned to their communities following captivity or forced labour are especially vulnerable.  We are therefore keen to work with governments and organisations in helping to protect victims from ever being subject to human trafficking again.  That is why we are funding a reintegration centre in Lao Cai, Vietnam, to support girls rescued from trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government cares deeply about human trafficking.  It has been highlighted as a Coalition Priority, the Prime Minister is personally engaged on the issue, and last week the Foreign Secretary spoke about his commitment to tackling the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of this commitment is an acknowledgement that that human trafficking is a transnational threat that requires a transnational response.  As the Foreign Secretary said, it is a threat ‘that we cannot inure ourselves against through unilateral action alone’. I will hand over to Mark to go through our own government strategy and where we require international coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have invited you here this evening because we want to work with you - NGOs, charities, representatives of other governments.  We want to explore where we can deepen our cooperation and collaboration.  Human trafficking is a plague that affects all of our countries - it fuels organised crime, it exacerbates the drugs trade, and it endangers our citizens.  But worst of all, it destroys the lives of some of the world’s most vulnerable people, stripping them of their freedom, their dignity, and their humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 19th century, Great Britain was at the forefront of efforts to abolish the slave trade.  With courage commitment and tenacity, it was able to change global norms and have the practice universally repudiated.  Now in the 21st Century, slavery is less visible than it was then, but we do not kid ourselves that it has gone away.  We realise that we must work together with the same courage, commitment and tenacity to ensure that we finish the work that we began to eradicate this hideous crime in all of its forms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
