<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state-universities-and-science-department-for-business-innovation-and-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state-universities-and-science-department-for-business-innovation-and-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for Universities and Science</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47153</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-billion-investment-for-uk-science-and-research"/>
    <title>£1 billion investment for UK Science and Research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash boost comes from the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (UK RPIF), which will deliver over £1 billion to support the development of new facilities and projects in areas including life sciences, energy and advanced manufacturing. The projects announced today are:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A £48 million partnership between Manchester University, Christie Hospital and Cancer Research UK to develop the Institute for Cancer Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An £85 million partnership between UCL (University College London) and the Great Ormond Street Hospital for The Centre for Children’s Rare Disease Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £32 million partnership between Queen’s University Belfast, The Atlantic Philanthropies and a Wellcome-Wolfson Capital Award to deliver the next phase of the Institute of Health Sciences. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £34 million partnership between the University of Nottingham and GlaxoSmithKline to support the Centre of Excellence in Sustainable Chemistry. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £38 million partnership between Swansea University, British Petroleum (BP), and TATA Steel Europe for the development of the Energy Safety Research Institute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £60 million partnership between Brunel University, TWI and other companies to develop a National Research Centre for Structural Integrity. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £150 million partnership between Imperial College London and Voreda to contribute to the development of a major new campus adjacent to the White City regeneration area.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This takes the  total number of projects supported by the fund to 14.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities will shortly be able to bid for the remaining £80 million of public investment from the fund. This must be matched by at least double from private sources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is fantastic that our top businesses and top charities are queuing up to collaborate with our world-class universities. They want to work together to deliver innovation, commercialisation and growth, which will help make sure the UK competes and thrives in the global race.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The winning projects will tackle the key issues we face - like fighting disease, ensuring energy efficiency and improving infrastructure - for the benefit of all.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK RPIF was first launched with £100 million of public finance in May 2012 and, in response to the large number of high-quality bids, the Government recently tripled the public support to £300 million. All projects have to include private funding from industry or the charitable sector worth a minimum of double the public contribution - making more than £1 billion of investment in total.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UKRPIF is managed and allocated by Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE), working in collaboration with devolved counterparts.  All proposals are assessed by an independent assessment panel.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/whatwedo/rsrch/howfundr/ukresearchpartnershipinvestmentfund20122015/#d.en.72999."&gt;HEFCE’s fund details&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/More-than-1-billion-to-be-invested-in-UK-science-and-research-68276.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: More than £1 billion to be invested in UK science and research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/science"&gt;BIS Science &lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47568</id>
    <published>2012-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uuk-conference-a-world-without-boundaries"/>
    <title>UUK conference: "A world without boundaries"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s great to join you all at Keele as our hosts celebrate their 50th anniversary. Recalling the creation of universities back in the 1960s reminds us of an optimistic sector in one of its most ambitious periods. Today, even during this era of inevitable austerity, I believe that we can still be ambitious and optimistic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-place-of-he-in-the-nation"&gt;The place of HE in the nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 has certainly been a big year for Higher Education, with our reforms coming into effect. I recognise that inevitably some stress and uncertainty accompanies changes on this scale. The Government appreciates the maturity of the sector and the leadership of vice chancellors in what are, for some, challenging times. In particular, I appreciate the Government’s close working relationship with UUK. We cannot always agree, but our discussions are always open and founded on mutual trust. More than that, they are based on a shared belief that our universities are a tremendous national asset which we need to sustain and to grow.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In popular consciousness, of course, 2012 will be remembered for the Olympics and Paralympics - which gave our universities some excellent opportunities to demonstrate their place in national life. I congratulate UUK for illustrating the many connections between universities and the Games. We all think especially of Usain Bolt and his fellow Jamaican sprinters thanking their Birmingham University hosts after capturing all the medals in the men’s 200 metres final. But there have also been plenty of examples of volunteering and community engagement. We can all be proud of the university research which improved the performance of our athletes and the university-designed equipment which gave them a competitive edge. Now, the University of Worcester has launched a new degree programme for those wanting to study and ultimately work in disability sport.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debt of Olympians and Paralympians to HE is just one example of a wider debt of many of us to our universities. Last week, I was at the annual British science festival, sharing the excitement around the discovery of the Higgs Boson and most recently the discovery that redundant DNA is not so redundant after all. Again, British academics and universities are at the heart of these breakthroughs. With your contributions to the intellectual life of our nation, to educating the next generation, and to innovation and research, universities are more central to our society than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-our-national-assets-cyber-security"&gt;Protecting our national assets: cyber security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HE’s growing economic importance was made plain at the recent launch of the Government’s cyber security guidance because quite simply, much of the UK’s intellectual property resides in our universities. Only this month, Oxford University confirmed that its online security had been compromised by a cyber attack - just a day after the Cambridge University network experienced disruption. The Government will work closely with universities to ensure that the UK’s higher education system has a visible and credible international reputation for protecting commercially sensitive research from the growing risks posed via cyber space. But we can go further than just protection. Although UK universities are potential victims of cyber attacks, they can also be a large part of the long term solution. GCHQ, the EPSRC and BIS recently recognised eight UK universities as centres of academic excellence in cyber security. There is real scope to translate this knowledge into commercial opportunities and export earnings, while - for graduates - there are good prospects in cyber jobs as demand increases, providing of course they develop the right skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I can announce the first academic research institute - receiving total investment worth Â£3.8 million - to improve understanding of the science behind cyber threats. This new facility, based at UCL, will draw on university expertise in both technological and behavioural disciplines. Academic teams from UCL, Imperial, Newcastle and Royal Holloway will be the first beneficiaries of research money. The institute opens for business next month. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-kinds-of-impact"&gt;Other kinds of “impact”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, part of the case for well-funded universities - as suggested by the example of cyber security - is their economic benefit. But I readily acknowledge that this is not what drives many academics, for whom intellectual curiosity is the main motive. It is a noble motive, which must be respected. However, it does help when academics and universities demonstrate how their research contributes to a strong economy and a good society. We are supporting this crucial work.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce today that we are providing an extra Â£6 million for the Higher Education Innovation Funding to be shared amongst a number of universities to assist them in further driving growth, creating and supporting innovative enterprises and building strategic relationships.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Research Excellence Framework will, for the first time, recognise the highest levels of research excellence with reward for the past impact that it has achieved. I know that you are currently busy preparing impact case studies for the REF - and that you will all be aware of the breadth of “impact” that this encompasses. It is not about “commercialisation” but more widely anything which has an effect on, changes or benefits the economy, society, culture, public policy or services, health, the environment or quality of life.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The REF is an assessment of research excellence. It is not about “journal rankings” or “journal impact factors”. Whether the research output has been published in an open access journal, a traditional publication, or even if it hasn’t been published in any journal at all, this does not affect the assessment of its quality in the REF. REF panels will not make use of “journal impact factors”, rankings or lists, nor the perceived standing of the publisher, in assessing the quality of research outputs. An underpinning principle of the REF is that all types of research and all forms of research output shall be assessed on a fair and equal basis by experts in the relevant disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-access"&gt;Open access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, we have also announced that we are shifting to open access for publicly funded research published in these peer reviewed journals - following the excellent report from Janet Finch, the former vice chancellor of this university. Removing pay walls will have real economic and social benefits. Still, we understand that making the transition to “gold” open access has a cost - roughly one per cent of the national science and research budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I announced an extra Â£10 million to be allocated to our 30 most research intensive universities to assist with the costs. This is in addition to the contribution RCUK will be making to institutions to support payment of article processing charges associated with open access, through block funding grants from next April onwards. We’ll be providing more detail on this soon, and the UK Funding Councils will launch a consultation on setting a requirement that research outputs submitted to any REF should be as widely accessible as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="he-and-philanthropy"&gt;HE and philanthropy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another report, published only yesterday by HEFCE, I particularly commend to you. I took Professor Shirley Pearce’s excellent Review of Philanthropy in UK Higher Education on holiday with me, and very much enjoyed reading it - sad but true.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been substantial momentum since Eric Thomas’s excellent 2004 report. The matched funding pot has meant that many more universities and colleges have been able to attract philanthropic gifts over recent years, and voluntary giving has improved across the piece.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these financially strapped times a challenge for every institution is to diversify its income streams and develop strategies to stimulate donations- to position their institution as an attractive proposition. Both BIS and HEFCE will be giving the report’s recommendations serious attention. Shirley and her team have made many telling observations, including on donor behaviour. We will be guided on your views. We do need to remind people of the charitable status of many university activities. If the option of a charity number for a university would help, we can take it up with the Charity Commission. And it is right philanthropy is properly recognised in honours system, so do put people forward to us and the Cabinet Office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-new-fees-regime"&gt;The new fees regime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is the month when the first students will arrive at university under the new fees regime. I believe the financing changes, despite the controversy, are in the best interests of universities, students, and the nation. As the Institute of Fiscal Studies concluded over the summer, the new regime is “substantially more progressive” than the previous system - with the poorest 30 per cent of graduates set to pay back less over their lifetimes. The IFS noted that universities will receive more money to invest in education, while taxpayers will save around Â£2,500 per graduate. And we are proud of the extra financial support for part-time students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in constrained circumstances the reforms achieve three crucial objectives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we have saved money for the Exchequer without reducing the cash flowing to our universities. In 2011-12, the sum of teaching grant and student loan money reaching institutions was Â£7.2 billion. In 2012-13, it is Â£7.4 billion. The indicative figure for 2013-14 is Â£7.9 billion. That is not bad in these austere times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is more competition and choice for the benefit of students. Under the new funding system, students still receive public funding. We have to predict and control this cost, so - like every previous government - we have to maintain student number controls. But we favour relaxing these controls for individual universities within an overall total, so that more students can go to whichever university wants to accept them. We favour maximum possible choice for students, to accommodate for example those who may want to study locally, and those who may want to choose an institution offering lower tuition charges. We are moving from a world in which each institution is allocated a fixed number of students to what is indeed a more open and competitive system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, the AAB and core/margin policies seek to move towards those objectives, within the fiscal constraints we face. We asked HEFCE to implement them, including making the best assumptions they could about numbers. In order to set the necessary rules in a competitive system, the assumptions had to be fixed in advance.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is still too early to know fully what the outcome has been, and how students are responding. It looks as if there may have been fewer pupils achieving predicted AAB grades at “A” level, but rather more getting top grades in equivalent high-class vocational qualifications, such as BTECs. The net result may be total numbers getting AAB or equivalent which are closer to 80,000 than to 85,000, which was HEFCE’s best estimate. Different institutions will have been affected differently; that is inevitable when making significant changes, which are intended to take greater account of student choice. I recognise this comes at a time when there have been other pressures too. The number of 18 year olds is falling. Demand is unusually depressed this year because more students went straight to university last year, missing out a gap year. And more may be delaying until next year when ABB kicks in. The evidence from the Labour government’s changes in 2006 is that individual institutions can face a temporary jolt when changes like this are introduced. All this creates real pressures for some institutions. But HEFCE will take this year’s outcomes into account as it implements the changes we announced for 13/14, in the shape of a move to ABB or equivalent, plus a more flexible margin policy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third objective to which the reforms contribute is the greater information becoming available to prospective students - what I consider to be the final piece in the jigsaw. The Which guide has only just gone live, and I was pleased to attend the launch. Later this month we will be launching new Key Information Set data - which will also be available on university websites and on the updated Unistats site, enabling comparisons among institutions. The key indicators and summary information for students are unquestionably a force for good, but they are certainly not perfect and we should strive to improve them. HEFCE will carry out a comprehensive review of the student information landscape starting next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-revolution-in-teaching"&gt;A revolution in teaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add all this together and we’re looking at what amounts to a revolution in teaching - the largest cultural change in our universities for a generation. Research has been the primary focus of attention for a long time; it’s time for teaching to be in the spotlight as well. In 2010 two important reports were published - not just Lord Browne’s but also Graham Gibbs’s conclusions on how to measure teaching quality. It’s also worth remembering, as we approach the 50th anniversary of the Robbins report, that Robbins himself was preoccupied with teaching quality. I met Claus Moser earlier this year, one of Robbins’s key researchers alongside Richard Layard, and he confirmed that teaching was uppermost in their minds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keele, of course, put heavy store by teaching from the very beginning. Indeed, the 1964 Hale report on “University Teaching Methods” found that it was, at one time, the only institution with a Research Fellow on university teaching. I am also glad to acknowledge that the NUS, whose 90th anniversary we marked last night, has long campaigned about the quality of teaching.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now universities really do need to focus on the excellence of their teaching. At the end of this new term there will be many students returning home whose parents will be asking what they got for Â£3000. How crowded were the seminars? What were the labs like? How many essays did you write? How much academic feedback did you get? Every university in this room needs to be confident your students will have good answers to those questions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An environment that focuses on engaging students in their academic study means that those students are continually encouraged to apply themselves. I hope that applicants will make full use of the KIS data in figuring out which institutions can offer the most appropriate teaching environment for their individual needs - and that universities will adjust to student- and parent-power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="student-numbers"&gt;Student numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbins, of course, is most associated with expansion of the sector, even though that was partly set in train before he reported, as Keele perfectly illustrates. Perhaps we can best view the history of our HE sector as successive waves of expansion - a progressive interpretation that I welcome. There are periods between the waves where consolidation is the order of the day - like the current one where the number of 18-year-olds is in decline - making the raw UCAS application figures somewhat misleading. However, I believe that more growth will come and universities can rise to the challenge of proving Kingsley Amis wrong in his sour prognostication that “More will mean worse”.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed various surveys show that the number of young people aspiring to go to university has increased steadily over the past 10 years. The most recent Sutton Trust survey, published in April this year, encouragingly showed that around three quarters of year 10 to 12 pupils were likely to apply to university with a similar proportion of those in year 13 actually applying. According to the Millennium cohort study, 97 per cent of mothers want their children to go to university. I’m also very encouraged by the evidence that increased fees are not putting off young people from poor backgrounds - with a recorded fall of just 0.2 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="improving-access"&gt;Improving access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the more reason to welcome Les Ebdon, who has now started work as the Director of Fair Access. OFFA has additional resources to support as well as challenge institutions. Vince Cable and I wrote to HEFCE and OFFA in May, asking them to develop a shared strategy for promoting access which maximises the impact of all spending by Government, HEFCE and institutions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much going on now that it is right to assess what works best to widen participation and broaden access, taking into account the latest available evidence here and abroad.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes it is right for institutions to seek to broaden access because real meritocracy means making sure talent is spotted, not wasted. Individuals must be considered on their merits, and institutions’ procedures must be, as we say in the White Paper, “fair, transparent and evidence-based”. And we all understand the Director’s duty to protect academic freedom, including an institution’s right to decide who to admit and on what basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-providers--vat"&gt;New providers &amp;amp; VAT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the HE sector grows it needs to continue to be open to new types of provider. It always has been. Represented here today are universities that can trace their origins back to ancient foundations, mechanics institutes, Anglican teaching colleges, Colleges of Advanced Technology - all of which took a different route to university status. This year we have eased number limits and I hope as a result we will see at least 10 smaller institutions calling themselves universities for the first time - including alternative providers, so long as they are of the necessary standard.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, HMRC published a consultation on extending the VAT exemption to for-profit providers of HE. Currently, the majority of these providers cannot benefit from this exemption in the same way that not-for profit providers can. This potentially puts them at a competitive disadvantage in the market and runs counter to our vision of a more level playing field for all. I welcome this opportunity to review such treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-strategy-and-education-exports"&gt;Industrial strategy and education exports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Vince Cable launched our industrial strategy on Tuesday, we identified education as one of the key sectors of the future. Our universities, for one, are internationally recognised. We can do more to take advantage of our position.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are a great British export industry, and in a growing market - in 2000 there were just over 2 million students worldwide studying outside their own countries. Ten years later this had doubled to 4 million. By 2020 it is predicted to be around 7 million. Our education exports are already worth around Â£14 billion, and could rise to around Â£20 billion in 2020 and nearly Â£27 billion in 2025, representing an annual growth rate of approximately 5 per cent.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our key economic partners of the future like Turkey, Indonesia, Brazil are experiencing a surge in the number of young people. They are keen to invest in this generation through more HE at home and more opportunities abroad. That is why HE now has such an important role in our trade missions. Earlier this year, vice chancellors accompanied the PM and me to Asia. We’re going to Brazil later this month.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for UK education overseas extend significantly beyond teaching students. For example, other countries are attracted to the expertise that UK institutions can offer in governance models, professional development and curricular design; construction, management and financing. Some foreign education systems, particularly in emerging markets, have complex needs. For them, we are adopting a new approach, which we are calling “system-to-system” - facilitated and coordinated by the UK Government. Under this umbrella, the new UK Education Services will identify opportunities, then initiate and mobilise consortia to win the contracts. It could include higher education, further education and schools, as well as a range of non-education specific services. I am taking a delegation on a system-to-system education export mission to Colombia and Mexico later this year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system-to-system approach is not about replacing or duplicating the many excellent initiatives underway. But system-to-system supplements the bilateral opportunities already undertaken by many institutions and other organisations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overseas students travelling to the UK to study is just one way we can grow. Last year 400,000 overseas students came to the UK to study. But for the first time this was exceeded by the record 500,000 people who benefitted from British higher education while living abroad. I salute the trail blazers like Nottingham, Liverpool Reading, UCL and Newcastle with campuses abroad. On a recent visit to the US I was struck by the surge of activity in distance learning. We may be at a tipping point in distance learning as technology offers more efficient and more effective ways of online learning than ever before. We will be doing more work on this in BIS over the months ahead as I believe these forms of education are really going to take off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visas-and-the-situation-at-london-met"&gt;Visas and the situation at London Met&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few sectors of our economy with the capacity to grow and generate export earnings as great as higher education. Every overseas student on average pays fees of about Â£10,000 a year and spends almost as much while they are here. That means 400,000 overseas students bring in almost Â£8 billion a year. They make a big contribution to the economies of cities like Bradford and Exeter and Manchester, as well as London.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not allow the London Met issues to jeopardise this success story. I am grateful to the whole sector for its prompt, coordinated and effective response to the UKBA’s decision to remove London Met’s tier 4 sponsor licence. Both UUK and the NUS are playing a full role in the London Met task force that I set up within hours UKBA’s announcement. Individual universities are offering places for the mini clearing operation that goes live next Monday.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not lose sight of the individual students who are most affected by the current situation and we must maintain confidence across the world in the fair deal for overseas students. They may face costs of moving to alternative accommodation and costs of applying for a new visa. So I can announce today that we are setting up a Â£2 million fund to help legitimate overseas students at London Met who face extra costs through no fault of their own as a result of transferring to another institution. This will provide certainty to London Met students at what is a stressful and unsettling time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope no other institution will face a similar situation in future. But it makes sense for the sector to plan now for how it would manage that risk if it did arise - we need to underline the message to students and potential students and their families that the UK is a safe and welcoming destination. There are examples of protection schemes in other countries and in other sectors - the ABTA scheme is one obvious example. So I very much welcome UUK’s willingness to develop proposals for a sector-led response to discuss with all its members. I look forward to seeing the results of that work.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must go further to protect our international reputation in the short-term too. We have already used Foreign Office posts to signal that we remain open to overseas students and I have agreed with your President, Eric Thomas, that we will jointly author an article to offer to key newspapers in our target markets explaining that overseas students are welcome here, and reminding them of what a great opportunity it is to study in UK.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year, countries around the world send their best and brightest here to learn. When they come, they bring with them the potential to add a rich and diverse cultural scene to many of our towns and cities. They bring a great opportunity to make our courses more international in scope and to contribute to enabling a well-rounded education for our home students. This is a globalised world, and our people should consider themselves privileged to be exposed to such talented people from all its corners. Without international students, we would not only be poorer economically - we would also be more boring, more insular, and more ignorant of the wider world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why transparency in the immigration statistics is vital. We therefore want to publicise disaggregated figures so that the debate can be better informed. The ONS is planning improvements in its methodology so that in future it will be possible to better identify students in the emigration flows.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make clear the attitude of the government. There is no limit on the number of legitimate students from overseas studying at British universities. They have to have the language skills and the academic training to benefit from Higher Education here. It is in everyone’s interest to maintain our high standards. The vast majority of international students are here legitimately, study hard, contribute to our economy, and take nothing from us except a world-class education. Where things are working at their best, they also make us more cosmopolitan, sustain links between our communities with heritage in other parts of the world and those places, and make the higher education offer more diverse than it otherwise would be. It is crucial that we sustain and develop these advantages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusionâ?¦&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition believes in our great higher education institutions. Whenever David Cameron is listing our great national assets, he puts our universities high on the list. We are proud of our international reputation. We are proud so many students from around the world want to come and study here. We are proud that the lives of so many British people are transformed by the opportunity to study at our great universities. And everything we know about our culture, the needs of our economy, and the aspirations of our young people tells us that our universities will have an even greater role in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://disqus.com/?ref_noscript=deptforbusinessinnovationandskills"&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://disqus.com"&gt;blog comments powered by Disqus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47126</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/london-metropolitan-universitys-licence-revoked"/>
    <title>London Metropolitan University's licence revoked</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;30 Aug 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 29 August 2012, the Tier 4 sponsor licence of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/sitecontent/newsarticles/2012/august/28-LMU-revoked1"&gt;London Metropolitan University (London Met) was revoked&lt;/a&gt; due to non-compliance with its sponsorship duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision was made following a period of suspension and audits of the University’s student records by UKBA which identified a number of serious breaches of their sponsor duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Met students with a current valid visa do not immediately face a change in their migrant status. They will receive direct information from the UK Border Agency to inform them of changes to their status.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS are convening a task force to be lead by HEFCE, which will include UUK, UKBA and the NUS, to work with London Met to support affected students and enable genuine students to find another institution at which they can continue their studies in the UK. The task force will start work immediately to protect the interests of these students.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government recognises the important contribution that international students make to the UK, and is committed to keeping our education system one of the best in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome all genuine and legitimate students, and there is no cap on the number of international students who can be accepted to study in the UK. We fully appreciate the economic benefits and wider enrichment these students bring to the UK. We want to encourage students to come and study at our world-class academic institutions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities Minister David Willetts announced the formation of a task force to help overseas students affected by the decision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is important that genuine students who are affected through no fault of their own are offered prompt advice and help, including, if necessary, with finding other institutions at which to finish their studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have asked HEFCE to lead a task force, which will include UUK, UKBA and the NUS, to work with London Metropolitan University to support affected students and enable them to continue their studies in the UK. The task force will start work immediately.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that the decision affected only London Metropolitan University which had had its licence to sponsor non-EU students revoked. Britain remains a top class destination for international students, and welcomes them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there are concerns for legitimate overseas students who will be affected and London Metropolitan University has set up a Help Centre to support and advise students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number is +44 (0) 20 7133 4141 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;UK Border Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Home Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmet.ac.uk/"&gt;London Metropolitan University&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47122</id>
    <published>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/a-level-results-and-the-start-of-clearing"/>
    <title>A-Level results and the start of Clearing</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;16 Aug 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/corporate/images/ministers/willetts-100x140.jpg?w=100&amp;amp;h=140&amp;amp;as=1" alt="David Willetts"&gt;“Congratulations to all those receiving their A-Level results today. I know how hard students have worked to achieve these results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Students are benefiting from a more diverse and competitive higher education sector. So there is a good choice of high quality courses. We have also introduced more flexibility into the system by allowing open recruitment of AAB students so that they can access the university of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Already more than 350,000 applicants have achieved the grades they need and are now off to university. For those who don’t get the results they had hoped for, there are still many other options out there. There are over 25,000 courses with vacancies in clearing so it is worth looking to see what is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Alternatively I would encourage students to consider studying part time or perhaps pursue an apprenticeship. You can also choose to reapply next year. Under our new reforms graduates will have to make a greater contribution towards the cost for their degree, but there will be more generous financial support available while you study and fairer repayment arrangements when you leave university.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/David-Willetts-congratulates-A-Level-students-67eb9.aspx"&gt;BIS press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/inthenews/inthenews/a00212869/nick-gibb-congratulates-students-on-their-a-level-results-"&gt;DfE press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ucas.com/about_us/media_enquiries/media_releases/2012/resultsdayupdate"&gt;UCAS press notice - Results day update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/EducationAndLearning/UniversityAndHigherEducation/StudentFinance/Typesoffinance/index.htm"&gt;Student finance 2012/13: what money can you get?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47116</id>
    <published>2012-07-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research"/>
    <title>Government to open up publicly funded research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;16 Jul 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has announced that it will make publicly funded scientific research available for anyone to read for free, accepting recommendations in a report on open access by Dame Janet Finch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will likely see a major increase in the number of taxpayer-funded research papers freely available to the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science Minister David Willetts said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Removing paywalls that surround taxpayer funded research will have real economic and social benefits. It will allow academics and businesses to develop and commercialise their research more easily and herald a new era of academic discovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This development will provide exciting new opportunities and keep the UK at the forefront of global research to drive innovation and growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s decision is outlined in a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/science/docs/l/12-975-letter-government-response-to-finch-report-research-publications.pdf"&gt;formal response (PDF, 90 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; to recommendations made in the Finch Report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="better-access-for-the-public"&gt;Better access for the public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently most formally published research is only available behind restricted paywalls. Reforms will see publications opened up to a greater audience, providing more opportunities for research and development across a range of sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also support the commercial exploitation of research, contributing to the Government’s economic growth agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the recommendations that have been accepted by the Government are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving to deliver open access through a ‘gold’ model, where article processing-charges are paid upfront to cover the cost of publication. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walk-in rights for the general public, so they can have free access to global research publications owned by members of the UK Publishers’ Association, via public libraries. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the licensing of access enjoyed by universities to high technology businesses for a modest charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The details of how these measures should be developed will be worked on by funders in consultation with universities, research institutions, authors and publishers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Aug - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publishers.org.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=2299:finch-willetts-rcuk-green-oa-and-embargoes&amp;amp;catid=503:pa-press-releases-and-comments&amp;amp;Itemid=1618"&gt;Explanatory note on public Open Access policy by the Publishers’ Association&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research-67d1d.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Government to open up publicly funded research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/science/docs/l/12-975-letter-government-response-to-finch-report-research-publications.pdf"&gt;Government response to the Finch Report (PDF, 90 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.researchinfonet.org/publish/finch/"&gt;Report of the Working Group on Expanding Access to Published Research Findings - the Finch Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/media/news/2012news/Pages/120716.aspx"&gt;Research Councils UK - RCUK announces new Open Access policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/news/newsarchive/2012/statementonimplementingopenaccess"&gt;Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE) statement on implementing open access &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/news/newsarchive/2012/name,73613,en.html"&gt;HEFCE press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/science"&gt;Science policy at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47562</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/space-a-new-direction"/>
    <title>Space - A new direction</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning, everyone - and let me add a personal welcome to our distinguished guests today: Francesco Profumo, Enrico Saggesse, Vladimir Popovkin and of course Jean Jacques Dordain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be back at Farnborough as we celebrate 50 years of the UK in space. It was back in 1962 that the UKs first satellite, Ariel 1 was launched third after the USA and the then USSR. It was the start of a major home-grown industry and a true British success story. And I was delighted that, 50 years to the day, on April 26th 2012, the UK signed a â?¬300 million contract to build the Solar Orbiter - a pioneering project to better understand how the Sun affects the Earth. It was the largest single contract placed by ESA with the UK space industry in two decades, and a great way to mark a half century of scientific and technological advancement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than surveying the past five decades, allow me to highlight some of the progress achieved in the UK since the formation of the UK Space Agency in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Agency has done a fine job carrying forward the Innovation and Growth Strategy agreed with industry through the Space Leadership Council. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Satellite technology is now an integral part of the Government’s policy for broadband delivery in rural and hot spot areas. Public investment of around Â£40 million in satellite broadband technologies has leveraged more than Â£500 million of capital funds from the market to deliver UK-owned and UK-operated services. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The space cluster in Harwell, the ESA facility is up and running - and the joint ESA/UK business incubator has met its first-year target of establishing 10 new companies. There are in fact 12 firms now located there, with a further three about to join them. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further evidence of UK progress came only yesterday, with the announcement that leading US company Aerojet is to create a facility in Northern Ireland - and several dozen new jobs - to build rocket thrusters for satellites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the research side, we’ve had the first results from Cryosat that quantify the polar ice sheets - a major step towards understanding the rate of long-term change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve just delivered to NASA the first instrument for the James Webb Space Telescope - the giant successor to Hubble. And, thanks to UK expertise, we can look forward to the Planck satellite delivering a detailed map of the echoes of the Big Bang - showing the first structures in the Universe more than 13 billion years ago.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, perhaps, the space sector continues to buck general economic trends. Today, we are announcing the latest update on the size and health of the UK industry - and it’s very encouraging. The report shows that growth remains positive at an average of 7.5 per cent over the latest period surveyed - with downstream business doing particularly well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sector was worth Â£9.1billion in 2010/11 - compared to Â£7.5 billion in 2008/09 - and is providing jobs for 29,000 skilled workers. Space is one of the UK’s key high-tech growth industries. I fully expect this growth trajectory to continue, as UK industry breaks into new markets and seizes more export opportunities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space-related technologies are advancing at a substantial pace - nowhere more so, arguably, than in launch systems. This is an area where the likes of Virgin Galactic and potentially the Skylon space plane being developed by Reaction Engines’s could be game changers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, it appears, is sticking with SpaceX’s traditional launcher model, while our Russian colleagues here continue to provide a valuable service through Soyuz. This presents an opportunity for us to seize the advantage in terms of both technology and regulation. Space tourism and commercial space are just beyond the horizon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at present, in my view, Europe is not ready to grab this opportunity - and we must not lose out. We must formulate a regulatory framework that will allow reusable aircraft-type launchers to operate here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that Reaction Engines are making a significant announcement this afternoon regarding progress on their pre-cooler technology. Their SABRE engine already represents 30 years of incredible British R&amp;amp;D. It’s a remarkable world first, and the pace at which they’re advancing illustrates the urgency of laying the appropriate groundwork now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why i can announce today that I will be working with Justine Greening at the Department for Transport, to determine how the UK, indeed the whole of Europe, can best position itself to take advantage of space plane activities. We’ll be exploring the type of certification needed for space crafts and identifying the essential characteristics of an operational spaceport. Antonio Tajani, European Competition Commissioner has also agreed to pursue this matter with the European Air Safety Agency.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area where I’m keen to see further progress is at Harwell. Besides the positive news emerging from the business incubator, my department has funded the development of the International Space Innovation Centre, and last year’s Â£10 million investment in the National Space Technology Programme has brought in an extra Â£17 million from other sources. Some 50 new projects are underway as a result, from designing giant telecommunications satellites to testing “green” rocket propellants compliant with future safety requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m therefore delighted to announce today that the Satellite Applications Catapult will also be located at Harwell. The Catapult will give real impetus to commercial development from our space assets. Today we are also announcing the Technology Strategy Board delivery programme. From its Â£250 million budget for speeding up innovation in priority areas over the coming financial year, up to Â£10 million will be allocated to space.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture, of course, is making sure that space continues to be a key enabler of economic growth - and that’s the central goal of the revised Civil Space Strategy that I am publishing here today. The document, covering the next four years, focuses on creating new opportunities for industry, bolstering the role of space in the UK’s infrastructure and furthering the National Space Technology Programme. As such, it reflects the themes I’ve covered today, like regulating commercial space and improving knowledge of how the planet is changing, as well as addressing skills and training issues. It certainly captures the breadth of activity falling within the Space Agency’s remit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to security matters, I recently met with colleagues in France and we agreed that space situational awareness - addressing the small but growing risk of satellites crashing into each other or colliding with other debris - is a growing issue. This is an area where we’ve tended to rely on the USA for information, but the UK does need to consider taking responsibility for managing its own issues. This is important in the context of our own satellites and those we share with European partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the recent conclusion of the Wimbledon championships, I note that the smallest object we can currently track in low Earth orbit is equivalent to a spotting a tennis ball at a distance of 3,000 kilometres - making the undoubted powers of Hawkeye technology in SW19 seem rather humdrum by comparison. It’s vital that the UK has the capability to predict potential collisions with space debris or other satellites, and the Space Agency - together with other government departments - will be determining the scope of that capability in ways that are complementary to both our US and our European friends.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by looking forward to November, because 2012 is an important year for ESA, with the ministerial council taking place in Italy. The backdrop for the meeting is inevitably uncertain, given Europe’s current economic troubles. Nevertheless, as I await advice on the UK position from the Space Leadership Council, I hope we can reach a point that will see the role of ESA strengthened in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also several important European-wide programmes which will require attention - not least the ESA missions to Mars in 2016 and 2018, for which our council hosts are also our major European partner. I am pleased that we now have a viable way ahead for Exomars, following NASA’s withdrawal from the project last year. I repeat my gratitude to the Russians for stepping into the breach - and to the other ESA member states currently rethinking priorities so that this mission can proceed. From a UK perspective, I’m looking forward to saying that our export drive - courtesy of Astrium - has extended to other parts of the solar system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only remains for me to hand you over to my co-chair on the UK’s Space Leadership Council, Andy Green.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47103</id>
    <published>2012-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/england-to-be-best-in-world-for-university-business-collaboration"/>
    <title>England to be best in world for university business collaboration</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;26 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the review of university-business collaboration by Professor Tim Wilson, David Willetts has announced new plans to strengthen that collaboration.  This will include improvements to the regime for sandwich courses, promotion of a new framework for business and universities to work together, and ensuring a better fit between graduates and jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s plans include:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting the Council for Industry and Higher Education (CIHE) to create a National Centre for Universities and Business. The centre will focus on strengthening the strategic partnership between universities and business with a view to driving economic growth and recovery. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stimulating student demand for sandwich courses by instituting a 15 per cent cap on fees for a sandwich year. This more reasonably reflects the costs of a sandwich place year and will encourage universities to invest in and expand sandwich course provision. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the Graduate Talent Pool service for a further three years. This is a high-quality online resource that brings together graduates and businesses, and advertises internship vacancies, which now includes a strict quality assurance process. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with graduate employers to promote fair recruitment and the use of new more detailed records of student achievement.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/England-to-be-the-best-place-in-the-world-for-business-university-collaboration-67bdd.aspx"&gt;Read the Press Notice in full: England to be the best place in the world for business-university collaboration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/f/12-903-following-up-wilson-business-university-collaboration-next-steps"&gt;Government Response to the Wilson Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/w/12-610-wilson-review-business-university-collaboration.pdf"&gt;The Wilson Review&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47556</id>
    <published>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/whats-the-good-of-government"/>
    <title>What's the good of government?</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="what-calories-tell-us-about-fairness-between-the-generations"&gt;What calories tell us about fairness between the generations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great honour to be invited to give this lecture. It is an opportunity for me, a free market Conservative, to explain the useful things Government can do. Especially when this government is having to get a grip on the public finances, as anyone would with the deficit we inherited, there is a particular need to step back and be clear about what Governments can do and why. I am not going to start with abstract principles and then deduce the consequences for public policy. That sort of argument does not persuade people any more, if it ever did. Instead I am going to start by counting calories.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calories are a universal measure which enable us to get to the human fundamentals behind calculations of money, tax and benefits. Anthropologists have studied primitive tribes of hunter-gatherers in New Guinea and the Amazon, measuring the calories individuals consume as against the calories they obtain by hunting and gathering during their lives. When you are a young child you are a net consumer of calories, as any parent knows. Then as the children grow older they do some hunting but still can’t meet their full calorie needs themselves: mankind goes for diverse food of high nutritional value which is quite hard to obtain so you need a long time learning how to catch fish or which berries are poisonous. Then in adulthood you become a net producer of calories. As their physical powers decline older people become once more net recipients of calories collected by others. So out in the Amazonian rain forest at this moment a 40 year-old hunter is probably carrying six fish back to his tribal encampment thinking he has done a hard morning’s work but after he has given two fish to the kids and two more to his elderly parents there will only be two left, one of which he will give to his partner though at least she will provide in return for the sweet potatoes she has been collecting.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts like Ronald Lee also calculate the ages of these transitions to being a net producer of calories and then back to being a consumer. They reckon that in these tribes you become a net producer of calories at around the age of 16 to 18. You are a net contributor through your adult years becoming again a net recipient of calories obtained by others when you are about sixty years old. These are ages which we might recognise.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This observation about tribes in the Amazonian rain forest therefore tells us something rather important about the modern welfare state and its roots in fundamental features of human existence. Most income tax is paid by people in middle age and publicly financed services like education health care and benefits go particularly to people aged under 16 or over 60. During their lives each member of the tribe of hunter-gatherers is both a contributor and a recipient. On average when they die the transactions over their lives should net out at perfect balance. At any one moment you might be paying in or be a dependant but overall it balances. This is what holds human society together: if we were born able to fend for ourselves from the first day then none of this would have developed. This cat’s cradle of exchanges and obligations is, at any one moment, a shift of resource from one generation to another. But equally, if we look over the life cycle, it is how any one generation can spread its own consumption through its life.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The family is the most important of these exchange mechanisms, though it matters to us all far more than that. We do things for our children and our elderly parents because we love them. But in doing so we are also protecting a network of reciprocal altruism by which we hope we will get support from our children when we are old. It is also the logic of the modern welfare state. At any one moment it can look like a device to take from people earning a lot to those with less. But on a longer view it enables us to shift our individual consumption to times when our earnings are less. But the exchanges across the generations can also be thought of as a mechanism for us to reallocate our own income over time. A toddler cannot go into a bank and borrow the full amount for their education because as the economists would say, capital markets are imperfect. We need the welfare state to do some of this for us.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the logic of our reforms of higher education. Students do not pay fees upfront: unlike many countries we provide loans for this on terms far better than commercial. In fact it is more like a requirement to pay back through a 9% higher rate of income tax on earnings above Â£21,000. In general going to university does boost your earnings so it is reasonable to expect graduates to pay back out of their earnings. If they are in low paid jobs then they do not pay back. It is a good example of the smoothing of income and spending over the life cycle which is just what Government can and should do.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his classic paper on pensions the Nobel prize-winning economist Paul Samuelson said, “Giving goods to an older person is figuratively giving goods to yourself when old.” The modern welfare state is part of this reciprocal relationship. That is why everyone gets understandably angry if they think people who have not paid in and not participated in the network of obligations are claiming the benefits. These networks extend beyond families to wider groups. In my simplified example everyone had the same life course but actually there are many uncertainties - you don’t know exactly when you will be unable to hunt any more or exactly how many children you will have. It is efficient for these risks to be pooled. And by and large the nation is the biggest pooler of risk we have got. Provided we are clear about the risks we are expecting Government to take on and why, the welfare state can carry out a very valuable function indeed.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is that welfare is an expression which is half-American and half-English and this generates a lot of confusion. The idea of the welfare state was originally popularised in Britain in the 1930s, as a contrast with what was called the Nazi warfare state. Welfare then meant wellbeing so the idea was that British governments saw their role as being to serve their citizens whereas Hitler used the German people as cannon fodder to fight his wars. But in America welfare has the more specific meaning of means-tested non-contributory benefits which you get without paying in to the insurance pool; they are in contrast to contributory social security which has much more popular support and legitimacy - and gets far more public spending. The danger is that all the negative associations which in the US go with a specific form of means-tested welfare payments are attributed to a far wider range of public programmes which we have in every modern economy including the US itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people fear that we are not committed to maintaining the basic principles of the welfare state with tax financed education and health and pensions. Let’s be clear: those programmes of the welfare state which shift spending between the different stages of the life cycle and pool shared risks make sense and Conservatives therefore back them. They are part of the exchange between the generations of which we can be proud. As I argue in my book, The Pinch, the contract between the generations is fundamental to society be it a tribe of hunter-gatherers or in the modern welfare state. There is a Conservative case for the welfare state. But of course, the welfare state always needs reform - to reflect our values and changing circumstances. It’s why we have to raise the pension age as life expectancy is increasing so fast. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-economic-growth-changes-things"&gt;How economic growth changes things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classical political tradition assumes a static world without economic growth. But if there is growth you can argue that the next generation is going to be better off than us and so our obligation to help them is weakened. We can load more obligations onto future generations confident they can take the burden. I do not agree with this approach. Disraeli was right when he criticised a opponent because “He seems to think posterity is a pack-horse, always ready to be loaded.” Politics falls into disrepute when citizens think Governments are just shifting problems out into the future and never tackling them today: this Coalition can be proud of our long term reform agenda.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can hope that future generations will be richer than us but this does not excuse us from our obligation to them. We enjoy the fruits of investment by earlier generations who were poorer than us and we have a similar obligation to generations coming after us. The Victorians did not build their sewers and public buildings out of cheap plaster because we would be richer than them and could afford to do our own rebuilding. Instead they built for future generations despite hoping that future would be richer than them. As the African proverb has it, “The world was not left to us by our parents. It was lent to us by our children.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we were working out the science budget in the last comprehensive spending review I appreciated the argument that we were beneficiaries of a great tradition of British scientific enquiry and had a duty to pass it on in good shape to the next generation, and not to be remembered as the generation that undermined it. It is also of course one of the most powerful reasons bringing down the deficit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are beginning to see a role for government. It helps to sustain the contract between the generations. This contract provides the mutual insurance pool from which we can all draw. And as we have benefitted from the extraordinary engine of modern economic growth we have an obligation to ensure it still works for generations coming after us.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can think of this obligation not in terms of income but in terms of assets. We have an obligation as a minimum to maintain the assets of our society - natural, physical and human. That was Margaret Thatcher’s famous observation that, “we do not have a freehold on the Earth only a full repairing lease.” So growth achieved by consuming not investing, and by destroying the environment rather than improving it, is no growth at all. This line of argument leads economists like Dieter Helm to argue for a full measure of assets so we can check we are indeed growing them not destroying them. It’s why sustainability matters so much. The work you do here measuring climate change is of course an important part of that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge we face is very stark. What if we are not passing on to the next generation valuable assets they can develop but liabilities and costs which will burden them? One very vivid measure of this is the Â£1 trillion of government debt that has now accumulated - roughly half of it during the 13 years of the last Government. There is only one right way of easing this burden on future generations. We must get a grip on public borrowing and get the economy growing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few things more important we can do for our future and for future generations than get the real economy right. Whilst we over-estimate the power of Government to change things in the short term if anything we underestimate what it can do in the longer term. This is what industrial policy is all about and in the rest of this lecture I want to set out how the Coalition’s thinking has developed here. We are having to do so much to reduce the budget deficit that the scale and ambition of our developing industrial strategy is being overlooked. But both parties in the Coalition understand the importance of rebalancing the economy to investment and exports away from borrowing and domestic consumption: it is a crucial part of our shared mission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-strategy"&gt;Industrial strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising the growth rate in a mature Western economy is one of the hardest challenges facing any Government. That is why it is so tempting to believe that a boom fuelled by borrowing represents an increase in the underlying growth rate. This is an illusion to which Governments succumbed in the 1980s and again in the last decade. We will not fall for such mistakes again. That is why we are raising standards in education and skills. That is why we are tackling the financing of companies especially small companies where classic models of bank finance appear to have broken down, not least because of barriers to entry facing new banks. That is why we are clearing away the barriers in the jobs market or the planning system for example which obstruct growth. This is Government getting out of the way. But we cannot just remove barriers - we have to be builders too. This is where our industrial strategy comes in.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not be crippled by a fear that any industrial strategy cannot possibly work because it must mean repeating the mistakes of the 1960s and 1970s. I am the proud possessor of a copy of the 1965 National Plan. Looking at it now one is struck by the extraordinary and absurd detail of the calculations for the future performance of particular sectors. This was sheer hubris. Nobody can or should plan like that. That is why I entered Government assuming that industrial policy begins as governments trying to pick winners but soon becomes governments rescuing losers. Vince Cable and I agree that in an economy threatened by low growth Government can and must deliver an industrial strategy. Michael Heseltine is helping us do just that. Most of what we are proposing is what they already do across America.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to focus on a crucial part of that, our strategy for high tech growth, drawing on my particular responsibilities for science and innovation. Promoting the technologies of the future has already emerged as one of the crucial themes of the review of industrial policy launched by George Osborne in the Budget. There are three elements to what we are doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="securing-the-research-base"&gt;1. Securing the research base&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with the securing the research base. It benefits from ring fenced cash protection for current spending of Â£4.6 billion a year over this Parliament. I detect an anxiety that we are not supporting blue sky research but let me be clear that we do. The Research Councils distinguish between responsive mode grants which start with an approach from a researcher and challenge grants which are in streams of funding specifically for national and global challenges, though of course here smart original ideas are rewarded too. Across the research councils overall, approximately two-thirds of spending is on responsive mode and one third is on directed mode.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government can bear the big risks of scientific innovation, which are too great for any individual company. It is another example of that risk pooling I talked about earlier. Then, as we lower the risks of new technologies, companies step in and do their bit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right that scientists should range freely and do blue sky research. Civilised advanced societies should support that sort of activity. But there are utilitarian arguments too. Even the purest blue sky research is likely to end up with practical impact, though nobody can predict what that will be in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="creating-stronger-links-between-academic-researchers-and-business"&gt;2. Creating stronger links between academic researchers and business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot just support pure research. Our second task is to make stronger links between academic researchers and business. Cutting-edge science often requires technological developments for research and these can themselves generate new applications. For example, the fundamental advances in DNA have both driven and depended on technological advances in genetic sequencing. Britain has great strengths in this area with firms like Solexa Sequencing, now part of Illumina, and more recently Oxford Nanopore. Both of these businesses are spin offs from academic research which received public funding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now broadening the training of researchers so they have more opportunities than ever before to experience the world of business. The Research Councils have increased their investment in collaborative training which involves private, public or charity research partners by a fifth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, for example, I announced around Â£60 million of investment for the BBSRC’s Doctoral Training Partnerships, which will give the next generation of researchers an opportunity to take up professional internships in business. Today I can announce a new programme of manufacturing fellowships that were first outlined in the Growth Review. The EPSRC has initially awarded four prestigious fellowships to scientists making the transition from industry to academia: from Qinetic and IBM to Exeter, BAE to Cranfield and Talecris Biotherapeutics to UCL. Each fellow will lead a Â£1 million research programme with clear commercial potential, lending their business expertise to enhance collaboration with the science base. EPSRC will also be funding additional manufacturing fellowships, to enable business access to state of-the-art technologies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="systematically-identifying-new-technologies"&gt;3. Systematically identifying new technologies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These initiatives quite rightly encourage individual initiative but we also need a systematic look at the technological advances on the horizon. That is the third element in our policy. In July 2010 we published a Foresight report, Technology and Innovation Futures: UK Growth Opportunities for the 2020s. That report revealed a clear pattern with technological advance in four areas neatly summarised as BNIC - Bio, Nano, Info and Carbo which I set out in a speech in January. They provide a useful framework to make sure we do not ignore major new technologies. One of the most exciting developments is the convergence of technologies, for example linking advance in information technology and in biological sciences - dry and wet coming together. One reason why we need to sustain our broad science base is so we can make these connections. And we must never overlook the role of the humanities and social sciences here. So for example rapid advances in haptic technologies - using touch-based interaction - require us to understand human behaviour as well as physical science.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can report today that I have commissioned the Government Office for Science to review and refresh their earlier report: it should be available in the summer so it can feed in to the development of our industrial strategy. It would be surprising and indeed rather worrying if this new report were radically different from the one we published two years ago - it would suggest we had no reliable handle on developments in science and technology. But we have to remain alert to new developments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public funds are inevitably limited so exercises like this enable us to fund the work with the greatest potential. So the Technology Strategy Board then assesses which of these technologies are likely to have the great commercial potential and backs them in particular - energy efficient computing and energy harvesting are particular priorities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another priority area, synthetic biology, I’m pleased to make two announcements. The TSB, together with the BBSRC, EPSRC and ESRC, is investing up to Â£6.5 million to encourage businesses to explore new industrial applications for synthetic biology. Separately, the EPSRC is leading on a Â£6 million grant to a consortium comprising Imperial, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Newcastle and King’s to develop a new platform technology for the production and commercialisation of new products.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many reasons why people are sceptical of industrial strategy is the false dawns promised as new technology developments never quite happen. I do wonder why we aren’t yet flying in to work on our personal jet-packs, having seen Sean Connery’s James Bond use one in Thunderball in the 1960s. But sometimes we can deliver what used to be science fiction - those automatic doors in Star Trek slid open because stage hands operated pulleys but the technology soon caught up. Every week I get to see the most amazing advances in our laboratories and research labs which give me confidence we can remain at the cutting edge of new technologies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Fylingdales on the Yorkshire Moors we can track an object the size of a tennis ball 3,000 miles out in space. Earlier this month I opened the new robotic labs in Bristol which are probably the largest and most sophisticated in Europe. A robot picked up a packet of crackers. Not much new there I thought, until it was explained that it had picked the packet up to get it in its eyeline so it could read the name on the packet and respond to instructions from the user to collect a particular item.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago I attended the handover of a piece of British and European kit for the James Webb telescope so sensitive that when it is in orbit, it could see the light of a single candle on one of the satellites of Jupiter. We are sometimes so cool and sceptical that we lose our capacity for wonder at what science and technology right here in Britain can achieve. Our Foresight reports enable us review these developments systematically.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government playing a creative role to drive innovation and generate output &lt;br&gt;
All this adds up to Government playing a creative and constructive role working with researchers, universities and business to promote innovation and achieve the greatest possible economic value. Increasingly I think of this less as the passing of a baton in relay race and more as a partnership in which both Government and business and other players are all active at the same time. With my combined responsibilities for universities and science all within BIS we can harness the power of Government to play a far more constructive role than I would have envisaged two years ago. It is what they do not just in Germany or South Korea but in the USA too. We should not let myths about free market America inhibit us from doing the same here.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some basic steps we can take which are far more effective than I imagined two years ago. So here is Industrial Strategy 101. We set up a leadership council probably co-chaired by a BIS minister and a senior industry figure in which researchers, businesses perhaps regulators and major public purchasers come together. We use it to get them talking to each other frankly. Then we commission a trusted expert to prepare a technology road map which assesses where the relevant technologies are heading over the next five years or so, what publicly funded research is going in to drive it, and what business is likely to do. Just this exercise, with no increase in public funding, can transform behaviour. Some of the big companies for example might have a HQ abroad and it means British managers and indeed BIS ministers can show to head office what we are doing and so encourage more investment here. It can encourage businesses sitting on piles of cash to invest when they see how it fits in alongside investment others are committed to putting in. I have done it with, amongst others, space technologies, regenerative medicine, high-performance computing, and now with synthetic biology. Only last week Vince Cable and Mark Prisk, who do something very similar with big advanced manufacturing sectors, showed how triumphantly effective our approach can be. Their work with the Automotive Council was crucial in giving GM the confidence to invest more in the UK.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even this is not enough on its own. Here are ten further new things we are doing as part of our high tech industrial strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are creating seven Catapult Centres linking business and public funding for new research projects. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are introducing one of the world’s most generous tax incentives for R&amp;amp;D with tax credit worth up to 225 per cent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are changing the tax reliefs for investment in start-ups so academics can stay in academia and work part time for a company and still enjoy tax relief. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are liberalising the rules so research councils fund co-operative research groups like Imanova in Hammersmith in which UCL, Kings, Imperial and MRC together take over and run a medical research facility. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are using inducement prizes to reward innovation through a new centre opening at NESTA this year. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are using procurement to encourage innovation by increasing spend through initiatives like the Small Business Research Initiative. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have brought back the Smart awards first introduced by David Young to help start-ups with the cost of getting proof of concept and proof of market so they can get commercial investors in. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have backed venture capital with public investment in to the tune of Â£200m over four years through the Enterprise Capital Fund programme. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are developing improved access to publicly funded research so individuals and companies can get more out from the research we finance. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are backing clusters like Harwell and Daresbury which are now enterprise zones, Tech City, and of course the excellent Babraham and Norwich research and innovation campus clusters here in which we are investing an extra Â£70m. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are all new initiatives for growth and innovation which this Coalition is implementing. It is not an exhaustive list either. There is a lot more going on. Now we are applying this approach to our biggest manufacturing sector which can also gain a lot from applying high technology. That is the big sprawling part of our economy encompassing food and drink manufacturing and agriculture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-other-half-of-the-life-sciences-agenda"&gt;The other half of the life sciences agenda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly six months ago the PM gave a powerful speech on life sciences. It reverberated across the sector and I know it has registered with companies headquarters in Japan, the US and Switzerland as well. That focussed on the role of life sciences in human health. But there is the other half of the bio-sciences - from animals to agri-foods.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It draws on many of the same scientific advances notably genomics as human health. It also has important links to human well-being. The epidemics of the future may be zoonotic - the result of a pathogen in crossing the species barrier and attacking humans. We still do not do enough to link veterinary science and medical science in a shared research endeavour of comparative clinical science. And the security of food supplies is a real challenge as the population grows and climate change threatens some traditional agricultural areas. We really would be failing to deliver on our obligation to future generations if we left them with a public health crisis and a deterioration in food supplies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means sophisticated scientific research. We all like to think of food and agriculture as natural. But the only reason we can feed ourselves now is generations of scientific research, selective breeding and industrial advance - our Industrial Revolution proceeded in parallel with an Agricultural Revolution.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are experiencing a period of scientific revolution now. Advances in rapid gene sequencing technology allow for the identification of desirable traits that can give rise to an accelerated natural selection process. This science of genomics has great potential to revolutionise plant breeding and crop development in future. GM is already a part of this in many countries. Here, there are still decisions for us to take - and I realise people have different views. But well-informed decisions require evidence. The scientific experiments going on at Rothamsted and elsewhere are essential for gathering that evidence. The independent regulators say that the risks are tiny. Whatever our personal views on GM, everyone must surely want to protect the integrity and freedom of British science - and allow these experiments to proceed.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason for the anxiety around GM is the belief that our food just grows naturally. It’s a bit more complicated than that. Compare Apple and the tomato. Apple is one of the great innovators. A lot of sophisticated science and engineering goes into an iPad or an iPhone. We like to think of the humble tomato as vey different. But the modern tomato is equally the product of generations of scientific advance which has developed genetic traits that give it the colour, taste, and shape we want as well as the capacity to stay ripe for longer. Since January this year, according to Google Scholar, well over 1,000 academic publications on tomato genetics have been published. We should all be a bit more willing to take pride in this scientific achievement rather than ignore it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agri-science challenges our assumptions in another important way too. One of the challenges to the case for a high tech industrial strategy is that high tech is always going to be a small part of the economy and the real challenge is to raise the performance of the basic bread and butter sectors. The OECD definition of a high tech sector is one which devotes more than 4% of turnover to research. This does mean that most of the big sectors of most economies are not defined officially as high tech. But this ignores the pervasive effects of advances in general purpose technologies which are the very ones we are trying to back in our high tech growth strategy. One of the biggest single drivers of American productivity growth in the past decade was a transformation of performance in retailing, notably Walmart. It may not be officially high tech but it was using advances in IT systems that certainly were in order to transform its performance. The same can be true of agriculture and food manufacturing which can gain enormously from advances in biosciences. And it is not just us who gain. Some of the poorest parts of the world facing rapid climate change depend on rapid advances in agri-science to avoid famine. That is why our partnership in BIS is not just with DEFRA but also DFID who offer enlightened support for agricultural research.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the importance of this, I am announcing today very substantial grants from the BBSRC worth Â£250 million to our leading research institutes. They include Â£14.5 million for the world-class Genome Analysis Centre here in Norwich. Here is an example of what this is all about. At the moment we can grow just over 12 tonnes of wheat on a hectare of land in the most productive and efficient parts of the country. The BBSRC have set the challenge of getting that up to 20 tonnes of wheat by 2020. It really will be the next Agricultural Revolution. The research we are funding will help make this happen.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment by Government to research in the biological sciences is only a first step however. We need to do much better at linking our upstream research to the practical needs of farmers and the food industry. We will be working with them and DEFRA to ensure this research is applied as effectively as possible. I know that industry is keen to work with us to do just this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have ended up where we started - producing and consuming calories. But I hope that in the course of this lecture you have seen how these basic human needs show what Government can do. We are not detached and above the fray. Instead we are engaged, creative and constructive.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made five announcements today: the Â£250 million of BBSRC grants; the EPSRC manufacturing fellowships, each worth Â£1 million; the two separate investments in synthetic biology; and a refreshed report from the Government Office for Science on future technologies, to inform the evolving industrial strategy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are backing the risk takers, and are willing to take a risk ourselves. As Government is an insurance pool, we can take bigger risks than any other player. It is this attitude to risk that I will consider in a lecture at Imperial next month. Meanwhile I thank you for your hospitality and congratulate again on your research network here which brings together the university, the hospital and institutes. It is one of the finest in the country and we can all take great pride in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18640</id>
    <published>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/public-access-to-publicly-funded-research"/>
    <title>Public access to publicly-funded research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am very grateful for this opportunity to set out the Government’s approach to accessing and publishing research findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very fortunate to have such outstanding science and research capacity in this country. It is second in its range and volume only to the US. When it comes to the output generated from the funding that goes in, it is quite simply the most productive in the world. And no other country produces such a high proportion of work that is excellent. The recent review by Reed Elsevier, amongst others, provides the rigorous evidence behind these statements. With 1% of the world’s population and 4% of its researchers, we produce 6% of the world’s academic articles and 14% of those which are most highly cited. There are about 1.7 million academic articles published around the world, of which about 120,000 come from UK research. Thanks to the quality and success of our publishing industry, meanwhile, 400,000 of the world’s academic papers are published in the UK. If the rest of Britain performed like our research and publishing community, we would have rather fewer economic problems to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition is absolutely committed to sustaining this excellence. That is why we have protected cash spending for science and research. It is also why we have introduced higher fees and loans to be repaid by graduates, despite the intense controversy, to ensure our universities are well funded even as public spending is being cut back. Initiatives such as the life sciences strategy, the new Catapult centres, and the extra funding for high-performance computing are all aimed at strengthening our research capabilities in the face of intense international competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research base is one of our greatest economic assets. But it also enriches us in deeper ways. It enriches our cultural life to have such a range of intellectual activity here. We have an extraordinary window on the world: just about whatever happens anywhere, from a hostage taken in an obscure tribal area to a new scientific experiment, there is almost always someone in the UK who can help us understand it. This is an extraordinary privilege that we enjoy and which we should not take for granted. It contributes immeasurably to the quality of our national life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition set out its strategy on research and innovation last December. We understand that academic research is not a sausage machine where you simply put public money in one end and count the patents and the peer-reviewed articles that come out the other end. Instead we think of it as an ecosystem with subtle and intricate interdependences. It has many elements. Crucial is a spirit of free - and occasionally eccentric - intellectual enquiry. That in turn is sustained by our autonomous universities and our learned and professional societies. The ecosystem includes great charitable foundations like the Wellcome Trust. It is enriched by historic collections of data and objects organised with extraordinary skill and care. You, our world-class publishers of academic research, are another key part of this ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise the value which publishers add. Peer review is a crucial part of the research process. It takes various forms in which academics generously give their time to scrutinise draft articles. But value can also be added by identifying the academics to conduct peer review, through the editorial function of signalling which research is of the highest worth, and by helping others to find it. I do not scan the cacophony of opinion on the web to try to work out what is happening in the world: my laptop is set to open at the BBC news page. I do not follow wild and wacky online rumours. Instead I trust - well, usually - our leading newspapers and magazines to sort through the news for me. This process of winnowing data and research and then ranking them is of great value. Somehow it has to be paid for. But the way we pay for it is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a student, you went to the library to take physical copies of journal articles down from the shelves. The best articles were in the best journals. The physical location of books meant they were already sorted and ranked. The canon was embodied in, and indeed protected by, the need for the physical organisation of stuff in libraries, and museums and galleries too. Nowadays, the canon is not so easily sustained by the act of organising material in physical space: this is a profound change which has wider effects on our culture and our politics, with which we are still grappling. You do not have a Dewey Decimal system on the web. Instead, as David Weinberger puts it, everything is miscellaneous. The more data and freely available comment, the more important it becomes to sort and shape that information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as reading some of the articles set by my tutors, I also remember browsing through the pages of the leading journals to see which articles were well-thumbed. It helped me to spot the key ones I ought to be familiar with - a primitive version of crowd-sourcing. The web should make that kind of search behaviour far easier. It offers a democratised version of the traditional canon. We are still at the early stages of harnessing the full power of the web to help us find and rate material. It is so frustrating to try to track something on the web, face 1.5 million results, and then give up after the first few. (Ironically, Google’s own search engine began as a device for measuring and tracking citations in academic journals; one reason why the ranking of results is still basically done by number of hits.) But researchers, just like the rest of us, spend too much time searching for material which they know must be out there on the web but can’t quite track down. Sir Tim Berners-Lee argues powerfully for the importance of developing a far more flexible semantic web. That is one of the challenges for our new Open Data Institute. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have far more research material freely available, and we need to be better at editing and sorting it. The challenge is to discharge both of these crucial functions better. This is the challenge facing your industry but you are not on your own. It is one that we share, since Government has responsibilities for intellectual property, copyright and, of course, funding much research. We can work on this in partnership. Let me now set out our approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our starting point is very simple. The Coalition is committed to the principle of public access to publicly-funded research results. That is where both technology and contemporary culture are taking us. It is how we can maximise the value and impact generated by our excellent research base. As taxpayers put their money towards intellectual enquiry, they cannot be barred from then accessing it. They should not be kept outside with their noses pressed to the window - whilst, inside, the academic community produces research in an exclusive space. The Government believes that published research material which has been publicly financed should be publicly accessible - and that principle goes well beyond the academic community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I might speak from the experience of writing my own book, The Pinch, on fairness between the generations. It was very frustrating to track down an article and then find it hidden behind a pay wall. That meant it was freely accessible to a professional in an academic institution, but not to me as an independent writer. That creates a barrier between the academic community and the rest of us, which is deeply unhealthy. I’ve heard of other anomalies: the lone researcher who enrols on an evening course he never attends in order to gain library access, since it’s cheaper than buying the articles he needs to read; the small business owner for whom one advantage of employing a sandwich-year student is because she can print off research papers through her university library. So there has to be a right to roam freely across the achievements of publicly-funded UK research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence underpinning our ambition for public access is compelling. For example, publicly funded and freely available information from the Human Genome Project led to greater take up of knowledge and commercialisation than from earlier protected data. To date, in fact, every dollar of federal investment in the Human Genome Project has helped generate $141 for the US economy. Separately, a report this year from the US Committee for Economic Development has concluded that the US National Institute of Health’s policy of open access after one year has accelerated scientific progress and the transition from basic research to commercialisation; generated more follow-on research and more citations; and reduced duplicate or dead-end lines of inquiry - so increasing the US government’s return on its investment in research. The researcher Philip Davis, meanwhile, has found that when publishers randomly made certain articles open access on journal websites, readership increased by up to 250% compared to protected articles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise this move to open access presents a challenge and opportunity for your industry, as you have historically received funding by charging for access to a publication. Nevertheless that funding model is surely going to have to change even beyond the positive transition to open access and hybrid journals that’s already underway. To try to preserve the old model is the wrong battle to fight. Look at how the music industry lost out by trying to criminalise a generation of young people for file sharing. It was companies outside the music business such as Spotify and Apple, with iTunes, that worked out a viable business model for access to music over the web. None of us want to see that fate overtake the publishing industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wider access is the way forward. I understand the publishing industry is currently considering offering free public access to scholarly journals at all UK public libraries. This is a very useful way of extending access: it would be good for our libraries too, and I welcome it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided we all recognise that open access is on its way, we can then work together to ensure that the valuable functions you carry out continue to be properly funded - and that the publishing industry remains a significant contributor to the UK economy. I believe that academic publishing does add value, not least because peer review is at the heart of our system of determining and communicating high-quality research. We do not yet have any reliable version of peer review on the net. The controversy about the status and reliability of reviews on Trip Advisor is a reminder of how precious genuinely objective peer review is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be deeply irresponsible to get rid of one business model and not put anything in its place. That is why I hosted a roundtable at BIS in March last year when all the key players discussed these issues. There was a genuine willingness to work together. As a result I commissioned Dame Janet Finch to chair an independent group of experts to investigate the issues and report back. We are grateful to the Publishers Association for playing a constructive role in her exercise, and we look forward to receiving her report in the next few weeks. No decisions will be taken until we have had the opportunity to consider it. But perhaps today I can share with you some provisional thoughts about where we are heading. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial options are, as you know, called green and gold. Green means publishers are required to make research openly accessible within an agreed embargo period. This prompts a simple question: if an author’s manuscript is publicly available immediately, why should any library pay for a subscription to the version of record of any publisher’s journal? If you do not believe there is any added value in academic publishing you may view this with equanimity. But I believe that academic publishing does add value. So, in determining the embargo period, it’s necessary to strike a suitable balance between enabling revenue generation for publishers via subscriptions and providing public access to publicly funded information. In contrast, gold means that research funding includes the costs of immediate open publication, thereby allowing for full and immediate open access while still providing revenue to publishers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are versions of the green option - creating a single and very short standard embargo period for all publicly funded research - which may not work. There are, of course, differences between disciplines. In the arts and humanities, and to some extent the social sciences, the half-life of an article is longer than in, say, medicine. One of the key features of a science is that all previous knowledge is embodied in current theory, so older work may be honoured but does not have to be read. Literature, philosophy and historical writing are very different: it would be very peculiar to think you did not need to read Shakespeare or Kant or De Tocqueville. An article in the humanities or social sciences may be essential reading for much longer, so a green open access policy would have to take account of this difference. That is why our Research and Innovation Strategy referred to public access at “or around” the time of publication. This point was also addressed in the draft policy from RCUK - and we will reflect on it further in the light of Janet Finch’s findings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Wellcome Trust has been rightly praised for its decision to move to gold open access. As the Research Councils have proposed in their own draft policy, Wellcome are treating the costs of publication as an inherent part of the research process. This is the key feature of the gold option and again recognises the need to pay for publication and editorial functions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we await Janet Finch’s advice, perhaps the most important question is how we get from here to there. We have to work out, with you, how to manage any transition, and it’s particularly tricky in an open international environment. The UK has many of the leading academic journals globally - of the world’s 23,000 peer-reviewed journals, 5,000 are published from the UK - but we do not have so many of the world’s academic libraries and research institutes. This means our journals are an important export industry, with perhaps 80% of their revenues coming from sales abroad. Let me put this crudely. At the moment, American and Chinese libraries have to pay for journals containing the results of our scientists’ research. In future we could be giving our research articles to the world for free via open access. But will we still have to pay for foreign journals and research carried out abroad? If so, would we not only have undermined a business model but an export industry too? And there could be collateral damage for our learned societies, a very important part of our research ecosystem, as many rely on journal subscriptions from abroad for part of their income. Those chauvinistic statistics with which I began this speech show that 94% of articles are published outside the UK, and we might still need to pay to access them while giving them ours. If so, there would be a clear shift in the balance of funding of research between countries. That is why, together with representatives of the academic community, I will be encouraging international action. Indeed, this is an area where if we can work together on an agreed approach we can then take a lead internationally and shape the debate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to report therefore that representatives of the European Commission will be coming to BIS very soon to discuss open access. We share common objectives with the Commission and want to ensure that a sustainable strategy is developed for Europe as a whole. I will also be discussing the whole issue with colleagues beyond the EU. Fortunately there is already a lively debate on these issues in the US, and we hope they will be implementing similar initiatives. The US Committee on Economic Development, for example, advocates building on open access initiatives taken by the National Institute of Health, arguing that the costs involved are outweighed by the economic benefits derived from greater utilisation of research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another group we need to think about who do not conventionally have a place at the table. Earlier, I referred to my experience as someone outside the academic system trying to access academic research. The gold option would have helped researchers like me without a conventional academic post. But academics sometimes forget about a second type of outsider - someone who is conducting academic research without an official academic post but who legitimately expects to publish it in an academic journal. In future they will meet a new obstacle if they need to pay to be accepted in an academic journal. This is quite a significant issue in academic disciplines such as local history, where we have a rich literature generated by many highly skilled amateurs. I know some publishers already respond flexibly to this issue, for example through fee waivers for lone scholars, and I am keen to know if this might offer a sustainable way forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need to take account of the rapid technological change now underway. We are seeing an extraordinary surge in the sheer volume of data being released. It all goes back to Moore’s Law. It was originally a proposition about transistors - that their capacity would double every two years. But in its modern form, the law includes improvements in software too. In this form it says that computing capacity doubles every 18 months. And far from falling behind on this we appear, if anything, to be speeding up - with some estimates that capacity is now doubling roughly every 13 months. While processing speeds may have increased a thousand times, another estimate is that better algorithms have improved performance 43,000-fold. In his 2000 book The Age of Spiritual Machines: When Computers Exceed Human Intelligence, Ray Kurzweil shows the power of Moore’s Law by applying it to the well-known story about the origins of chess. When the creator of chess demonstrated it to the king of Persia he was so impressed by the new game that he invited the inventor to name his reward. The man is supposed to have said he had a simple request: just one grain of rice for the first square of the chessboard, two grains for the next square, four for the next, eight for the next and so on for all 64 squares, with each square having double the number of grains as the square before. The king readily agreed, and for the first part of the chessboard, it was fine. But by the time they had gone to the second half of the board the squares were going to require more grains of rice than were available in his entire kingdom. This is the power of compounding. We are now experiencing this with IT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts say that we are now reaching the second half of the chess board with enormous amounts of data now being generated - as with gene sequencing for example. The transformation of our capacity to handle very large amounts of data is going to have revolutionary effects. Some of the conventional distinctions between micro and macro analysis will erode as macro analysis starts emerging from very large volumes of micro data. I am persuaded by the argument that we are going to see a new era of data-intensive scientific discovery. And its implications spread way beyond academia to business. Instead of physically building prototypes, we can model them on computers. This is one reason why we invested a further £150 million in high performance computing. As they say, we must out-compute to compete. Our skills in software writing and computer simulation give us a real advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data mining is becoming an important part of scientific advance, with computer scientists working collaboratively with researchers and publishers to develop the necessary tools and technologies. With well over a million academic articles every year, researchers wanting to keep abreast of developments in their field are going to need analytic tools just to know where to start. There are proven benefits for humankind from text and data mining, such as the discovery of new treatments for Alzheimer’s. So we are considering how to advance UK capability in data mining in the light of the recommendations on intellectual property from Ian Hargreaves. Again we recognize that everyone adds some value here and we need to move forward in a way that shares the gains from text mining between everyone who contributes to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that publishers share an appreciation of the potential of these technologies, and that some of you are supporting developers in creating new applications. I would like to thank the publishers who have engaged with the Hargreaves process. The Government wants to see an environment which enables researchers to use datasets from a number of different publishers without undue costs or obstacles - and without undermining research publishing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally let me update you on how other Government agencies are approaching the challenges ahead. They too will wait for Janet Finch’s report - there will be no final decisions until then. Recently, RCUK set out some ideas in draft and caused some excitement around the world. Actually I take some encouragement from this as it shows we can lead the debate and do have the capacity to shape international discussions. Like all of us in Government the Research Councils recognise that we need academic publishing as part of the research process. To enable greater public access to Research Council-funded research information and simplify networking between researchers and SMEs, the Councils are now investing £2 million in the development of a UK “Gateway to Research” portal. Set to open next year, the gateway will enable users to establish who has received funding and for what research. It will provide direct links to actual research outputs such as data sets and publications. They are already working to ensure information is presented in a readily reusable form, using common formats and open standards. I am delighted that Jimmy Wales of Wikipedia will be advising us on these common standards and helping to make sure that the new government-funded portal for accessing research really promotes collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEFCE is also considering the issue. Peer review and assessment of impact are crucial to their allocation of research funding. The debate on open access will inform HEFCE’s planning for the research excellence process that succeeds the current one which concludes in 2014. Open access could be among the excellence criteria for qualifying articles in the future. We are developing a coherent strategy, with the decisions reached by the Research Councils and HEFCE meshing with the Hargreaves proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this has given you some sense of the approach we have taken in Government. Delivering transparency and access while protecting legitimate business models is an important challenge, and we are tackling it. When we came to Government we immediately set up Hargreaves. We have accepted his report and are acting on it. Then we had the roundtable on open access after which I set up the Finch group. We explained our overall approach in the Research and Innovation Strategy. Government, the Research Councils and HEFCE have all been working towards a common policy, and we have tried to maintain an open dialogue with the publishing industry throughout. There is a lot going on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we all are aware of the tricky issues around moving to open access, we must not lose sight of the big prize here. Open access is not an end in itself, it is a means to an end. That end is improved popular involvement with the quite extraordinary output of our research community. I do not want to see science and humanities further removed from the so-called general reader. I was very struck by comments from Alice Bell of Imperial in the Times Higher that this could be a real opportunity to break down some of the barriers between academic professionals and the wider community. That is happening already with the surge of high quality popular science writing. I see it as well in the flourishing of science festivals and literary festivals. We welcome this. I hope that greater public access to research can be part of this very healthy trend in our culture. At the end of this we can hope to see science and research brought closer to the wider public. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47554</id>
    <published>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/public-access-to-publicly-funded-research--2"/>
    <title>Public access to publicly-funded research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am very grateful for this opportunity to set out the Government’s approach to accessing and publishing research findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very fortunate to have such outstanding science and research capacity in this country. It is second in its range and volume only to the US. When it comes to the output generated from the funding that goes in, it is quite simply the most productive in the world. And no other country produces such a high proportion of work that is excellent. The recent review by Reed Elsevier, amongst others, provides the rigorous evidence behind these statements. With 1% of the world’s population and 4% of its researchers, we produce 6% of the world’s academic articles and 14% of those which are most highly cited. There are about 1.7 million academic articles published around the world, of which about 120,000 come from UK research. Thanks to the quality and success of our publishing industry, meanwhile, 400,000 of the world’s academic papers are published in the UK. If the rest of Britain performed like our research and publishing community, we would have rather fewer economic problems to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition is absolutely committed to sustaining this excellence. That is why we have protected cash spending for science and research. It is also why we have introduced higher fees and loans to be repaid by graduates, despite the intense controversy, to ensure our universities are well funded even as public spending is being cut back. Initiatives such as the life sciences strategy, the new Catapult centres, and the extra funding for high-performance computing are all aimed at strengthening our research capabilities in the face of intense international competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research base is one of our greatest economic assets. But it also enriches us in deeper ways. It enriches our cultural life to have such a range of intellectual activity here. We have an extraordinary window on the world: just about whatever happens anywhere, from a hostage taken in an obscure tribal area to a new scientific experiment, there is almost always someone in the UK who can help us understand it. This is an extraordinary privilege that we enjoy and which we should not take for granted. It contributes immeasurably to the quality of our national life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition set out its strategy on research and innovation last December. We understand that academic research is not a sausage machine where you simply put public money in one end and count the patents and the peer-reviewed articles that come out the other end. Instead we think of it as an ecosystem with subtle and intricate interdependences. It has many elements. Crucial is a spirit of free - and occasionally eccentric - intellectual enquiry. That in turn is sustained by our autonomous universities and our learned and professional societies. The ecosystem includes great charitable foundations like the Wellcome Trust. It is enriched by historic collections of data and objects organised with extraordinary skill and care. You, our world-class publishers of academic research, are another key part of this ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise the value which publishers add. Peer review is a crucial part of the research process. It takes various forms in which academics generously give their time to scrutinise draft articles. But value can also be added by identifying the academics to conduct peer review, through the editorial function of signalling which research is of the highest worth, and by helping others to find it. I do not scan the cacophony of opinion on the web to try to work out what is happening in the world: my laptop is set to open at the BBC news page. I do not follow wild and wacky online rumours. Instead I trust - well, usually - our leading newspapers and magazines to sort through the news for me. This process of winnowing data and research and then ranking them is of great value. Somehow it has to be paid for. But the way we pay for it is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a student, you went to the library to take physical copies of journal articles down from the shelves. The best articles were in the best journals. The physical location of books meant they were already sorted and ranked. The canon was embodied in, and indeed protected by, the need for the physical organisation of stuff in libraries, and museums and galleries too. Nowadays, the canon is not so easily sustained by the act of organising material in physical space: this is a profound change which has wider effects on our culture and our politics, with which we are still grappling. You do not have a Dewey Decimal system on the web. Instead, as David Weinberger puts it, everything is miscellaneous. The more data and freely available comment, the more important it becomes to sort and shape that information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as reading some of the articles set by my tutors, I also remember browsing through the pages of the leading journals to see which articles were well-thumbed. It helped me to spot the key ones I ought to be familiar with - a primitive version of crowd-sourcing. The web should make that kind of search behaviour far easier. It offers a democratised version of the traditional canon. We are still at the early stages of harnessing the full power of the web to help us find and rate material. It is so frustrating to try to track something on the web, face 1.5 million results, and then give up after the first few. (Ironically, Google’s own search engine began as a device for measuring and tracking citations in academic journals; one reason why the ranking of results is still basically done by number of hits.) But researchers, just like the rest of us, spend too much time searching for material which they know must be out there on the web but can’t quite track down. Sir Tim Berners-Lee argues powerfully for the importance of developing a far more flexible semantic web. That is one of the challenges for our new Open Data Institute. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have far more research material freely available, and we need to be better at editing and sorting it. The challenge is to discharge both of these crucial functions better. This is the challenge facing your industry but you are not on your own. It is one that we share, since Government has responsibilities for intellectual property, copyright and, of course, funding much research. We can work on this in partnership. Let me now set out our approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our starting point is very simple. The Coalition is committed to the principle of public access to publicly-funded research results. That is where both technology and contemporary culture are taking us. It is how we can maximise the value and impact generated by our excellent research base. As taxpayers put their money towards intellectual enquiry, they cannot be barred from then accessing it. They should not be kept outside with their noses pressed to the window - whilst, inside, the academic community produces research in an exclusive space. The Government believes that published research material which has been publicly financed should be publicly accessible - and that principle goes well beyond the academic community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I might speak from the experience of writing my own book, The Pinch, on fairness between the generations. It was very frustrating to track down an article and then find it hidden behind a pay wall. That meant it was freely accessible to a professional in an academic institution, but not to me as an independent writer. That creates a barrier between the academic community and the rest of us, which is deeply unhealthy. I’ve heard of other anomalies: the lone researcher who enrols on an evening course he never attends in order to gain library access, since it’s cheaper than buying the articles he needs to read; the small business owner for whom one advantage of employing a sandwich-year student is because she can print off research papers through her university library. So there has to be a right to roam freely across the achievements of publicly-funded UK research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence underpinning our ambition for public access is compelling. For example, publicly funded and freely available information from the Human Genome Project led to greater take up of knowledge and commercialisation than from earlier protected data. To date, in fact, every dollar of federal investment in the Human Genome Project has helped generate $141 for the US economy. Separately, a report this year from the US Committee for Economic Development has concluded that the US National Institute of Health’s policy of open access after one year has accelerated scientific progress and the transition from basic research to commercialisation; generated more follow-on research and more citations; and reduced duplicate or dead-end lines of inquiry - so increasing the US government’s return on its investment in research. The researcher Philip Davis, meanwhile, has found that when publishers randomly made certain articles open access on journal websites, readership increased by up to 250% compared to protected articles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise this move to open access presents a challenge and opportunity for your industry, as you have historically received funding by charging for access to a publication. Nevertheless that funding model is surely going to have to change even beyond the positive transition to open access and hybrid journals that’s already underway. To try to preserve the old model is the wrong battle to fight. Look at how the music industry lost out by trying to criminalise a generation of young people for file sharing. It was companies outside the music business such as Spotify and Apple, with iTunes, that worked out a viable business model for access to music over the web. None of us want to see that fate overtake the publishing industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wider access is the way forward. I understand the publishing industry is currently considering offering free public access to scholarly journals at all UK public libraries. This is a very useful way of extending access: it would be good for our libraries too, and I welcome it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided we all recognise that open access is on its way, we can then work together to ensure that the valuable functions you carry out continue to be properly funded - and that the publishing industry remains a significant contributor to the UK economy. I believe that academic publishing does add value, not least because peer review is at the heart of our system of determining and communicating high-quality research. We do not yet have any reliable version of peer review on the net. The controversy about the status and reliability of reviews on Trip Advisor is a reminder of how precious genuinely objective peer review is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be deeply irresponsible to get rid of one business model and not put anything in its place. That is why I hosted a roundtable at BIS in March last year when all the key players discussed these issues. There was a genuine willingness to work together. As a result I commissioned Dame Janet Finch to chair an independent group of experts to investigate the issues and report back. We are grateful to the Publishers Association for playing a constructive role in her exercise, and we look forward to receiving her report in the next few weeks. No decisions will be taken until we have had the opportunity to consider it. But perhaps today I can share with you some provisional thoughts about where we are heading. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial options are, as you know, called green and gold. Green means publishers are required to make research openly accessible within an agreed embargo period. This prompts a simple question: if an author’s manuscript is publicly available immediately, why should any library pay for a subscription to the version of record of any publisher’s journal? If you do not believe there is any added value in academic publishing you may view this with equanimity. But I believe that academic publishing does add value. So, in determining the embargo period, it’s necessary to strike a suitable balance between enabling revenue generation for publishers via subscriptions and providing public access to publicly funded information. In contrast, gold means that research funding includes the costs of immediate open publication, thereby allowing for full and immediate open access while still providing revenue to publishers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are versions of the green option - creating a single and very short standard embargo period for all publicly funded research - which may not work. There are, of course, differences between disciplines. In the arts and humanities, and to some extent the social sciences, the half-life of an article is longer than in, say, medicine. One of the key features of a science is that all previous knowledge is embodied in current theory, so older work may be honoured but does not have to be read. Literature, philosophy and historical writing are very different: it would be very peculiar to think you did not need to read Shakespeare or Kant or De Tocqueville. An article in the humanities or social sciences may be essential reading for much longer, so a green open access policy would have to take account of this difference. That is why our Research and Innovation Strategy referred to public access at “or around” the time of publication. This point was also addressed in the draft policy from RCUK - and we will reflect on it further in the light of Janet Finch’s findings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Wellcome Trust has been rightly praised for its decision to move to gold open access. As the Research Councils have proposed in their own draft policy, Wellcome are treating the costs of publication as an inherent part of the research process. This is the key feature of the gold option and again recognises the need to pay for publication and editorial functions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we await Janet Finch’s advice, perhaps the most important question is how we get from here to there. We have to work out, with you, how to manage any transition, and it’s particularly tricky in an open international environment. The UK has many of the leading academic journals globally - of the world’s 23,000 peer-reviewed journals, 5,000 are published from the UK - but we do not have so many of the world’s academic libraries and research institutes. This means our journals are an important export industry, with perhaps 80% of their revenues coming from sales abroad. Let me put this crudely. At the moment, American and Chinese libraries have to pay for journals containing the results of our scientists’ research. In future we could be giving our research articles to the world for free via open access. But will we still have to pay for foreign journals and research carried out abroad? If so, would we not only have undermined a business model but an export industry too? And there could be collateral damage for our learned societies, a very important part of our research ecosystem, as many rely on journal subscriptions from abroad for part of their income. Those chauvinistic statistics with which I began this speech show that 94% of articles are published outside the UK, and we might still need to pay to access them while giving them ours. If so, there would be a clear shift in the balance of funding of research between countries. That is why, together with representatives of the academic community, I will be encouraging international action. Indeed, this is an area where if we can work together on an agreed approach we can then take a lead internationally and shape the debate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to report therefore that representatives of the European Commission will be coming to BIS very soon to discuss open access. We share common objectives with the Commission and want to ensure that a sustainable strategy is developed for Europe as a whole. I will also be discussing the whole issue with colleagues beyond the EU. Fortunately there is already a lively debate on these issues in the US, and we hope they will be implementing similar initiatives. The US Committee on Economic Development, for example, advocates building on open access initiatives taken by the National Institute of Health, arguing that the costs involved are outweighed by the economic benefits derived from greater utilisation of research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another group we need to think about who do not conventionally have a place at the table. Earlier, I referred to my experience as someone outside the academic system trying to access academic research. The gold option would have helped researchers like me without a conventional academic post. But academics sometimes forget about a second type of outsider - someone who is conducting academic research without an official academic post but who legitimately expects to publish it in an academic journal. In future they will meet a new obstacle if they need to pay to be accepted in an academic journal. This is quite a significant issue in academic disciplines such as local history, where we have a rich literature generated by many highly skilled amateurs. I know some publishers already respond flexibly to this issue, for example through fee waivers for lone scholars, and I am keen to know if this might offer a sustainable way forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need to take account of the rapid technological change now underway. We are seeing an extraordinary surge in the sheer volume of data being released. It all goes back to Moore’s Law. It was originally a proposition about transistors - that their capacity would double every two years. But in its modern form, the law includes improvements in software too. In this form it says that computing capacity doubles every 18 months. And far from falling behind on this we appear, if anything, to be speeding up - with some estimates that capacity is now doubling roughly every 13 months. While processing speeds may have increased a thousand times, another estimate is that better algorithms have improved performance 43,000-fold. In his 2000 book The Age of Spiritual Machines: When Computers Exceed Human Intelligence, Ray Kurzweil shows the power of Moore’s Law by applying it to the well-known story about the origins of chess. When the creator of chess demonstrated it to the king of Persia he was so impressed by the new game that he invited the inventor to name his reward. The man is supposed to have said he had a simple request: just one grain of rice for the first square of the chessboard, two grains for the next square, four for the next, eight for the next and so on for all 64 squares, with each square having double the number of grains as the square before. The king readily agreed, and for the first part of the chessboard, it was fine. But by the time they had gone to the second half of the board the squares were going to require more grains of rice than were available in his entire kingdom. This is the power of compounding. We are now experiencing this with IT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts say that we are now reaching the second half of the chess board with enormous amounts of data now being generated - as with gene sequencing for example. The transformation of our capacity to handle very large amounts of data is going to have revolutionary effects. Some of the conventional distinctions between micro and macro analysis will erode as macro analysis starts emerging from very large volumes of micro data. I am persuaded by the argument that we are going to see a new era of data-intensive scientific discovery. And its implications spread way beyond academia to business. Instead of physically building prototypes, we can model them on computers. This is one reason why we invested a further Â£150 million in high performance computing. As they say, we must out-compute to compete. Our skills in software writing and computer simulation give us a real advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data mining is becoming an important part of scientific advance, with computer scientists working collaboratively with researchers and publishers to develop the necessary tools and technologies. With well over a million academic articles every year, researchers wanting to keep abreast of developments in their field are going to need analytic tools just to know where to start. There are proven benefits for humankind from text and data mining, such as the discovery of new treatments for Alzheimer’s. So we are considering how to advance UK capability in data mining in the light of the recommendations on intellectual property from Ian Hargreaves. Again we recognize that everyone adds some value here and we need to move forward in a way that shares the gains from text mining between everyone who contributes to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that publishers share an appreciation of the potential of these technologies, and that some of you are supporting developers in creating new applications. I would like to thank the publishers who have engaged with the Hargreaves process. The Government wants to see an environment which enables researchers to use datasets from a number of different publishers without undue costs or obstacles - and without undermining research publishing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally let me update you on how other Government agencies are approaching the challenges ahead. They too will wait for Janet Finch’s report - there will be no final decisions until then. Recently, RCUK set out some ideas in draft and caused some excitement around the world. Actually I take some encouragement from this as it shows we can lead the debate and do have the capacity to shape international discussions. Like all of us in Government the Research Councils recognise that we need academic publishing as part of the research process. To enable greater public access to Research Council-funded research information and simplify networking between researchers and SMEs, the Councils are now investing Â£2 million in the development of a UK “Gateway to Research” portal. Set to open next year, the gateway will enable users to establish who has received funding and for what research. It will provide direct links to actual research outputs such as data sets and publications. They are already working to ensure information is presented in a readily reusable form, using common formats and open standards. I am delighted that Jimmy Wales of Wikipedia will be advising us on these common standards and helping to make sure that the new government-funded portal for accessing research really promotes collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEFCE is also considering the issue. Peer review and assessment of impact are crucial to their allocation of research funding. The debate on open access will inform HEFCE’s planning for the research excellence process that succeeds the current one which concludes in 2014. Open access could be among the excellence criteria for qualifying articles in the future. We are developing a coherent strategy, with the decisions reached by the Research Councils and HEFCE meshing with the Hargreaves proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this has given you some sense of the approach we have taken in Government. Delivering transparency and access while protecting legitimate business models is an important challenge, and we are tackling it. When we came to Government we immediately set up Hargreaves. We have accepted his report and are acting on it. Then we had the roundtable on open access after which I set up the Finch group. We explained our overall approach in the Research and Innovation Strategy. Government, the Research Councils and HEFCE have all been working towards a common policy, and we have tried to maintain an open dialogue with the publishing industry throughout. There is a lot going on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we all are aware of the tricky issues around moving to open access, we must not lose sight of the big prize here. Open access is not an end in itself, it is a means to an end. That end is improved popular involvement with the quite extraordinary output of our research community. I do not want to see science and humanities further removed from the so-called general reader. I was very struck by comments from Alice Bell of Imperial in the Times Higher that this could be a real opportunity to break down some of the barriers between academic professionals and the wider community. That is happening already with the surge of high quality popular science writing. I see it as well in the flourishing of science festivals and literary festivals. We welcome this. I hope that greater public access to research can be part of this very healthy trend in our culture. At the end of this we can hope to see science and research brought closer to the wider public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
