<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state-business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state-business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for Business and Enterprise</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61079</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/30-million-boost-as-start-up-loans-for-young-entrepreneurs-expanded"/>
    <title>£30 million boost as Start-Up Loans for young entrepreneurs expanded</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Thousands more young people have the opportunity to apply for government loans to turn their business ideas into reality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has today announced a boost to the government’s Start-Up loans scheme, with funding being increased by £30 million to £110 million over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also said that due to demand from those who had just missed out on the scheme, and the challenges faced to secure loans to start a business, the age limit for applying will now be extended from 24 to 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-Up Loans provide budding entrepreneurs a range of support to get their business idea off the ground, including access to a business mentor as well as funding in the region of £2,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 3000 people have applied or registered an interest in a Start-Up loan; when their business plan is robust and approved, applicants are able to access the financial support, with a repayment period of up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that the scheme has been live over £1.5 million worth of loans have been approved, helping over 460 new businesses get off the ground. Around 100 new businesses a week are expected to reach approval stage in January, with thousands more in the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Start-Up Loans scheme forms an integral part of the Business in You campaign, which encourages the start up and growth of new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startuploans.co.uk/"&gt;Visit the Start-Up Loans Company for more information and details on how to apply.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business"&gt;Tools and guidance for businesses on Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/start-up-loans-scheme-expanded/"&gt;Read the full story on the Number 10 website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57424</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The government has today published new data detailing lending by specific banks through the Enterprise Finance Guarantee scheme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past 5 years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57077</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:38:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"/>
    <title>Update on Enterprise Finance Guarantee lending  </title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Minister for Business and Enterprise Rt Hon Michael Fallon on new data detailing lending by specific banks.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures by individual bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to ensuring that viable small and medium-size enterprises can obtain the finance they need for working capital and investment. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; plays an important part in this, with over 9,900 &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; being offered loans with a value in excess of £1 billion since May 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has made a number of important changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme during the last twelve months. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans are now available to an additional 3,800 businesses with an increase in the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million. The maximum £1 million lifetime scheme limit has been replaced by a rolling £1 million limit. We also raised by 7%, the level of lenders &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; annual loan portfolios to which the Government guarantee applies from 13% to 20%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was made to address the legitimate concern of lenders that they would breach their annual claim limit. In doing this, the Government committed to a more even share of the risk of default with the lenders, with the aim of removing that as a barrier to lending &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; is a demand led scheme, accounting for one to two per cent of overall &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; lending. While utilisation is directly linked to subdued demand for credit in the wider economy, overall &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending levels are disappointing. There have been some positive signs, with a number of the main banks increasing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending this financial year, albeit from a low level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that banks lend responsibly and make use of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; when it is appropriate to do so, but it is clear from the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures that a number of lenders could and should be doing more. The publication of individual bank &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures is intended to help achieve this. In parallel, we are exploring with the banks ways of flexing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; to address debt serviceability, which is the principal reason behind loan declines. Further detail will be provided in the New Year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, already publishes a wide range of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures, which are updated on a quarterly basis. Publication of individual &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures will further enhance this, allowing business customers to identify which banks are making most use of the scheme, and also enable participating lenders and new market entrants to identity new opportunities, thus increasing choice and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a further step towards greater transparency in bank lending, specifically to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"&gt;The full list of available &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56972</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:03:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-figures-show-government-is-winning-war-on-red-tape"/>
    <title>New figures show government is winning war on red tape</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Minister pledges tougher action to eliminate burdens on enterprise.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business will benefit from nearly £1 billion in reduced red tape costs thanks to government action, independent figures revealed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Statement of New Regulation reports that the overall closing balance for ‘One-in, One-out’, the government rule that dictates that every new cost on business must be balanced by an equivalent saving, is predicted to be around £836 million since January 2011. These figures are independently verified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the statement shows that the government expects to reduce the regulatory burden by around a further £83 million between January 2013 - when ‘One-in, One-Out’ is replaced by ‘One-in, Two-out’ - and June 2013.  Expected measures include reforms to environmental regulation, employment law and consumer law.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said that Whitehall is increasingly putting the needs of businesses centre stage, but vowed to go further and faster to roll back barriers to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every department is predicting either a zero balance or being in credit at the start of One-in, Two-out, showing that the de-regulatory agenda is having an impact right across Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the overwhelming majority of government measures affecting business are deregulatory, with only ten new items imposing new costs on business compared with 89 that will save money or will impose a zero net cost. The costs from the ‘ins’ (£6 million) are also dwarfed by the savings from the ‘outs’ (£89 million), giving a predicted net saving to business of £83 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent deregulatory measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;changes to modernise and simplify the registration of company charges, saving £21.9 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a series of changes to building regulations to reduce cost and complexity for industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less heavy-handed Health and Safety regulations for low-risk businesses including shop and offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improvements to speed up processes covering adoption and foster-carer eligibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government has a very simple objective: to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business.  This requires a fundamental culture change in Whitehall, so that new regulation is only imposed as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve made a promising start, but firms still struggle with excessive red tape.  We’ll now push departments to go further to bear down on costs imposed on business, and we’ll fight harder to get EU bureaucracy off the back of our entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time this Statement sets out EU measures that will be introduced during the reporting period, giving businesses time to prepare for these changes.   Fifty-seven EU measures are expected to be implemented into UK legislation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every six months the government publishes a Statement of New Regulation listing of all the regulations it plans to introduce and remove in the next six months, and showing the net direct costs to business. The Fifth Statement of New Regulation is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘One-in, One-out’ rule was introduced on 1 September 2010 and applies to regulations introduced from January 2011.  The rule prevents any government department introducing new regulation that will impose a direct net cost on business and voluntary organisations - unless the department can find savings by removing or modifying another regulation of an equivalent cost. ‘One-in, Two-out’ will also operate in this way, but the removal or modification must be of twice the equivalent cost. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like ‘One-in, One-out’ , ‘One-in, Two-Out’ will not apply to EU legislation unless it has been converted into UK law in a way that goes beyond minimum EU requirements, putting UK businesses at a disadvantage.  A number of other areas are exempt from the rule, including tax administration and civil emergencies regulation. More detail is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When developing a new regulatory or deregulatory proposal, each Government department must carry out an impact assessment. This includes estimating the likely cost to business. To ensure estimates are credible, the impact assessment is considered by an independent body, the Regulatory Policy Committee (RPC). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited, with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The government announced on 10 September 2012 that at least 3,000 of the regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. A second phase of the Red Tape Challenge will start in spring 2013.  More information on the Red Tape Challenge is avaiable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alongside the drive to remove superfluous regulation, government is working to ensure that necessary regulations on business are enforced more efficiently. Focus on Enforcement reviews are being carried out across a number of sectors where aspects of the enforcement regime may be imposing unnecessary burdens on business, making inefficient use of public sector resources or hampering economic growth.  At Autumn Statement, the government also announced a number of measures to tackle systemic issues, including the lack of consistent fees and charges and appeals mechanisms. The Focus on Enforcement website is available &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/iscuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56434</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-tackles-red-tape-head-on-with-package-of-measures"/>
    <title>Government tackles red tape head on with package of measures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of the way that appeals are handled by regulators launched today is the first stage of a new wave of bureaucracy busting measures announced by the government, Business Minister Michael Fallon confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and other interested parties will have a chance to take part in a review of the effectiveness of appeals mechanisms operated by national and local regulators. The Focus on Enforcement Appeals Review will give those affected the opportunity to talk about their experiences of formal and informal appeals processes, and suggest how they could be made to work more effectively, providing a swifter route to resolution and better industry understanding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will also gather examples of approaches that have successfully helped businesses understand regulators’ decisions and meet their obligations more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have started a bonfire of excessive red tape, but I know that it is just as important that we look at the way that regulations are enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is room for far more effective enforcement which reduces the burden on business which stick to the rules.  Despite best efforts, sometimes things can go wrong – that has become clear from previous Focus on Enforcement Reviews. So I want to hear views on how we can improve the way appeals currently work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greater clarity and trust between regulators and businesses will lead to better enforcement of the law and higher standards across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest review follows a package of new measures announced at the Autumn Statement to tackle systemic problems with the way regulations are enforced and cut the unnecessary red tape and burdens that companies have to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a consultation on placing a legislative duty on non-economic regulators to have regard to growth and take into account the economic impacts of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new accounting system for regulators, so that in future regulators will have to publish impact assessments for prior consultation, scrutiny and challenge by industry, of the impacts of all changes in their activities that have a significant (positive and negative) financial impact on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consultation on an amended Regulators’ Compliance Code to ensure regulators are internally and geographically consistent, give consideration to earned recognition, and offer minimum service standards to those they regulate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government action to ensure regulators are transparent about the fees they charge and bear down on their costs and improve their efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also today, as part of the package the government announced plans to cut bureaucracy by widening the range of regulations included in the Primary Authority scheme. The plans would see the scheme covering age-related sales of gambling, the Housing Health and Safety Rating system for assessing potential hazards in dwellings, sun-bed tanning and Welsh regulations for single-use carrier bag charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships are reducing regulatory burdens for companies and allowing them to grow. It’s now time to extend the scope of the scheme to streamline the way regulators work with businesses, improve protections to the public and help local authorities to target their resources against rogue traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major business groups such as the CBI, British Retail Consortium and FSB are strongly in favour of Primary Authority and of its extension. The Trading Standards Institute and Chartered Institute of Environmental Health are also in favour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence arising from sector-specific Focus on Enforcement reviews has already indicated that businesses have concerns about how current appeals systems operate. These include confusing or multiple appeals mechanisms lack of transparency and in some cases resolution taking excessively long periods of time.   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The forthcoming review will invite evidence from all sectors of the economy and any regulatory regime. Appeals mechanisms for economic regulators are not included in the scope of this review. Interested parties can participate in the review of appeals at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year at Budget, the government announced a new approach to cutting red tape, looking at how rules are enforced, rather than the rules themselves. A series of Focus on Enforcement Reviews have shown that in addition to sector-specific issues, there are also systemic enforcement issues limiting industry that affect most if not all sectors. So, rather than tackling systemic issues case by case, the Government’s Autumn Statement package  aims to change the system, creating greater clarity and fairness for businesses while ensuring regulators focus their resources where they are needed most. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Primary Authority Scheme is run by the Better Regulation Delivery Office, an independent unit within the Business Innovation and Skills Department (BIS). See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are currently 602 businesses and 93 local authorities involved in Primary Authority partnerships, covering over 58,000 premises and over 1.57 million employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the scope of the scheme, or the list of regulations which can be covered by partnerships, can be achieved by secondary legislation. The consultation announced today runs until 24 January 2013 to allow feedback from stakeholders before secondary legislation is introduced into Parliament.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Housing Health and Safety Rating System (HHSRS) is a risk-based evaluation tool to help local authorities identify and protect against potential risks and hazards to health and safety from any deficiencies identified in dwellings. It was introduced under the Housing Act 2004 and applies to residential properties in England and Wales.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47134</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/business-minister-unlocks-new-business-potential"/>
    <title>Business minister unlocks new business potential</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business minister Michael Fallon announces extra support including less red tape for challenger businesses.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;20 Sep 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenger businesses to be freed from red tape &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Sep/minister-unlocks-business-potential#mentors"&gt;22,000 business mentors now accessible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Sep/minister-unlocks-business-potential#support"&gt;Extra money to help entrepreneurs, including women in business, find the right mentor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the MADE entrepreneur festival in Sheffield, Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon announced that there will be new independent scrutiny of the rules and regulations that are barriers to growth for challenger businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are innovative enterprises that do not follow established ways of business working, and which might be held back by burdensome bureaucracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Challenger businesses create wealth and jobs - we should champion them at every opportunity. They put new products on our shelves, innovate our service industry and create new markets using the latest technology. I don’t want these pioneers falling foul of outdated regulations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am now looking in more depth at the rules and regulations that are holding back our most forward-thinking entrepreneurs. That’s why in addition to the package of proposals I’m publishing today, I am also strengthening the role of the independent Regulatory Policy Committee to make sure that regulation barriers to challenger businesses growth are removed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experimental &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge work&lt;/a&gt; uncovered a wide range of issues - not all purely regulatory, but relevant to this theme. Key proposals are to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new independent role to champion deregulation for innovative businesses &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage a self regulating approach in the peer-to-peer finance industry by increasing membership of their finance associations and building on their consumer code of practice &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help knowledge-based businesses to secure finance by working with banking and accountancy experts to improve existing guidance and raise awareness of the Government schemes which can help &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify ways to drive down costs in applying for and defending patents, including examining the operation of the US ‘small entity’ regime &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make it cheaper and simpler for SMEs to challenge potential infringements of their trade marks &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide a better balance to the rights of consumers and online traders by implementing a new Consumer Rights Directive to replace the existing distance selling regulations &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amend the Estate Agents Act (1979) to take out of its scope intermediaries such as private sale portals, which only advertise properties and provide a means for sellers and buyers to communicate with each other.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the report: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/enterprise/docs/r/12-984-removing-red-tape-for-challenger-businesses.pdf"&gt;Removing red tape for challenger businesses (PDF, 284 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister also announced Northamptonshire as the “most enterprising place in Britain”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="business-mentors-now-accessible"&gt;22,000 business mentors now accessible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon also gave an added boost to entrepreneurs by announcing that a network of 22,000 mentors is now accessible on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mentorsme.co.uk/"&gt;Mentorsme website&lt;/a&gt;. He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Business mentors play a vital role in helping SMEs to build their knowledge base as the support comes from someone who has been there and done it before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is great that we now have a vast network of accessible business mentors but we want to grow that number even further and give greater choice to our entrepreneurs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="extra-money-to-help-entrepreneurs-including-women-in-business-access-more-support"&gt;Extra money to help entrepreneurs, including women in business, access more support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure that entrepreneurs, particularly women in business, are aware that this support is available, Culture Secretary Maria Miller has today announced that £100,000 will be invested to help them find the right mentor to help their business prosper. This will bring the total government investment in the mentoring programme to £1.8 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon will be making the announcements at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.madefestival.com/"&gt;MADE entrepreneur festival&lt;/a&gt; in Sheffield. There he will meet young entrepreneurs and take part in the Intuit 100-up session, where young business people will be matched up with volunteer business mentors, trained through the Get Mentoring initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unlocks-new-business-potential-at-entrepreneurial-festival-68056.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unlocks new business potential at entrepreneurial festival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Northamptonshire-named-most-enterprising-place-in-Britain-6805a.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Northamptonshire named most enterprising place in Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/enterprise/docs/r/12-984-removing-red-tape-for-challenger-businesses.pdf"&gt;Report: removing red tape for challenger businesses (PDF, 284 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47564</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/importance-of-aerospace"/>
    <title>Importance of aerospace</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Mark Prisk sets out the government's commitment to the aerospace industry through funding, education and partnerships.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a Government, we value the aerospace sector. As the Prime Minister said yesterday, when opening the show, this is a £24bn industry with 100,000 direct jobs and many more besides.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the prospects for the sector are remarkable. 27,000 fixed wing aircraft alone will be needed between now and 2030. That’s a $3.2trillion market. These are just some of the reasons why we formed the Aerospace Growth Partnership.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by partnership, we mean not just Government and industry working together, but also industry with industry (greater collaboration/innovation).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the Secretary of State has launched our Strategic Vision for Aerospace. It is a statement of intent from both Government and industry, that far from giving up our position in global market; we are going to build on our strengths and broaden our customer base.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It underlines this Government’s commitment to a clear industrial strategy - working with industry to recognise where the UK has strong capability and then backing it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means in the short term the Aerospace Growth Partnership looking at what capability currently exists in UK, and what needs to be done to improve it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means in the medium term looking at opportunities for UK business on upgrade programmes and to introduce new technology.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it means in the long term that we want to be more competitive and win the maximum work on next generation of aircraft, which is why work is already underway to identify the key technologies to achieve that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On technology, we know that business is looking for greater certainty about the quantum and flow of funding available. We realise that an industry like aerospace needs longer term predictability from Government if you’re to have the confidence to invest. So we are committed to work with you on this through the Aerospace Growth Partnership.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The danger of any Government/industry forum is that it could simply be about words. The Aerospace Growth Partnership is not about words. Indeed it has already acted.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus in the Budget, we’ve agreed to £60m to create UK Centre for Aerodynamics.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And over past two days we have now announced nearly £200m of jointly funded programmes with business. These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first £47m research and technology projects on aerodynamics as priorities for the Aerodynamics Centre; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A series of manufacturing process research projects totalling £80m to be delivered through the TSB and led by Rolls-Royce &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creation of 500 Masters level places for aerospace engineers, (in which business will invest alongside Government) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And in addition, there is a £15m joint Government and industry investment announced today, through the Technology Strategy Board, for 11 major business-led R&amp;amp;D projects. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the Aerospace Growth Partnership is not just about money. Much of our work is about how business engages with government; and how business engages with itself especially across supply chains. Our work will continue until December when Aerospace Growth Partnership produces a final report, but we’re already seeing positive progress.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, as the Strategic Vision is developed into a long-term strategy, the Government will play its part by: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximising the impact it can have on growth, by aligning all our policy levers to encourage investment and exports; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And creating a more educated workforce, that is the most flexible in Europe. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To date, the Aerospace Growth Partnership process has involved some 80 business people directly involved in our working groups - for example on Technology, Supply Chain Competitiveness, Manufacturing Capability, and External Engagement. They have been supported by eight full-time secondees from business - some really bright young talent.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the experience with the secondees has been so beneficial, that we are now considering how we can make secondees a permanent feature of the dialogue between government and business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-listening-and-acting"&gt;Government listening and acting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke earlier about partnership. Partners listen to each other, so in that spirit I have some good news.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbus, Rolls-Royce, Boeing and others have come to us and requested that the UK Government ratifies the Cape Town Convention and Aircraft Protocol. The aims of this are to bring speed, certainty and cost savings to the process of repossessing aircraft and engines, in cases of insolvency or default, where these assets are in a country whose legal system may not make that an easy process. The hope is that the benefits to financiers then result in reduced finance costs for airlines.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to confirm to you today that we are committed to ratifying the Convention. We first have some more work to do with business, following our Call for Evidence, to clarify the costs and benefits involved. And as part of our policy process we plan to consult on changes to the law needed for UK ratification. So we will be working closely with business to complete the process, as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence"&gt;Defence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of us listening is on defence - a major part of our advanced manufacturing base. The Government has twin responsibilities in relation to defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firstly, to ensure that our armed forces, national security, and law enforcement agencies have the best capabilities we can afford, at the best value for money for the taxpayer. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Secondly, to recognise that a healthy and competitive defence and security industry, contributes to growth and a re-balanced economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I have made clear this morning, our experience on the civil side with the Aerospace Growth Partnership has been a positive one.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we now intend to start a similar dialogue with the defence and security industry. That will help maximise the value to our economy of this industry without undermining our efforts to get best value for the MOD as customer.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are doing much already to promote defence exports and encourage defence SMEs. There are other areas where we can do more to encourage investment into the UK. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to exploit synergies between civil and military technologies; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also need to promote reforms that encourage the movement of people between defence and other parts of our advanced manufacturing base to help develop and sustain vital engineering skills. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the Prime Minister has asked my Secretary of State to lead on work in this area and you will be hearing more from us about that soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I want to say something briefly about skills in aerospace.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sector is not only growing at an incredible rate (effectively doubling in size every 15 years), but we also know technologies in next generation aircraft are likely to be radically different. So it is essential that we continue to attract young talent with the right skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are expanding substantially expanding the number of apprenticeships right across industry.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also creating 24 University Technical College, so from 2014 onwards, thousand more young people can gain good engineering skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also pleased to see that up to 10,000 young people are expected to participate here in Futures Day on Friday in a wide range of events, and so get a taster of the exciting career opportunities in aerospace. BIS is proud to be a Gold Sponsor and I would like to congratulate ADS in putting together such a fantastic programme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like also to thank you for your involvement in 2 other joint projects with Government: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See Inside Manufacturing - the aerospace industry hosted over 60 events in June alone aimed at young people, undergraduates and teachers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make it in Great Britain - aerospace is a major participant of exhibition later this month at Science Museum, which showcase the best of our design, engineering and manufacturing. I hope to see you there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope that these events will inspire the next generation of engineers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, this is a sector with a big future. One that will create growth and prosperity for the UK for many years to come. It won’t be easy, but together we can win out. I look forward to working with you all, to turn that ambition into reality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47121</id>
    <published>2012-07-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/top-inventors-make-it-in-great-britain"/>
    <title>Top Inventors Make it in Great Britain</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Minister Mark Prisk has announced the finalists of a nationwide competition to find the UK’s next big pre-market products, processes and concepts.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;4 Jul 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successful entries of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://makeitingreatbritain.bis.gov.uk/NEWS-04072012091538"&gt;Make it in Great Britain Challenge&lt;/a&gt; include new technology which could offer relief to tinnitus sufferers and a pram that folds into a rucksack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are two of the 17 finalists announced today in the challenge, backed by Dragon’s Den tycoon Deborah Meaden and Business Minister Mark Prisk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other top brainwaves include an eco-friendly alternative to concrete and an engine that cuts fuel consumption by two thirds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inventions are all still in development and winning could get them into production. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK is full of creative manufacturing expertise, and I’m delighted that we are able to celebrate some of the best pre-market ideas through the Challenge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve had a great response, and I’m particularly excited by some of the entries received in the Breakthrough category. I’d urge the public to get voting and tell us who they would like to receive the honour of being named the People’s Choice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team of six expert judges came up with the 17 shortlisted entries, which will all go on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/visitmuseum/galleries/make_great_britain.aspx"&gt;display at London’s Science Museum&lt;/a&gt; this summer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will benefit from the exposure of their idea to multi-national companies and the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning entries will showcase alongside names such as Mars and McLaren, and leading small and medium businesses like Ultra Global in celebration of manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visitors to the six-week exhibition will be invited to vote on their favourite entry. The winners from each weekly vote will feature together in the final week of the exhibit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/seeinsidemanufacturing/"&gt;See Inside Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://makeitingreatbritain.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Make it in Great Britain website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Make-it-in-Great-Britain-Challenge-finalists-unveiled-67c60.aspx"&gt;Press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47109</id>
    <published>2012-06-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/manufacturers-open-doors-to-careers"/>
    <title>Manufacturers open doors to careers</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Minister Mark Prisk has officially launched this year’s See Inside Manufacturing programme to encourage young people to consider a career in manufacturing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;18 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;See Inside Manufacturing involves businesses from across the food &amp;amp; drink, aerospace &amp;amp; defence and automotive sectors. They will open their doors for over 100 events throughout June to show young people, teachers and careers advisers what exciting opportunities exist in 21st century manufacturing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people are expected to visit iconic names such as Coca Cola, Mars, Warburtons, Aston Martin, BMW, Jaguar Land Rover, Airbus and GKN Aerospace over the coming weeks and get hands on with the latest designs and technologies that make Britain one of the world’s leading manufacturing nations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Minister visited Coca Cola Enterprises in Edmonton, London where he joined pupils from Uxbridge College to see for himself how the famous drink is made.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This year See Inside Manufacturing is bigger and better following the success of its pilot last year in the automotive sector - when over 1000 people visited 100 events across the country to learn more about the exciting opportunities available in manufacturing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Manufacturers-open-doors-to-careers-67b73.aspx"&gt;Read the Press Notice in Full - Manufacturers open doors to careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/seeinsidemanufacturing/"&gt;See Inside Manufacturing: BIS microsite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://makeitingreatbritain.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Make it in Great Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://audioboo.fm/boos/806118-mark-prisk-on-ellesmere-port-and-the-make-it-in-great-britain-campaign-makeitingb"&gt;Hear Mark Prisk on why 2012 is about changing perceptions of manufacturing careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
