<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-without-portfolio</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-without-portfolio.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister without Portfolio and Chairman of the Conservative Party</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17189</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/inter-faith-week-and-a-year-of-service-speech"/>
    <title>Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service speech</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to thank you all for coming to this a wonderful event, marking both Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks also to the Faith-based Regeneration Network, Mitzvah Day, the Co-exist Foundation and others for their help in making the event a reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for the people here, it’s Inter Faith Week every week and it’s A Year of Service every year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because day in, day out, you are giving your time, your energy, your hearts and your souls to making your communities better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United by faith and driven by faith - whichever faith that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Sikh-run Nishkam Centre in Birmingham, which provides a whole range of training and educational opportunities for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Sewa Day, which inspires Hindus across the country to acts of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like the St Vincent de Paul Society, which provides gifts and hospitality to the needy in the run-up to Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These projects and many more prove that faith motivates good works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today you have a government that doesn’t deny that fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a government that supports, celebrates and - in my case - shares that motivation. A government that does God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know that people who ‘do God’ do good things up and down the country every single day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys show people of religious observance are more likely to become volunteers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see that fact in the 30,000 faith-based charities making a difference throughout Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="interfaith-action"&gt;Interfaith action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the interfaith movement officially started in 1893 with the ‘World’s Parliament of Religions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s major religions came together in Chicago for serious discussions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I don’t think they would have a parliament; they’d have a day of social action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because today interfaith dialogue has become much more about interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always argued that interfaith shouldn’t just be tea in a draughty church hall or a samosa in the local mosque between the imam and the vicar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t just be clergy to clergy: it should be congregation to congregation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I helped get a programme called Active Faith off the ground - which, of course, became Near Neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the wonderful projects we see here today are just a small selection of the 300 local projects that have been supported so far.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producing projects like the Departure Café, a drop-in centre and community hub for Tower Hamlets, which I hope to visit soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of local congregations coming together to ‘do their bit’ underpin our support for the A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’ll agree - there can be no better way of marking Her Majesty the Queen’s many years of service to our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Year of Service has produced some fantastic projects, like the wonderful Mitzvah Mummies, who I went to see yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers and their toddlers, meeting, talking to and sharing moments with residents of a retirement home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integenerational interaction - such a simple idea and so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Faith and Communities, every day I see the power and the potential of interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last Thursday as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a catch-up with the Chief Rabbi… A meeting with Christian groups… An introduction with the Buddhist Network… A speech at my department’s Eid event… And a House of Lords debate on the importance of religion in society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the common thread running through these events wasn’t the fact these people observed a faith. It was that they were inspired to do good things as a result of their belief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I’m so proud that we have so many local and national 300 inter faith organisations in the UK - more than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I’m so proud that 3 Faiths Forum, the Joseph Interfaith Foundation, the Christian-Muslim Forum are leading the way in the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I am so heartened to see the launch this week of advice to couples and families on interfaith marriages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-identities"&gt;Stronger identities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had my own theory on inter faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that if you are stronger in your identity then you are more tolerant of others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who don’t associate with people of other beliefs because they think it somehow weakens theirs - they have got it the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if you’re a person who unites with people of other faiths for a common goal - it doesn’t make you less of a Muslim, less of a Hindu, less of a Jew - it makes you more of one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is no more powerful demonstration of one’s security in one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I went to the Vatican earlier this year and argued that Europe should be stronger in its Christian identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Christian heritage of Britain is what has made me feel comfortable here in practising my faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending my daughter to an Anglican convent school made her feel stronger in her identity. When she would swap ‘Amen’ for ‘Ameen’ during the Lord’s Prayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain leads the world in its interfaith ethos. But I think we can build on the progress we’ve made since that conference in American back in 1893. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that if we - people of all faiths and none - pull together, we can defeat the intolerance and bigotry faced by people of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, an attack on a mosque is an attack on a church; an attack on a gudwara is an attack on a synagogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, an attack on one faith is an attack on all faiths. So let’s be inspired by the story of Siavosh Derakhi, who has recently been recognised for founding Young Muslims Against Anti-Semitism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by the words of President Obama, following the release of the abhorrent, gratuitously offensive ‘Innocence of Muslims’ film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he said: “to be credible, those who condemn that slander must also condemn the hate we see when the image of Jesus Christ is desecrated, churches are destroyed, or the Holocaust is denied. Let us condemn incitement against Sufi Muslims, and Shia pilgrims.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by all the good things that are done and can be done in the name of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the subject of inspiration I want to present this beautiful piece of artwork.
Doctor Fox, I know you’re accepting this on behalf of the Evelina Hospital, so thank you, and also to the extremely talented artist Sam Cowan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m off to see some more fantastic artwork now as I go and award the winner of the Faith Through a Lens competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me once again thank you for coming today and thank you for all you do. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27239</id>
    <published>2012-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-priorities-for-the-commonwealth-in-2012"/>
    <title>UK priorities for the Commonwealth in 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Howell discussed Commonwealth priorities with an influential group of stakeholders on 9 January, at a conference organised by The Round Table: The Commonwealth Journal of International Affairs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Howell said the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Perth in October resulted in some of the most significant reforms in Commonwealth history.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Howell said the Perth meeting was the start of a process, which he hoped would bring real progress for the Commonwealth in 2012 and the future. He used the meeting to describe some of the key challenges for the Commonwealth in 2012, including:    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His desire to see swift implementation of reforms to the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group (CMAG).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His desire to see UK involvement in the newly created Ministerial Task Force to consider the outstanding Eminent Person Group recommendations for modernisation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further work on taking forward the charter for the Commonwealth through national consultation leading to an accessible and relevant document for all Commonwealth citizens.
The Minister said the Commonwealth Foreign Ministers meeting in September would be a key milestone for the organisation in 2012 to progress key priorities post Perth.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also said that the Commonwealth was not a top down organisation and civil society had a significant role to play. Lord Howell concluded by reiterating UK support for the Queen Elizabeth Diamond Jubilee Trust, which has been established to commemorate the extraordinary service of HM The Queen’s 60 years as Head of the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27194</id>
    <published>2011-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-expresses-concern-over-violence-in-kazakhstan"/>
    <title>Minister for Europe expresses concern over violence in Kazakhstan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today he said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was very concerned to hear about the clashes in the city of Zhanaozen in western Kazakhstan. My sympathy and thoughts are with the victims and their families. I welcome the Kazakhstani government’s initiative to set up a commission to investigate this event, led by Deputy Prime Minister Shukeev; a prompt, full and open investigation into these events is the best way forward. The reports of further violence near the village of Shetpe in the same region are worrying and I urge calm and restraint on all sides.  I also welcome the intention of the Kazakhstani authorities to engage with local representatives. I hope that renewed dialogue will help to resolve, in a peaceful manner, the broader socio-economic grievances.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26638</id>
    <published>2011-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-to-visit-bosnia-for-srebrenica-anniversary"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi to visit Bosnia for Srebrenica anniversary</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her attendance will underline the importance the Government attaches to this anniversary and its commitment to justice and reconciliation in the Balkans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government has committed considerable programme funding to Srebrenica-related projects since 2000 including to construction of the memorial complex in Srebrenica; contributing to a UNDP regional recovery programme and to public infrastructure renewal; support to the International Commission for Missing Persons in its work to identify the remains of missing persons (which has inter alia generated important evidence for ICTY trials); and legal secondments to the team in the Bosnian State Prosecutor’s Office dealing with Srebrenica-related crimes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi is meeting on Sunday evening with the High Rpepresentative, Dr Valentin Inzko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning, will be the keynote speaker at the launch of this year’s Srebrenica Summer School, an international programme for graduate research into issues such as transitional justice, genocide and post-conflict studies. She will then lay a wreath at the commemoration of victims of the Srebrenica massacre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, she will meet with the presidents of Bosnia to discuss the latest political developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Srebrenica is a name that now resonates around the world as a lesson in the consequences of unchecked evil.  But we must never lose sight of the fact that the genocide at Srebrenica is about the massacre of individuals - each of them mourned by friends, families and loved ones.  Today is also an occasion to restate our commitment to justice for those responsible for war crimes.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/25195</id>
    <published>2010-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2010-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-meets-secretary-general-of-the-organisation-of-the-islamic-conference"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi meets Secretary General of the Organisation of the Islamic Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary General Ihsanoglu welcomed Baroness Warsi as the first Muslim British Minister visiting the OIC HQ, and indicated his pleasure on the willingness of the UK for further strengthening relations with the OIC, as evident in the growing number of high level officials from the UK meeting with the OIC Secretary General in recent months.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their second meeting in six months, Professor Ihsanoglu and Baroness Warsi discussed opportunities for deepening UK-OIC relations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Baroness Warsi expressed her firm support for the recent agreement between the UK’s Department of International Development (DFID) and the Islamic Development Bank to send a secondment from DFID to the IDB, which was announced during Secretary of State Andrew Mitchell’s valuable visit last month. Baroness Warsi commented that, “this appointment is a positive step in further strengthening UK relations with the OIC which is the most prominent organisation in the Muslim world.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi acknowledged the importance of the OIC and underlined UK support for the OIC’s work. As Britain’s first Muslim Cabinet Minister, Baroness Warsi also discussed her desire to raise awareness within the wider Muslim world of the successes of, and opportunities available to people of all races, faiths and genders in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/25414</id>
    <published>2010-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-a-fantastic-few-days-in-pakistan"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi: “A fantastic few days in Pakistan”</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the third day of her first visit to Pakistan as Britain’s first female Muslim Cabinet Minister, Baroness Sayeeda Warsi (Chairman of the UK Conservative Party and Cabinet Minister without Portfolio) gave a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinpakistan.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=Speech&amp;amp;id=22576418"&gt;keynote speech&lt;/a&gt; at Fatima Jinnah University in Rawalpindi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/slideShow/index.gne?group_id=_groupid_&amp;amp;user_id=ukinpakistan&amp;amp;set_id=72157624545049506" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an event organised by the Ministry of Women’s Development and hosted by Fatima Jinnah University, Baroness Warsi took part in a panel discussion on the theme of “Women and Leadership”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel, moderated by broadcaster Saima Mohsin, comprised of the Adviser to the Prime Minister on Social Affairs, Shahnaz Wazir Ali; the Adviser to the Prime Minister on Women’s Development Yasmeen Rehman; the Vice-Chancellor of Fatima Jinnah Womens University Mrs Saeeda Asadullah Khan; Dr Shahla Javed Aslam, Chairwoman of Chamber of Commerce; and Ms Nasreen Azar, Co-Chair of the National Commission for the Status of Women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have had a fantastic few days in Pakistan.  Everywhere I have been, people have given me an amazingly warm welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course it is great that a woman, a Muslim, whose family originated in Pakistan can get into the British Cabinet.  But it’s wrong to think of this as somehow exceptional and, to the extent that it is exceptional, it shouldn’t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to give women the skills, knowledge and confidence they need to stand up for themselves.  We need to give women the power to sweep away all those cultural stigmas and chauvinistic laws which suffocate them.  And for me: that boils down to one thing - education”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/25375</id>
    <published>2010-07-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-07-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/remembering-srebrenica"/>
    <title>Remembering Srebrenica</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the occasion of the 15th anniversary of the genocide, in which over 8000 people were killed the Prime Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today marks the 15th anniversary of the massacre at Srebrenica, in which over 8000 Bosnian men and boys were killed as they fled for their lives through the forests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even today, the remains of many of the victims are undiscovered and unidentified, their families still searching for closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all those who lost loved ones, I offer my deepest sympathy on this anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must never forget the act of genocide that happened at Srebrenica. It was a crime that shamed Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We owe it to the victims to learn the lesson of Srebrenica: that evil must be confronted if humanity is to be protected. We owe it to the victims to ensure that those indicted for this appalling crime are pursued relentlessly until they are brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government I lead will not rest in its efforts to make sure that Ratko Mladic is brought to the International Criminal Tribunal at the Hague, alongside other fugitives like Goran Hadzic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we must continue to build a brighter future for Bosnia and Herzegovina and the region. We welcome recent steps towards reconciliation, such as the motion by the Serbian Parliament condemning the crimes committed at Srebrenica and apologising to the victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s new Government will take a close interest in the region. We will work hard to enable Bosnia and Herzegovina and the whole Balkan region to move forward, and in due course to join the European Union and NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we look to the future, we pledge never to forget the past, and to do all in our power to ensure that such an atrocity can never be repeated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anniversary will be marked with a ceremony in Srebrenica on 11 July. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=22515003"&gt;Baroness Sayeeda Warsi&lt;/a&gt; will represent the British government at the ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/25332</id>
    <published>2010-06-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-06-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-and-baroness-warsi-visit-bradfords-newest-mosque"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary and Baroness Warsi visit Bradford's newest mosque</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;ATL Centre for Enterprise, Manningham, hosted an informal but lively discussion including the government’s direction on foreign policy, an update from the Cabinet meeting and the Foreign Secretary’s recent trip to Pakistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary and Baroness Warsi then went on to tour Bradford’s newest mosque, in Horton Park. This is a major new mosque development which is nearing completion. The mosque has been under construction for the best part of ten years, much of the funding has been raised by the local Muslim community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On touring the mosque the Foreign Secretary congratulated the members of Suffa Tul Islam organisation for the tremendous effort and community support that has come together to build this focal point of the community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/25314</id>
    <published>2010-06-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-06-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-minister-meets-with-the-organisation-of-the-islamic-conference"/>
    <title>UK Minister meets with the Organisation of the Islamic Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi’s meeting with Secretary General Professor Ekmeleddin Ihsanoglu included discussion of the many common areas of interest between Britain and the OIC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meeting coincided with the decision by Foreign Secretary William Hague to appoint the UK’s first Special Representative to the OIC. The position will be held by the current British Consul General in Jeddah, Kate Rudd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the meeting Baroness Warsi, the first female Muslim Cabinet Minister in the UK, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to have met Professor Ihsanoglu. We had a warm and productive meeting to discuss the many issues where we share common goals with the countries of the OIC.  The appointment of a Special Representative to OIC is one way that we can work more closely with this important organisation. The Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary have both emphasised the importance we attach to Britain’s relationships with the countries of the Gulf, the Middle East and the wider Islamic world and we look forward to cooperation with the OIC over the years to come”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
