<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/minister-of-state--16</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/minister-of-state--16.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27920</id>
    <published>2012-09-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lord-howell-appointed-as-personal-adviser-to-the-foreign-secretary-on-energy-and-resource-security"/>
    <title>Lord Howell appointed as personal adviser to the Foreign Secretary on Energy and Resource Security</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Rt Hon Lord Howell of Guildford has today stepped down as Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and has been appointed as personal adviser to the Foreign Secretary on Energy and Resource Security.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to thank Lord Howell for his invaluable support and advice over the last two and a half years. He has been an exceptional Minister.  I look forward to his continuing contribution in a different capacity, as my personal adviser focusing on the crucial challenges and opportunities of energy and resource security, where I know he has an important contribution to make.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27835</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/celebrating-the-role-of-business-and-sport-in-the-commonwealth"/>
    <title>Celebrating the role of business and sport in the Commonwealth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Minister for the Commonwealth Lord Howell highlighted the relationship between business and sport within the Commonwealth family at an event on 2 August.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Commonwealth Lord Howell addressed Ministers, High Commissioners, senior business leaders and sports journalists.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosted at Scotland House by the Commonwealth Business Council, The Scottish Government, Scottish Enterprise, the Glasgow 2014 Commonwealth Games and UKTI, the event focussed on the steps that are being taken to use the 2014 Commonwealth Games in Glasgow as a platform to leverage business engagement and promote trade and investment across the Commonwealth and beyond.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office Minister spoke about the increasing business opportunities surrounding the Commonwealth Games.  He was delighted that the agenda was helping people think afresh of the huge trading opportunities in the Commonwealth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stated that we need to work together to ensure that the organisation and its networks realises its full potential. He wished Glasgow every success as the host of the Commonwealth Games 2014 and was confident they would make a significant and positive contribution to the future of the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27831</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-speaks-at-opening-gala-of-creative-cities-collection-2012"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister speaks at Opening Gala of Creative Cities Collection 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell: "This is an excellent cultural initiative bringing together paintings from all over the world, with the majority being provided by UK and Chinese artists."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 1 August, FCO Minister Lord Howell spoke at the Opening Gala of the Creative Cities Collection 2012, a week-long exhibition to forge new links and closer relations between artistic communities in China and the UK, with particular focus on Olympic Host Cities Beijing and London. The event forms part of the Inspire 2012 Programme, often known as the Cultural Olympiad. The exhibition is at the Barbican from 2nd to 7th August, and entry is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the event, Lord Howell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was delighted to be invited to address the Opening Gala of the Creative Cities Collection. This is an excellent cultural initiative bringing together paintings from all over the world, with the majority being provided by UK and Chinese artists.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exhibition complements two other important UK-China cultural events currently being held:  “UK Now”, the largest ever festival of British art in China, involving over 100 events in 17 cities; and “Tomb Treasures of Han China”, an exhibition at Cambridge’s Fitzwilliam Museum displaying the largest and most important collection of ancient royal treasures ever to leave China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Opening Gala I paid tribute to the growing depth and breadth of the Sino-British cultural relationship; these exhibitions are testament to the importance we attach to this relationship, and they will help us develop it further.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27705</id>
    <published>2012-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-urges-bahrain-to-increase-pace-of-reform"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister urges Bahrain to increase pace of reform</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Minister of State Lord Howell met the Bahraini Minister for the Interior, Lieutenant General Sheikh Rashid bin Abdullah Al Khalifa to discuss the implementation of reforms in Bahrain and the prospects for political dialogue.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the meeting, Lord Howell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Bahraini Government has made some progress in addressing the recommendations of the Independent Commission of Inquiry, but wider concerns still need to be addressed. I urged the Government to increase the pace of reform and ensure that the human rights of all Bahraini citizens are fully respected.  For the long-term stability of the country, I encourage all parties to enter into an inclusive and constructive political dialogue without preconditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Kingdom of Bahrain and the United Kingdom have a long friendship and we remain strong partners in the region. The UK stands ready to assist Bahrain as it moves ahead with comprehensive reform.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28879</id>
    <published>2012-06-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-relations-with-the-gcc-region-a-broadening-partnership"/>
    <title>UK Relations with the GCC Region: A Broadening Partnership</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell spoke about the United Kingdom’s relations with the countries of the Gulf Co-operation Council at the GCC and the City Conference on 20 June.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here this morning at the GCC and the City Conference to address such a distinguished range of guests.  I would like to thank the Middle East Association and MEED Events for the invitation to take part.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gulf has changed dramatically in recent years.  Its economies are developing rapidly, creating exciting opportunities for investment in both directions.  And while the energy sector remains an essential component, this is also a region that is diversifying.  Working to unlock these opportunities, and exploring the broader challenges the region faces going forward, will be the focus of my remarks today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also believe we need to think bigger.  So I will share too some thoughts on how and why we in the United Kingdom should broaden our partnership with the Gulf.  The region is growing in confidence on the international stage; becoming a network with an increasingly influential voice.  America is learning that it no longer calls all the shots.  We should take advantage of this growing confidence and work with the GCC region - through government; business; civil society; through all channels - to respect and support its development; and by extension, our own prosperity and security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stronger commercial links&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first put these issues into context.  The impressive growth in the Gulf’s economy in recent years has made it one of the most prosperous regions in the world; with a combined GDP now of around US$1.4 trillion.  While many Western nations were struggling with the global slowdown exacerbated by the crisis in the Eurozone last year, growth in the GCC region reached 8% of GDP, spurred by high oil prices.  This year GDP growth is projected to remain impressively strong, averaging almost 5%.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this solid economic backdrop, governments across the region are embarking on ambitious investment programmes.  They are seeking to diversify their economies, and to meet the growing aspirations of their people.  In infrastructure alone there are plans to invest an estimated $2 trillion over the next decade.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Britain we are striving to be the Gulf’s commercial partner of choice.  We exported around £10 billion worth of goods last year, which is more than we exported to Latin America and the Caribbean combined.  More than to China, three times what we sell to India, it also represented an increase of 10% over the year before.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a trend that we want to see continue, indeed intensify.  But we will only be able to achieve this if we work harder and think more creatively.  We are facing unprecedented competition from the emerging economies, particularly in Asia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we as a Government have sought to put growth and prosperity back at the heart of our foreign policy.  Our overseas network is working tirelessly to support UK business in the region - as our staff in Muscat did recently, supporting HSBC as it merged its Omani operations with Oman International Bank to become the second-largest bank in the country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also established a network of bilateral trade agreements with the Gulf states to identify and raise awareness of commercial opportunities, and to tackle barriers to business.  We are being ambitious, targeting, for instance, a 60% increase in trade with the UAE over just six years, to £12 billion by 2015.  And alongside this, we are continuing our work with the Gulf states to address problems that ultimately stifle growth, including corruption.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t just about what the Government can do for British companies.  The business community also needs to better respond to what the countries in the region want.  It is simply not enough in this time of global competition for us to knock on the door, sell our wares and move on.  Gulf countries want long-term partnerships, training and high quality after-sales service.  So it is pleasing to see that more and more British investors are taking this approach; building enduring relationships to support our mutual prosperity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sovereign Wealth Funds&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is it, by any means, just a one-way street: inward investment from the Gulf totalled around $2.25 billion last year.  One need look no further than the London skyline to see the impact this is having on Britain.  The Shard, to be officially opened next month after significant Qatari investment and little more than three years of construction, is a truly towering example of what can be achieved when we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shard is just the tip - albeit a tall one - of a very large iceberg, as GCC countries invest the large surpluses they have accumulated in recent years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant proportion is being channelled into financial assets, with the Gulf emerging as a major supplier of global capital.  It is home to some of the world’s largest Sovereign Wealth Funds, with an estimated US$1-1.5 trillion in assets under sovereign management.  The City of London already plays an absolutely key role within these capital markets.  But I believe we can do even more to strengthen Britain’s position as the key business hub in and beyond Europe.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Government, we are reaching out to the Sovereign Wealth Funds across the Gulf to forge stronger, more strategic relationships.  At a time of global financial turmoil, the world clearly see Britain as a relative safe haven.  The queue of international customers buying up London residences bears testament to that!  We have taken action to reduce our budget deficit and rebuild our economy, which has secured stability; and we have a robust, reliable legal system.  So we are working more closely with the Sovereign Funds; helping them to identify opportunities for investment here.  And in doing so, we are also seeking to better understand their needs and investment criteria.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure is a particularly promising area.  The Chancellor, George Osborne, published the UK’s National Infrastructure Plan last autumn, which outlines our vision for the future of infrastructure in Britain.  This vision includes smart, sustainable infrastructure that will enable and ultimately underpin growth and prosperity.  It outlines £250 billion worth of investment across all sectors to deliver this plan - including energy, transport, utilities and communications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GCC states are in a unique position globally to make these investments, given the impact that current market turbulence is having on the traditional sources of capital for infrastructure.  A better position than already squeezed UK consumers.  And while this is, I know, often a new asset class for many investors, we believe that the plan offers a once-in-a-generation opportunity to invest in the UK’s future, to help drive sustainable, long-term and mutually beneficial growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shifting energy patterns&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crucial element of our relationship with the GCC region is, clearly, our co-operation on energy - an issue that forms part of my Ministerial portfolio.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the demand side the emergence and rapid growth of new energy markets is driving global demand.  The IEA predict that, if unchecked, energy demand in non-OECD Asia will more than double over the next 25 years.  That would make it consume almost four and a half times as much as the European Union currently consumes.  Meanwhile, demand in Europe and the West is reaching a plateau.  As we impose more stringent constraints on our carbon emissions, we will need to invest in improving energy efficiency.  This is a good thing, but will have consequences for where energy producers in the Gulf look to find secure markets, and on how our global relationships develop.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the supply side, new technologies and new discoveries are also driving change.  The unconventional gas and now oil revolution in the US has demonstrated the availability of plentiful and relatively cheap energy sources.  Unconventional developments in Australia and China, and conventional discoveries in West Africa, will create new production hubs that may soon challenge the traditional hydrocarbon supply markets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Gulf also faces challenges closer to home.  Growing domestic energy demand, driven by demographic change, is reducing the export capacity of key GCC producers.  This is not only adding pressure to an already tight global energy market; it will also have a severe effect on government spending in the region, up to 80% of which is dependent on oil revenues.  And this comes at a time when the response of many Gulf States to regional tensions has been to increase public sector spending.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do these developments mean for the GCC region; and how should they - and we in Britain - react?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, the GCC’s oil producing countries have to make strategic decisions about their long-term interests.  As the global energy picture moves progressively eastward, they will be looking increasingly to China and the other emerging economies for secure energy demand.  This will doubtless affect how their relationships develop with traditional allies in Europe and the West.&lt;br&gt;
And our trade will need to change.  As new technologies develop in the West and we move towards much greater energy efficiency, new unconventional gas sources, nuclear energy and to renewable - hopefully commercial - we will become less dependent on Middle Eastern crude imports.  But that does not mean trade should cease.  Our relationship must mature further, moving away from the one-way supply of oil to more open economic co-operation, focussed on trade and technological exchanges.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key area for potential collaboration is energy efficiency.  It seems odd to think of the Gulf as facing a domestic energy crisis, but unless GCC countries tackle their growing energy consumption, the consequences for exports could be devastating.  Subsidy reform is essential, but remains unlikely while regional governments continue to increase spending.  The UK is leading the way in energy efficiency investment, so we should share these experiences with our partners in the Gulf.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of new energy sources will also be key.  Nuclear power can provide affordable and reliable energy across the region.  The UK has a global reputation in operation, safety and efficient regulation, and British companies are ideally placed to capitalise on the region’s emerging nuclear sector.   Renewable energy sources are also developing rapidly in the Gulf, especially photovoltaic and other solar energies.  The UK boasts market-leading expertise in such technologies, although the Chinese challenge is formidable, and I hear regularly about British business successes in these, and other growing renewable energy sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let us not forget traditional hydrocarbons.  New opportunities continue to emerge in the region, be they unconventional extraction in Saudi Arabia, exciting Gas-to-Liquids programmes in Qatar, or petrochemical and distribution deals in Oman.  UK businesses are at the forefront of these developments.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The GCC’s presence on the international stage&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the region develops and prospers, so it grows in confidence on the international stage.&lt;br&gt;
The GCC countries are becoming a network with an increasingly influential voice.  This has been particularly clear in Libya, where the GCC was a constructive and vocal supporter of the international action against the Gaddafi regime.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Libya is certainly not the only example.  The UAE is playing a leading role in the counter-piracy efforts in the region, and will host an important conference on the subject later this month.  The Darfur peace agreement was signed in Doha, with Qatar providing vital support for the process.   In Yemen, the GCC initiative was key to the process of transition, with Saudi Arabia providing leadership as a co-chair of the Friends of Yemen group.   And we are also seeing continued action on Syria - taken on a co-ordinated basis among GCC states - including the important political signal sent in March of closing the GCC Embassies in Damascus.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is clear too that the GCC countries have a growing role to play in shaping the region’s wider political as well as economic future.  As the Arab turmoil has shown us, lasting stability will depend on anticipating the hopes and goals of citizens; giving them a greater stake in the success of their country.  We therefore welcome, for instance, the King of Bahrain’s commitment to transparency and reform by commissioning and agreeing to implement the recommendations of the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry, following the unrest last year.  We will continue to support Bahrain’s efforts where it is taking incremental reform steps to deliver a safe and prosperous future for their people.  And we will support and welcome the same commitment to steady reform throughout the Gulf region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is in our national interest for this Government to step up its engagement with these Gulf countries - both on regional and wider international issues.  We are delighted that the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary will meet his GCC counterparts tomorrow for their summer meeting of Foreign Ministers, which is being held in London.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the networks we in Britain value most, the Commonwealth, also has a role here.  GCC countries share a growing interest in the Commonwealth connection.  They are understandably keen to partner with this expanding web of emerging economies, which is something we should continue to encourage.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A broader partnership&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this growing determination among the GCC that underlines the importance of broadening our partnership with countries in the Gulf in all senses.  We recognise this need, which is why the Government launched the Gulf Initiative two years ago.  The Initiative aims to increase the strength, breadth and depth of our relationship with the Gulf, and it is delivering: there have been more than 20 British Ministerial visits to the region in the last quarter alone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these was the Minister for Further Education, John Hayes, who visited Saudi Arabia and the UAE last month.  I mention this because I see education and training as a particularly promising area for growth.  Our links are already strong, with tens of thousands of students from GCC countries coming to the UK each year.  They choose to study here because of our reputation for excellence in education, training and research; because the UK has some of the best, most enduring educational brands in the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should nurture and build on this, which is why it is so satisfying to see British institutions establishing themselves in the region.  Our universities are reinforcing our reputation and supporting the development of the region by opening campuses - including University College London, which last year became the first British university to open a campus in Qatar.  Nor is it just universities, with top British schools such as Repton and Sherborne also rapidly establishing themselves as market leaders.  &lt;br&gt;
We are, then, working from a good base.  But I believe there is real scope to strengthen our links further in this and in other areas, from increasing our co-operation on security to expanding our exchanges in the ‘softer’ areas of design, arts, sports and so on, in fact in all cultural areas.&lt;br&gt;
And in doing so, we should not restrict our approach to our bilateral links alone.  It is not just about us; it is about making the most of the networks we value.  The European Union, for instance, could strengthen its links with the region - not least by concluding the EU-GCC Free Trade Agreement that has, unfortunately, been stalled for some time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear, I think, that Britain’s relationship with the Gulf - so important historically, and so important now - will remain absolutely key to our country’s prosperity and security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should accept too that it is an evolving relationship that has changed over time, and that will continue to change as the region develops and as global energy trends shift.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have made clear today, this poses both opportunities and challenges - for the region, and for Britain.  I firmly believe that if we work together to sustain a broader relationship with the Gulf, Britain and the GCC will remain enduring partners, even in these most rapid of changing times.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28880</id>
    <published>2012-06-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/iraq-s-natural-resources-and-the-potential-to-tackle-the-world-energy-challenges"/>
    <title>Iraq’s Natural Resources and the Potential to Tackle the World Energy Challenges</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell spoke about Iraq’s natural resources and its potential to tackle the world’s energy challenges at the Iraq Petroleum Conference on 18 June.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister, Ministers, Chairman and expert audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives me great pleasure to be here this morning to address such a distinguished range of guests at the Iraq Petroleum Conference.  I would like to thank the CWC Group for the invitation to take part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember well our discussions last year and am struck both by how much has changed in Iraq, although also by how many of the familiar challenges remain.  Of course, there has been considerable progress as we have heard.  To give one more example, oil production in BP’s massive Rumaila field has helped lift Iraq’s oil exports to 2.5 million barrels per day (mbd), overtaking Iran as the region’s second largest oil exporter.  And incidentally, this has only been possible thanks to the success of a major project by Foster Wheeler UK to increase export capacity from the south, already up from 1.8 mbd to a potential 2.7 mbd, and on track for much higher levels by the end of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly pleased to be speaking today about the role of Iraq in the global energy picture.  How we should respond to changing global energy trends is the vital strategic question that we should be asking at this time and I am delighted to be given this opportunity to share my thoughts on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Global Energy Challenge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global energy challenge is familiar to us all.  We must secure reliable and affordable energy in an increasingly volatile market, while simultaneously reducing the dangerous impact of climate change.  Our success at the former is essential to drive our global economic recovery; our success at the latter will define the lives of future generations.  Neither can be achieved in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge begins with a familiar story of opposing market fundamentals.  We all know that global oil demand, driven by the growing of markets in China and the East, will continue to expand for decades.  In 2011 we survived political and other disruptions such as Libya, Fukushima and Syria, yet production is now above consumption.  In the long term, there is less certainty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures from the International Energy Agency illustrate this well: over the next 25 years, the global demand for oil is predicted to grow by an additional 20 million barrels per day above current demand, while field depletion will remove around 47 million barrels per day from the market supply.  This means that by 2035, we will need to find at least 67 million new barrels per day to meet global demand.  This is the equivalent of around 3 million barrels per day every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put this in some context, when I became Secretary of State for Energy in 1979, conventional oil discoveries exceeded field depletion by almost 14 billion barrels and we were entering a boom in North Sea oil production.  The challenges in the Middle East were no easier to reconcile back then, but the market was infinitely more forgiving.  It is no understatement to suggest that the resource competition we face ahead is unlike anything that we have faced before, although even these predictions could be up-ended by events such as the shale gas and shale oil revolutions, and the discovery of vast new oil deposits such as Bakken in the US and dwarfing that, Russia’s Bazhenov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so our struggle for reliable and affordable energy takes us to ever more volatile and inhospitable environments.  The technological leaps we have made - from developing unconventional oils to gas-to-liquid production, from the deep pre-salt fields of Brazil to arctic exploration in Siberia - these are testament to our ingenuity and endeavour.  I believe that the progress we have seen in Iraq over the past decade is as important as these technological achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iraqi production&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iraq has a vital role to play in meeting the global energy challenge, whatever form it takes.  The natural wealth of Iraq is immense and its potential significant.  It is the nation’s tragedy that historic mismanagement and political repression allowed so little of this wealth to reach its people in the past.  Iraq’s challenge, our challenge, is to harness the vast oil lakes beneath Basra and Kirkuk, Baghdad and Erbil, and use them to drive development for the benefit of all Iraqis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success would be hugely beneficial, not just for the people of Iraq, but for the global energy market too.  Iraq has demonstrated an ability and a desire to lead this process, and we should applaud their tenacity and determination.  The ambitious targets and investment in domestic infrastructure speak volumes.  And the year on year growth in production - as much as three million barrels per day last month, including 2.5 million in exports - demonstrates clearly the technical and innovative capacity the country has never lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Iraq boasts not only enviable oil resources, but also substantial natural gas reserves.  These must be harnessed for electricity generation first and foremost to unlock Iraq’s domestic economic potential.  But gas will also grow to play a major part in Iraq’s exports in the long term.  The joint venture between Shell and the South Gas Company shows that Iraq is already thinking in these terms.  We should commend this foresight and welcome the contribution that Iraq can soon make to global energy security in gas, as well as in oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Role in the global market&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Iraq deserves to retake its position at the energy top table.  Over the next twenty years, it could be that that we will see the country develop into one of the key global players in the energy market.  This will bring with it great responsibility.  And for this reason, Iraq should be asking itself some important questions about the road ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through investment in spare production capacity, Iraq has the potential to become a stabilising force in the market.  I believe that Iraq could be the next swing producer, akin only to Saudi Arabia, and could grow to play a crucial role in steadying the spikes and troughs of the global energy market.  Such a move would require significant investment, and a responsible hand at the wheel, but could provide the reliable engine that drives stable and prosperous development for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could also help guide OPEC to work more closely with consuming nations through international organisations, including the International Energy Forum, to the mutual benefit of producers and consumers.  The divisions that beset OPEC and pit the so-called ‘doves’ against the ‘hawks’ are noteworthy.  Iraq could help turn the organisation towards a new and more stabilising path that helps producers and consumers to stabilise supply and demand, whilst seeking to meet Asia’s voracious appetite for energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us not get ahead of ourselves.  The oil beneath Iraq has existed for millennia.  The country has long had the natural wealth to develop in all the glorious ways we predict today, yet through mismanagement, repression and political turmoil it has singularly failed to do so.  The path to realising this potential will not be without difficulty.  And this will be compounded by changing global energy trends, as demand shifts from the historic energy hubs in Europe and the West to the rapidly growing markets in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges in Iraq&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment is vital.  We must work to create an environment where profitable investment is encouraged and can flourish.  Trust, confidence, a stable underlying political climate and, of course, physical security are the necessary conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, the results of the fourth oil and gas bidding round last month were disappointing, with only three of twelve blocks awarded.  A combination of factors, including unattractive contract terms and geologically riskier acreage, led to a lukewarm response from 39 companies that paid the entrance fee to bid.  Leaders need to take note of global energy developments.  With growth in unconventional gas pushing down prices worldwide, gas production is less attractive than in the past.  Some analysts estimated that the blocks on offer needed a $10-20 per barrel fee to be viable - up to ten times the $2 per barrel cost bravely accepted by BP for production in the Rumaila oil field in the first round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the current political disquiet in Iraq continues to reduce certainty in financial markets.  Without stability, the capital that can drive Iraq’s development will stay away.  Political leaders need to address this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unblocking the long-stalled Hydrocarbon Law would be a good start.  I don’t believe any of us expect to see a solution in the near future.  And though we can point to the record production of the last few months, and take heart from the growing domestic budget, it would be wrong to pretend that this is business as usual.  Without a robust legal framework, business cannot operate with confidence.  And lack of confidence will ultimately undermine attempts to drive lasting economic and political development in Iraq.  The gains from a settled pattern between Erbil and Baghdad would be enormous - with a major stride to end political deadlock, and with Kurdistan ambitions, including a goal of 2 mbd from the region by 2019 - further reinforcing Iraq’s overall prominence in world oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses also face a number of operational challenges in Iraq which increase the risk to working in the country.  Progress must be made to improve the efficiency of imports, and tackle bureaucracy and regulation, if businesses are to be encouraged to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragile security situation also undermines business operations.  I speak to industry regularly about these challenges, and it seems to me that their impact is less on the major oil companies, who have experience operating in fragile environments, but rather more on smaller companies working along the supply chain, whose operations can be seriously impeded.  And it is the smaller businesses that often provide the innovative leaps and unique skills that make our grandest ambitions achievable.  If Iraq is to play a positive role tackling the global energy challenge, then these companies must be with us on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that tackling security is a key priority of the Iraqi Government - and for Prime Minister Al-Maliki personally - and the UK stands beside the government in its work to ensure a substantial and permanent improvement in security for all Iraqis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Government response is that we are providing support to Iraqi institutions and the rule of law under our Arab Partnership agenda, which should help counterbalance some of the dangers of over-centralisation of power.  We are working with our Gulf allies to promote greater engagement in Iraq and encouraging the Iraqi government to play a constructive role in key regional issues like the Syria crisis and the Iran challenge.  We see strong engagement by both the UK and our partners as essential to promote accountable, inclusive and transparent government, which is in turn essential for robust inward investment flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities in Iraq&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iraq is a country that brims with potential, in a region that brims with potential.  Indeed, greater co-operation between Iraq and its neighbours - and across the region as a whole - would also help to secure success.  We are already seeing some progress; the improved relations between Iraq and Kuwait, for instance, which we should welcome.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I believe Iraq is approaching its richest seam.  Yes, I see challenges.  But I see opportunities too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK business is ideally positioned to capitalise on these opportunities.  Looking around this room today, I see expertise from across the oil sector, from upstream investment analysts to scientists developing the next petrochemical breakthroughs.  British industry has a lot to be proud of, especially in the energy field.  Our expertise in project management and engineering; in design, manufacture and installation of advanced equipment; in geotechnical and reservoir management; in ground-breaking research and development; and in learning and skills training - all of these can and, I believe, will be essential components of the Iraqi energy story. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that Iraq will be part of our future, and we must make sure that British industry is part of theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is clear, Ladies and Gentlemen, that a prosperous and secure Iraq will be indispensible for a stable and affordable oil market over the coming years.  And success in this will help drive global economic recovery.  We must work together to ensure we achieve this ambition; an ambition that is in all of our interest, from humble politicians to captains of industry.  Technology and markets will be our friend.  Political instability, violence and natural disasters, like the Japanese tsunami and all the Black Swan events, will be the foes to be overcome by innovation, ingenuity and well-regulated market forces, and above all, political wisdom and far-sightedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in our economic interest, for our businessmen and women; it is in the region’s interest, to promote stability and security; it is in our global interest, to drive economic recovery; and, most importantly, it is in Iraq’s interest, to capitalise on its rich natural resources and become the country that its people know it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27583</id>
    <published>2012-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-introduces-eu-treaty-amendment-bill-to-the-house-of-lords"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister introduces EU Treaty Amendment Bill to the House of Lords</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell said that the treaty change will help eurozone countries take forward a key aspect of their plan to resolve the crisis and secure financial stability.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introducing the EU (Approval of Treaty Amendment Decision) Bill today, he said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A stable and healthy eurozone is important for the UK’s long-term growth and prosperity. This treaty change is firmly in the UK’s national interest, since it makes explicit the ability of eurozone countries to set up a permanent European Stability Mechanism to support other eurozone countries in financial trouble. This will be a fund by the eurozone, for the eurozone, and, unlike the situation this Government inherited, the UK will not be liable through the EU budget for any future eurozone bailouts. This treaty change will help eurozone countries take forward a key aspect of their plan to resolve the crisis and secure financial stability.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Treaty amendment will add the following new paragraph to Article 136 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“3. The Member States whose currency is the euro may establish a stability mechanism to be activated if indispensable to safeguard the stability of the euro area as a whole. The granting of any required financial assistance under the mechanism will be made subject to strict conditionality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Treaty change was agreed by EU leaders at the December 2010 European Council. The draft Treaty change Decision was then examined by Parliament in March 2011, under the provisions of previous legislation. Both Houses gave their approval. The Decision was then adopted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/global-issues/international-institutions/european-council-decision-article-136"&gt;March European Council in Brussels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By agreeing to the Article 136 Treaty change, the Prime Minister secured agreement that the ESM will remove any UK liabilities for future euro area programmes of financial assistance under the EU Budget. As the preamble to the Decision states, “the European Council agreed that, as this mechanism is designed to safeguard the financial stability of the euro area as whole, Article 122(2) of the TFEU will no longer be needed for such purposes. The Heads of State or Government therefore agreed that it should not be used for such purposes.” The ESM will replace both the European Financial Stability Facility and the European Financial Stabilisation Mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Bill is a result of the commitment this Government has made to stricter public and Parliamentary controls on EU Treaty changes. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/european-union/eu-act/"&gt;EU Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; enshrined in law that that approval of EU Treaty changes such as this require a Parliamentary statement to be laid by a Minister, followed by an Act of Parliament. The statement was laid by the Foreign Secretary on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/global-issues/international-institutions/EU-Act-2011-statement-131011"&gt;13 October 2011&lt;/a&gt; and confirms that as this Treaty change only applies to eurozone Member States, it does not fall within section 4 of the EU Act and consequently, no referendum is required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The provisions in Article 136 TFEU only apply to eurozone Member States and do not apply to the UK. However, any changes to the EU Treaties must be ratified by the UK and all other EU Member States before they can enter into force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28871</id>
    <published>2012-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/making-the-most-of-our-relations-with-latin-america"/>
    <title>Making the most of our relations with Latin America</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell reaffirmed Britain's commitment to deepening relations and co-operation with Latin America at the Latin America Investment Forum.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When this Government took office we made it clear that we wanted to reinvigorate the UK’s relationship with old friends, allies and networks. Nowhere was this more urgent than in Latin America. This Latin American Investment Forum is testament to the revival of our connections with that special region. And it presents an invaluable opportunity for exploring avenues for cooperation, collaboration, and support. It is a great pleasure for me to be here today to be a part of that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Longstanding Connection&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something very special about the bond between the United Kingdom and Latin America.  We were among the very first countries to recognise the potential of the region in the 19th Century, when Foreign Secretary George Canning helped negotiate Brazil’s independence. Britain gave more support to the 19th Century independence movements in Latin America than any other foreign power, this included volunteers, thousands of whom fought bravely in the armies of the great Liberator Simon Bolivar, as well as financial assistance and diplomatic recognition. We enjoyed close trading links during that time and played a big part in your early economic development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British mark on the region of which I am perhaps most proud was made by a man named Charles Miller.  Born in Sao Paolo to a Scot in 1874, he was sent at the age of 10 to be educated in Southampton.  When he returned to Brazil in 1894, he filled his suitcase with two footballs and a manual of the rules of the game.  He worked to set up the first football league in Brazil, the Liga Paulista, and won the inaugural championship, playing as a striker for Sao Paolo Athletic Club.  Many attribute the genesis of the ‘beautiful game’ in Latin America to Charles Miller, and I am more than happy for the United Kingdom to take the recognition for this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by the late 20th century, Britain had looked away.  Four of our Latin American Embassies were shut, diplomats withdrawn and our links faltered, just as Latin America began its extraordinary rise.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reengaging with Latin America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government came to office determined to give new energy to the relationship that Britain has with the region and we believe that we have now opened a new chapter in our shared history. Under this Government we are actively developing our diplomatic and our economic engagement.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary announced in November 2010 his intention to drive Britain’s most ambitious effort to strengthen ties with Latin America in 200 years, since the days of Canning. This is not just rhetoric. Since then, we have been turning our words into action.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are literally cementing our commitment by opening a new consulate in Recife, re-opening our Embassy in El Salvador, and expanding our diplomatic staff across Latin America.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have welcomed Latin American leaders to our country including President Pinera, President Santos and President Martinelli and Foreign Ministers Holguin and Almagro.  Last year, the number of British Ministerial visits to the region more than trebled compared with the number in previous years.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have set targets to double our trade with Brazil, Mexico and Colombia by 2015 - and good progress has been made, UK exports to these countries have increased by 15%, 11% and 30% respectively.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have just signed a ‘Science without borders’ agreement which will bring 10,000 Brazilian students to British universities over the next four years and are committed to attracting bright young adults from all Latin American countries to our universities. And the British Council has trebled its budget for the region, investing in cultural exchanges, English language training and education. In every way, Britain is back in Latin America; and back to stay.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Relationships for a Networked World&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not about re-setting the clock.  The relationships that we seek to forge with all the countries of the region are modern, adaptive, and reflective of the new realities of international relations.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;States are increasingly organising themselves into networks.  New networks like the Community of Latin American and Caribbean States (CELAC); old networks like the Commonwealth; political networks like the European Union and economic networks like ASEAN.  Regional groups are certainly strengthening across the world, but these groups are not rigid or immutable.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor have they diminished the role of individual states as some predicted. On the contrary, regional networks have allowed diverse states with diverse needs to pursue diverse objectives together.  It is now easier than ever before to build fluid and dynamic partnerships, alliances and connections.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building networks is about harnessing one’s connections; using the connections of others and finding other like-minded groupings that share similar ends, and possess complementary means.  For example, rapidly growing economies like China are extending their economic ties across the world, including in Latin America. There is enormous benefit in three-way commercial cooperation among Latin American, Chinese and  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UK interests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we want to make the most out of our connections around the world.  We are a member of one of the world’s longstanding global networks - the Commonwealth - with 54 nations that brings together countries in Europe, the Americas, Africa, Asia and the Pacific and which contains a third of the world’s population and some of its fastest growing economies.  We are also the world’s sixth largest trading nation even though we comprise just 1% of the world’s population; second only to the USA in the amount of money we invest abroad and always outward looking and intrepid in nature.  One in ten British citizens now lives permanently overseas.  We are also an important and active member of a European Union.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make these networks accessible to others.  We want to create networks of networks.  We want to connect our connections.  And we see real potential for doing just that in Latin America.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New groupings regional actors such as the Union of South American Nations (UNASUR), the Community of Latin American and Caribbean States (CELAC), and of course, Mercosur reflect a growing self-confidence in Latin America about the region’s increasing importance on the world stage.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, we want our Latin American partners to use us as a springboard into the European Single Market - the World’s largest trading bloc.  We want to exchange experience and knowhow between you and the Commonwealth.  We are pushing for a free trade agreement between the EU and Mercosur.  Most importantly, we want to bring our people together with your people.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complementing the networks of states of which I speak, informal networks of business-men and -women, individuals, and members of civil society, allow people around the world - who are becoming ever more interconnected - to work together. The Latin American Investment Forum is a perfect example of such a network.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade and Investment&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a common misnomer that states trade with one another.  States can set the conditions in which trade takes place, but ultimately it is, of course, businesses that do the vast majority of trade.  So my government is wholeheartedly committed to encouraging British companies to do business with their Latin American counterparts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an uncertain financial world, Latin America stands out on economic prospects. Its growth has remained resilient in the face of the global financial crisis. The middle classes are expanding and poverty is falling.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments across the region have implemented fundamental reforms to their economies to make them more open and competitive.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin America is also an easier place to do business than many other emerging markets. The population of Latin America is close to 600 million people, more than the population of the EU.  It contains the largest group of democracies outside Western Europe.  We share values, interests and aspects of culture with many Latin American countries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British companies have already has great success in the region, including HSBC, Rolls Royce, and Anglo-American. BG Group announced US$30bn investment in Brazil over the next decade, making them the largest British investor and the largest foreign investor in the Oil &amp;amp; Gas sector. 58 of the FTSE 100 companies are doing business in Latin America.  But only 1.4% of UK exports reach Latin America.  We need more UK companies to consider doing business there.  And we need a wider range of sectors active in the region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries across Latin America have ambitious plans for their future. Colombia is investing $54 billion in infrastructure over the next 3 years. Venezuela has investment plans worth more than $200 billion to develop its oil and gas reserves and infrastructure by 2030.  Over the next four years, Brazil has $350 billion worth of investment planned.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has the expertise and experience to assist in these plans.  We can offer world class services in structuring the finance to underpin these investments. We have many years’ experience of managing public-private partnerships.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proud to be a leader in low carbon construction. This will be showcased this summer at our innovatively and sustainably constructed Olympic Park. UK project and financial management of this £9.3bn project has ensured that the Park is ready on budget and well in advance of the arrival of the Olympic Flame on 27 July. Of course, we will be keen to share our experience of hosting the Olympics with Brazil, who will succeed us as hosts and who are also holding the next World Cup. But British construction experience goes far beyond sports projects and will be relevant to the vast majority of the Latin American infrastructure plans on the table.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our expertise in science and innovation is world class. We have niche experience in many sectors in which many states in Latin America are specialising.  We are also regarded as a global leader in agrifood technology and innovation, particularly in food safety, traceability, functional foods and science and novel foods.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is on the cusp of a revolution in renewable energy which will pave the way to a low carbon economy.  Our companies have already taken huge steps to exploit wind, waves and tides to generate electricity. As such, they are well-placed to offer expertise and respond to the opportunities in Latin America.  In Brazil renewables currently represent 45.4% of Brazil’s energy matrix and 86.2% of their electricity matrix, making the country’s energy sector one of the world’s cleanest. Hydropower accounts for 80% of Brazil’s energy consumption. Generation from alternative renewables is expected to double from 8% to 16%. So we want to see British companies partnering Brazilian ones, sharing experience, and working together for a low carbon future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is a leader in responsible mining. Peru has became the first country in the Americas to become a compliant member of the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative (EITI).  This British initiative, promotes common international standards for revenue transparency and accountability in the oil, gas and mining industries.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our expertise in other methods of extraction is world-class too. With the growth in Colombia’s oil and gas sector there are plenty of opportunities for British suppliers to provide high value machinery to oil and gas companies there. And in looking towards Colombia’s offshore oil and gas exploration, there are important opportunities for UK boutique consultancies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my government is aware of the opportunities and will do what it can to support trade and investment between our country and those of Latin America.  We have increased our political links with states in the region, but there is still further to be done.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to deepen our dialogue and cooperation on issues such as economic policy, climate change, innovation, education and broader foreign policy challenges.  We want to do more to help tackle security issues in Central American countries.  And we need to improve British accessibility to the region.  More direct flights are essential.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So making the most of our relations with Latin America will be a central priority for the Foreign Office, as part of an approach that puts promoting trade and commercial interests at the heart of our foreign policy.  Nothing will come to us by right or by virtue of the past. We have to work hard to earn our living as a nation and maintain our international influence.  We have set out to pursue British interests and the global good in a systematic fashion while making the most of the new opportunities for influence and action presented by a networked world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our re-engagement with Latin America is central to this strategy.  It is how we shall seek to secure the long-term health of our economy, the long-term resilience of the international system and connections to face the long-term challenges posed by the 21st century.  We are back in Latin America. And we are back for the long term.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27430</id>
    <published>2012-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-commonwealth-all-party-parliamentary-group"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister welcomes Commonwealth All-Party Parliamentary Group</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Minister for the Commonwealth Lord Howell welcomed the launch of the new All-Party Parliamentary group</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 13 March, Minister for the Commonwealth Lord Howell attended the launch of the Commonwealth All-Party Parliamentary Group, chaired by Richard Graham MP.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the launch of the APPG, Lord Howell said that the Commonwealth was a “necessary network of the 21st century” and highlighted the relationship between the Commonwealth’s values of democracy, human rights and good governance and the prosperity of the citizens of the Commonwealth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Group’s objectives are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To ensure members are kept briefed by the Commonwealth Secretariat on developments to strengthen the Commonwealth network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To keep members fully aware of the range of non-parliamentary activities and programmes carried out under the Commonwealth brand, both on Governmental and non-governmental levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To take advantage of opportunities of the developing Commonwealth network for Britain’s political and commercial activities, and for Britain’s general positioning in the new international landscape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28878</id>
    <published>2012-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-quest-for-influence-in-a-re-shaped-eu"/>
    <title>Britain and the quest for influence in a re-shaped EU</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Lord Howell talked about Britain's role in the EU, and the EU's role in the world when he spoke at the Future of Economic Governance in the EU conference on 8 March.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an introduction to today’s discussions, I’d like to set the Eurozone crisis and Britain’s role in the EU in a broader context that I think is necessary to see what is happening and where we are going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thesis this morning will be that resolving the Eurozone crisis is a necessary but insufficient step to securing EU Member States’ economic future. The real issue at stake is how the EU can maintain its influence and its relevance in a changing world. Our quest is to drive forward the necessary changes within the EU in order to retain both its influence and by extension our influence in a world that is almost running away from us and moving at such a speed that even the most astute commentators are finding it hard to keep up with what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Europe is central to how we orientate ourselves in a changing world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe faces two big economic challenges: resolving the Eurozone crisis and responding to the relative shift of economic power both eastwards with the rise of Asia and southwards. We and the whole of the rest of Europe need to address both these trends if we are to compete in the global economy and maintain the level of prosperity to which we have become accustomed. We talk boldly about growth and prosperity but it will indeed be a struggle to maintain our current level of prosperity in the new conditions that we must face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Europe of which we are a part is recovering from the biggest financial crisis for generations. The actions this Government has taken to reduce our deficit and rebuild our economy have helped restore stability and there are now encouraging signs for the UK: businesses surveys for January show all sectors growing; inflation fell significantly in January, which is much needed good news for family budgets; consumer confidence rose according to Nationwide; and retail sales saw a strong start to the year, significantly exceeding market expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it can be said that the UK has taken decisive action to put our own house in order. The immediate challenge for Europe, of which we are a central part, is to sort out the problems of the Eurozone and to restore growth. Europe is our neighbourhood and still our largest market.  It is in Britain’s interest to see our neighbours’ problems sorted out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we support the Eurozone’s efforts to implement the package of measures agreed last October.  Europe’s banks must be properly capitalised. We need a firewall big enough to deal with the full extent of the crisis.  We need to restore stability to Greece, which remains an acute challenge, as this morning’s papers demonstrate.  I welcome progress on an additional 130bn euro package and work is ongoing as we speak. Eurozone leaders have stood behind their currency and are trying to place Greek debt on a sustainable footing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And given the subject matter of today’s conference, I should make clear the Government welcomes the improvements in economic governance in the Eurozone - both in last year’s ‘six pack’ of governance measures and in the new proposals - the so-called 2 pack.  They will play an important role in improving fiscal stability in the euro area, which will help our economy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, ladies and gentlemen, we face a more fundamental challenge: economic power is shifting from West to East and from North to South and diffusing away from both states and governments into the immense power of the world wide web and the entire social network is increasingly playing its part. New landscapes are emerging as are new types of competition. The IMF forecast China to grow in 2012 by 9%, India by 7.5% and Africa by 5.8%;  the EU is forecast to contract by 0.3%. Chinese growth provides a big opportunity as a market for our goods. The problem is that western growth has stalled. Unemployment is rising - more than 24 million people are out of work across Europe, an additional one and a half million unemployed compared to a year ago. Other countries are making what we make - but they’re making it more cheaply, better and with more advanced technologies.  Other countries are creating ideas for things which we don’t make - but of course we could. Just this week, we learnt that Brazil has taken the UK’s place as the 6th largest economy in the world, owing in large part to its vast size. We have even more reason to increase our competitiveness or risk being left behind.That is what that simple statistic reminds us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing both these challenges is central to our government’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Hannay Question&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go further on this subject, just let me now deal with one particular issue that comes up again and again in the House of Lords, given the importance that we place on Europe for the future, I want to head off claims of isolationism up front.  Let me be totally clear: this government wholeheartedly believes that our national interest is best served by being a willing and active member of the EU and of course by all kinds of other international community structures in this thoroughly interdependent world, including I may say the Commonwealth, which I have responsibility.  But Europe cannot isolate itself from the changes happening in the world.  Nor can the UK isolate itself.  Our response to a changing world puts Europe front and centre. So there is no isolation argument here, we are in fact more involved than ever and anyone who doubts that should try sitting behind my desk in the Foreign Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain has not signed the Fiscal Compact, but we intend to continue playing a strong forward role in the European Union. We are driving a like-minded group on growth which spans euro ins and outs.  Ahead of the March European Council, the Prime Minister set out an action plan for jobs and growth in a letter to Mr Barroso and Mr van Rompuy to which 11 other EU leaders signed up.  This letter effectively became the agenda for the Council and our ideas gained broad support from Heads of State and Government from across Europe from Lisbon to Warsaw. Our proposals on free trade, deregulation and completion of the single market were included in the final communique from the summit, agreed by all 27 Member States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are comfortable with an EU operating on different levels along alternative pathways. In this age of the World Wide Web and self-assembled networks, the EU should offer the flexibility and resilience of a network rather than the rigidity and vulnerability of a bloc. Flexibility is needed in certain laws and regulations, particularly in the context of a fixed exchange rate and the euro itself. Indeed that is a point that Nigel Wicks makes in his brilliant contribution to the online publication that accompanies this conference. Too much harmonisation stifles innovation, so while we are in the EU, but neither in the Euro nor Schengen. We opt out of many justice and home affairs provisions. We reject the concept of inner and outer cores, or fast and slow lanes. Like most people in Britain, we do not want to say yes to everything in the EU, but nor do we want to say no to everything in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it is in our national interest, we participate fully in the EU. We are amongst the group of Member States pushing ahead with a EU patent which promises to deliver savings to business and encourage innovation. We have one of the best records for implementing EU legislation. We champion the single market and are open to foreign ownership of major companies operating in the UK. I expect many of you heated your home this morning with energy provided by a EU company or used public transport or a mobile phone operated by EU providers. The UK accounted for around 12% of total contributions to the EU budget last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a wide range of issues which go to the heart of Europe’s place and role in the world - the single market, improving Europe’s competitiveness and taking tough action on Syria and Iran - we play a leading role and there is no distinction between Eurozone and non-Eurozone members at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our vision for Europe: how a changing Europe can help the UK maintain competitiveness in a changing world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me just say a word about what George Bush called this ‘vision thing’, there can be little doubt that Britain’s membership of the EU has allowed us to reap economic benefits.  UK trade with EU Member States is worth £200 billion per year to our economy.  Our membership of the Single Market provides British business with access to 500 million consumers without customs and trade barriers. Many things that we take for granted are owed to European co-operation: the ease and low cost of travel in Europe; the fact that we can retire to Spain and draw our pension there; that we can work anywhere we want in Europe and can use our mobile phones at lower cost when we get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the rise of emerging markets now is the time to ask: what kind of Europe do we actually want? For the UK, the answer is clear. Our vision is a Europe that is strong, reformed and outward-looking. Europe can play an important role in guaranteeing the UK’s future prosperity and security through trade, energy security and extending our reach through its external policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me turn first to trade. Alone, the UK’s GDP is obviously dwarfed by the likes of the United States and China. Our strength in trade bargaining is bound to lie in acting together. Together, the EU has the highest GDP in the world. With its combined weight, the EU can press ahead with new and ambitious trade deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has already benefited from EU Free Trade Agreements. The South Korea Free Trade Agreement alone is expected to save European exporters £1.35 billion annually in tariff reductions.  It is expected to benefit the UK economy by about £500 million per annum. And over the coming months we hope to conclude EU Free Trade Agreements with India, Canada and Singapore, all three of which are active and leading Commonwealth countries. Completing all the bilateral trade deals now on the table could add 75 billion pounds to Europe’s GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also opportunities to deepen economic integration between the EU and US, including through a Free Trade Agreement, which if realised would have a bigger impact than all of the other agreements put together. Our ambition does not stop here. We are working towards an EU-Japan Economic Partnership Agreement that will help to strengthen our relationship with a key partner in Asia, and will reinforce our own powerful and intimate bilateral relationship with that remarkable country which accounts for 9% of the world’s GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we have a goal to create well-functioning and integrated EU electricity and gas markets. We want to harness the benefits of Europe as a network. Increased competition should put downward pressure on prices, which is much needed.  Greater market integration will encourage innovation and green growth.  And increased trade and diversification should also reduce our vulnerability to supply and price shocks.  A single market in energy - which we want to achieve by 2014 - could add 0.8% to EU GDP, but will need vast investment in new interconnectors, transmitting electricity and gas across the European continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Europe is about more than trade. It always has been. In the last 12 months, EU sanctions have been used to bring collective EU pressure to bear against regimes involved in human rights violations or which posed a security threat.  These include Libya (under Qadhafi) Iran, Syria, Zimbabwe, Burma and Belarus.  The EU has helped defuse tension between Kosovo and Serbia and bring stability to Bosnia and Herzegovina, and of course we have to continue working on that very hard.  And in response to the Arab Spring, an epochal historical event in our neighbourhood and which demanded a response from us that recognised its importance, the EU reformed the European Neighbourhood Policy providing significant incentives for those countries seeking meaningful reform, underpinned by clear conditions and of course is backed by our own Arab Partnership Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the potential is there for the EU to help us all maintain our standing in the world.  And we are determined to help the EU fulfil this potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How will we help Europe adapt to a changing world to deliver this vision?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are pressing the EU to take action now to lay the foundations for our long term prosperity. This is why our Prime Minister among twelve heads of government sought and obtained concrete commitments to action at the recent European Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Single Market is Europe’s greatest economic achievement.  But it is not yet complete. Since it was created, our economies have shifted towards services; technology has changed enormously, meaning that more business is done online. Over 40% of Europeans buy goods online but fewer than 1 in 10 of us have bought something online from a trader in another EU country. We must help Europe complete the Single Market - in services, online, and yes, in financial services as well. Completion could translate into an additional 7% of UK GDP and 14% at the EU level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to push the Commission to reduce the cost of doing business. We can’t compete globally if it costs 3 times as much to open a business in the EU as it does in Brazil. That is wrong; but we are making progress. Two weeks ago, we achieved agreement in Brussels exempting small businesses from certain EU accounting rules. These measures will significantly simplify the preparation of annual accounts for more than 5 million of Europe’s smallest companies and will result in potential savings of up to €3.5 billion Euros annually for micro-businesses, including around 1.2 million small businesses in the UK. And we are working with other Member States to push the Commission to carry out a growth test for all new proposals and only take forward those that have a positive impact on growth, on enterprise and on innovation investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our future prosperity depends on matching the most nimble economies in harnessing key innovation processes. For every Euro invested in venture capital in the EU, five Euros are invested in the US. We need to act decisively to improve investment opportunities for innovative start ups, fast growing companies, and small businesses. To do this we need to create an EU wide venture capital regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, standing outside the Euro does not lessen our commitment to the European process  and nor to the efforts of those trying to sort out the short term crisis which is having such a chilling effect on our economy and indeed the global economy, nor as a means of securing our place in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of influence is vitally important. But the issue is less the UK’s position in Europe, but Europe’s position in the world. People want to be a member of a club that is successful and offers prospects. Whilst the Eurozone is seeking to remedy the flaws in its economic governance model, we need to set our sights higher on creating a solid economic framework for the future. That is the thinking behind the Prime Minister’s growth initiative. We need the EU to reform now so we can compete in the future. Otherwise we will leave a diminished place in the world for the next generation and confront the new landscape and the new distribution of power that I have described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am often asked how we can increase our influence in Brussels. My answer is this. If you share our agenda for reform, speak out. Don’t rely on the Government to make all the running on what you care about in the EU. If one has business operations in other Member States and direct links to the European Commission, they should be using them to argue for the Europe you want to see in the future. The world is changing. We need to change. Europe needs to change. And we need to do so together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
