<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-personnel-welfare-and-veterans</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-personnel-welfare-and-veterans.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28536</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/armed-forces-discount-card-launched-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>Armed Forces discount card launched in time for Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 50 high street companies and businesses have pledged generous discounts to show their support for the Armed Forces Community through the Defence Discount Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Defence Privilege Card, which will be available to sign up for online next week, will ensure our Armed Forces Community get exclusive discounts from participating stores across the country. This new card will provide money off items ranging from children’s toys and winter knitwear to mobile phones and even food shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 24,000 members of the Armed Forces Community have joined the scheme to date. Examples of the discounts they will now be able to access include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An example of the Defence Privilege Card" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1361/DefenceDiscount-5Dec2012_2519.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of the Defence Privilege Card [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10% off all groceries at Iceland&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20% off phone contracts at Vodafone&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20% off tickets at Vue Cinemas&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an introductory 20% followed by 15% off everything in store at Austin Reed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10% off everything at KFC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 to 10% off gift cards ordered from the Defence Discount Service website for most major supermarkets, Boots, Toys R Us, Topman, Currys, Debenhams, House of Fraser, B&amp;amp;Q, Homebase and H Samuel.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The roll-out of the new Defence Privilege Card coincides with the publication of the first annual report on the Armed Forces Covenant. This sets out key disadvantages the Government has tackled over the last year to improve life for our Armed Forces Community and ensures personnel and their families are not unfairly affected by their service to their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron welcomes Service personnel to No 10" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1362/DefenceDiscount-5Dec2012_2503.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron welcomes Service personnel to No 10 Downing Street [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Handing out the first Defence Privilege Cards at No 10 Downing Street yesterday, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that we have managed to get so many companies to sign up to this - and just in time for Christmas. As well as allowing people to save money, these discounts are a token of the immense appreciation that we all have for our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is fitting that the cards are launched in the year that the military have done so much for our country, not just abroad but here in the UK, showing the very best of British during the Olympics and the Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces, their families and our veterans reflect what is best in our society. That is why we are committed to rebuilding the Armed Forces Covenant and it is with great pride that I am publishing the first ever Armed Forces Covenant report today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17806</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T09:55:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T09:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lorraine-kelly-launches-christmas-box-appeal"/>
    <title>Lorraine Kelly launches Christmas Box appeal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event launched the annual Christmas Box campaign for the Armed Forces, run by the charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;uk4u Thanks!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign sees 22,500 boxes - affectionately known as ‘square stockings’ - sent to servicemen and women across the world who are working away from their families and members of the Armed Forces recuperating in hospital this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorraine Kelly joined members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; Commando Recruiting Troop on the zip wire descending 80 feet (24 metres) from the top of Wellington Arch in Hyde Park down to the ground below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were greeted at the bottom by Father Christmas who gave everyone a 2012 Christmas Box painted in the colours of the Diamond Jubilee Medal ribbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas Boxes being handed to soldiers in Afghanistan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1326/boxes2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas Boxes being handed to the men of 35 Engineer Regiment in Afghanistan in 2011 (library image) [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the launch, Lorraine Kelly said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be showing my support once again for such a worthwhile cause as the Christmas Box appeal, and I had a great time with the Royal Marines on the zip wire today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can join me in wishing a Happy Christmas to all our servicemen and women away from their families at this time of year by donating to the charity uk4u Thanks! who’ll send each of them a fantastic box full of goodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also present were other members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/" title="British Army"&gt;Army&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; who have received a Christmas Box while serving on operations on Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Soldiers with Christmas Boxes" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1327/boxes3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Soldiers at Forward Operating Base Shawqat in Helmand province in 2011 with their Christmas Boxes (library image) [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;uk4u Thanks! works with the Armed Forces to send the boxes, containing some 20 items, out to locations such as Afghanistan, the Falklands, and ships and submarines across the world in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do not use the British Forces Post Office system so as not to delay parcels from families and friends getting through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Minister Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas can be difficult for many of our servicemen and women who are deployed on operations away from their families when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can all therefore show that we are thinking of them by donating to charities such as uk4u Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45358</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-06-address-to-the-armed-forces-community-covenant-conference"/>
    <title>2012/11/06 - Address to the Armed Forces Community Covenant Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Cromwell’s troops once declared that, “on becoming soldiers, we have not ceased to be citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would go further and say that the men and women of today’s Armed Forces - through their dedicated, demanding and often dangerous service to their country - are, to quote Winston Churchill, “twice the citizen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is not fair that, because of the nature of their service, they should have unequal access to the services on which we all depend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept of creating a fair deal for our Armed Forces - past and present - is at the core of the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have already heard from General Rollo and others about what this means from the military perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from this Government’s perspective it is about encouraging the whole of society to recognise its moral obligation to our Service men and women, and to the families that support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cannot be achieved by central government alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can address some of the issues by getting all departments to understand the unique requirements of the military, better coordinating the allocation of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work closely with charities such as The Royal British Legion, which has recently published its Best Practice Guide to Community Covenants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to see Chris Simpkins here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Armed Forces Covenant needs to be implemented by all sections of society: including by local communities, local charities and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is at the local level that many issues are best resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-covenant"&gt;Community Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why Community Covenant Partnerships are central to the delivery of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tremendous progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much actual delivery is down to local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have well and truly picked up the ball and started running with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant is close to my heart on a number of levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of you will know I began my political career in local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I served as a councillor on Basildon Borough Council.  It was a robust council. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was once described as the only council in the UK where councillors actively heckled the public gallery during meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know what it’s like to be a councillor dealing with competing priorities, with limited resources and financial pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that not everyone you assist remembers to say thank you after you’ve helped them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me, while I’m here, say “thank you” - all of you - for what you’ve done to support our Armed Forces through the Armed Forces Community Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As councillors, supported by your officers, you have been a credit to the people who elected you to public office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also want to say that nobody can say that local government has not stepped up to the plate on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And anyone who does will have to get by me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that as representatives of your communities you are often best placed to pick up on the needs of the Service personnel who reside in your jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is vital, because the requirements of a soldier posted to Wellington barracks, just the other side of St James’s park, might be very different from the requirements of a sailor based in rural Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can’t dictate what you should do from the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s up to you to decide how you should do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps I can suggest three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, that you all appoint an Armed Forces champion - a councillor who is nominated to make sure that the principles of the Covenant are carried through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, that in your housing allocation policies you ensure serving personnel and veterans get the best possible treatment.  And ideally, where possible, you appoint a Senior Housing Officer to be responsible for this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And please bear in mind that around 1 in 10 adults is a veteran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thousands live in your areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, on education, that you do everything you can to help Service children get the education they deserve, particularly working to mitigate any disruption to schooling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, by following Oxfordshire Council in accepting school applications from Service families before they are posted and have basing addresses in the area to which they are going to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has long been an issue for service families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sense of urgency to get all of this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our troops are going to be coming home from Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they have given so much for us, it is only fair that we try to give something back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a window of opportunity to get things right for our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my aspiration is that in this time before they have all come home we achieve national coverage for the Community Covenant, so that wherever our Armed Forces and veterans live they know their local authority will be looking out for them and critically their families as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to your hard work I know we are making real progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a position where Community Covenant Partnerships have been signed by over 200 local authorities, up and down the UK, with more on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of the first annual report on the Armed Forces Covenant, which is not far away now, will lay out this progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the principle of no disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second that special consideration is appropriate in some cases, especially for those who have given most such as the injured and the bereaved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now the law of the land that the Secretary of State must provide a report to Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would be arrogant in the extreme to believe that we could solve all the problems in a single year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we have now initiated a process that will allow us to address problems systematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase Churchill again: With regard to the matter of the Armed Forces Covenant Report, this is not the end.  It is not even the beginning of the end.  It is not even the end of the beginning.  This is in fact the beginning of the beginning.  But nevertheless this process has now well and truly begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I saw that this morning when I was in my own patch in Essex, co-signing a Community Covenant, which was signed by Essex County Council and all 14 other local authorities in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may know, I once applied to be a candidate in a by-election in Kensington and Chelsea.  I lost out to some chap called Michael Portillo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that time I was asked by a lady from Chelsea with a cut glass accent, “Mr Francois, would you say that you are proud to call yourself an Essex Man?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No Madame, but I am very proud to be a man from Essex.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have never been prouder than when I saw all of the local authorities of Essex sign their Community Covenant, one after another this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also very proud of all the other local authorities across the country that have signed their Covenant agreements as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These partnerships have helped local authorities to understand the needs of Service families, introducing practical measures to improve their access to GPs, dentists, local schools and housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everywhere I go, I get feedback that part of the value of the Community Covenant comes from establishing a framework for dialogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dialogue between local authorities: unitary, county, district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dialogue between sectors: private, public, voluntary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a dialogue between communities: military and civilian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But fundamentally this is a dialogue between individuals: person-to-person contact that works out problems and gets things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this network of conversation people are discovering low cost or no cost measures that add up to have a genuine impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple things, like the staff who provide some of Gateshead Council’s frontline services asking, the question, whenever people approach the council: are you part of the Armed Forces community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not all just about communication and coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant is backed by a separate £30m Grant Scheme to support local projects that benefit veterans, serving personnel and the communities they live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will hear from the leaders of three successful projects later today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the scheme, in June 2011, we have received 240 bids - 120 of which have been successful - amounting to £5 million of already allocated funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will have instantly realised, this is a far higher success rate than most bids to the National Lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to the Community Covenant Grant - it really could be you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next panel considering grant applications will sit on 13 December this year with a deadline for submissions to the MOD for bids of 28 November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following panel will sit on 14 March 2013 with a deadline of 28 February 2013 - that is two bidding rounds you can apply to so get your pens out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two days time I will be back in Essex to see the Royal Anglian Regiment, my old regiment, march through the Borough of Basildon - with trumpets sounding, drums beating, fifes playing and colours flying - as they exercise the freedom of the borough which they were give two years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you how much these parades mean to those returning from operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are really important to them and to their families who miss them while they are away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And particularly also to those who have lost loved ones in the service of their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I thank all of you who have granted freedom to your local Armed Forces and encourage others who can to consider doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe wholeheartedly in the value of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why all local authorities in England and Wales have recently been sent a letter that I have co-written with Sir Merrick Cockell laying out the merits of the Community Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be writing in the same terms to local authorities in Scotland very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who have yet to sign a Community Covenant, I hope that you leave here today with a whole host of reasons to do so, and a clearer idea of how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who have already signed a Community Covenant, I would encourage you to share your ideas and experiences - which are helping to turn the Covenant into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud of the progress we have already made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think together, working in partnership, we can do more - particularly in the context of our returning troops, which gives immediacy to the whole project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must all play our part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, particularly at this time of remembrance we must never forget the fact that we live in a free country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that we can only do this thanks to some very special people - our Service men and women - who are prepared to lay down their lives to protect that freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something which we should not take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recognised this in the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Community Covenant gives this real form at local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us - all of us - owe these people a debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must honour the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s roll up our sleeves and get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45352</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-31-the-confederation-of-service-charities-cobseo-agm"/>
    <title>2012/10/31 - The Confederation of Service Charities (COBSEO) AGM</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been the Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans for little over two months now and it is an honour to be able to fulfil this role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My portfolio covers issues like: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure that we do what we can to strengthen the backbone of our Armed Forces - the forces families who support them; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure our wounded get the best care we can provide;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure that the hidden wounds of war are treated too with the new emphasis on mental health;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping Service personnel succeed in civilian life when they leave;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making sure that we continue to honour the service of our community of veterans, who make up around 1 in 10 of our adult population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you seeing a pattern here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concerns are basically your concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody knows better than you, the life changing work that your organisations do on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not need any convincing of the value of COBSEO members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering services; sharing the burden; helping to meet our collective obligations under the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to take this opportunity to thank you for everything you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You complement the work of the MOD in a huge number of areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly view the relationship as symbiotic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are partners, very definitely not rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-cobseo"&gt;Importance of COBSEO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO is central to making this partnership work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are lucky in Britain to have such a wide range of dedicated Service charities helping those who have given so much to their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some who question the very existence of service charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shouldn’t this all be done by Government?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else do we pay our taxes for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the MOD does directly fund a lot of the work that COBSEO organisations help with, but for me, it just isn’t an either or.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity is a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never allow the cynics, or those who seem to believe that making a contribution to society should be exclusively for the public sector, we should never allow them to devalue what is achieved by organisations like COBSEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chairman, the State claims no monopoly on good will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the Big Lottery Fund which is providing £35m for veterans projects like the Forces in Mind Trust run in partnership with COBSEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society is stronger and healthier for the contribution that charities make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of you has your own niche - representing special groups and possessing your own expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That diversity is a massive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also makes it difficult for the MOD to be in constant touch with all the work that is going on out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to establishing a proper dialogue, COBSEO provides an effective and powerful, unified voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD is approached by hundreds of charities a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to know that all of those charities are legitimate, well run and sustainable before we engage with them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO membership is useful because it gives us an additional degree of confidence in a charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But COBSEO is not the only way charities can represent themselves to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the embedded charity staff in personnel recovery centres, to the close working relationships between military Welfare Officers and a wide range of charities - there are thousands of interactions between the MOD and COBSEO members at grass roots level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the strategic level COBSEO is an important channel of communication and advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charities are often well placed to pick up on the concerns of the groups that they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that in his earlier address the Chairman raised concerns about the future status of the Independent Medical Expert Group (IMEG) which has been subject to review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce today, that following discussions with the Cabinet Office, Ministers there have agreed that the IMEG will now be established permanently as an Advisory Non-Departmental Public Body in order that it can continue to provide independent expert medical advice on matters relating to the Armed Forces Compensation Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are keen to hear what you have to say. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why COBSEO is an influential member of the Armed Forces Covenant Reference Group - the CRG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This body helps to steer the direction of the Armed Forces Covenant, which recognises society’s moral obligation to our Service men and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have always understood this moral obligation and been at the forefront of meeting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense, then, that you help us to identify where disadvantage exists and where special provision is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when the Chancellor announced that money from fines levied on banks involved in Libor rate fixing would be spent on the Armed Forces Covenant, it was only right that this £35 million would be allocated in partnership with the CRG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money will go towards supporting the Armed Forces community, including through Service charities, funding work that will address some of the disadvantages that the Armed Forces community face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-armed-forces-covenant"&gt;The Armed Forces Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Covenant is being implemented by many sections of society: by national and local government, by local communities and, of course, by charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of these efforts can be wasted, if we apply our resources to the wrong areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is another area where your advice is so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to your help the Covenant is starting to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over a year ago we launched the Community Covenant Scheme, encouraging local authorities to meet the unique requirements of the Service personnel and their families living in their jurisdictions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a position where Community Covenant Partnerships have been signed by over 200 local authorities, up and down the UK, with more on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance in my own patch in Essex, the County Council will sign the Community Covenant next week in the run up to Remembrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These partnerships have enabled local authorities to understand the needs of Service families and introduce practical measures to improve their access to GPs, dentists, local schools and housing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant Scheme is backed by a separate £30m Grant Scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £5m has already been released to support local projects that benefit veterans, serving personnel and the communities they live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also re-launched the Defence Discount Service, helping to recognise the contribution of our Armed Forces by providing them and their families with financial savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are many other initiatives at national and local level which help make the Covenant a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the Covenant is getting society to understand how much it owes the Armed Forces - past and present - and the families that have supported them - and to encourage society to find ways of repaying that debt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need you to continue helping deliver the Covenant, but we also need you to help judge the progress of that delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charities’ commentary on the Secretary of State’s Annual Report on the Covenant is one of its most important sections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It holds us to account and it gives us guidance on how we might improve in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of this first annual report, which is not far away now, will show progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is only a beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this job I am absolutely determined to put flesh on the bones of the Covenant to give it real form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to use it to improve the lives of service personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still much to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hope that when you see the report you will feel that we have made a good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that you too have been discussing your future today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been told that this AGM represents something of a crossroads for COBSEO and its members as you decide your long term direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right that these are decisions for you to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me just say though that I have been impressed with how much impact COBSEO has made with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value the coherence it gives to Service charities and the validating role it has with regards to its members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these are functions that you might like to consider taking forward and developing in partnership with the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We certainly don’t want you to lose your individual identities as charities.  They define you and they focus you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the confederation of charities that COBSEO represents, works very well from our perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever decisions you make, I look forward to continuing the extremely productive relationship that we have forged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you and Good Luck.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45363</id>
    <published>2012-10-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-02-address-to-the-surgeon-general-s-triple-serpent-conference"/>
    <title>2012/10/02 - Address to the Surgeon General’s Triple Serpent Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Philip [Surgeon Vice Admiral Philip Raffaelli, the Surgeon General] for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pleasure to join you at the end of the first day of the Surgeon General conference - and so soon after taking up my post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this has been a long day and the bar beckons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to join you later for a drink - medicinal purpose only of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I discussed with my team was getting me some early opportunities to see you on your own turf - and the work you do for our Armed Forces Personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to visit our troops in Helmand in the coming months, and I will make sure that includes the Hospital in Camp Bastion - and, of course, its new maternity ward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am planning to see some of you at the Royal Centre for Defence Medicine at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of my first public duties was to be present when HRH The Prince of Wales opened the Jubilee Complex at Headley Court last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, for me, was both a humbling and an inspirational experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the bravery the men and women of our Armed Forces possess is not just expressed on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was incredibly impressed by the spirit of our wounded personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was equally impressed by the care and commitment shown by the people who look after them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am advised that even our US and Israeli colleagues would admit that we are now world leaders in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to start today by saying thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You work at the cutting edge of medical science and the first beneficiaries are those to whom the people of this country owe a great debt - those who risk life and limb to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of them are alive now because of you - and, compared with previous conflict, many of the seriously injured can expect to lead much more fulfilling lives because of the efforts you make. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that this is our first meeting I thought I would use this occasion to let you know where I’m coming from, and to talk just a little bit about the challenges we face together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-together"&gt;Working Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just a little about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Father served in the Royal Navy in World War Two, he fought at D-Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own service was as a TA Officer with the Royal Anglian Regiment during the 1980s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a different army then, trained for a very different war - a war that thankfully never came to pass.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I never saw active service and I have no medals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have worn the uniform, and, as a Reservist, I also remember what it was like to juggle Service with life outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that counts for something with you - because it certainly counts for something with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked to come to the MOD, and I am doing a job I want to do, working to improve the lives of the best and most dedicated people our country has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that this is something you have been doing probably your whole professional lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you are recognised internationally as experts in your chosen field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not coming here to second guess you as professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am here primarily to listen and learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as a Minister, I also intend to be pro-active in getting things done, not sitting back and waiting for problems to cross my desk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young platoon commander I was taught to seize the initiative and that is what I plan to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that my fresh eyes and ears will be of help in trying to get to the heart of some of the issues so that together we can make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are those issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="operations"&gt;Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first priority, of course, is operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan remains the number one priority for the Ministry of Defence and the Armed Forces and the work of the doctors, nurses and medics on the front-line is quite simply awe-inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at the National Arboretum last week and read the memorial for Army Medical Officer Capt Noel Chavasse, the only man to win the Victoria Cross twice during World War One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Chavasse died from his wounds at Passchendaele but not before saving the lives of countless others, which is what earned him the Bar on the Victoria Cross he originally won at the Somme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example of Captain Chavasse lives on in today’s medics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week we honoured Corporal Julie May, who twice put her own life at risk to save colleagues in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She received a Mention in Dispatches for attending to an IED casualty despite the significant danger posed by secondary devices in the area, and for stabilising an Afghan soldier whilst her position was under fire.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear stories like this I am truly impressed by the courage and skill displayed by members of your profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As UK Forces draw down from a combat role between now and 2014, one of the greatest challenges will be to make sure that we maintain the right medical support in theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be difficult to strike the right balance between reductions in scale and maintaining the capability and the capacity to deal with the unexpected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But strike the right balance, we must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the withdrawal from Afghanistan, we will to identify what lessons learned and new skills might be embedded in the Defence Medical Services for the future and, indeed, transferable into current NHS practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-we-are-now"&gt;Where We are Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back here at home Defence Transformation will be the vehicle that will shape the future of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now part of Joint Forces Command, which is one of the first tangible signs of transformation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach will be addressing you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the history of Defence Medical Services has been one of transformation - not always positive and certainly not straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over the last few decades - just as the Armed Forces themselves have changed from the massed forces that trained to face the Warsaw Pact across the North German Plain - Defence Medical Services has changed too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the virtually autonomous Single Services that ran their own hospitals when I served in the 1980s, to consolidated joint Defence Medical Service today - where the patient is the focus, which is part of the wider medical community, and which collaborates far and wide to ensure that evidence based, cutting edge medicine and treatment are embraced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially evident in the work being done in partnership with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The establishment last year of the National Institute of Health Research Centre for Surgical Reconstruction and Microbiology in Birmingham enables military personnel to share advances and surgical innovation with the NHS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples of the partnership approach are the work being done with the Royal British Legion and Imperial College London on blast injury, and the King’s Centre for Military Health Research on mental health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will be meeting Professor Simon Wessely to talk about his pioneering work at King’s, which is doing so much to further develop our understanding of the psychological effects of warfare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I did my Masters in War Studies at King’s College, under Sir Laurence Friedman, so I am looking forward to visiting my alma mater in the not too distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know this transformation hasn’t been easy, or without controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have come a long way since the outcome of Defence Cost Studies 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I think we should be proud of the quality of the care that is now being provided to our Service people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Clinical and Academic Units at Queen Elizabeth Hospital, our Service personnel have access to some of the best medical care available in dealing with the most serious injuries with all the key specialities, such as plastics and neurosurgery, under one roof. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see for myself next week how having a military ward in a cutting edge NHS hospital provides a reassuring environment for our service personnel while at the same time providing a level of care that would be difficult to recreate in a purely Service environment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as I have seen for myself, at Headley Court, the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre provides world class care and we are constantly investing in staff, facilities, patient welfare and treatments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly, and personally, pleased that this Government is helping you to focus attention on mental health - which had, perhaps, for many years not been given the priority it really deserved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to continue to champion a through life approach to mental health, drawing on the work of my new Ministerial colleague Doctor Andrew Murrison, as well as the considerable amount of research undertaken at King’s College. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is where we are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Care Quality Commission report praised the facilities available to casualties in theatre, as well as those for patients at Headley Court. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t happen by accident. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens because of people like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no successful organisation can be complacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn briefly to the future&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must continually strive for greater excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in today’s economic climate we must also strive for greater efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to go into detail on the pressures on the Government purse or on the Defence Budget - and I don’t want to get partisan about the reasons for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say we are where we are, and we face a delicate balancing act: reducing the fiscal deficit while making sure front-line services are protected as much as possible; making sure that our service personnel get the best care available, because the best is what they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is no pot of gold to fix things with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward we are going to have to be innovative and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the work underway on Defence Medical Services 2020 cannot happen in isolation from the wider changes taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true when it comes to Reserves, who will play an increasingly important role in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the autumn, we will be looking closely at the deal for Reservists and employers to make sure the offer to both supports our plans for a larger, more integrated Reserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is also true when it comes to the changes taking place in the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already had a very productive meeting with Dr Dan Poulter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan is a GP and the new Minister within the Department of Health with responsibility for the provision of secondary healthcare to Service personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have agreed to work together on a number of Service personnel and Veterans’ issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the planning application to build the Defence and National Rehabilitation Centre at Stanford Hall in Nottinghamshire is soon to be submitted to the Local Authority - and I am hoping to go and see the site for myself next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have committed to work with the Department of Health, the NHS and the project team to ensure that the National element of the project is given a high priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this close working together is framed by the Armed Forces Covenant, in which healthcare is a key and enduring obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has already been made in delivering against our commitments, such as a greater focus on mental health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we go forward, the challenge will be to continue working successfully with the NHS as both organisations - them and us - go through transformation and reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will soon be a major change in the management of primary healthcare in Defence itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is designed to provide opportunities for better use of resources, improved quality through sharing best practice and expanded career options for medical staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Surgeon General has set out his clinical priorities that range from Combat Casualty Care, to Mental Health and Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, throughout this transformation we need to advance these clinical priorities, see through the cutting edge research, become even more efficient and even more patient focussed, while improving the standard of care provided to our Armed Forces personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be what my officials refer to as - “challenging”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are only going to succeed if we work together to achieve all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;‘#Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in no doubt, that when the Government sends the young men and women of our Armed Forces into harms way, we have a moral obligation to make sure they are properly equipped for the task they have been set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That they are given the best medical care available on the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that they and their families are properly looked after when they are away and when they get home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined to strive as hard as I can as a Minister to ensure that this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that together, with your help, that is what we will achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together, let us do our best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45353</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-09-20-address-to-the-army-families-federation-conference"/>
    <title>2012/09/20 - Address to the Army Families Federation Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here with you today and for us to have this early opportunity to get to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to understand better where you are coming from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for you to get a sense of where I am coming from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is par for the course for a new Minister to say how ‘delighted’ they are by their appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I say I am delighted, I really mean it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked to come to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I want to be and I intend to do everything I practically can to improve the lot of our service personnel, to support you - their families - and to help our veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to start by telling you a bit about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father, Reginald Francois, served in the Royal Navy in WWII.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was at D-Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own service was as a TA Infantry Officer with the Royal Anglian Regiment in the 1980s, during the cold war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army I was a part of was trained for a very different type of war - a war that, thankfully, never came to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a Reserve not a Regular, I never saw active service, I was never shot at (other than in training), and I have no medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But…the Queen’s Commission hangs on my wall at home, I understand and appreciate the military ethos, I have worn the uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that counts for something with all of you - because it certainly counts for something with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has changed in the Army since I served and I can’t claim to have experienced all the pressures you face, but I hope that I do, at least, understand what some of them might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pressures-of-army-life"&gt;The Pressures of Army Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, let me paint a picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A junior NCO in the army, married with small children, is posted to Afghanistan for yet another operational tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s away for over six months - tough for the family with all the stresses and strains at home to deal with alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He returns, but after just a few months receives the news that his unit is to be posted to a new base. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as all the emotional disruption of a family moving home, his wife will have to give up her job as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They may face a battle to get their children into new schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll need a new doctor, new dentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their new accommodation is ok, but there are some things that still need doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having got through all this, they are then told to prepare for another ‘unaccompanied’ six month tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to tell you what this feels like to live through - you know far better than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want the support provided to you, to get closer to matching the support you provide to our soldiers - ensuring that someone who loves his job, and loves his family, doesn’t have to choose between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we move forward?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give a brief sit rep of where we are and what I have in my in tray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="operations"&gt;Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months, here at home, most eyes have been on the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it showed a side of our Army that many people don’t see -not just competing and winning medals in both the Olympics and Paralympics - but the faces behind the camouflage: the fellow citizens doing difficult jobs with commitment, calmness and competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the short notice of parts of this deployment was very disruptive for some of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to say thank you to our servicemen and women for the outstanding support they gave to the greatest show on earth, and to thank all of you for your support to them while they were doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while this was happening the efforts of tens of thousands of people, in the MOD, in the Army, and the thoughts of many of you, have been focussed on our forces in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan remains the number one priority for the Ministry of Defence and the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our troops remain in the firing line, as events over the last few weeks have shown all to well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No-one pretends that the strategy we’re following - training the Afghans to take on the fight themselves - is easy or without risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it remains the right strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission is one of national security, so we must complete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown of troops between now and the end of 2014 will be done sensibly - meeting the requirements of force protection as we proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="army-2020"&gt;Army 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But coming home they are - not just our troops in Afghanistan, but our troops in Germany too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to my next topic - Army 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few years the Army will become based much more predominantly in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial announcement about the basing review will be made by the end of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should help to reduce some of your uncertainty and lay out the future footprint for the Army, and give it the structure to deal with the unexpected and unplanned, rather than the more predictable deployments of the Iraq and Afghanistan campaigns of the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what the Strategic Defence and Security Review and Army 2020 has been about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining the Army as the formidable fighting force we need to protect national security - but generating that force in a different way, on a different scale, and prepared to do different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the decisions that have been taken have been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that behind every Service Number, there is a person, a livelihood, and often a family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the economic climate of the foreseeable future, the only way we are going to meet the needs of national security, is to make sure that our Armed Forces are sustainable as well as powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as difficult as they have been, I support the changes that have been made and I intend to ensure that the implementation of Army 2020 is done as sensibly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation produces a new set of challenges for the Army and across the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-employment-model"&gt;New Employment Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me talk briefly about one of these - the New Employment Model - the career structure that will be needed to make sure life in the Army is an attractive option for the brightest and the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD is now embarking on the early design phase of the New Employment Model (NEM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of this will be the recognition that our Armed Forces should have a fair deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It aims to provide greater domestic stability for Service Personnel and their families, whilst continuing to support them when they are required to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a measured process and we will take as long as necessary to get this right - looking at everything from career paths, to terms and conditions, to accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is made more difficult by the fiscal conditions we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the restrictions on the public purse, we can’t just throw money at problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Employment Model must reflect the best use of taxpayer’s money, as well as meet the needs of Defence, and of personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Families Federations will have a vital role to play as we work to get this right and we will consult with you very carefully along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NEM will be an important part of making sure we meet the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant, which is what I want to turn to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="armed-forces-covenant"&gt;Armed Forces Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, there have been improvements in a number of areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The better operational welfare package, the greater capacity of the recovery capability, education bursaries, families welfare grants, action on many of the little but cumulative things that make service life sometimes difficult for families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is still a long, long way to go, and there is no room to be complacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Armed Forces Bill team last year, I am proud to say that I helped enshrine the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now looking forward to helping put them into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My predecessor, Andrew Robathan, is particularly proud of the way the Community Covenant scheme has mushroomed - from a standing start a year ago to nearly 150 local authorities signed up today - and they are coming in all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Lincolnshire Council became the latest recruit signing the Community Covenant only yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Community Covenants are already starting to see improvements in the provision of local services for military families. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple things, like Oxfordshire County Council allowing base addresses to be used prior to postings for school applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As these pledges grow and dialogue deepens, I hope your local authorities will start to better understand your unique needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the Community Covenant Grants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the scheme began just over a year ago, £5m has been allocated to innovative projects, driven by local people, and including 36 new grants worth over £1m that have just been approved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I can announce today a whole host of new local projects that have got the go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extensions to two schools in North Yorkshire, which educate a high proportion of service children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New veterans’ services in Nottinghamshire and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A scheme in Cornwall to get younger members of the Armed Forces community together with locals to help them integrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These latest projects demonstrate the high regard the public has for the Armed Forces - people up and down the country showing their support and gratitude through each new idea and initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="accommodation"&gt;Accommodation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course making progress on some things has been more difficult because of budgetary restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me briefly turn to the issue of Housing which I know is close to your heart  -  and is also close to mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there has been some positive progress, I know that it is not enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my political career, in the last century, as a councillor on Basildon District Council in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a robust council - it still is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was once described as the only council in the country where the councillors actively heckled the public gallery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I learned my trade there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 3 years, I was Vice Chairman of the Housing Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I am a little rusty, I do have some practical experience of housing issues which I plan to bring to bear in my role as a Minister. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I campaigned on this issue when I was first elected to Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I’m in a position to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So one of my main priorities in this job is to find ways to keep improving your accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to be able to say more about this in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the sit rep - big changes, tight resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, there is a huge agenda for us to get our collective teeth stuck into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army Families Federation is one of the key organisations that can help get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your views are highly valued. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You pick up on the issues that matter, making sure that the MOD is aware of what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your latest quarterly report is testament to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you are also a great organ for communication, action and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The military teaches the principle of combined arms - all elements in a battle group working together co-operatively to achieve the maximum possible effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what we need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t got a magic wand and I certainly don’t have a pot of gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job is to fix those things that I can and use whatever clout I have across Government to get those things fixed that I don’t control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I can promise is to do the best job I can - and you have that promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am where I want to be, doing a job I want to do, working to improve the lives of the best and most dedicated people the country has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud to be given the opportunity to do that, and, with your help, working together, that is what I aim to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39709</id>
    <published>2012-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/generous-public-urged-think-twice-before-sending-unsolicited-christmas-gifts-to-troops"/>
    <title>Generous public urged: think twice before sending unsolicited Christmas gifts to troops</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With just 100 days to go until Christmas Day, some generous members of the public may be considering sending presents to Armed Forces personnel serving abroad to help them celebrate the festive season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while everybody in the Forces is hugely grateful for the sentiment behind such gifts, the message is very clear: if people wish to show their support for those serving in austere conditions in Afghanistan, there are far more effective ways of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The volume of mail arriving at Camp Bastion for onward distribution to other locations in Afghanistan causes three key problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;private mail sent to deployed personnel by their loved ones can become significantly delayed amongst all the other items from members of the public. Receipt of letters or gifts from a parent or spouse are very important for morale in theatre and for the peace of mind of families back home. The delays unsolicited mail inevitably cause to the delivery of the much more anticipated personal mail can create real disappointment and stress. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the onward delivery of goodwill parcels to forward operating bases necessitates additional resupply flights and convoys which places Service personnel at additional risk in what is already a difficult and dangerous operating environment. Every time an additional convoy is laid on, more troops are put at risk of enemy attack. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the type of items included in many welfare parcels are either already readily available in theatre or are simply not appropriate for the Afghan environment. Not only does this mean that the items go to waste, but time and resources have to be diverted from crucial operations to organise their disposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the MOD is launching a campaign to remind members of the public that they can express their support in different ways - including by donating to a special fund that the Ministry of Defence has established to enable those who want to make a personal contribution to troops’ welfare support to do so in a co-ordinated way which does not cause these problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Staff at Lashkar Gah dealing with unsolicited mail" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1426/StaffdealingwithunsolicitedmailinLashkarGah.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Staff at Lashkar Gah dealing with unsolicited mail (library image)
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2009]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain James Talman, Controlling Postal Courier Officer on Operation HERRICK, based at Camp Bastion, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mail is really important to all our troops here. However, if people send out unsolicited parcels addressed to ‘any soldier’, or even to a named individual who is not known to them, they will simply clog up the system and delay the packages from friends and families which are so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we all appreciate people’s support, I would ask members of the public not to send any unsolicited mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Douglas Ralph, responsible for Operational Welfare at the Ministry of Defence, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no denying that receiving a parcel can provide a morale-boost to serving personnel but what the troops on the ground really want is to receive their personal mail - the letters from loved ones and close friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the sheer number of welfare packages we have seen enter the system in the run-up to Christmas in previous years has caused serious delays to those all-important personal items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While we are all enormously grateful for the generosity of people who want to support the Armed Forces, packages from strangers can never make up for the delay they cause to mail from relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The message is clear: if you wish to show your support for the troops, the most effective way of doing so is to support an official registered Service charity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different ways in which people in the UK can thank forces deployed overseas for their work and commitment. Helpful advice and a list of recommended Service charities which accept public donations to assist deployed personnel and their families back at home can be found on the Ministry of Defence website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these funds send welfare parcels to Afghanistan - but they do so, in consultation and partnership with the Armed Forces, in a co-ordinated way which does not put undue pressure on resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD provides a comprehensive Deployed Welfare Package which includes a free mail service for families and friends, 30 minutes of telephone calls a week and internet access, there are still areas where life in an operational theatre can be improved over and above that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and in order to enable members of the public to make a contribution to the welfare of personnel in an appropriate way, the MOD Operations Welfare Fund was established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priority for spending from the fund is set by commanders in theatre for those items which have the most impact in enhancing the morale of their personnel and any money donated to this fund enables commanding officers on the ground to bid for items which their men and women have asked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of items purchased through the fund are Wii handsets, portable DVD players, games and table tennis tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make a donation can send a cheque to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations Welfare Fund&lt;br&gt;
J1 Operation HERRICK&lt;br&gt;
PJHQ, Sandy Lane,&lt;br&gt;
Northwood, Middlesex,&lt;br&gt;
HA6 3HP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recommended charity is &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;uk4u Thanks!&lt;/a&gt; which already delivers a Christmas box of practical gifts and fun treats to every soldier, sailor and airman deployed overseas - in Afghanistan and elsewhere - and those in hospital and recovery centres in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its parcels are delivered via the supply chain, meaning there is no impact on the mail network. Although the charity benefits from corporate sponsorship, it also needs donations from the public to continue its work bringing Christmas cheer to thousands of personnel. For more details visit their website at Related Links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government is dedicated to the care and welfare of the men and women of our Armed Forces, particularly those deployed on operations. This is reflected in the Deployed Welfare Package, a key part of which is the safe and timely delivery of free personal mail from family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past this mechanism has been used by the general public to show their support and resulted in huge volumes of unsolicited goodwill parcels being sent, which have overwhelmed the in-theatre postal and logistics capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst unsolicited mail is well-intentioned, mail sent by families and friends is the most important to deployed personnel and is our absolute priority. Moreover, unsolicited mail strains the logistics supply and prevents mail from families getting through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason the MOD will be repeating its unsolicited mail campaign. Rather than sending their own letter or parcel, I would encourage people to make a donation to one of Britain’s excellent Service charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They might also consider ‘uk4u Thanks!’ - a charity that provides Christmas gifts to deployed Service personnel. Once again I would like to say thank you to the British public, on behalf of the MOD and Armed Forces, for their incredible support of our serving personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45354</id>
    <published>2012-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-09-11-address-to-the-ministry-of-defence-welfare-conference"/>
    <title>2012/09/11 - Address to the Ministry of Defence Welfare Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here with you today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first pass on apologies from my colleague Andrew Murrison for his absence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have found out over the last few days with my wonderful civil service team, as Ministers we are no longer wholly in charge of our own destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since agreeing to speak here, Andrew has been made Minister for International Security Strategy at the MOD and has been sent abroad on departmental business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m sorry that he can’t be here as originally scheduled and he has asked me to pass on his compliments and his apologies to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew and I were elected to parliament together in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both have a track record of campaigning in Parliament on service welfare issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you will agree with me that Andrew’s reports on mental health and amputees are testament to his knowledge, experience and passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as MOD Ministers, we will be working closely together to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew served as a Medical Officer in the Royal Navy for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Father, Reginald Francois, also served in the Royal Navy in WWII. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was at D-Day &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own service was in the 1980s, as an Infantry Officer in the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a very different Army than the one of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were trained for a very different war - a war that thankfully never came to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the Berlin Wall, we were never put to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never saw active service, I was never shot at (other than in training), and I have no medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But…the Queen’s Commission hangs on my wall at home, I understand and appreciate the military ethos, I have worn the uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that counts for something with all of you - because it certainly counts for something with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all of that, I am looking forward to getting stuck into the challenges that together we face and today’s conference is an ideal opportunity to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to start by saying thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two small words, but I genuinely mean that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you - for all the hard work you do to help improve the lives of the men and women of our Armed Forces - and the families who support them - and the veterans to whom the country owes a great debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are difficult economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the British public continue to show how much they value our Armed Forces - in the respect they show, in the time they give, and in money they donate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That generosity is evident in this room today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes much of your work possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As patron of my local branch of the Royal British Legion, I have seen first hand the difference that can be made by charitable organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You all changes lives - and that you can be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again, thank you most sincerely for what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-public-and-the-armed-forces"&gt;The Public and the Armed Forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, outside of garrison towns, it is rare these days for civilians to have direct contact with our contemporary Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this summer has seen a powerful exercise in Defence engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly one of the most powerful domestic exercises since National Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Olympics many people have now had first hand experience of the men and women of our Armed Forces providing the venue security and resilience that the Games needed to run safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, serving and former members of our Armed Forces took part and won medals as part of both the Olympic and Paralympic teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They really are the best of British and we salute everything they have achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what else have we seen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just the professionalism which we have all come to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have seen the person behind the camouflage - a fellow citizen, doing a difficult and sometimes dangerous job, with commitment and calm competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this process, the Armed Forces Covenant has become a bit more real, a bit more solid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to talk today about the progress made meeting the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant and tackling some of the welfare issues that we all know exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to look ahead to the challenges over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="priorities"&gt;Priorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While here at home most eyes have been on the Olympics, the eyes of tens of thousands of people, in the MOD, in the Armed Forces, have been focussed on Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan remains the number one priority for the Ministry of Defence and the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are beginning the withdrawal of UK troops consistent with our intention to move out of a combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our troops remain in the firing line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you working with our wounded, those of you working with bereaved families, know very well the price that continues to be paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The withdrawal of troops between now and the end of 2014 will be done sensibly - in consultation with our partners, in accordance with the conditions on the ground, and meeting the requirements of force protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But coming home they are - not just our troops in Afghanistan, but our troops in Germany too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few years our Armed Forces will become more predominantly UK based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will become structured to deal with the unexpected and unplanned, rather than the more predictable deployments of the Iraq and Afghanistan campaigns of the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide a new set of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where will our forces be based? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How will they be supported?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What career structure will be needed to make sure life in the Armed Forces is an attractive option for the brightest and the best?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the basing plan due this Autumn, the MOD is embarking on the design phase of a New Employment Model to answer the last two questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a very complex process - looking at everything from career paths to terms and conditions, allowances to accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A daunting task at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is made more difficult by the fiscal conditions we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the restrictions on the public purse, we can’t just throw money at problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new employment model must reflect the best use of taxpayer’s money, as well as meet the needs of Defence, and of individual soldiers, sailors, airmen and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the Strategic Defence and Security Review has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that behind every Service Number, there is a person, a livelihood, and often a family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the economic climate of the foreseeable future, the only way we are going to meet the needs of national security, is to make sure that our Armed Forces are sustainable as well as powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward there is limited room for manoeuvre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will have to continue to prioritise strictly and only make promises we know we can fulfill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, where the Government can act, we will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is worth reflecting briefly on what we have achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improvement in the operational welfare package - doubling the operational allowance, better R&amp;amp;R arrangements, more council tax relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better support back home with the enhanced capacity of the recovery capability delivered with Help For Heroes and the Royal British Legion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on mental health working with Combat Stress and others to provide better care - and crucially better awareness - spotting those who need help, inside and outside the services, and getting help to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubling the Families Welfare Grant, bursaries for the higher education of bereaved Service children, IVF for the seriously wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action on many of the little but cumulative things that make service life sometimes difficult for families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Armed Forces Bill team last year, I am proud to say that I helped enshrine the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now looking forward to helping put them into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July, the cabinet committee that oversees cross-government action on the Covenant (and on which I now sit) met jointly with the Covenant Reference Group to discuss an early draft of the Annual Report that we are committed to producing and presenting to Parliament by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will be held to account quite rightly for what is done to make the Covenant a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-strength-from-diversity"&gt;Building Strength from Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One manifestation of the Covenant in operation has been the growing strength of Armed Forces charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is fantastic news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diversity in the charitable sector is part of its vitality and strength - responding to needs in a passionate, dynamic and often innovative way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overcoming institutional inertia. Challenging the establishment way of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that very diversity can sometimes be confusing for those looking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not knowing where best to go or who to go to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes signing up to a project only to find it doesn’t meet all their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not always receiving continuity of support as they need different types of help at different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, one of the challenges that we have to work on today is to maintain the strength of diversity whilst achieving better co-ordination and through-life care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our shared aim must be greater effectiveness of support - and greater access for those who need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Government is constrained in ways that the third sector is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can understand the frustrations that are felt when you just want to get on with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD can sometimes be a challenging partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the right shape of partnership we can provide both agility and permanence in the services we deliver to support the Armed Forces community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is strength in the diversity of welfare and charitable provision that is represented right here in this room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passion, the commitment, the innovation, the agility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must marry it with the permanence and continuity that Government provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because when money is tight - and it certainly is - we must make sure that every penny spent goes on reaching the people who are in need, and provides them with the practical help they require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion ladies and gentlemen let me say this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is par for the course for a new Minister to say how ‘delighted’ they are by their appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I say I am delighted, I really mean it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked to come to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to doing everything I practically can to improve the lot of our service personnel - to help support their families - to assist our veterans - and to make sure we never forget the debt we owe to the whole Armed Forces community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no pot of gold. You all know this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the military teaches the principle of combined arms -  all elements in a battle group working together co-operatively to achieve the maximum possible effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My message to you today is that with your help….and looking at the list of attendees today, I mean, quite literally, with your help…….that is exactly what I propose to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to us, working together, to try and do even better for those who keep this country safe and free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck and enjoy the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18746</id>
    <published>2011-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-12-01-mod-civilian-apprentice-awards"/>
    <title>2011/12/01 - MoD Civilian Apprentice Awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon, Ladies and Gentlemen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Bernard [Gray - Chief of Defence Materiel] for that introduction, and for inviting me to say a few words before presenting this year’s MoD civilian apprentice awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also thank all of today’s sponsors for their continued support of this important event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted that Lady Cardwell could be with us once again - after last year’s snow prevented her attendance for the first time since 1982 - to present the Sir David Cardwell Memorial Prize.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David was one of Bernard’s predecessors - in charge of buying the equipment our Armed Forces need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the organisation has changed greatly since Sir David’s time in charge, some things endure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships continue play an important role in helping us to produce the engineers and craftsmen of the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly 500 apprenticeships and 300 advanced apprenticeships were completed last year; we’re here today to recognise the best of them - 29 in all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the value of apprenticeships to our Armed Forces and our broader economic well-being is as high as ever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, in the modern age, the work of the engineer and the craftsman is not as revered as it should be in the eyes of the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many students are lured away from inventing the future and making things people can actually use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet heavy industry generates more cash, more exports, more technology, and more jobs than many of the more fashionable sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want engineers and craftsmen to be the wonder of our age as they were in the Britain of Telford and Brunel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An architect may have designed London’s latest landmark - the Shard - but it takes engineers and craftsmen to build it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also takes excellence, and in a range of fields. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the practical engineering skills which Brunel would admire, today’s engineers need other skills like project management in their toolbox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our prize-winners today have shown they have the tools to meet the demands of modern engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why they have a great deal to offer to our Armed Forces and to our economy; and I want to reflect briefly on that this morning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because this isn’t some abstract debate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women in our Armed Forces - particularly those on operations - rely on the quality of the equipment and support we can provide them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, soldiers in Afghanistan rely on their vehicles to carry out their mission as well as keep them safe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anything breaks down it can be a life-threatening situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes the job of today’s engineers and craftsmen a vital one, though they don’t always get the credit they deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the engineers of the future are not born; they’re made, and they’re nurtured. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships play such an important role in that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the MoD continues to value and support apprenticeships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our scheme remains an enviable one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a unique opportunity to work on some of the country’s most advanced engineering and equipment projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from our perspective, it’s a shrewd investment in our future workforce. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the work on the new aircraft carriers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an apprentice supporting the MoD project team, while others are embedded with industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this colossal project has reinvigorated industry apprenticeship schemes across the six shipyards engaged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 800 apprentices are currently involved, and this number is set to increase as production continues to ramp up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever they’re working, these apprentices are proud to learn their trade on such a prestigious project which will be at the heart of Britain’s defence for decades to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we want everyone who undertakes an apprenticeship provided by us to stay with us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that some will go on to use their skills elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in good times, we should welcome the contribution they will make to the broader economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s particularly welcome in tough economic times like these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t defer investing in our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a false economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing now in the skills we will need in the future is a key part of our plan for recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as true for us in the public sector as it is for those in the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want a skills system where responsibility is shared between government, employers, and employees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we want to address the problem of youth unemployment so that young people are earning or learning again before long-term damage is done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we launched a £1 billion Youth Contract last week which will provide over 400,000 new work places for 18 to 24 year olds over the next three years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships are at the heart of this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, we want to double the incentive payments to encourage employers to take on young apprentices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good news for young people up and down the country, and good news for the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pay-off for business is a skilled, motivated, and loyal workforce. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m proud to be the MoD’s apprentice champion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need more engineers and craftsmen like you - you are becoming a rare breed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are vital to the Defence of this country, and central to its future prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted that we can recognise your achievements with your friends and family today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18739</id>
    <published>2011-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-01-local-government-association-conference"/>
    <title>2011/11/01 - Local Government Association Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Sir Merrick for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My congratulations on organising a fascinating day with some excellent speakers - they’re still to come..! -and workshops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a Councillor myself, and my wife is currently - within Westminster - so I have some understanding of the issues you face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to see so many representatives from across local government, and the voluntary and charitable sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are in the vanguard of our plans to cement the bond between our communities and the Armed Forces through the Armed Forces Covenant and Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone down the years would have embraced such localism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General de Gaulle once observed of France, “How can you govern a country which has 246 varieties of cheese?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He would have really struggled in Britain which - according to the gloriously named British Cheese Board - boasts over 700 distinct local cheeses! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he would have despaired at your job, Merrick, representing as you do hundreds of councils and thousands of councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, in part, De Gaulle’s complaint seems to have been that localism interferes with the smooth pursuit of the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps so in France, but in Britain I’ve always believed that’s the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government believes in ‘small government’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Westminster and Whitehall should lead on those issues which are truly national in scope. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, at most, they should complement - not substitute - local efforts on everything else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why decentralising power is at the heart of this government’s agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet Britain’s Armed Forces straddle the national and local divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one level, they are rooted in lock communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the British infantry system of county regiments helped to forge deep ties between those who serve - often alongside neighbours and friends - and the communities they left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At another level, our Armed Forces are woven into the fabric of our nation’s history and psyche. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson on the quarterdeck; the Pals on the Somme; the SAS on TV as they stormed the Iranian Embassy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage, sacrifice, excellence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why the British public have a deep respect for, and pride in, our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But respect and pride are not the same as understanding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces Community may be an integral part of our society, but in recent decades the link has declined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When World War II ended in 1945, there were around five million men and women in uniform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone in the country knew someone close who had served. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents and her generation gave up their youth in the service of this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Service generation only added to the ledger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for many years, our Armed Forces have been a professional, volunteer force - declining in number - while the older generations have dwindled. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public understanding of our Armed Forces has declined as a result.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matters hugely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of our Armed Forces depends on them knowing that they have their country’s support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliament has taken to welcoming home units of the Armed Forces, and yesterday we welcomed 3 Commando. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked them to go to war, and it is right that we welcome them home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such support requires the public to understand the role of our Armed Forces, and the sacrifice our men and women in uniform make with their families. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never take public support for granted, even in times of plenty.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor should we under-estimate their principled conviction that our Armed Forces Community should get the support they need and the dignity they deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That they should suffer no disadvantage as a result of serving; indeed should receive special consideration in some instances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that they have a right to expect a whole of society approach - not just a top-down, or bottom-up one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m pleased to say that in the 18 months since the General Election we’ve taken action over a very broad canvas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time ever, the principles I have mentioned (no disadvantage) will be recognised in the law of the land through the Armed Forces Bill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the front line, we’ve doubled the operational allowance and extended it to Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve improved the Rest and Recuperation leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve doubled Council Tax relief from 25% to 50% for all personnel on operations, including Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, we set out - in the ‘Today and Tomorrow’ paper - what we’re doing to give the Covenant practical effect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, we have endorsed all of Andrew Murrison’s recommendations for improving mental health care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have allocated resources for 36,000 Service children as part of the pupil premium, and introduced a separate fund for schools with high proportions of Service children.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are giving our personnel a high priority in Affordable Housing Schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, as I’ve said, the Armed Forces Covenant is not just about action from the centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are fewer than 200,000 serving members of our Armed Forces, whereas there are still more than four and a half million people who have served. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With their families, our Armed Forces Community is roughly one in six of the total population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing support to this vast number of people involves all areas of local government working with communities up and down the land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10 NHS Armed Forces Networks have proved particularly useful in ironing out local healthcare and adult social care issues through their extensive local networks.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, an RAF couple were devastated to hear that their application to adopt a child had been scuppered by orders posting them overseas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Authority had withdrawn from the process as ‘suitable’ counselling services would not be available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contacting their regional Armed Forces Network lead, they were able to get SSAFA Forces Help to liaise with the Local Authority until the issue was resolved and the adoption went ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ‘no disadvantage from service’ principle in action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also shows the importance of local authorities forging links with Service charities and the wider voluntary and charitable sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in June, four counties became the first in Britain to demonstrate community-led support for the Armed Forces through the Community Covenant scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll hear more about best practice later this morning from three of the counties involved so far - Oxfordshire, Hampshire, and North Yorkshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further seven councils have signed, with over 30 in the pipeline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant has been well-received, and my hope is that every community will sign one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important as a symbol of our beliefs, and it’s important as a commitment to action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon you will hear more about the Community Covenant Grant Scheme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have allocated up to £30 million until 2015 to fund projects which support the aims of the Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel considered the first bids last month. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to announce that we have approved 11 superb bids in full, and another two in part, totalling over £400,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly pleased to see that those bids will draw in matched funding of over a quarter of a million pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the successful bids themselves, they include help towards a new Scout and Guides Headquarters in Bedale; supporting the Dover Diamond Jubilee Tattoo; and helping elderly residents in their village during adverse weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions on another 14 applications will be made once we have received some additional information.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are all approved, it would take total project funding past £1 million in just this first round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panels are due to sit again in December and March, and quarterly thereafter - so it’s not too late! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, Defence is a very human endeavour -  and the consequences of Service life are very human too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that today inspires you to deepen the relationship between our Armed Forces and the communities they’re drawn from. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because that relationship is as important now as it’s ever been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How we, as a nation, treat our Armed Forces Community is a litmus test of who we are as a nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m confident that the nation will respond to the challenge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that it will be driven in part by localism in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
