<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28542</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-46-million-submarine-command-system-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £46 million submarine command system contract</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Design Services Arrangement contract will ensure that the system, which is used to navigate vessels as well as gather intelligence and defend against attacks, is maintained and developed over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy operates three classes of submarine, totalling 10 vessels, which are used to safeguard the UK’s interests around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, different combat systems are used across the fleet. This new contract will help drive adoption of a common combat system across all current and future Royal Navy submarines, with considerable benefits to training, maintenance and updating costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="John Hudson, Philip Dunne and Rear Admiral Simon Lister" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1364/20121206subs01_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;John Hudson, Managing Director of BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines, Philip Dunne, and Director Submarines Rear Admiral Simon Lister (library image) [Picture: Mike Vallance, BAE Systems]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s submarine fleet is second-to-none and plays a key role in protecting our waters and interests both at home and abroad. This latest commitment to maintain and develop this vital technology throughout the fleet will ensure that we can continue delivering first class capability for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Command Systems on board our submarines contain many vital technologies and it is very important that our submarines retain their technological edge, both now and in the future. This contract will help secure that position for the MOD and UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/our-company-rzz/our-businesses/maritime---submarines" title="BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines"&gt;BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines&lt;/a&gt; and will safeguard around a total of 30 jobs at the company’s sites in Ash Vale in Surrey and Weymouth in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17638</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-helps-small-firms-showcase-defence-innovation"/>
    <title>MOD helps small firms showcase defence innovation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organised by the Ministry of Defence’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.science.mod.uk/engagement/enterprise.aspx" title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;Centre for Defence Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;, the event gives small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a unique opportunity to engage with big business and offer up ideas and technology that could be used by the Armed Forces in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs were joined at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre in London by academics and researchers from two of the country’s leading universities - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/" title="University of Bristol"&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/" title="Lancaster University"&gt;Lancaster University&lt;/a&gt; - who also had products to pitch to industry representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies on show at the event were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbsr.co.uk/" title="Blue Bear Systems Research"&gt;Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s ‘Morphing Wing’ - based on the dynamics of a bird’s wing, this is designed to enable the next generation of unmanned aerial vehicles to be faster, more agile and have greater stability and duration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dreampact.com/" title="Dreampact Ltd"&gt;Dreampact Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s compact heat-sensing video camera - a handheld camera that can also be mounted on a rifle to allow more effective surveillance operations in pitch darkness, bad fog or dust.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1288/DSC_0837.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne speaks at the inaugural Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s ‘Marketplace’ provides a shop window for small and medium-sized enterprises in the most practical sense, helping those which have received research and development funding from the MOD to access their full potential for commercial applications in the UK defence sector and the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation is vital to our national security and the country’s economic growth. We remain committed to providing our Armed Forces with the very best equipment available, which is why we will continue to invest over £400m a year in Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jono Byrne, Head of the Centre for Defence Enterprise, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we have broken fresh ground in developing the Department’s engagement with small and medium-sized enterprises and academia. Over half of our contracts go to small and medium-sized enterprises and academia and it is vital that we are able to bring these Centre for Defence Enterprise-funded innovators, their ideas and capabilities, into the defence supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne chats with delegates" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1289/DSC_0941.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne chats with delegates at the Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted with the response and support we have had from prime contractors as they too understand the benefits such a concept can bring. This is only the start for the ‘Marketplace’ and, like all good innovation, I look forward to further improvement; for example, making use of online tools and involving investment companies as well as defence companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Kurth, Managing Director of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.boeing.co.uk/Products-Services/Boeing-Defence-UK" title="Boeing Defence UK"&gt;Boeing Defence UK&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to attend the inaugural ‘Marketplace’ event and look forward to seeing the areas of technology the Centre for Defence Enterprise has identified in support of our Armed Forces. We see the ‘Marketplace’ as a fantastic opportunity to engage with small and medium-sized enterprises that have relevant innovation and technology for potential work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise (CDE) is committed to finding new revolutionary ideas and working to make them a reality in the future. Since 2008 the CDE has received more than 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at over £35m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17595</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-contracts-safeguard-hundreds-of-uk-shipyard-jobs"/>
    <title>MOD contracts safeguard hundreds of UK shipyard jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contracts cover the long-term maintenance of the Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) Flotilla of naval support ships. They have been awarded to five British companies and will secure a further five years of maintenance support for the 13-strong RFA Flotilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of fuel tankers, stores ships, a medical facility and landing ships, the RFA provides essential support such as food, fuel, munitions and other vital supplies to the Royal Navy at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cammell-laird.com/" title="Cammell Laird website"&gt;Cammell Laird Shiprepairers &amp;amp; Shipbuilders Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Birkenhead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ap-group.co.uk/" title="A&amp;amp;P Group website"&gt;A&amp;amp;P Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt; (ship repair facility), based in Falmouth&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lr.org/default.aspx" title="Lloyd's Register website"&gt;Lloyd’s Register&lt;/a&gt;, based in Bristol&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.trimline.co.uk/" title="Trimline Ltd website"&gt;Trimline Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Southampton&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hempel.com/" title="Hempel UK Ltd website"&gt;Hempel UK Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Cwmbran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="United States warship alongside RFA Cardigan Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1283/FJ120053055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;United States warship USS Devastator (left) alongside the Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Cardigan Bay (library image) [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Simpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships are crucial to the work of the Royal Navy and without them it simply could not operate. These substantial contracts will not only safeguard hundreds of UK jobs but will ensure that these ships can continue in their roles for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Commercially Supported Shipping for Defence, Equipment and Support, Commodore (RFA) David Preston, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These contracts represent the best value for money for Defence and each of the companies has a proven track record in supporting the Royal Fleet Auxiliary on a worldwide basis. This ability to support the Royal Navy wherever they are deployed is critical to UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA personnel are uniformed civil servants employed under the UK Merchant Shipping Act. They are structurally aligned with the Royal Navy and have a high level of specialist military training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17580</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/25m-mod-weapons-contract-sustains-450-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£25m MOD weapons contract sustains 450 UK jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has agreed to purchase additional &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/paveway4.cfm" title="Paveway IV"&gt;Paveway IV&lt;/a&gt; bombs from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raytheon.co.uk/" title="Raytheon UK"&gt;Raytheon UK&lt;/a&gt;. These weapons are to be carried by our Tornados in Afghanistan and will also provide a key capability to be carried by the Typhoon and Lightning II aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract announced today will sustain around 450 jobs at Raytheon UK’s plants. It will secure 300 highly skilled defence sector jobs in Glenrothes, Scotland, and 150 in Harlow, Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also sustain a number of jobs at Raytheon’s subcontractors - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.portav.com/" title="Portsmouth Aviation"&gt;Portsmouth Aviation Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, Exelis in Brighton, Chemring in Ardeer and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thalesgroup.com/" title="Thales Group"&gt;Thales&lt;/a&gt; in Basingstoke, Hampshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paveway IV proved highly effective during the 2011 air campaign over Libya. Its global positioning system technology gives the UK the capability to conduct 24-hour precision attacks against a wide range of targets. Aircrew also have the ability to reprogramme the weapon during a mission, offering capability to attack a wider range of targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This highly sophisticated UK-developed and manufactured weapon is the backbone of the RAF’s precision bombing capability. This contract to boost the MOD’s weapon stocks will sustain hundreds of skilled jobs in the defence manufacturing sector in both Scotland and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By balancing the Defence Budget, we are able to commit with confidence to equipment programmes which help to safeguard our national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paveway munitions have long been a success story for the Royal Air Force in terms of their precision bombing capability. The ability to operate in any weather means that we are able to support operations 24/7. Paveway IV weapons are a real asset, not only to the Royal Air Force, but also to Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the MOD has this year awarded contracts worth more than £100m to Raytheon for orders of around 1,600 Paveway IV bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17808</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-12-03-centre-for-defence-enterprise-marketplace"/>
    <title>2012/12/03 - Centre for Defence Enterprise Marketplace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning to everyone, and thank you Richard [Brooks] for that kind introduction. I am very pleased that so many people have been able to make it here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an exciting moment for the Centre for Defence Enterprise (&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched by the previous Government in 2008 as a delivery mechanism for allowing better access for technology &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; (Small and Medium Enterprises) to defence research and ultimately the wider Defence Market, I see the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now as helping the Ministry of Defence achieve two principle goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;firstly to act as the entry point for new science and technology innovation bringing new thinking and ideas to Defence &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and secondly to act as a key bridge linking &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to the main defence suppliers, as well as investors and wider Government, as part of the MOD’s priority to raise participation by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in defence procurement &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; calls for, receives and assesses research proposals. It then funds, supports and promotes projects that it regards as plausible with potential to meet defence needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It encourages innovative companies to address Defence issues through face to face surgeries, unclassified and open conferences, and through its innovative electronic contracting portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this activity is run from a small base in a commercial office block at the Harwell Science and Innovation Campus in Oxfordshire. One of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strengths is its fleetness of foot, born of a lean and efficient structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To provide visibility of the MOD’s requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To inform and support new supply networks that widen the MOD’s supplier base &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And above all to get the best and most innovative ideas into MOD’s Science and Technology Programme &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks another important milestone of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. A new turn in &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s evolving journey to discover innovation, and then help in the realisation of those ideas into defence and security capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what innovation has been discovered. In the last four years the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has received nearly 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in some 600 contracts, worth around £35 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few projects have made it directly into the hands of users, but that is an exception for most research work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to see those &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities who have successfully demonstrated innovative technology, to have the chance to present their capabilities to our prime contractors - boosting their prospects of being taken into the supply chain. And that’s what today’s marketplace is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some amazing ideas and technologies which have been developed by the innovators we have funded. I hope you will be able to stay and hear the details today, some of which are also on view in the exhibition downstairs on the second floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="exhibition-examples"&gt;Exhibition Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward shortly to going round this exhibition, and to meeting the people who are working to deliver innovative battle winning capabilities which support the front line. And I encourage you all to look around if you have the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example, on display downstairs is Blue Bear Systems Research and their morphing wing for small Unmanned Air Vehicles based on the dynamics of a bird wing. This project exploits the design work already done by Mother Nature, to help ensure our next generation of UAVs can be both faster and more agile, as well as having greater endurance when required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the compact, high performance heat sensing video camera developed by Dreampact, which can be handheld or rifle mounted for surveillance or gunsight use in conditions of total darkness, fog, smoke or dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our universities are also represented today with ingenious electronics and autonomously learning logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the projects featured demonstrate the ingenuity and practical focus of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities that we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation to flourish is vital to our national security and our prosperity, contributing to export led recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wider-st-policy"&gt;Wider S&amp;amp;T Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my new role I have responsibility also for Defence exports as well as procurement, so encouraging responsible Defence exports is a particular priority for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is partly to stimulate this growth which is why the MOD has protected its annual investment in Science and Technology at 1.2% of the Defence Budget - over £400 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is protecting this budget so important? Well, in a future that is so unpredictable, defence science and technology provides insurance against the future threats and conflicts we may face; and supports the MOD’S ability to be an intelligent customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our defence transformation programme transfers responsibility for primary equipment procurement to the Commands, each will need to build capability to look forward to its future needs. This will better align our science and technology spend to the research and development priorities of our front line commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence is about developing Armed Forces and Defence capability that can deal with a broad range of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blueprint for agile, adaptable Armed Forces is Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be effective Future Force 2020 must have the best equipment available: class leading platforms, complex weapon systems and supporting ISTAR assets. Our personnel need the best training and personal equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector and our world class academic institutions will be central to deliver this Future Force. The complexity of much of these platforms needs, by necessity, substantial industrial capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cyber, to space, to nano technology, Britain has world leading companies underpinned by world leading scientific research, some of which I have already seen helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profitable and high tech British Defence and Security sector is essential to achieving all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although many of the platform projects will be managed through large system level contracts by our Prime contractors, there will be numerous participants in the supply chain, from large companies, to academia, to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="smes"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; make an enormous contribution to the economy and in particular to innovation. And I want to take a moment to emphasise their role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; are not the only source of original thinking in our sector, but they often provide the niche expertise which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know that The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in supporting &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in this area, helping them to commercialise their high tech ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank my predecessor, Peter Luff, who I am delighted to see is with us today. Peter did much to champion Science and Technology, the crucial role of Small and medium sized enterprises to delivering innovation, and to starting the conversation that led to this event today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, like him, am a champion of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; doing innovative work in the Defence and Security sector. They are the lifeblood of any sector. In defence they deliver innovation, flexibility, efficiency and agility, when responding to our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; - whose issues are often very different from those of Primes - have their own platform within the defence industry to engage with the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why I chair a dedicated &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Forum which addresses the concerns of smaller companies, and why the MOD is taking a significant number of steps, alongside wider Government to work to ensure &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; can reach their potential when responding to defence requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has a detailed action plan, led by our &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Champion, Les Mosco, who will be talking to you later today, to drive forward &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; involvement in defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have addressed some really important issues such as the treatment of IPR for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify issues that MoD needs to address and which the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; themselves need to think about too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are encouraging our prime contractors to inform us of the part &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; play in their own supply chain and I have personally invited the Chief Executives of our top twenty suppliers to attend today’s event - and I am particularly pleased to see some of them here today and I am grateful for the leadership they are showing at the senior level in support of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, even to a business as small as a one-man band, is to support, not stifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cde"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final word about &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. Since its launch the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has established a reputation for reaching out across a very wide spectrum of the engineering and scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has worked closely with the Technology Strategy Board and benefited through working with its Knowledge Transfer Networks and Small Business Research Initiative and I am glad to see that Mark Glover from TSB is here today to see the blossoming fruits of this collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But above all else, it is you, the defence and security community, that shaped the advances that we see within in the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; today. Thank you for your strong support of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; started off as pilot scheme. And four years on it has become a going concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But innovation never stops, there is always something new to try, something that can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now an exciting new phase has begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our White Paper ‘National Security through Technology’ committed Government to broaden &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s remit to cover both the defence and security domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 3rd October, here in this building, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; held its first event for GCHQ and MI5. This attracted over 300 &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and resulted in over 170 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘National Security through Technology’ also committed &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; to provide more support to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in understanding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how MOD and National Security operates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development of routes to market for potential defence and security products; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to enhance exploitation mechanisms between &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;, the wider MOD and our suppliers &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognising fears expressed by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in the consultation, we committed to keep &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; small and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am most grateful that Richard Brooks, the Programme Director for MOD’s Science and Technology Programme who is here organising this day, is ensuring that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; is not distracted or inhibited by bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst staff numbers have grown, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; remains small and agile with only 12 staff, yet now able to run more research calls, more seminars and more workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; can hold more regular surgeries - ‘one to ones’ - where individuals and companies can get personalised guidance on what the MoD is looking for, and practical help on how to pitch an idea to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set a target of 150 one-to-one appointments for this financial year. This figure will be passed before the end of this month and &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now expects to hold more than 200 such appointments by the end of the financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="marketplace"&gt;Marketplace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through our science and technology budget, we fund &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to work on specific projects for us. They keep the intellectual property rights for their work, and can develop them however they want, once they have completed their project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the effort so far has been focussed on the engagement of &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities and supporting the best ideas with proof of concept funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to help more - which brings us, finally, to today’s Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all this event is a start, and I look forward to seeing this idea develop and innovate rapidly like all the best &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for those of you, &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, universities and Prime Contractors, who have contributed already to the thinking of how today’s Marketplace will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim is an MOD-facilitated initiative whereby &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; gives &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities, who have successfully demonstrated their credibility and capability, the opportunity to present their innovations and capabilities to the UK’s key defence suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By providing this opportunity, the MOD is seeking to ensure that these &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; will have an increased probability of development funding and mentoring, so that they can fully develop their ideas into products suitable for the defence, security or other civilian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that the MOD does have an important role to play in helping to maintain a dynamic pool of innovation which can drive defence applications forward and lead to economic benefits for the whole nation, beyond the immediate Defence objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will only get this by leaving companies free to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And free to work together. So today is all about bringing people together. Then it is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to take a couple of questions before we move downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45348</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-20-science-and-technology-in-optimising-security-defence-and-security"/>
    <title>2012/11/20 - Science and Technology in Optimising Security, Defence and Security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Professor Bernard Silverman and City Forum for that introduction and for inviting me to join you here to open today’s Round Table event with many of the country’s leading defence and security scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am quite sure that some of you, at events like this, are quite capable of standing up and explaining with convincing authority what the world is going to look like in ten, twenty or even thirty years time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be able to describe a compelling vision of future threats and future technologies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oil shortages and global famines; bioterrorism and space wars; Chinese hegemony and European superstates.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much may be foreseeable by commentators and academics, but the reality for those of us in the Ministry of Defence is that we cannot know with certainty what is going to happen in the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that we are helpless against unpredictable events.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot prevent the passage of time, but we can influence its course and prepare for its currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Security Strategy laid out potential threats and prioritised perceived risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It depicted a world in which the only certainty is uncertainty.  Where national events can very quickly escalate to global crises and where threats to the UK can come from diverse and unexpected sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can mitigate risk through international development, investment in multinational institutions, diplomacy and capacity building, but at some point we know that military intervention will be required to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Science and Technology Laboratory and our Development Concepts and Doctrine Centre do some excellent work looking at the types of scenarios in which our Armed Forces might be required to intervene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they would be the first to admit that they possess no crystal ball, which is why they look at many scenarios, not one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the key to responding to an unknown future is flexibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Ministry of Defence that is about developing Armed Forces and Defence capability that can deal with a broad range of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to use the language of this conference we cannot afford to prepare for just a single type of “game changer”, we must consider all possible game changers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blueprint for agile, adaptable Armed Forces is Future Force 2020.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-technology"&gt;Importance of Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be effective Future Force 2020 must have the best equipment available: class leading platforms, complex weapon systems and supporting ISTAR assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it not just about kit.  Our Armed Forces must be well trained and understand how best to use their equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profitable and high tech British Defence and Security sector is essential to achieving both those goals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to know what our next security challenge will look like, but I confidently predict that the private sector and our world class academic institutions will be central to helping us deal with it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cyber, to space, to nano technology, Britain has world leading companies underpinned by world leading scientific research, developing applications, some of which I have already seen helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation to flourish is vital to our national security and our prosperity, contributing to export led recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my new role I have responsibility for Defence exports as well as procurement, so encouraging responsible Defence exports is a particular priority for me.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is partly to stimulate this growth which is why the MOD has protected its annual investment in Science and Technology at 1.2% of the Defence Budget - over £400 million a year  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of guaranteeing a minimum level of S&amp;amp;T funding is in line with recommendations from Lord Heseltine’s recent thought provoking review.  He highlights the valuable role that government investment can have in catalysing private sector innovation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why more than 60% of our S&amp;amp;T budget is spent outside of government - including a new £32 million research contract which we recently signed with BAE Systems to explore the next generation of maritime capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of the contract is designed to maximise the reach of our S&amp;amp;T funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the project will be managed by a team from BAE, there will be numerous participants in the research, from large companies, to academia, to SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine also mentions the contribution that SMEs make to the economy and in particular to innovation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, like my predecessor Peter Luff, whom I know relished his role in supporting Science and Technology, am a champion of the SMEs doing innovative work in the Defence and Security sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that SMEs are not the only source of original thinking in our sector, but they often provide the niche expertise which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in supporting SMEs in this area, helping them to commercialise their high tech ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last four years the CDE has received nearly 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at around £35 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be holding a marketplace on 3rd December where those SMEs who have successfully demonstrated innovative technology will have a chance to present their capabilities to our prime contractors - boosting their prospects of being introduced into the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are some amazing ideas and technologies which have been developed by the innovators we have funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example, on display at this CDE event will be Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd, which is developing a morphing wing for small UAVs based on the dynamics of a bird wing.  This project exploits the design work already done for us by Mother Nature to help ensure our next generation of UAVs will be faster and more agile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the heat sensing compact video camera developed by Dreampact Ltd, which can be handheld or rifle mounted for surveillance or gunsight use in conditions of total darkness, fog, smoke or dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the projects featured at the CDE Marketplace demonstrate the ingenuity and practical focus of the SMEs we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for you to understand how we are using CDE to leverage innovation I want to tell you the story of a company called Crib Gogh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crib Gogh was a one man company based in Stoke-on-Trent developing innovative load carrying systems for soldiers - mainly vests and rucksacks with ergonomic weight distribution and energy dissipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crib Gogh received an initial £56,000 from CDE, followed up by a second contract from Dstl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this funding the company is now able to submit proposals for production level equipment into DE&amp;amp;S, the part of the MOD that acquires and supports equipment and services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has developed a lightweight prototype stretcher that is now under assessment by Dstl. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has boosted Crib Gogh’s profile enabling it to develop relationships with specialists in lightweight materials and pursue export opportunities in Europe and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has increased its turnover allowing its expansion and the recruitment of an additional employee with two more posts being considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to SMEs, even to a business as small as a one-man band, is to support, not stifle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we fund SMEs to work on specific projects for us.  They keep the intellectual property rights for their work, and can develop them however they want, once they have completed their project with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the commercial potential for Defence related intellectual property can also be shown by the success of P2i.  This company was created to exploit the liquid repellant technology coming from a Dstl project, which developed clothing to protect Service personnel from chemical attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P2i’s revolutionary nano-coating process dramatically reduces the&lt;br&gt;
surface energy of a material, so that when liquids come into contact with it they form beads and simply roll off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is so successful that P2i has been able to position itself as a world leader in this field. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology has been successfully applied to a wide range of products, such as electronic devices, filtration products and clothing - including Kangol hats now being marketed by the US actor Samuel L. Jackson.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our S&amp;amp;T investment can stimulate commercial applications well beyond the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that the MOD does have an important role to play in dipping into a dynamic pool of innovation to drive defence applications forward which can lead to economic benefits for the nation far more valuable than just for the immediate Defence objective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we only get that by leaving companies free to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-operations"&gt;Current Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Minister for Defence Equipment Support and Technology I have two main challenges:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, to ensure that our Armed Forces have the equipment they need for today;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, to ensure that our Armed Forces have the equipment they need for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of our business means that a good proportion of the MOD’s endeavour and resources will always be focussed on current operations of the day.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our first priority remains Afghanistan.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the men and women of our Armed Forces are making the greatest sacrifices and this is where we must put our main effort.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But meeting current requirements is not distinct from developing future capabilities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War does not stand still, it evolves - measures and countermeasures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been in Afghanistan for more than ten years now.  And in that time the equipment used by our troops has changed, in some areas, beyond recognition.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing the equipment for current operations involves a never ending feedback loop - the needs of theatre, the development and testing of solutions, the deployment of novel capabilities and then returning to the new needs of theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is yesterday’s tomorrow: the equipment being used in Helmand now is the product of research and development effort from years in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the gears of counter-terrorism have forced us to shorten the time between identifying a need and deploying a solution - to save lives and to increase capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of the Foxhound patrol vehicle, partly funded by the MOD’s Science and Technology budget, is an outstanding example of this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound employs world leading technology to provide an unparalleled balance of protection, weight and agility for a vehicle of its class.  It can drive away with only three wheels and its engine can be replaced easily and quickly in challenging conditions.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound took just 40 months from concept to initial operating capability, an impressive timeline for such an advanced platform.  Forty months to design it, build it and deploy it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this urgency these vehicles are now being used by our troops in Afghanistan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these vehicles are not just of utility to our operations in Afghanistan.  They are so flexible and capable that they will form the backbone of Army 2020, the blueprint for our future Army.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flexibility was built into the design.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is Foxhound built to work in a wide variety of environments, but it has the potential to be modified easily in the future - for example, by replacing the current crew compartment with an alternative configuration to meet future requirements.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adaptability of Foxhound and the speed at which it was taken from concept to operational deployment were only possible because of a strong partnership between the MOD, the Defence scientific community and the Defence Industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good communications between the customer, the developers and the manufacturers were at the heart of the project’s success.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can rightly be proud of Foxhound, which was designed and built in Britain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it represents a model for how the MOD and Defence Industry can collaborate to deliver innovative operational capability: urgently, flexibly and above all intelligently.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the MOD to apply these principles to all of our procurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="intelligent-customer"&gt;Intelligent Customer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already made great progress towards this goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence budget has been balanced for the first time in a generation - eliminating the vast £38 billion black hole we inherited from the previous administration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many difficult decisions have been taken.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult, but necessary decisions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the MOD’s equipment and support spending within the £160bn budget envelope we have set for the next ten years is essential.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining the overheated, essentially aspirational, equipment programme of the last Government was not an option.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would have condemned us to face future conflicts hamstrung by a deficit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the budget now includes proper contingency funding, which will allow us to respond proactively to future events.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But procurement reform is not just about fiscal management, it is also about ensuring the best equipment for our future Armed Forces and the best value for money for the taxpayer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are looking at improving DE&amp;amp;S to allow an injection of private sector expertise, tools and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a great believer in the wisdom of one sector above another.  I believe that we can all learn from each other: Government, industry and academia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becoming a more intelligent customer requires dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-co-operation"&gt;International Co-operation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That dialogue must include international co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For in a world of new realities - with fiscal constraints and unpredictable threats - none of us, not even our friends here today from the US, can afford to maintain all possible capabilities to deal with all possible eventualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative research is not just nice-to-have, it is absolutely essential if we are to maintain a technological advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country can claim to have a monopoly on innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Defence research we are working with a number of countries bilaterally, or through organisations such as NATO: from traditional allies such as Australia, with whom we have recently signed a co-operative facilities arrangement, and France, where 60 projects are under consideration for collaboration, to emergent powers such as India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year our Chief Scientific Adviser signed a Letter of Arrangement with his Indian counterpart agreeing to pool science and engineering experience on areas such as advanced explosives and factors affecting human performance on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is really important that we work alongside a diverse range of partners, especially on issues of technological interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In circumstances where we don’t know what the next operation will be or who we will need to work alongside, building interoperability is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that technology remains an enabler, not an inhibitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion, I’m afraid I have been unable to give you a simple and definitive answer on how to deal with future uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to offer some vision of building flexibility into our Armed Forces so they can respond to the future, whatever shape it takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the MOD it is a case of hedging, not speculating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vibrant Science and Technology community in this country is at the heart of our strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you what our next major operation will be.  I can’t tell you what the next significant technological advance will be.  I can’t even tell you, with certainty, what the next threat to the UK will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can tell you that it will be the ingenuity and drive of our scientists and businesses, and the bravery and dedication of our Armed Forces that will allow us to respond in the way this country has always responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History has shown that Britain has in-built resilience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanks, radar, computing - necessity has always born us invention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never be complacent, but we should always be confident that we can and will deal with the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I trust that you will use today’s conference to help define where the defence and security industry can most benefit our Armed Forces of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45367</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-16-odgers-berndtson"/>
    <title>2012/10/16 - Odgers Berndtson</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Odgers Berndtson and Berwin Leighton Paisner for providing this opportunity to talk to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first formal speech to a defence industry forum since taking over my responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already briefly met some of you, or colleagues from the companies you represent, at one of our “industry days” last month at Abbey Wood, and some brave souls who attended the recent party conference in Birmingham recently, for which I am grateful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am delighted to be able to speak to you collectively in a little more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a steep learning curve, having not had the benefit of a background in the military.  So I am standing by to engage, initially with the Armed Forces to understand their needs and operational requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But developing a dialogue with you is also an important part of my path along this curve and will shape the way I approach this complex role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So tonight I will touch on Defence acquisition, but I also want to give you a sense of who the new Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology is and what my priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by telling you a little about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told you I am not a military man - although I did have some modest exposure to Salisbury plain as an army cadet at school and to the RAF as a member of the University Air Squadron at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came into politics after a career in business.  I was first elected in 2005 at the tender age of 46 - one of the eldest of my cohort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My constituents often tell me, and it is a view that I happen to share, that those elected to Parliament can contribute most to their communities if they have experience of the world beyond Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experience is twenty years in business advising major corporates - working across a range of sectors and companies - including retail - I hope some of you may at some stage have bought a book from an Ottakar’s bookshop, a company I co-founded in 1988 and sold to Waterstone’s, a year after I was elected, in 2006 - by luck as it happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am, by background, a businessman and an entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that this commercial experience will give me a useful and relevant perspective on some of the issues I will be dealing with at the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is already clear to me that being a Minister at the MOD will be unlike anything I have done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise that defence of the realm is the first duty of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is a great privilege to be working in the Ministry of Defence with some of the best, brightest - and bravest - people that our country has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in that context I would just like to pay tribute to my predecessors and good friends, Peter Luff and Sir Gerald Howarth, whom many of you have got to know well.  Both have been most gracious in offering me their full support in this new role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I come to the department not representing any vested interests - but with a clear focus on my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is to do my best for the men and women of our Armed Forces who rely, sometimes for their very lives, upon the equipment and support for which I am now responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also determined to do my best for British taxpayers, who are hard-pressed, especially at the moment, and deserve effective and efficient Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am determined to do my best for the British economy, to ensure where possible that the defence equipment sector plays its part in the growth agenda for Britain: to recruit British engineers; to encourage British technology; and to develop British exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing business in Britain to contribute to Britain’s defence: generating the equipment and support that our Armed Forces need to protect the country; and generating jobs and revenue for the UK that can help balance the cost of defence to the Treasury - and in the final analysis - the taxpayer, where the financial burden ultimately falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With shrinking Defence budgets in many developed countries, I understand how difficult it is out there for the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am under no illusion that the world of defence equipment, procurement and support is simple and straightforward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we face unique and difficult challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cannot be met by Government alone - or by business alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a clear need for us to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my first message for you tonight is that I am here not just as a customer, but also as a collaborator, to listen, to understand - and to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been given a clear mandate from the Prime Minister and the Secretary of State to encourage a strong and viable Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why I am pleased that I have been given the added responsibility for Defence Exports, as well as for procurement, within the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about that today, but let me start by outlining some of those challenges I referred to a moment ago.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are difficult times for our Armed Forces as they undertake a tough transformation while continuing to operate in dangerous circumstances in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations have to remain the No 1 priority - and it will be my No 1 priority to make sure that our Forces have all they need to get that job done as safely as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these are difficult times for the country as a whole and Defence must continue to play its part in putting the economy on the right track. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fortunate to arrive at the Ministry of Defence after many of the toughest decisions have already been taken.  Thanks to the courage of the Secretary of State Philip Hammond, and his predecessor Liam Fox, we now have a balanced budget for the first time in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme has been reined in and we have a deliverable path towards Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in contrast to the previous Government who operated an unfunded wish list.  Those years of over-programming created a climate of uncertainty and criticism that was beneficial neither to us nor to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I see my first task as ensuring that the MOD’s equipment and support spending is kept within the £160bn budget envelope we have set for the next ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be publishing our Equipment Plan in the coming months. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide you, our contractors, with greater granularity than ever before about how money will be spent across the breadth of capabilities, providing a year-by-year breakdown for equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that this will help you to build your planning on a firmer foundation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, the Defence Industrial Strategy that Jim Murphy seems to think existed under the last administration was built on the shifting sands of a fantasy programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing little certainty - and therefore no ability to plan properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a strategy at all - it was more of a mirage.  And I don’t mean the aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I will heed his advice accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By eliminating the black hole in the Defence budget, and putting the equipment programme on a sustainable basis, we are providing industry with the confidence that we can deliver the programme that will underpin Future Force 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been tough to achieve that balanced budget - sacrifices have had to be made that, I’m sure many of us would rather we hadn’t had to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has meant job losses - in the Armed Forces, in the civil service, and yes, in the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is why we can’t afford to lapse from our discipline now - because that would just mean bigger cuts in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward the MOD is determined to be a more intelligent customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone with whom the Defence sector can do business - effective and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This links to my second priority, which is to ensure that Defence Procurement plays its part in the transformation programme within the MOD, to make the procurement function as efficient as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this efficiency should be delivered through abandoning the annual efforts of the previous administration to fit the equipment programme, often at the last minute, within that year’s spending limit - pushing programmes into subsequent years, introducing inevitable cost and delay into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the noble Admiral Lord West recognised that this was a “ludicrous” way to procure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that both private sector and public sector understand what it is that we each seek to achieve from a programme - and make sure those objectives are in concert rather than in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which prompts me briefly to comment on last weekend’s revelations focused on certain former senior officers claims to influence the way military equipment is procured. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that such claims are exaggerated and equipment decisions are chosen by current not former MOD decision makers. The system we have is completely robust, but we are looking at whether any rules have been broken.  We are also considering the level of access we give retired officers to the MOD and ensuring we are informed of their commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These types of issues, though, should not dissuade us from pursuing legitimate and transparent consultation with industry.  It is essential that we continue to share skills and experience - bringing private sector discipline and productivity to public procurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are looking at restructuring DE&amp;amp;S to allow for the injection of new ideas and new experience from the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already stated its preference for an option which establishes a Government Owned, Contractor Operated -  or GOCO - entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are legitimate concerns about this process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most relate to propriety, accountability and measuring performance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have been engaging with industry in recent months to gain your input, as we explore further the options and begin to develop a commercial strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we have also begun earlier this month a Soft Market Testing exercise with potential providers to sound out their issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is undoubtedly an innovative approach to defence procurement and so it is all the more important to make sure incentives are aligned, but also to ensure that the interests of Defence and equipping our Armed Forces remain paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we decide and whatever we do, I would stress that we will continue the engagement we have started with our main contractors to ensure industry is well informed and any concerns can be taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been looking closely at plans within the department to reform the arrangements in place for single-source procurement through the Yellow Book with its Review Board. This has remained in effect in broadly similar form since first introduced in 1968.  I’ll repeat that: 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many of the companies represented here took part in the consultation around this reform earlier this year and I am grateful for the responsible way in which you recognised the merits of reform. I hope to be in a position to publish our conclusions in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of collaboration needs to be at the heart of everything we do, at every level: from Prime to SME, from local to international, bottom-up as well as top-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keen to champion SMEs, just as my predecessor did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make a vital contribution to the national economy, but also to local economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my appointment I have visited a company in my own constituency, Grainger &amp;amp; Worrall, which makes engine casings for high performance cars and Formula One, but also has some products used in defence. This was something I was previously ignorant of, despite this not being my first visit.  Perhaps the company did not believe this was something they could talk about to an outsider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company is a medium sized employer in a national context, but one of the largest employers within its community and its fortunes affect the wellbeing of hundreds of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs often provide the source of innovation and adaptation which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in this area to open MOD’s science and technology investment to our high tech companies.  And it will be holding a marketplace of some of the best SME ideas for you, our Primes, on 3rd December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those SMEs who have successfully delivered innovative technology will have a chance to present their capabilities to our primes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be your chance to take advantage of the MOD’s investment in early stage technology, to improve the product you deliver to us, and have available for export. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you will agree that it will be in all our mutual interests to nurture the innovation that these companies can drive. So, I would urge you to make sure you are represented at this event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also ask you to consider how you can monitor better the contribution of SMEs to your own procurement for the MoD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has aspirations for the proportion of procurement provided by SMEs across Whitehall. As the MOD is the largest direct purchaser in Government this has particular relevance to me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am keen to encourage our Prime contractors to do a better job at informing my officials of the number of SMEs and the value of their contributions to contracts placed with larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the other end of the scale our new approach to industrial engagement encourages overseas based suppliers to invest in the UK’s defence and security sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working with overseas based suppliers through the Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy to promote the UK as a prime location for their supply chains and for research and development investment, and technology transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This policy initiative to encourage inward investment was launched this Spring and has already secured its first accredited member, with another about to sign and several other overseas based contractors showing considerable interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third priority, where I believe a fresh collaboration can take place, is working together to encourage your business growth through exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the previous Government, I am not embarrassed about responsible Defence Exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need responsible exports and we shall be clear about the licencing regime which governs what can be sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am clear that Britain’s Defence sector is a vital strategic asset to this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only for the vital role you play in helping to create military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also for the contribution you make to Britain’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jobs you sustain, the skills you maintain and the taxes you pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because we recognise the importance of that strategic asset that we worked so hard to ensure that the UK’s national security interests were properly protected in the BAE/EADS merger negotiations - something of a major, if completely unexpected, preoccupation in my first month as a Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong UK Defence sector - manufacturing, servicing, and crucially exporting - is a vital part of our strategy of rebalancing our economy so it can return to sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the MOD is committed to supporting the Defence Growth Partnership work led by BIS and announced by the Prime Minister at the Farnborough International Air Show in July. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It builds on the successful model of joint Government and Industry engagement already established for the Aerospace sector. The partnership will identify ways to remove barriers to growth and enhance the competitiveness of the UK defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will contribute to the overall approach set out earlier this year in our National Security Through Technology White Paper -working to enable UK-based industry to be competitive and provide the best value for money in meeting our defence and security needs, as well as helping you to export successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Defence exports are unlike other products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are more than simple sales of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are high value, highly regulated and play an important role in foreign policy as well as just contributing to balance of payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow governments are partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us in our pursuit of bilateral relationships - and in pursuit of national security and international stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, in terms of industrial and technological co-operation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can Government do better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - we can optimise your prospects for export success in the formulation of our own acquisition plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about acquisition processes that will take better account of the commercial landscape - building in exportability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This needs a new system for building robust business cases - setting out why more readily exportable capabilities are also in the interests of UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - We can help to make sure that UK products are the best and most advanced on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure the wider package on offer to our allies is as attractive as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Export success depends on more than just the hardware on offer and I will back you in meeting the wider requirements of our allies.  For instance, by providing the capacity, wherever possible, for training alongside UK Forces, or helping you to provide long term equipment support and the responsible transfer of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the first rate innovation the UK defence industry creates, the MOD cannot fulfil its mission of defending the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But innovation is also key to exports in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be impossible to sustain this innovation without sustaining the science and engineering skills on which it is built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our intention to sustain investment in defence science and technology, halting years of decline in this spending, to ensure our Armed Forces continue to use state of the art techniques and equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why in one of my first acts as a Minister, I signed a concordat for the MOD to support the exciting Bloodhound project which hopes to smash the land speed record in a cutting edge vehicle driven by an RAF pilot, with support from the Army’s Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers and using Typhoon test engines from the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This MOD support is specifically to inspire young people to study maths and science at school - becoming the engineers of the future that you and we, at the MOD, so urgently need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging engineers and scientists in Britain to make the most of their innovative talent is critical for our future export prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - we can intervene when necessary, banging the drum for British products whenever Ministers are overseas - from the Prime Minister down, to a degree that Labour completely neglected to do in their years in Government, with some notable exceptions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague told us last week, to the incredulity of the party conference audience, that he is already the first Foreign Secretary since we were last in Government to have made bilateral visits to Canada, New Zealand and Australia - three of the Five Eyes grouping, our closest defence partners.  None of his Labour predecessors did so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that this whole Government is energised to help you create opportunities to sell your world leading products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promotion activity in government is led by the Defence &amp;amp; Security Organisation within UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment, who you will all know well, and with whom I am already working closely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to combine responsibilities for defence procurement and for exports within MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My role will be to enable both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In concluding I want to re-emphasise my commitment to maintain a dialogue with you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to cutting bureaucracy and helping you on exports, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to developing science and engineering skills and supporting innovation, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, when it comes to developing the best way ahead for reform of acquisition and the future of DE&amp;amp;S, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the MOD to be a world leader in defence acquisition, so that other nations look at the UK model as an exemplar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we are going to achieve this is with your support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34762</id>
    <published>2012-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-37m-viking-regeneration--2"/>
    <title>Green light for £37m Viking regeneration</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Used extensively by the Royal Marines, the 99 Viking vehicles, which can be launched straight from the back of a ship and propelled through water before landing for a beach assault, are in line for a major overhaul by BAE Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were deployed to Afghanistan in 2006 for their versatility across tough terrains before they were later replaced by Warthog. Viking will now be fitted with new mine blast protection bodywork and brought back to their original amphibious standard, having been adapted for the rigours of land operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £37 million mid-life upgrade to the Viking fleet of amphibious vehicles will keep these highly capable vehicles in service with the Royal Marines into the 2030s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With a balanced defence budget, for the first time in a generation, we are able to deliver with confidence the equipment our Armed Forces require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Marines from the Armoured Support Group Yeovil 'test drive' a Viking amphibious all-terrain vehicle onto HMS Bulwark via the ship's well dock (library image)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1671/Green_light_for__37m_Viking_regeneration2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from the Armoured Support Group Yeovil 'test drive' a Viking amphibious all-terrain vehicle onto HMS Bulwark via the ship's well dock (library image) [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Martin Carney, Crown Copyright/MOD 2007]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commandant General Royal Marines, Major General Ed Davis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that the contract for the regeneration of our Viking amphibious vehicles has been announced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Viking is an essential asset for the Royal Marines in conducting short notice crisis response operations around the world and any modifications which enhances operational effectiveness and makes life that bit safer for our personnel is always welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 99 Viking vehicles, 19 are set to be fitted with top-mounted guns and nine more will allow the firing of an 81mm mortar from the vehicle. All will have improvements made to their braking and suspension systems. As well as new front and rear car hulls the Vikings will have the latest mine-protected v-shaped underbody which is designed to protect the occupants should it drive over an explosive device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regeneration programme is expected to be completed by the end of 2014 and will secure the vehicle’s service life until its expected out of service date of 2031.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35325</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-defender-moves-into-her-new-home"/>
    <title>HMS Defender moves into her new home</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship’s arrival at her new base brings Defender a step closer to her first deployment. She will now undergo sea trials before being declared ready for operations in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with the world-leading Sea Viper missile defence system, the 7,500-tonne vessel is able to defend against multiple attacks from even the most sophisticated anti-ship missiles, approaching from any direction and at supersonic speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Peter Luff, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This latest addition to our fleet of state-of-the-art destroyers marks the remarkable progress being made on the Type 45 programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Defender, together with her five sister vessels, will form a formidable fleet and ensure that the Royal Navy remains a powerful maritime force on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Defender passes between the harbour walls at Portsmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1678/HMS_Defender_moves_into_her_new_home2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Defender passes between the harbour walls at Portsmouth [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Claire Myers, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;HMS Defender is the fifth of six Type 45 warships built for the Royal Navy, and was launched at the BAE Systems’ Govan shipyard in Glasgow in October 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Type 45s will provide the backbone of the UK’s naval air defences for the next 30 years and beyond. The destroyers will be capable of carrying out a wide range of operations, including anti-piracy and anti-smuggling activities, and disaster relief work and surveillance operations, as well as high intensity war-fighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Ship Support (Alliance), Commodore John Newell, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Entry into HM Naval Base Portsmouth of this very powerful and advanced warship is not only a great day for the Royal Navy but also for the Destroyers Project Team and our industry partners who ensured this magnificent vessel was ship-shape and ready to be accepted from BAE Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Defender is a welcome addition to the fleet and, when she enters service, she will help ensure that the Royal Navy can react to any defence challenges anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final vessel in the Daring Class, Duncan, is due to undertake her first set of sea trials later this year, and is due to be accepted into service in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45364</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-12-ssafa-fund-raising-dinner-ads-event-as-part-of-farnborough-2012"/>
    <title>2012/07/12 - SSAFA Fund Raising Dinner (ADS event as part of Farnborough 2012)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Sir Stephen [CAS].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you to the ADS team for hosting tonight’s dinner.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on a very successful Farnborough 2012, and to all the sponsors and donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you are laying plans for an equally successful Farnborough 2014, and a show within a show - the Unmanned Aerial Systems Expo. This is a really important area for us and the UK needs to demonstrate leadership. This initiative is therefore doubly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks to Robin for his remarks, and to you in the aerospace industries for recognising so  generously the support from ministers across government at this year’s show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of government representation is certainly a far cry from the days when you were lucky to be able to secure just one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we do value the aerospace sector - civil and defence - and we understand the role of government in supporting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting it with words and deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words with real intent. And tangible deeds that count. Such as the Chancellor highlighting the aerospace sector in his Budget speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the old cliche has it, “actions speak louder then words.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visit companies, not just defence companies, I always wait for that moment when they give me the well worn line about people being their greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It too is a cliche - but it happens to be true, as all good cliches are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret in business is to mean it, and to be able to demonstrate a genuine commitment to it. Not just to say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s not a company going through the motions and just paying lip service to this maxim which impresses me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really impresses me is a company proving that the men and women who work for them really are their greatest resource&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because people matter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s my theme tonight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know for a fact, for example, that SSAFA Forces Help does demonstrate that commitment and support in a very practical way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA knows that people are at the heart of defence and that what they do when they serve Queen and country demands a generous response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a week when the platforms have taken centre stage, it’s worth reminding ourselves that for Defence people really are our greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That stunning display from Typhoon was only possible because of the skills of the pilot - Scott,  the people in the engineering crew on the ground, the people in industry who support the plane, the people in four nations who make it and the brilliant people who designed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People, always people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know he’s not here so I can say nice things about him behind his back, that link is personified in the work of your chairman, General Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, who moved from platforms to people when he moved from CDM to SSAFA. MOD’s loss was SSAFA’s gain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have emotions, ambitions, skills, hopes and fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it turns out there are even those in the defence industry who have emotions too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - let me just say for the record that I’ve always found Robin Southwell to be a business like chap, a matter of fact kind of guy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His role as ADS President is to fight your corner, champion your interests and act as an advocate for industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his job in EADS is to sell me anything he can. And he does a good job in both roles, in a robust kind of way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he is a man who says what he thinks. I think “shooting from the lip” is the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was still rather taken aback when I opened the Financial Times  earlier this year - Friday 24 February to be precise - and saw a piece about the defence industry’s relationship with Government which read - and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love,” says Robin Southwell, head of the UK arm of EADS, the pan-European defence contractor and president of ADS, the industry’s biggest trade group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was - as you can imagine, because I do like to think of myself as emotionally aware and sensitive man - most concerned by this heartfelt plea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the next time that I met Robin I went out of my way to ensure that he did feel sufficiently cherished. That he got the love he craved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember engulfing him in a fond embrace in the street outside Portcullis House in the Palace of Westminster. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, Robin did seem rather taken aback.  I like to think he was probably just carried away by the sheer emotion of the moment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, though, he was reacting to my comment that this demonstration of love discharged all MoD’s financial obligations to EADS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, “We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tribute-to-industry"&gt;Tribute to industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do hope that everyone here this evening from industry appreciates that we do recognise the vital contribution you are making to our defence effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular your responsiveness in recent years when it has come to our operations in Libya and Afghanistan in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, thanks to your efforts, our forces today are better equipped than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that because of the universally positive feedback I get from one very discerning focus group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People whose lives very often depend on the way we deliver  acquisition and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking here of course about our servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meet them regularly on my visits to theatre and here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They speak in glowing terms about the quality and availability of their equipment.  The protection and cutting edge, battle winning capability of the equipment you produce and we provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your contribution is likely to grow as we develop the Total Support Force concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you will make that contribution with people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their talent and dedication will enable our Armed Forces to keep the nation safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one major obstacle - and I’ll be talking about this in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have heard what the Prime Minister said on Monday about the Aerospace Growth Partnership and the beginning of a similar dialogue with the defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the approach set out in the Aerospace Growth Partnership  and the National Security through Technology White Paper, we will now begin a dialogue with you to see what we can do to create an environment in which you are strong and can flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope it will put paid, once and for all, to some of the speculative debate about our real intent our the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper may be tough love Robin, but it is love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, though, we can also start looking forward and talking about the wider context. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be much to talk about. Challenges and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the top of the agenda I believe will be the obstacle I referred to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the whole issue of skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any business needs the right people to succeed. Your companies are no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - of course you need a healthy order book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But without skilled engineers in particular you simply won’t be able to develop and integrate the equipment, to write the software, to understand and interpret our requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these people we cannot safeguard our operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know you can’t find them. At all levels of engineering and in all disciplines there seems to be a shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met one engineering company a few months ago who’ve given up looking for engineers in the UK and are recruiting from Spain, Portugal and Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smaller defence companies I meet complain about all kinds of things, and understandably so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But top of their list is skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked about these issues endlessly as a nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers just aren’t valued sufficiently highly in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an urban myth that this country doesn’t make anything anymore. And that manufacturing is dead or dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So schools don’t encourage bright young people into science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And anyway they’re often too focussed on university and not enough on technical vocational options for their pupils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities offer too many general courses that don’t produce the technical, specialist skills you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely passionate about the need to do more about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not making specific suggestions here tonight to address it, but I certainly hope it will be a major theme of the dialogue the Prime Minister announced on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the only one, but perhaps the most important one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people are indeed our most important asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s show is of course a great chance to enthuse and inspire future generations of engineers and scientists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you’ll be doing that at tomorrow’s dedicated Futures Day when you should have 7,500 young people there from schools and universities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets hope their visit to Farnborough tomorrow will inspire some of these young people to pursue a career in science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of initiative I warmly commend - it’s definitely the way forward for our science and technology sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the Bloodhound world land speed record project which is doing excellent work to inspire school pupils with the massive excitement of technical innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus tonight has been on people and I have spoken about the needs of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also the case in Defence, that people in industry serve the people in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask a lot of these servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also ask a lot of their families.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We owe them all a huge debt of gratitude for the sacrifices they make on our behalf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the work of SSAFA is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the money you raise this evening will make a real difference to the lives of thousands of men, women and children. Serving personnel, families and veterans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA promises a lifetime of support - and it delivers just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our oldest service charities, it works tirelessly to provide a wealth of practical, hands on support and guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its people include many experts and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to health and social work, for example, and running the SSAFA Norton Homes which provide accommodation for families visiting injured personnel recovering at Birmingham and Headley Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a huge pool of committed volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of men and women who give up their time to work in communities, bases, units and garrisons up and down the country, as well as overseas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money you pledge tonight will ensure SSAFA Forces Help has the money it needs to continue this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Defence Minister I have the huge privilege of working with and for the United Kingdom’s Armed Forces - quite simply the  bravest, most committed people it is possible to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are our nation’s greatest asset, and tonight our generosity can demonstrate our understanding of that vital truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
