<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17638</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-helps-small-firms-showcase-defence-innovation"/>
    <title>MOD helps small firms showcase defence innovation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organised by the Ministry of Defence’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.science.mod.uk/engagement/enterprise.aspx" title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;Centre for Defence Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;, the event gives small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a unique opportunity to engage with big business and offer up ideas and technology that could be used by the Armed Forces in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs were joined at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre in London by academics and researchers from two of the country’s leading universities - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/" title="University of Bristol"&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/" title="Lancaster University"&gt;Lancaster University&lt;/a&gt; - who also had products to pitch to industry representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies on show at the event were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbsr.co.uk/" title="Blue Bear Systems Research"&gt;Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s ‘Morphing Wing’ - based on the dynamics of a bird’s wing, this is designed to enable the next generation of unmanned aerial vehicles to be faster, more agile and have greater stability and duration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dreampact.com/" title="Dreampact Ltd"&gt;Dreampact Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s compact heat-sensing video camera - a handheld camera that can also be mounted on a rifle to allow more effective surveillance operations in pitch darkness, bad fog or dust.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1288/DSC_0837.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne speaks at the inaugural Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s ‘Marketplace’ provides a shop window for small and medium-sized enterprises in the most practical sense, helping those which have received research and development funding from the MOD to access their full potential for commercial applications in the UK defence sector and the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation is vital to our national security and the country’s economic growth. We remain committed to providing our Armed Forces with the very best equipment available, which is why we will continue to invest over £400m a year in Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jono Byrne, Head of the Centre for Defence Enterprise, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we have broken fresh ground in developing the Department’s engagement with small and medium-sized enterprises and academia. Over half of our contracts go to small and medium-sized enterprises and academia and it is vital that we are able to bring these Centre for Defence Enterprise-funded innovators, their ideas and capabilities, into the defence supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne chats with delegates" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1289/DSC_0941.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne chats with delegates at the Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted with the response and support we have had from prime contractors as they too understand the benefits such a concept can bring. This is only the start for the ‘Marketplace’ and, like all good innovation, I look forward to further improvement; for example, making use of online tools and involving investment companies as well as defence companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Kurth, Managing Director of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.boeing.co.uk/Products-Services/Boeing-Defence-UK" title="Boeing Defence UK"&gt;Boeing Defence UK&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to attend the inaugural ‘Marketplace’ event and look forward to seeing the areas of technology the Centre for Defence Enterprise has identified in support of our Armed Forces. We see the ‘Marketplace’ as a fantastic opportunity to engage with small and medium-sized enterprises that have relevant innovation and technology for potential work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise (CDE) is committed to finding new revolutionary ideas and working to make them a reality in the future. Since 2008 the CDE has received more than 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at over £35m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17595</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-contracts-safeguard-hundreds-of-uk-shipyard-jobs"/>
    <title>MOD contracts safeguard hundreds of UK shipyard jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contracts cover the long-term maintenance of the Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) Flotilla of naval support ships. They have been awarded to five British companies and will secure a further five years of maintenance support for the 13-strong RFA Flotilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of fuel tankers, stores ships, a medical facility and landing ships, the RFA provides essential support such as food, fuel, munitions and other vital supplies to the Royal Navy at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cammell-laird.com/" title="Cammell Laird website"&gt;Cammell Laird Shiprepairers &amp;amp; Shipbuilders Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Birkenhead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ap-group.co.uk/" title="A&amp;amp;P Group website"&gt;A&amp;amp;P Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt; (ship repair facility), based in Falmouth&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lr.org/default.aspx" title="Lloyd's Register website"&gt;Lloyd’s Register&lt;/a&gt;, based in Bristol&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.trimline.co.uk/" title="Trimline Ltd website"&gt;Trimline Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Southampton&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hempel.com/" title="Hempel UK Ltd website"&gt;Hempel UK Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Cwmbran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="United States warship alongside RFA Cardigan Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1283/FJ120053055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;United States warship USS Devastator (left) alongside the Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Cardigan Bay (library image) [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Simpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships are crucial to the work of the Royal Navy and without them it simply could not operate. These substantial contracts will not only safeguard hundreds of UK jobs but will ensure that these ships can continue in their roles for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Commercially Supported Shipping for Defence, Equipment and Support, Commodore (RFA) David Preston, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These contracts represent the best value for money for Defence and each of the companies has a proven track record in supporting the Royal Fleet Auxiliary on a worldwide basis. This ability to support the Royal Navy wherever they are deployed is critical to UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA personnel are uniformed civil servants employed under the UK Merchant Shipping Act. They are structurally aligned with the Royal Navy and have a high level of specialist military training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17580</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/25m-mod-weapons-contract-sustains-450-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£25m MOD weapons contract sustains 450 UK jobs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has agreed to purchase additional &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/paveway4.cfm" title="Paveway IV"&gt;Paveway IV&lt;/a&gt; bombs from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raytheon.co.uk/" title="Raytheon UK"&gt;Raytheon UK&lt;/a&gt;. These weapons are to be carried by our Tornados in Afghanistan and will also provide a key capability to be carried by the Typhoon and Lightning II aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract announced today will sustain around 450 jobs at Raytheon UK’s plants. It will secure 300 highly skilled defence sector jobs in Glenrothes, Scotland, and 150 in Harlow, Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also sustain a number of jobs at Raytheon’s subcontractors - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.portav.com/" title="Portsmouth Aviation"&gt;Portsmouth Aviation Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, Exelis in Brighton, Chemring in Ardeer and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thalesgroup.com/" title="Thales Group"&gt;Thales&lt;/a&gt; in Basingstoke, Hampshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paveway IV proved highly effective during the 2011 air campaign over Libya. Its global positioning system technology gives the UK the capability to conduct 24-hour precision attacks against a wide range of targets. Aircrew also have the ability to reprogramme the weapon during a mission, offering capability to attack a wider range of targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This highly sophisticated UK-developed and manufactured weapon is the backbone of the RAF’s precision bombing capability. This contract to boost the MOD’s weapon stocks will sustain hundreds of skilled jobs in the defence manufacturing sector in both Scotland and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By balancing the Defence Budget, we are able to commit with confidence to equipment programmes which help to safeguard our national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paveway munitions have long been a success story for the Royal Air Force in terms of their precision bombing capability. The ability to operate in any weather means that we are able to support operations 24/7. Paveway IV weapons are a real asset, not only to the Royal Air Force, but also to Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the MOD has this year awarded contracts worth more than £100m to Raytheon for orders of around 1,600 Paveway IV bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
