<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T12:25:01+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60241</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:25:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-258-million-sea-king-helicopter-support-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £258 million Sea King helicopter support contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MOD has agreed a £258 million contract to support Sea King helicopters, which will sustain 500 jobs across the UK.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; fleets of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-Mk5" title="Sea King Mk5"&gt;Sea Kings&lt;/a&gt; are best known for providing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/UK/Search-and-Rescue" title="Search and Rescue"&gt;Search and Rescue&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt;) services in the UK and Falkland Islands. They can also be used to carry troops and provide airborne surveillance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extension to the Sea King Integrated Operational Support (&lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt;) contract will ensure continued technical and maintenance support for the 90-strong helicopter fleet for the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD originally signed the &lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt; arrangement with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.agustawestland.com/" title="AgustaWestland"&gt;AgustaWestland&lt;/a&gt; in 2005 and this is the final phase of the deal which is expected to sustain around 500 jobs at AgustaWestland’s UK headquarters at Yeovil, in the industry supply chain and at several &lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt; bases across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5786/45153254g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter is pictured on an operation over Helmand Province, Afghanistan (stock image) [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This phase of the contract will provide support until Sea King is retired from service in 2016 and replaced by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin MK1"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Sea King helicopter fleet has been in service for over 40 years providing a vital capability in air/sea rescue and surveillance. This maintenance agreement, securing 500 jobs across the UK, demonstrates our commitment to keeping this aircraft in top condition until it is retired from service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy Captain Tony Gray, Defence Equipment and Support Sea King Team Leader, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing this contract ensures value for money for the taxpayer while maintaining the provision of search-and-rescue helicopters around the UK, 24-hours-a-day throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56977</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-to-auction-off-radio-spectrum"/>
    <title>MOD to auction off radio spectrum</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Ministry of Defence is planning to auction some of its radio spectrum in the first direct sale of its kind by a government department.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radio spectrum refers to the radio waves over which all wireless communication takes place, including radio, television, radar, satellite, mobile voice and data. Under plans announced today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to auction around 200 Megahertz (&lt;abbr title="Megahertz"&gt;MHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) of its spectrum usage rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes as market demand for extra spectrum is mounting, fuelled by the sharp rise in the use of spectrum-hungry devices such as smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale will give private operators the chance to buy more spectrum to support the introduction of fourth-generation mobile services to people in cities, towns and villages across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively the spectrum could be used by fixed-line operators to provide wireless access to broadband services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum being sold by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is all below 15 Gigahertz (&lt;abbr title="Gigahertz"&gt;GHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is regarded as the most useful and valuable part of the radio spectrum because of its wide range of applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of all spectrum below 15GHz is held by the public sector and is used for a broad range of services including defence, emergency services, transport and science. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; holds around three-quarters of all publicly-held spectrum and one-third of all spectrum below 15GHz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome this opportunity to free up much-needed spectrum. We hope that the sale will help drive the roll-out of new generation networks and universal access to broadband, both of which are vital to the UK’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale follows the announcement made in the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/spend_index.htm" title="Spending Review"&gt;2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; that at least 500MHz of public spectrum below 5GHz will be released by 2020 for new mobile communications uses. The spectrum to be sold off is being cleared of military users to contribute towards this target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are expected to start at the end of 2013, with the auction completed by the summer of 2014. Ahead of this, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to produce an Industry Brochure in early spring 2013 and to host an Industry Day in early summer 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55926</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65 million contract to refit HMS Ocean</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65 million upgrade, securing more than 600 UK jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The warship was moored on the Thames during the London 2012 Olympic Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at Devonport Royal Dockyard in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project, securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to the ship’s radar, gun, command system and living quarters. In addition, around 1,200 metres of new pipework will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter Number 10 Dock at Devonport Royal Dockyard to begin her refit [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympics duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28542</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T17:03:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-46-million-submarine-command-system-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £46 million submarine command system contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A £46 million contract to support and maintain a new combat system across the Royal Navy's submarine fleet has been awarded to BAE Systems.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Design Services Arrangement contract will ensure that the system, which is used to navigate vessels as well as gather intelligence and defend against attacks, is maintained and developed over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy operates three classes of submarine, totalling 10 vessels, which are used to safeguard the UK’s interests around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, different combat systems are used across the fleet. This new contract will help drive adoption of a common combat system across all current and future Royal Navy submarines, with considerable benefits to training, maintenance and updating costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="John Hudson, Philip Dunne and Rear Admiral Simon Lister" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1364/20121206subs01_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;John Hudson, Managing Director of BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines, Philip Dunne, and Director Submarines Rear Admiral Simon Lister (library image) [Picture: Mike Vallance, BAE Systems]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s submarine fleet is second-to-none and plays a key role in protecting our waters and interests both at home and abroad. This latest commitment to maintain and develop this vital technology throughout the fleet will ensure that we can continue delivering first class capability for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Command Systems on board our submarines contain many vital technologies and it is very important that our submarines retain their technological edge, both now and in the future. This contract will help secure that position for the MOD and UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/our-company-rzz/our-businesses/maritime---submarines" title="BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines"&gt;BAE Systems Maritime - Submarines&lt;/a&gt; and will safeguard around a total of 30 jobs at the company’s sites in Ash Vale in Surrey and Weymouth in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17638</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T15:39:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-helps-small-firms-showcase-defence-innovation"/>
    <title>MOD helps small firms showcase defence innovation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>MOD held its first 'Marketplace' event today allowing small UK businesses to pitch ideas to some of the world's biggest defence companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organised by the Ministry of Defence’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.science.mod.uk/engagement/enterprise.aspx" title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;Centre for Defence Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;, the event gives small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a unique opportunity to engage with big business and offer up ideas and technology that could be used by the Armed Forces in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs were joined at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre in London by academics and researchers from two of the country’s leading universities - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/" title="University of Bristol"&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/" title="Lancaster University"&gt;Lancaster University&lt;/a&gt; - who also had products to pitch to industry representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies on show at the event were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbsr.co.uk/" title="Blue Bear Systems Research"&gt;Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s ‘Morphing Wing’ - based on the dynamics of a bird’s wing, this is designed to enable the next generation of unmanned aerial vehicles to be faster, more agile and have greater stability and duration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dreampact.com/" title="Dreampact Ltd"&gt;Dreampact Ltd&lt;/a&gt;’s compact heat-sensing video camera - a handheld camera that can also be mounted on a rifle to allow more effective surveillance operations in pitch darkness, bad fog or dust.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1288/DSC_0837.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne speaks at the inaugural Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s ‘Marketplace’ provides a shop window for small and medium-sized enterprises in the most practical sense, helping those which have received research and development funding from the MOD to access their full potential for commercial applications in the UK defence sector and the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation is vital to our national security and the country’s economic growth. We remain committed to providing our Armed Forces with the very best equipment available, which is why we will continue to invest over £400m a year in Science and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jono Byrne, Head of the Centre for Defence Enterprise, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we have broken fresh ground in developing the Department’s engagement with small and medium-sized enterprises and academia. Over half of our contracts go to small and medium-sized enterprises and academia and it is vital that we are able to bring these Centre for Defence Enterprise-funded innovators, their ideas and capabilities, into the defence supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne chats with delegates" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1289/DSC_0941.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne chats with delegates at the Centre for Defence Enterprise 'Marketplace' event [Picture: Neil Houghton, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted with the response and support we have had from prime contractors as they too understand the benefits such a concept can bring. This is only the start for the ‘Marketplace’ and, like all good innovation, I look forward to further improvement; for example, making use of online tools and involving investment companies as well as defence companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Kurth, Managing Director of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.boeing.co.uk/Products-Services/Boeing-Defence-UK" title="Boeing Defence UK"&gt;Boeing Defence UK&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to attend the inaugural ‘Marketplace’ event and look forward to seeing the areas of technology the Centre for Defence Enterprise has identified in support of our Armed Forces. We see the ‘Marketplace’ as a fantastic opportunity to engage with small and medium-sized enterprises that have relevant innovation and technology for potential work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise (CDE) is committed to finding new revolutionary ideas and working to make them a reality in the future. Since 2008 the CDE has received more than 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at over £35m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17595</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T15:05:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-contracts-safeguard-hundreds-of-uk-shipyard-jobs"/>
    <title>MOD contracts safeguard hundreds of UK shipyard jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Around 800 jobs in the UK maritime sector have been safeguarded after the MOD extended five maintenance contracts worth a total of £349m.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contracts cover the long-term maintenance of the Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) Flotilla of naval support ships. They have been awarded to five British companies and will secure a further five years of maintenance support for the 13-strong RFA Flotilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of fuel tankers, stores ships, a medical facility and landing ships, the RFA provides essential support such as food, fuel, munitions and other vital supplies to the Royal Navy at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cammell-laird.com/" title="Cammell Laird website"&gt;Cammell Laird Shiprepairers &amp;amp; Shipbuilders Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Birkenhead&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ap-group.co.uk/" title="A&amp;amp;P Group website"&gt;A&amp;amp;P Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt; (ship repair facility), based in Falmouth&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lr.org/default.aspx" title="Lloyd's Register website"&gt;Lloyd’s Register&lt;/a&gt;, based in Bristol&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.trimline.co.uk/" title="Trimline Ltd website"&gt;Trimline Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Southampton&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hempel.com/" title="Hempel UK Ltd website"&gt;Hempel UK Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, based in Cwmbran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="United States warship alongside RFA Cardigan Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1283/FJ120053055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;United States warship USS Devastator (left) alongside the Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Cardigan Bay (library image) [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Simpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships are crucial to the work of the Royal Navy and without them it simply could not operate. These substantial contracts will not only safeguard hundreds of UK jobs but will ensure that these ships can continue in their roles for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of Commercially Supported Shipping for Defence, Equipment and Support, Commodore (RFA) David Preston, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These contracts represent the best value for money for Defence and each of the companies has a proven track record in supporting the Royal Fleet Auxiliary on a worldwide basis. This ability to support the Royal Navy wherever they are deployed is critical to UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA personnel are uniformed civil servants employed under the UK Merchant Shipping Act. They are structurally aligned with the Royal Navy and have a high level of specialist military training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17580</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T14:58:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/25m-mod-weapons-contract-sustains-450-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£25m MOD weapons contract sustains 450 UK jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Manufacturing jobs in the British defence industry have been secured by a £25m contract for Paveway IV precision weapons for the RAF.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has agreed to purchase additional &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/paveway4.cfm" title="Paveway IV"&gt;Paveway IV&lt;/a&gt; bombs from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raytheon.co.uk/" title="Raytheon UK"&gt;Raytheon UK&lt;/a&gt;. These weapons are to be carried by our Tornados in Afghanistan and will also provide a key capability to be carried by the Typhoon and Lightning II aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract announced today will sustain around 450 jobs at Raytheon UK’s plants. It will secure 300 highly skilled defence sector jobs in Glenrothes, Scotland, and 150 in Harlow, Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also sustain a number of jobs at Raytheon’s subcontractors - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.portav.com/" title="Portsmouth Aviation"&gt;Portsmouth Aviation Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, Exelis in Brighton, Chemring in Ardeer and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thalesgroup.com/" title="Thales Group"&gt;Thales&lt;/a&gt; in Basingstoke, Hampshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paveway IV proved highly effective during the 2011 air campaign over Libya. Its global positioning system technology gives the UK the capability to conduct 24-hour precision attacks against a wide range of targets. Aircrew also have the ability to reprogramme the weapon during a mission, offering capability to attack a wider range of targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This highly sophisticated UK-developed and manufactured weapon is the backbone of the RAF’s precision bombing capability. This contract to boost the MOD’s weapon stocks will sustain hundreds of skilled jobs in the defence manufacturing sector in both Scotland and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By balancing the Defence Budget, we are able to commit with confidence to equipment programmes which help to safeguard our national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paveway munitions have long been a success story for the Royal Air Force in terms of their precision bombing capability. The ability to operate in any weather means that we are able to support operations 24/7. Paveway IV weapons are a real asset, not only to the Royal Air Force, but also to Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the MOD has this year awarded contracts worth more than £100m to Raytheon for orders of around 1,600 Paveway IV bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17808</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:51:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-12-03-centre-for-defence-enterprise-marketplace"/>
    <title>2012/12/03 - Centre for Defence Enterprise Marketplace</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, MOD on Monday 3 December 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning to everyone, and thank you Richard [Brooks] for that kind introduction. I am very pleased that so many people have been able to make it here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an exciting moment for the Centre for Defence Enterprise (&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched by the previous Government in 2008 as a delivery mechanism for allowing better access for technology &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; (Small and Medium Enterprises) to defence research and ultimately the wider Defence Market, I see the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now as helping the Ministry of Defence achieve two principle goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;firstly to act as the entry point for new science and technology innovation bringing new thinking and ideas to Defence &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and secondly to act as a key bridge linking &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to the main defence suppliers, as well as investors and wider Government, as part of the MOD’s priority to raise participation by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in defence procurement &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; calls for, receives and assesses research proposals. It then funds, supports and promotes projects that it regards as plausible with potential to meet defence needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It encourages innovative companies to address Defence issues through face to face surgeries, unclassified and open conferences, and through its innovative electronic contracting portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this activity is run from a small base in a commercial office block at the Harwell Science and Innovation Campus in Oxfordshire. One of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strengths is its fleetness of foot, born of a lean and efficient structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To provide visibility of the MOD’s requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To inform and support new supply networks that widen the MOD’s supplier base &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And above all to get the best and most innovative ideas into MOD’s Science and Technology Programme &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks another important milestone of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. A new turn in &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s evolving journey to discover innovation, and then help in the realisation of those ideas into defence and security capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what innovation has been discovered. In the last four years the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has received nearly 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in some 600 contracts, worth around £35 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few projects have made it directly into the hands of users, but that is an exception for most research work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to see those &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities who have successfully demonstrated innovative technology, to have the chance to present their capabilities to our prime contractors - boosting their prospects of being taken into the supply chain. And that’s what today’s marketplace is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some amazing ideas and technologies which have been developed by the innovators we have funded. I hope you will be able to stay and hear the details today, some of which are also on view in the exhibition downstairs on the second floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="exhibition-examples"&gt;Exhibition Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward shortly to going round this exhibition, and to meeting the people who are working to deliver innovative battle winning capabilities which support the front line. And I encourage you all to look around if you have the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example, on display downstairs is Blue Bear Systems Research and their morphing wing for small Unmanned Air Vehicles based on the dynamics of a bird wing. This project exploits the design work already done by Mother Nature, to help ensure our next generation of UAVs can be both faster and more agile, as well as having greater endurance when required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the compact, high performance heat sensing video camera developed by Dreampact, which can be handheld or rifle mounted for surveillance or gunsight use in conditions of total darkness, fog, smoke or dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our universities are also represented today with ingenious electronics and autonomously learning logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the projects featured demonstrate the ingenuity and practical focus of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities that we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation to flourish is vital to our national security and our prosperity, contributing to export led recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wider-st-policy"&gt;Wider S&amp;amp;T Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my new role I have responsibility also for Defence exports as well as procurement, so encouraging responsible Defence exports is a particular priority for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is partly to stimulate this growth which is why the MOD has protected its annual investment in Science and Technology at 1.2% of the Defence Budget - over £400 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is protecting this budget so important? Well, in a future that is so unpredictable, defence science and technology provides insurance against the future threats and conflicts we may face; and supports the MOD’S ability to be an intelligent customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our defence transformation programme transfers responsibility for primary equipment procurement to the Commands, each will need to build capability to look forward to its future needs. This will better align our science and technology spend to the research and development priorities of our front line commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence is about developing Armed Forces and Defence capability that can deal with a broad range of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blueprint for agile, adaptable Armed Forces is Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be effective Future Force 2020 must have the best equipment available: class leading platforms, complex weapon systems and supporting ISTAR assets. Our personnel need the best training and personal equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector and our world class academic institutions will be central to deliver this Future Force. The complexity of much of these platforms needs, by necessity, substantial industrial capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cyber, to space, to nano technology, Britain has world leading companies underpinned by world leading scientific research, some of which I have already seen helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profitable and high tech British Defence and Security sector is essential to achieving all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although many of the platform projects will be managed through large system level contracts by our Prime contractors, there will be numerous participants in the supply chain, from large companies, to academia, to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="smes"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; make an enormous contribution to the economy and in particular to innovation. And I want to take a moment to emphasise their role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; are not the only source of original thinking in our sector, but they often provide the niche expertise which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know that The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in supporting &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in this area, helping them to commercialise their high tech ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank my predecessor, Peter Luff, who I am delighted to see is with us today. Peter did much to champion Science and Technology, the crucial role of Small and medium sized enterprises to delivering innovation, and to starting the conversation that led to this event today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, like him, am a champion of the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; doing innovative work in the Defence and Security sector. They are the lifeblood of any sector. In defence they deliver innovation, flexibility, efficiency and agility, when responding to our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential that &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; - whose issues are often very different from those of Primes - have their own platform within the defence industry to engage with the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why I chair a dedicated &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Forum which addresses the concerns of smaller companies, and why the MOD is taking a significant number of steps, alongside wider Government to work to ensure &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; can reach their potential when responding to defence requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has a detailed action plan, led by our &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; Champion, Les Mosco, who will be talking to you later today, to drive forward &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; involvement in defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have addressed some really important issues such as the treatment of IPR for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify issues that MoD needs to address and which the &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; themselves need to think about too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are encouraging our prime contractors to inform us of the part &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; play in their own supply chain and I have personally invited the Chief Executives of our top twenty suppliers to attend today’s event - and I am particularly pleased to see some of them here today and I am grateful for the leadership they are showing at the senior level in support of &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, even to a business as small as a one-man band, is to support, not stifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cde"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final word about &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;. Since its launch the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has established a reputation for reaching out across a very wide spectrum of the engineering and scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; has worked closely with the Technology Strategy Board and benefited through working with its Knowledge Transfer Networks and Small Business Research Initiative and I am glad to see that Mark Glover from TSB is here today to see the blossoming fruits of this collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But above all else, it is you, the defence and security community, that shaped the advances that we see within in the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; today. Thank you for your strong support of the &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; started off as pilot scheme. And four years on it has become a going concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But innovation never stops, there is always something new to try, something that can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now an exciting new phase has begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our White Paper ‘National Security through Technology’ committed Government to broaden &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s remit to cover both the defence and security domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 3rd October, here in this building, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; held its first event for GCHQ and MI5. This attracted over 300 &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and resulted in over 170 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘National Security through Technology’ also committed &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; to provide more support to &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in understanding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how MOD and National Security operates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development of routes to market for potential defence and security products; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to enhance exploitation mechanisms between &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt;, the wider MOD and our suppliers &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognising fears expressed by &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in the consultation, we committed to keep &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; small and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am most grateful that Richard Brooks, the Programme Director for MOD’s Science and Technology Programme who is here organising this day, is ensuring that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; is not distracted or inhibited by bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst staff numbers have grown, &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; remains small and agile with only 12 staff, yet now able to run more research calls, more seminars and more workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; can hold more regular surgeries - ‘one to ones’ - where individuals and companies can get personalised guidance on what the MoD is looking for, and practical help on how to pitch an idea to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; was set a target of 150 one-to-one appointments for this financial year. This figure will be passed before the end of this month and &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; now expects to hold more than 200 such appointments by the end of the financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="marketplace"&gt;Marketplace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through our science and technology budget, we fund &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to work on specific projects for us. They keep the intellectual property rights for their work, and can develop them however they want, once they have completed their project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the effort so far has been focussed on the engagement of &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities and supporting the best ideas with proof of concept funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to help more - which brings us, finally, to today’s Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all this event is a start, and I look forward to seeing this idea develop and innovate rapidly like all the best &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for those of you, &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, universities and Prime Contractors, who have contributed already to the thinking of how today’s Marketplace will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim is an MOD-facilitated initiative whereby &lt;abbr title="Centre for Defence Enterprise"&gt;CDE&lt;/abbr&gt; gives &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and universities, who have successfully demonstrated their credibility and capability, the opportunity to present their innovations and capabilities to the UK’s key defence suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By providing this opportunity, the MOD is seeking to ensure that these &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; will have an increased probability of development funding and mentoring, so that they can fully develop their ideas into products suitable for the defence, security or other civilian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that the MOD does have an important role to play in helping to maintain a dynamic pool of innovation which can drive defence applications forward and lead to economic benefits for the whole nation, beyond the immediate Defence objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will only get this by leaving companies free to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And free to work together. So today is all about bringing people together. Then it is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to take a couple of questions before we move downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34810</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/150-2012-mod-announces-new-46m-contract-for-foxhound-vehicles"/>
    <title>150/2012 -  MOD Announces new £46m contract for Foxhound vehicles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MoD is investing £46 million in acquiring fifty-one new Foxhound patrol vehicles for soldiers serving on the frontline in Afghanistan.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Minister Philip Dunne MP made the announcement during a visit to General Dynamics: Force Protection’s spares facility in Telford which provides spares for the Foxhound vehicle. The contract announced today is part of an overall investment of £340 million that the MoD has made in Foxhound since 2010. This is helping to sustain jobs at the Telford facility, the General Dynamics: Force Protection (GDLS:FPE) HQ in Leamington Spa and across the UK in the Foxhound supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed and built by GDL:FPE in Britain, Foxhound is one of the Army’s most agile protected vehicle. It uses leading-edge Formula 1 technology to provide unparalleled protection for its weight and class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Foxhounds were deployed to Afghanistan in June 2012 and are now being used by soldiers operating in mentoring and partnering roles with the Afghan National Security Forces. During the visit to the spares facility, Mr Dunne and Major Chris Thoms, the requirements manager for Protected Mobility at the MoD, met with staff who are also providing vital logistical support to the Army in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet with employees at General Dynamics: Force Protection who have helped make Foxhound a real procurement success story, taking only 40 months to develop it from the initial design to deployment in Afghanistan. The work being done by staff here in Telford is ensuring the vehicles can stay on the road and helping our soldiers do the vital job of engaging with Afghan forces and protecting the local population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Balancing the MoD’s budget means we can now confidently invest in equipment like Foxhound, which has the flexibility and adaptability to operate in a wide variety of environments, providing capability for the Army well into the future. This investment shows the MoD playing its part in delivering growth and sustaining jobs in the West Midlands industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in September when Foxhound was first operational in Afghanistan, Chief of Staff for the Bastion Force Protection Wing, Squadron Leader Jim Stewart, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Foxhound is an enormous leap forward in capability; the off-road mobility, enhanced protection and night-vision systems that it offers to the troops on the ground are unmatched in a vehicle of this size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 51 extra Foxhounds announced today are the latest to be ordered from GDLS:FPE as part of the £340 million investment that will provide the Army with a total fleet of 376 vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about Foxhound, contact Beth Cowley at the MoD Press Office on 0207 218 7714. Questions relating to General Dynamics: Force Protection should be directed to Julian Forsyth on 07850 915 164.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
