<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--25</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--25.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Women and Equalities</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2011-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/46972</id>
    <published>2011-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-marks-the-united-nations-international-day-for-elimination-of-violence-against-women"/>
    <title>Minister marks the United Nations International Day for Elimination of Violence Against Women</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to mark the day, she said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Violence against women and girls is a global problem that affects every country. Around the world one in three women and girls has been beaten or sexually abused in her lifetime, a truly shocking statistic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tackling such violence needs to be high on the international agenda and a priority for individual countries. That’s why the UK government has taken a range of action aimed at preventing violence and providing more support for victims as part of a comprehensive strategy ‘A Call to End Violence Against Women and Girls’.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have strengthened the law to protect victims of domestic violence and are consulting on further changes. We are working to increase convictions for rape by ensuring every report of rape is treated seriously, every victim is treated with dignity and every investigation and prosecution conducted thoroughly and professionally. We are protecting and supporting those facing forced marriage and will be consulting on whether to make forced marriage a criminal offence. And we are tackling negative attitudes to girls and women to prevent violence from occurring in the first place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will continue to use my role as the UK’s international ministerial champion to raise the voices of women and girls, at home and abroad.  We all need to speak out against violence against women, not just today but every day of the year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
