<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--31</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--31.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60873</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-this-new-years-eve-try-a-mocktail"/>
    <title>Driving this New Year's Eve? Try a mocktail</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Department for Transport has produced a number of non-alcoholic cocktail recipes to help designated drivers celebrate in style.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is encouraging drivers to opt for non alcoholic ‘mocktails’ in a bid to cut down on drink driving this New Year’s Eve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has produced a number of recipes – from a Berry Breezer to a Piña Banana – to appeal to those who are designated drivers on nights out.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is also warning party-goers to plan their way home in advance so they can celebrate the New Year in style, not in the cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting television advert highlighting the consequences of drink driving has been shown throughout December as part of the Department for Transport’s THINK! drink drive campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our message is clear: have a great New Year’s Eve, don’t risk the consequences of drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you get behind the wheel after drinking you risk losing your licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2011, 280 people were killed in accidents where the driver was over the limit. Do not let 1 selfish and foolish decision ruin your or another family’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, drivers aged between 20 and 24 failed more breath tests than any other age group. This year’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign is aimed at young people who are shown to be consistently over-represented in drink drive casualty figures. THINK! advises planning your journey home well in advance and treating your designated driver to a non-alcoholic Christmas cocktail. The recipes are easy to make at home and provide a festive alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is currently consulting on a package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers. This includes removing drink drivers’ rights to demand a blood or urine test. This is because evidence shows it is used as a delaying tactic by drivers caught over the limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also supported Coke’s designated driver scheme, which offered buy 1 get 1 free soft drinks in pubs around the country throughout December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACPO lead for roads policing, Deputy Chief Constable Suzette Davenport, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millions of people will be heading out for New Year’s Eve celebrations and we would ask the public to play their part in remaining safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen hundreds of people die from drink driving this year and it has to stop. Innocent people are needlessly dying on our roads and people who make the decision to drive after taking alcohol or drugs are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are someone who drinks and drives, by making a decision to stop in 2013 could save someone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is provisionally estimated that 2011 saw 280 deaths, 1,290 serious injuries and 9,990 total casualties directly related to drink driving incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign budget totals £783,925&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for a high-resolution copy of the advert the THINK! ‘moment of doubt’ TV advert, contact the Department for Transport’s press office on 020 7944 6898&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK! campaign posters can be downloaded directly from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/drink-driving.html"&gt;campaign site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for more information about the Department for Transport’s consultation into the removal of a driver’s right to a blood test, visit &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"&gt;the GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;read table RAS51004 to see drink drivers by age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="non-alcoholic-christmas-cocktail-recipes"&gt;Non-alcoholic Christmas Cocktail Recipes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="berry-breezer"&gt;Berry Breezer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half a fresh lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the lime and sugar together, add the juices, shake and strain over ice. Top with tonic and garnish with a lime wedge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="elderflower-spritzer"&gt;Elderflower Spritzer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of elderflower cordial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 lemon wedges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;half a teaspoon of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soda water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mint to garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the sugar and lemon wedges together, add the elderflower cordial, shake, top with soda, stir and add more ice as required. Garnish with a lemon wedge and a sprig of mint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="winter-warmer"&gt;Winter Warmer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of apple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lemon and cloves for garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heat the apple and cranberry juice together for 1 minute in the microwave, stir in the honey and serve immediately in a heated mug or handled glass. Garnish with a clove-studded lemon wheel. For an extra twist replace the honey with spiced sugar syrup. To make this, mix some sugar gomme, vanilla pods, a cinnamon stick, a handful of cloves and some cardamom and allow to infuse for 3 days. Sieve
the sugar and mix with the heated apple and cranberry juices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="citrus-mock-tini"&gt;Citrus Mock-tini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 fresh kumquats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons of lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marmalade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 millilitres of clementine juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the kumquats with the marmalade, add the clementine juice, shake, pour over ice and top with tonic. Garnish with spent kumquat shells. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pia-banana"&gt;Piña Banana&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 banana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon of almond syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres single cream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dash of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blend all the ingredients together with some ice until frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60311</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/clear-up-initiative-saving-economy-millions-by-reopening-roads-quicker"/>
    <title>Clear-up initiative saving economy millions by reopening roads quicker</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An initiative to improve incident clear-up times is saving the economy tens of millions of pounds annually.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and the economy are seeing huge benefits from a government-led initiative to reopen motorways and roads quickly following major incidents, Roads Minister Stephen Hammond announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;’ (collision, lead, evaluate, act and reopen) initiative - launched by the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) last year to improve incident clear-up times – is helping to save the economy tens of millions of pounds annually, with even more savings to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key achievement has been the success of 38 &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;/police-funded 3D laser scanners which allow police forces to capture evidence quickly following collisions - helping to reopen major roads and motorways more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show an average time saving of 44 minutes per investigation – a 5 minute improvement on test estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other initiatives include the launch of a new hands-free smart phone app that notifies users of incidents and congestion, as well as the planned roll out of incident screens to shield collisions and prevent rubber necking. Time savings associated with screens alone can be up to several hundred thousand pounds per incident.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is confident these measures will help reduce the estimated £750 million cost to the economy that incidents cause on the strategic road network in England annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more frustrating than being stuck in a traffic jam for hours on end.  There is also the shocking cost of those lost hours for our economy. That is why we are improving the clear-up of incidents so we can get our motorways and major roads re-opened as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now witnessing even greater than expected time savings as a result of the roll out of laser scanning programme. This and other elements of the initiative, such as the use of incident screens, will help to keep traffic moving and save the economy tens of millions of pounds a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very encouraged by the cooperation shown by the Highways Agency, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Police and other emergency services, and fully expect these initiatives to result in further time and cost savings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief Constable Sean White, lead on collision investigations for the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This equipment allows police to manage critical events in a more efficient way and present the most accurate and detailed evidence to criminal, civil and coroners’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The time saved by using this technology is more economically friendly and reduces disruption on the roads, while allowing for thorough investigations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the success of this equipment, which has reduced delays for road users and proved extremely important in police investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Highways Agency signing a memorandum of understanding to facilitate data sharing about heavy goods vehicles. Studies have shown this type of vehicle is involved in a high proportion of the longest incidents. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working closely with operators to make sure problems are addressed   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the roll out by the Highways Agency of new towing equipment (load cells) to remove heavier vehicles obstructing live lanes and spill kits to clear spillages from motorway lanes. Time savings associated with the use of load cells have been estimated at several million pounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the production and distribution of a &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet to emergency responders outlining the roles and responsibilities of key organisations involved in managing incidents on the strategic road network. The Highways Agency has also produced a film reinforcing the booklet’s messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of emergency response guidance, training and learning to take on board &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of the 2007 Road Death Investigation Manual (RDIM) – the guiding doctrine of &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the 43 police forces of England and Wales to investigate and report on collisions that have resulted in a death. This is expected to be published in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report which sets out the next steps of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; is currently being finalised for publication next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laser-scanners"&gt;Laser scanners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laser Scanning Technology (LST) saves time by quickly making a 3D image of the whole incident scene, rather than investigators painstakingly surveying multiple sections of a scene. This digital image of the site can then be viewed on a computer screen remotely allowing investigators to take measurements of where vehicles are in relation to each other and examine other important evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009, the Highways Agency carried out an independent trial of 3D laser scanning technology using results from separate trials conducted by the Metropolitan Police Service and Humberside Police. The trials found that on average using laser scanners saved a total of 39 minutes on investigation time per incident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;38 laser scanners were funded by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Police for use by 27 police authorities at a cost of £4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest figures relate to information compiled from incidents over 4 months from forces using them on the strategic road network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clear"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2010 the Police, Highways Agency, Ambulance and Fire Services, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and related sponsoring departments came together to review evidence and knowledge about the handling of motorway incidents, and to make recommendations for improvement  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/review-of-investigation-and-closure-procedures-for-motorway-incidents-preliminary-report/review-of-investigation-closure-procedures-motorway-incidents.pdf"&gt;resultant report, published in May 2011 as the ‘Review of investigation and closure procedures for motorways incidents’ (PDF, 345KB)&lt;/a&gt;, made 10 recommendations and came together as the &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; initiative. The recommendations included further analytical work and some more immediate actions around, for example, supporting the wider roll out of laser scanning technology for the police to assist in speeding up incident investigation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congestion on the strategic road network is estimated to cost the economy £3 billion each year, 25% of which is caused by incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single incident that closes a 3 lane motorway for 4 hours can cost several million pounds in lost time, and there are some 80,000 incidents that impact at least one motorway lane each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; makes just 5% difference to the cost of congestion on the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Road Network"&gt;SRN&lt;/abbr&gt; it could save over £30 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="incident-screens"&gt;Incident screens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 105 sets of incident screens which will be made available for use by the Highways Agency next year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each set has 30 screens which are loaded onto purpose-built trailers and can screen up to 75 metres if used end-to-end (the individual screens are approximately 2.1 by two metres high)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They cost £2.3 million with each set costing £22,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="smart-phone-app"&gt;Smart phone app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	The Highways Agency app received 5,000 hits within the first 2 months of its launch. Further &lt;a rel="external" href="http://press.highways.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Hands-free-traffic-app-makes-Highways-Agency-data-available-to-road-users-ready-for-summer-67e24.aspx"&gt;information is available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spill-kits"&gt;Spill kits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Highways Agency"&gt;HA&lt;/abbr&gt; traffic officers will be equipped with spill kits to clear up small spillages such as fuel or other fluids which leak onto the carriageways from vehicles. The spill kits will absorb small spills and will allow the road to be safely re-opened while reducing damage to the carriageway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="load-cells"&gt;Load Cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load cells will be fitted to the tow straps used by traffic officers and will allow them to clear live lanes - moving heavier or damaged vehicles to the nearest place of safety.  The load cell acts as a strain gauge and will ensure that the safe towing load is not exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60127</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T10:14:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/government-car-and-despatch-agency"/>
    <title>Government Car and Despatch Agency</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Announcing details of charges incurred by departments for the use of official government cars from 1 April 2011 to 31 March 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am publishing today details of the charges incurred by departments for the use of official government cars provided to ministers by the Government Car and Despatch Agency (&lt;abbr title="Government Car and Despatch Agency"&gt;GCDA&lt;/abbr&gt;) during the year 1 April 2011 to 31 March 2012. This is in line with previous annual statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charges recorded in the statement show a continuing reduction in the amount spent on official cars for ministers. Costs to departments have seen a 49% reduction in the latest figures when compared to those of the previous year and a 72% reduction when compared to the figures for April 2009 to March 2010:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2009 to 2010&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;April 2010&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;May 2010 to March 2011&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;2011 to 2012&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;£6.7 million&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.8 million&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2.9 million&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1.9 million&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Official cars are an essential service for ministers in order that they can carry out their work effectively but we are committed to continuing our focus on the cost of this service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charges recorded in the statement also reflect the progress made on restructuring the service to maximise value for money whilst improving standards of service delivery. This programme of reform includes the development of a new service model which will offer up further cost savings on the provision of the service. The new service model was announced in February 2012 and introduced in April 2012. The associated charges will be reflected in next years’ written ministerial statement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures for 2011 to 2012 are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Department&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Allocated cars (see footnote 1)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Allocated cost&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Ministerial car pool&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Total cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Attorney General’s Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£76,645.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£15,495.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£92,140.29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cabinet Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£58,097.77&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£24,456.90&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£82,554.67&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£71,075.32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,270.71&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£74,346.03&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Education&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£71,912.21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£91,270.73&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£163,182.94&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£83,689.50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£119,130.47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£202,819.97&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,740.81&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,740.81&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Energy and Climate Change&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£36,687.79&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£36,687.79&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£74,013.16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,691.82&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£79,704.98&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for International Development&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£31,649.41&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,434.94&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£80,084.35&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£84,818.65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£56,221.79&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£141,040.44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department for Work and Pensions&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£87,388.17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£57,117.69&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£144,505.86&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Department of Health&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,885.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£119,966.86&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£127,851.97&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£23,020.77&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£23,020.77&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HM Treasury&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£105,640.88&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£47,802.27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£153,443.15&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Home Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£75,922.71&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£60,919.17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£136,841.88&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ministry of Defence&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ministry of Justice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£91,509.03&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£103,405.45&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£194,914.48&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northern Ireland Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£34,289.71&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£34,289.71&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Scotland Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£60.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£60.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wales Office&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£78,067.12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,380.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£84,447.12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£998,314.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£855,362.88&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,853,677.21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where ministers were provided with a protected service because of their need for greater security, the costs related to this service are not included as this is not paid for directly by departments but centrally by the Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may use other means of transport or other secure providers of car services, so the official figures provided by &lt;abbr title="Government Car and Despatch Agency"&gt;GCDA&lt;/abbr&gt; for the statement may not reflect the total spend by departments on cars used for ministerial travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These figures do not cover the full costs of delivering the car service.  These are set out annually in the &lt;abbr title="Government Car and Despatch Agency"&gt;GCDA&lt;/abbr&gt; annual report and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;Number of Allocated cars as of the 31 of March 2012. One allocated car service terminated mid-year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new EU regulation is set to give passengers travelling by water improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57028</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:58:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-18-december-2012"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 18 December 2012</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Stephen Hammond gives details of the agenda at the Transport Council which will be taking place in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the last Transport Council of the Cypriot Presidency (the Presidency) taking place in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be asked to reach a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the Council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. I was very concerned when we first received the proposal from the Commission. The Commission’s impact assessment was inadequate and failed to make the required links between the costs and benefits of new requirements. It was also incomplete as it did not accurately assess costs in all member states. Our initial analysis was that it would cost over £1 billion pounds to implement while having an insignificant positive impact on road safety in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position we adopted during the negotiation of the draft periodic roadworthiness regulation at Council working group meetings has been to resist additional burdens where insignificant road safety benefit was identified. With the support of the UK and other member states in resisting excessive burdens, the Presidency has proposed moving from a regulation to a directive and has made substantial changes to the text that radically simplifies the implementation of the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has been positive and has resulted in a substantially improved and less expensive proposal and as such I hope the Presidency will be able to achieve a general approach on the dossier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency will provide a progress report on 2 other proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing the ‘connecting Europe’ facility. The UK abstained from the partial general approach agreed on this dossier at the June Transport Council. While we were broadly supportive of the text of the regulation we could not formally support agreement to the draft regulations in advance of an agreement on the overall Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;) negotiations as this could prejudge the overall &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The UK supports the thrust of the proposal in introducing a clearer, stable governance arrangement for the programme but has concerns that some of the European Parliament’s proposed amendments, such as the introduction of funding for applications to use the navigation systems, could have significant financial implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will adopt conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The UK welcomed this timely communication from the Commission and has been actively engaged in the drafting of Council conclusions. We support the broad aims of the communication – liberalisation of aviation and fair competition – and we are pushing to ensure that the Council’s conclusions reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will also adopt a proposal for a Council decision on the signature, on behalf of the EU, and provisional application of the Euro-Mediterranean aviation agreement between the EU and its member states, on the one part, and the State of Israel, on the other. The UK supports the signature and implementation of this agreement which forms a part of the EU’s external aviation policy to negotiate comprehensive air services agreements with neighbouring countries. This agreement will supersede the current bilateral agreements between individual member states and Israel. It aims at gradual market opening, promoting regulatory (e.g. safety) harmonisation and the promotion of open and fair competition between air carriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This agreement will integrate the Israeli aviation market into the European single market accompanied by convergence with EU aviation regulations. It will enhance opportunities for EU airlines and investors in Israel, provide consumer benefits as a result of increased competition and better access, and help to strengthen the economic links between the EU and Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the Commission will provide information on the cleaner power for transport package and aviation emissions trading scheme (&lt;abbr title="emissions trading scheme"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55904</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T10:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T10:01:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-accepts-proposals-to-improve-garage-standards"/>
    <title>Government accepts proposals to improve garage standards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Motorists encouraged to check their garage is industry-standard approved.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists are being encouraged to find out if their garage is approved by a set of industry-standard codes to make sure they are getting value for money.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call comes after the government accepted a number of proposals made by industry experts to help drive up standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Motorists’ Forum has set out a raft of recommendations aimed at making sure motorists have the best possible consumer experience when having their vehicles serviced or repaired in a report released today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will promote the wider adoption of self-regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;-&lt;abbr title="Trading Standards Institute"&gt;TSI&lt;/abbr&gt;) codes of practice by garages and encourage greater publication of information regarding services they offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an AA survey*, 78% of people always use the same garage meaning that only a minority of motorists shop around. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the work carried out by the Motorists’ Forum and believe the recommendations will help build on existing best practice in the industry without the burden of extra legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that consumers feel confident in the quality and the value for money of the services they are receiving from garages. The Forum’s report has offered some useful proposals for how this can be achieved more consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would urge motorists to find out if their local garage has been approved by the codes to ensure they are getting a fair service and value for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills will now use their strong relationships with the industry and stakeholders to promote the adopted recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK car service and repair sector is worth around £6.9 billion per year to the GB economy with 150,000 MOT tests taking place every working day.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="note-to-editors"&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Motorists’ Forum report on garage customer experience can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-report-of-the-motorists-forum-sub-group-on-improving-customer-service-experience-at-garages"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s response can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/government-response-to-motorists-forum-report-on-garage-customer-experience"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Motorists’ Forum is made up of a group of experts convened by the DfT. Organisations include the AA, RAC, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Centre for Automotive Management, &lt;abbr title="compulsory basic training"&gt;CBT&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Transport for London"&gt;TfL&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Association Of British Insurers"&gt;ABI&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Freight Transport Association"&gt;FTA&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Vehicle Rental and Leasing Association"&gt;BVRLA&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Parliamentary Advisory Council for Transport Safety"&gt;PACTS&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders"&gt;SMMT&lt;/abbr&gt; as well as representatives from the DfT and Highways Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Trading Standards Institute (&lt;abbr title="Trading Standards Institute"&gt;TSI&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be taking over responsibility for the consumer codes approval scheme from the Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;). The new scheme will maintain the rigour of the current scheme, but will streamline the approval process and make it self-funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Responsibility for vehicle roadworthiness and testing lies with DfT and &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; administers the MOT scheme. Responsibility for consumer protection legislation lies with the Department for Business Innovation and Skills (BIS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is already considerable consumer protection legislation in place to cover the practices of garages which choose to trade unfairly or who are not competent to trade; both from the perspective of individual consumer rights through sale of goods and services legislation, and through the application of criminal sanctions, principally via the Consumer Protection from unfair trading regulations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*AA Survey Outcome, Car Service/Repair, May 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56299</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:50:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/improving-motoring-services"/>
    <title>Improving motoring services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Consultation to suggest improvements about how motoring services are delivered.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Road users, businesses and other stakeholders were today invited to suggest improvements to the way motoring services such as driving tests and vehicle licensing are delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is putting customers firmly at the heart of the way motoring services are delivered so that they best serve the consumer while getting the best possible deal for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, the Department for Transport is outlining broad reform proposals for the 4 motoring services agencies: Driving Standards Agency (DSA); Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA); Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (VOSA) and the Vehicle Certification Agency (VCA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you drive, run a business or pay taxes you will be a customer of ours and I hope you will have your say about how we can improve the services we offer you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much progress has already been achieved and it is now much easier to use digital services to get driving licences, and sort out vehicle tax. We have also already announced that we are bringing the driving test closer to customers by exploring a range of different locations, such as colleges and retail premises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But there is more that can be done and this consultation is about the government listening to its customers before agreeing the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s 4 agencies are already engaged in programmes of reform to deliver long term financial stability and efficiency, and better services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation sets out a longer term view of the future of these reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Position the agencies at the forefront of digital services, ensuring that those who find access to digital services difficult are supported to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support economic growth and vehicle manufacturing by reforming the Vehicle Certification Agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring the driving test closer to the customer by exploring opportunities to improve convenience to customers. This includes assessing options for the delivery of the practical test. We are keen to explore all options that maintain the integrity of the test and high quality standards whoever is the provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transform &lt;abbr title="heaviy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt;, bus and coach testing by expanding joint ventures and collaboration with private sector providers, and reducing the number of government owned test stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliver better customer services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider rationalising the number of bodies and agencies involved in delivering services - delivering services as simply as possible, increasing flexibility and innovation, improving efficiency and reducing costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 7 March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation is the department’s response to the government’s broader vision for public services as set out in the civil service reform plan, the Open Public Services white paper and the government digital strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55825</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:50:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/consultation-on-motoring-services-strategy"/>
    <title>Consultation on Motoring Services Strategy</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Publication of the Motoring Services Strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of a &lt;a href="/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy"&gt;consultation document on the Department for Transport’s Motoring Services Strategy&lt;/a&gt;. In line with the government’s broader vision for public services as set out in the Civil Service Reform Plan, the Open Public Services White Paper and the Government Digital Strategy, the department is outlining broad reform proposals for its four motoring services executive agencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driving Standards Agency (DSA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (VOSA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vehicle Certification Agency (VCA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Strategy sets out three principles for the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;putting consumers and businesses at the heart of what we do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalising the number of bodies and agencies involved in the delivery of our services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working more closely and collaboratively with our partners to deliver services, and boost economic growth by creating opportunities for small and medium size businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To do this we will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maximise the digital delivery of services to motorists and improve the customer experience. We will also ensure that those who find access to digital services difficult are supported to do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reform the Vehicle Certification Agency(VCA) which provides high quality and trusted service to the automotive industry and is recognised for its quality and integrity.  We will look at ways to help VCA to grow and contribute more to the wider economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explore ways to improve the convenience to customers of the driving test by looking at the locations from which we deliver them &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transform &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt;, bus and coach testing by expanding joint ventures and collaboration with private sector providers, and reducing the number of government owned test stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalise the number of agencies and reconfigure our organisations to reduce cost and improve consistency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are inviting views and responses from as broad a range of organisations and users of our services as possible This will include road users, businesses, trade associations, road safety groups, transport associations and others. Improving the way we engage with and listen to them will help to design better services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 7 March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55854</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T10:14:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/garage-customer-experience--2"/>
    <title>Garage customer experience</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Government response to the Motorists’ Forum sub-group report recommendations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today publishing the &lt;a href="/government/publications/government-response-to-motorists-forum-report-on-garage-customer-experience"&gt;government’s response to the Motorists’ Forum sub-group report recommendations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Motorists’ Forum has set out a raft of recommendations aimed at making sure motorists have the best possible consumer experience when having their vehicles serviced or repaired in the report released today. The Department for Transport (DfT) and the Department for Business Innovation and Skills (BIS) have worked closely together to produce the government response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The car service and repair sector is worth around £6.9 billion per year to the GB economy with 150,000 MOT tests taking place every working day.  The garage industry is important both to transport policy (especially road safety) and as part of a wider landscape of consumer affairs.  It is important that consumers feel confident in the quality and the value for money of the services they are receiving from garages.  The Motorists’ Forum’s report has offered some useful proposals for how this can be achieved more consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome the work carried out by the Motorists’ Forum and believe the recommendations we plan to adopt will help build on existing best practice in the industry and encourage garages to improve customer services, without the burden of extra legislation.  The recommendations we will be adopting will promote the wider adoption of self-regulation (OFT-TSI) codes of practice by garages and encourage greater publication of information regarding the services they offer.  As of November this year we have already introduced the requirement to have vehicle mileages printed on MOT certificates to help combat ‘clocking’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DfT and BIS will now use their strong relationships with the garage industry and stakeholders to promote the adopted recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Motorists’ Forum sub-group report and the government’s response can be &lt;a href="/government/publications/government-response-to-motorists-forum-report-on-garage-customer-experience"&gt;found on the Gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/41713</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T10:36:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/road-safety"/>
    <title>Road safety</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Information on the current status of the Think! Road Safety campaign.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wanted to update the House on the launch of the government’s latest Think! Road Safety campaign, targeted at drink driving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action by successive governments over the last 30 years has meant that the number of people killed in drink drive accidents has been reduced by over three-quarters since 1979.  But drink driving remains a problem, 280 people lost their lives in 2011 in drink drive accidents on Britain’s roads. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in partnership with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acpo.police.uk/"&gt;Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, so that people see education and enforcement working together, the government has just relaunched its successful Think! campaign aimed at reminding drivers – particularly young drivers, who are over-represented in the casualty figures – of the risks of getting behind the wheel after consuming alcohol: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/"&gt;http://think.direct.gov.uk/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; enforcement anti-drink and drug driving enforcement campaign seeks particularly to focus on well-intentioned drivers who do not think they are breaking the law but may be over the legal limit by the time they get into their cars in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, at the end of last week I launched a further round of the very successful &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/campaign-to-reward-designated-drivers-launched-by-coca-cola-great-britain-and-think"&gt;designated driver campaign, in partnership with Coca-Cola&lt;/a&gt;. Now in its 5th year, the nationwide campaign offers designated drivers a ‘buy one get one free’ deal on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coca-Cola Zero at participating pubs.  The campaign began last Thursday and will run until the end of December. Further details are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/"&gt;http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
