<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--18</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--18.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60830</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-freedom-for-local-councils-to-prevent-unauthorised-traveller-sites--2"/>
    <title>Greater freedom for local councils to prevent unauthorised traveller sites</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposals to give councils more freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites have been published for consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be given greater freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites being set up and prevent long, drawn-out stalemates like Dale Farm, under proposals published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="temporary-stop-notices"&gt;Temporary Stop Notices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals would allow councils greater freedom to use temporary stop notices in relation to caravans that are in breach of planning control, and are used as a person’s main residence. This would be backed up with the potential for heavy fines of up to £20,000 on indictment or an unlimited fine on summary conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the current system councils are constrained as to when they can use these powers against caravans that are main residences, which can result in long delays and high costs to stop unauthorised development of this kind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long a small minority have abused the planning system, often at the expense of local communities who are forced to put up with unauthorised development in their area. This government believes in fair play, with everyone abiding by the same rules. These proposals will assist local councils in taking effective action against those who don’t.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-powers"&gt;Stronger powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporary Stop Notices enable councils to take action with immediate effect against unauthorised development without having to wait three days for a Stop Notice, or 28 days for an enforcement notice to come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to the outcome of the consultation, today’s proposals would remove restrictions on the use of temporary stop notices so councils can act quickly against new unauthorised sites, and save on the costs of enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60026</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:07:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-pension-scheme"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>This is a written ministerial statement about the abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions for councillors from April 2014.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 September 2001, the then Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions announced plans to give taxpayer-funded pensions to councillors, through access to the local government pension scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals came into force in 2003. The Councillors’ Commission report of the last administration noted that 912 councillors in England had joined that pension scheme by 2004. A Taxpayers’ Alliance survey in February 2009, across the whole United Kingdom, found that 3,527 councillors had pensions as of 2007 to 2008; a further survey in January 2012 found that figure had increased to 4,548 councillors by 2010 to 2011. The trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="abolition-of-taxpayer-funded-pensions"&gt;Abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in this government take a fundamentally different view to the last administration. We do not believe that taxpayer-funded pensions are justified. Councillors are volunteers undertaking public service; they are not and should not be employees of the council dependent on the municipal payroll. They are not professional, full-time politicians, nor should they be encouraged to become so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors do not receive a salary; rather, they receive allowances to compensate for their out-of-pocket expenses. Yet following changes made by the last administration, allowances have slowly become a form of salary, a situation worsened by the state-funded pensions. This is a corrosive influence on local democracy and independent thought, blurring the distinction between council staff and councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bit of the public sector needs to do its bit to help pay off the deficit inherited from the last administration. Local government grants are being reduced. Ministers have cut and then frozen their salaries. Public sector pensions, including parliamentary pensions, are being reformed to reduce the burden on taxpayers. It is only right that councillors do their bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that an occupational pension scheme intended for employees, and paid for by taxpayers, is an appropriate vehicle for councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="existing-pension-rights"&gt;Existing pension rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to consultation, we propose that there will be no access for councillors to the local government pension scheme in England from April 2014. In the interests of fairness, those councillors already in the scheme would have their accrued rights up to April 2014 fully protected, but would not be able to accrue any further benefits after that date in the existing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not prevent councillors contributing to a personal pension: if they put aside part of their (taxable) allowances into such a pension, then that is a matter for them; they will continue to receive income tax relief like any ordinary member of the population, subject to the prevailing tax rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although central records on councillors’ participation in the scheme are not held by my department, initial rough estimates suggest that this could save £7 million a year in taxpayers’ money. There is absolutely no case for increasing councillor allowances to compensate. Instead, councils may want to consider earlier, voluntary closure of the scheme to their councillors as a sensible saving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="civic-duty"&gt;Civic duty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility regulations for the local government pension scheme are overseen by my department. Although this is a centrally mandated change (as was its original introduction), we believe these reforms will assist localism and local democracy by encouraging a greater separation between councillors and officers. Robust local scrutiny of council spending requires councillors to be substantively independent of means and of thought from the body they are overseeing. Civic duty should not be bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe it will have any detrimental effect on people choosing to become councillors. The best thing we can do to encourage more people to take part in municipal public life is to decentralise power to local communities so being a councillor is a meaningful and rewarding role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="elected-mayors"&gt;Elected mayors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there is a greater expectation that an elected mayor is a full-time position. We therefore propose to consult on allowing elected mayors to remain in the scheme as a voluntary option (but not as an expectation), subject to local scrutiny, challenge and determination. The salaries of the mayor of London, members of the Greater London Assembly and police and crime commissioners will remain pensionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="timing"&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory consultation is required and will commence in due course, as part of the planned consultation on the wider reform of the local government pension scheme. We will consult with the Welsh Assembly government in respect of access to the local government pension scheme for councillors in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I would like to pay tribute to their often unsung and ongoing work in standing up for their local residents. We hope these reforms will further strengthen the integrity and independence of councillors and increase the respect within their communities for the voluntary work they undertake as champions of the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56532</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-fire-chief-to-lead-efficiency-review-of-fire-and-rescue"/>
    <title>Government fire chief to lead efficiency review of fire and rescue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An expert led review into the operational efficiency of the services delivered by fire and rescue authorities in England was announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the public sector deficit, the government has protected fire and rescue authority funding. Some reduction was unavoidable but it was back-loaded so sensible savings could be made without impacting the service the public gets. Overall, fire and rescue authority spending power reductions - which takes into account grants from central government and council tax, was limited to 2.2% in 2011-12 and 0.5% in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is to be conducted by former firefighter and out-going government Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, in the new year. The review will seek to identify ways fire and rescue authorities can pinpoint savings and improvements without reducing the quality life-saving services that the country’s fire firefighters are known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many authorities have begun making efficiencies, but there is more that can be done to be more transparent about spending or introduce joint working with other emergency services liked shared senior management structures, improved procurement practices and better use of estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths and incidents are at an all time low. Over the last decade attendance at incidences has fallen by 39% and attendance at fires by 48%. The review will help today’s fire service reflect that change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conducting the review, Sir Ken Knight will talk to key partners to help develop his findings including the Local Government Association, Fire Sector Federation, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association and the Fire Brigades Union, as well as individual authorities and other emergency services. The report is expected to be completed in the spring of 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We all recognise our firefighters perform an incredibly important public service. That is why spending for fire and rescue authorities, like other blue light services, has been protected. But we cannot escape the reality that every bit of the public sector has to help reduce the deficit we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Public safety is always our first concern and this review will make sure no stone has been left unturned in the quest for the most efficient and effective front-line fire service there can be. I know Sir Ken is passionate about the quality of fire and rescue services and he will bring an enormous amount of experience and knowledge to the task.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With over 40 years in the fire service, I know firefighters care deeply about public safety and want to provide the best possible service, but we need to make sure that service is as effective and efficient as possible. Many authorities have made great strides already, but there is much more that can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This review is a real opportunity to get to grips with what is happening on the ground, to highlight best practice and make sure that every option for efficient working is being explored. I will be talking to firefighters, fire authorities and union reps about how we can get there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review the ways in which fire and rescue authorities may deliver further efficiencies and operational improvements without reducing the quality of front-line services to the public. The review will examine options for savings both within and beyond the current Spending Review period, including through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefighter training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flexible staffing and crewing arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of retained firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaboration with emergency services and other organisations on service delivery and estates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing of senior staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;locally led mergers and operational collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new fire-fighting technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventative approaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with local businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conducting this review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir Ken Knight will talk to key organisations in the fire sector, including the Local Government Association, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association, the Fire Brigades Union, the Fire Sector Federation, individual fire and rescue authorities and others who Sir Ken deems relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Ken will undertake up to 10 visits to a representative range of fire and rescue authorities, including those covering urban and rural areas, and those constituted as metropolitan, county and combined authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department will provide Sir Ken with analytical support, in particular in looking at examples of efficiencies from outside of the fire sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will take into account the findings of previous reviews and reports and their recommendations, including the 2002 ‘Independent Review of the Fire Service’ (the Bain Report), the Audit Commission’s 2008 ‘Community Safety National Report’, ‘Rising to the Challenge’, the 2010 Fire Futures review, and the 2011/2012 ‘Independent Review of Police Officer’ and ‘Staff Remuneration and Conditions’ (the Winsor Reports).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="timeline"&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Announce review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December 2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct field work and analysis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January to March 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Write and present report to DCLG ministers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spring 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact-details-for-responses"&gt;Contact details for responses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sir-ken-knight-biography"&gt;Sir Ken Knight biography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight has been the UK Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser for England since October 2007, advising ministers and senior officials on policy matters including the structure, organisation and performance of fire and rescue services and crucially, providing advice during major and catastrophic emergencies. He is also responsible for the enforcement Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005 in Crown premises in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56197</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/preferred-bidder-for-the-fire-service-college-confirmed"/>
    <title>Preferred bidder for the Fire Service College confirmed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Fire minister Brandon Lewis has announced Capita as the preferred bidder for the purchase of the Fire Service College.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire minister said he was happy that the proposed sale of the college to Capita would achieve value for money for the public purse and secure the future of the college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that we are making real progress in securing the future of such an important facility. It is vital for the development of the Fire Service College that we put it on a sound footing, giving the private sector a chance to provide innovation and investment that will guarantee the future of a world-class asset.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure best value for money for taxpayers and enable the college to continue in its role, a number of conditions will be imposed on the proposed sale. These include commitments that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the college be preserved as a national training centre for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will continue to offer wider national resilience and emergency services training and exercises&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;government permission will be required if Capita wish to sell the incident ground&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councillor Kay Hammond, Chair of the Local Government Association’s fire services management committee, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is good news that government has listened to the views of the sector about the future of the Fire Service College and that it now looks set to get the outside investment it so badly needs. The Local Government Association and fire authorities will be keen to work with the future owners to help them transform the college into a first-class training facility fit for firefighters in the 21st century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association President, Vij Randeniya, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Chief Fire Officers’ Association welcomes the news that Capita has been selected. It has been a long and intensive process and we are glad that there is now clarity for the Fire Service College. We look forward to working closely with Capita to ensure that the very best provision is available for UK fire and rescue services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government now looks forward to holding constructive discussions with Capita to ensure that the transition from public to private sector is as smooth as possible and expects to complete the sale early in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Service College is a trading fund and executive agency of the department. Since becoming a trading fund in 1992, it has never been able to pay a dividend out of operating profits. The government’s response to Fire Futures on 12 April 2011 concluded that the college could achieve its full potential only if there was greater involvement from other sectors in its ownership, operation and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Options project considered 4 options for the future of the college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the status quo: the college remains as a trading fund of the department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a government owned contractor operated model: the assets remain under government ownership but management of the college is taken over by a private sector company under a long term contract, together with the staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disposal as a going concern: the college is sold to a private sector company who would continue to operate the college as a training centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closure: the college’s activities cease, staff are made redundant and the site is sold for an alternative use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the 4 options showed disposal as a going concern to be the best option, and the only one which both removes from government ongoing financial risks of ownership of the college and preserves a national training college for the fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers announced on 22 March 2012 that the Fire Service College would be sold as a going concern to a private sector company to continue operating as a training centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale process was launched on 10 April 2012 and the due diligence phase concluded in October with the receipt of final bids. Best and final offers were received in November. The aim is to complete the sale in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18642</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-announces-150-000-to-boost-great-british-pubs"/>
    <title>Minister announces £150,000 to boost Great British pubs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Community Pubs Minister Brandon Lewis has announced £150,000 funding for the Pub in The Hub community services project.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement followed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pubisthehub.org.uk/"&gt;Pub is The Hub&lt;/a&gt; ‘10 Years On’ event on 5 December 2012 where the minister was a keynote speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke about the key role pubs play in the social and economic life of many communities, often as community hubs, local service providers and a place where community relationships are formed and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to say that pubs contribute, on average, £100,000 per pub to the local economy as well as being strong sources of local employment for younger people to get involved in an entrepreneurial and innovative industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community pubs minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to announce we are giving Pub is The Hub £150,000 for their project. The government is taking decisive action to support community pubs including doubling business rate relief, which gives up to 100% discounts for small firms including pubs and postponing revaluation will also avoid local pubs facing an 11% rise in their business rates bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is on top of abolishing the last government’s cider tax, cutting red tape on live music in pubs and stopping unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price by supermarkets. We have given councils powers to offer local business rate discounts and the Community Right to Bid lets communities protect their pubs and guard against their unnecessary loss.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to see community pubs thriving everywhere and has introduced a series of measures to support them including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to introduce local business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, the department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:55:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis on early intervention pilots and neighbourhood community budgets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16664</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:24:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-rewards-for-local-growth-under-new-scheme"/>
    <title>Greater rewards for local growth under new scheme</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis has set out how local retention of business rates will reward councils for local economic growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; creates a new model for funding local authorities from April 2013, linking their financial revenue to the decisions they take to support local firms and local jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government will retain a 50% local share of business rates and then keep a 50% share of any growth they generate, subject to a levy, providing a strong incentive to go for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new system could deliver around an extra £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020, and generate more business rate income for councils to help pay off the deficit and support frontline services that protect vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following consultation responses, the government has changed the approach to the levy to increase the rewards for growth. The maximum levy will now be 50p in the pound. This translates into very real benefits for authorities: after the central share and levy payments, at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document also confirms the safety net for when councils experience unexpected drops in revenue will guarantee a real terms income from business rates of 92.5%. This means council income will never fall below 7.5% of its baseline funding level ensuring no area gets left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document confirms that the government will implement the majority of the technical proposals for the operation of the scheme set out in the summer consultation, together with changes to a number of detailed aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, after listening to councils, we are setting the central principles for how the new rate retention scheme will work next year. Ahead of the formal funding settlement next month this will give councils the certainty and security to begin planning their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The old flawed system of government handouts to local authorities encouraged a begging bowl mentality, with each council vying to be more deprived than its neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These reforms allow councils to stand tall, and rewards them for supporting local jobs and local firms. All councils, including the least prosperous, have the opportunity to gain from this system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation originally proposed a levy set at higher ratio. This would have meant that a district council with a business rates baseline of £100 million and a baseline funding level of £5 million would have been subject to a levy rate of 95p in the pound. So if the authority realised business rates growth of £2 million, £1 million of this would have been paid to the central share, £200,000 would have been paid to the county council, and £760,000 would have been paid in a levy, leaving the authority with £40,000 of growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s document confirms that levy rate will in fact be limited to 50p in the pound creating a much greater growth reward. This would leave that same authority with £400,000, ie 10 times more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;Business rates retention: policy statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/a-plain-english-guide-to-business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention: plain English guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"&gt;Written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16660</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:23:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"/>
    <title>Business rates retention</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Brandon Lewis on the business rates retention scheme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am today publishing a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;policy statement&lt;/a&gt; that provides early confirmation of the government’s policy decisions in a number of key areas following this summer’s technical consultation on the new business rate retention scheme. This policy statement will support local authorities, ahead of the provisional local government finance settlement, in their preparations for smooth implementation of the business rates retention scheme from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business rates retention scheme will enable local authorities to retain a large proportion of locally collected business rates to help fund the services they provide, thereby creating a direct link between business rates collected and local authority income, and reducing local authorities’ dependency on central government grants. The scheme will give all councils a strong incentive to go for growth and could add approximately £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy statement confirms government’s intention to proceed with the implementation of a range of proposals that were set out in the technical consultation. It also sets out a number of changes to those proposals, in response to comments received to the consultation, including the government’s intention to maintain the 1:1 proportionate levy but with a limit of 50p in the pound. This will translate into very real benefits for authorities, allowing at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally to be retained locally. In addition, the policy statement sets out the government’s intention to fix the safety net at 7.5% - the most generous level within the range consulted upon. This guarantee will be maintained in real terms, since baseline funding levels will be uprated by &lt;abbr title="Retail Prices Index"&gt;RPI&lt;/abbr&gt; for the purpose of calculating eligibility for the safety net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, government considers that these policy decisions will result in a system that provides a strong growth incentive for authorities, while being underpinned by robust protections to help councils maintain effective services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have placed a copy of the policy statement in the library of the House. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2"&gt;policy statement and a revised plain English guide to business rate retention&lt;/a&gt; are also available on the GOV.UK website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="data-consultation"&gt;Data consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also today publishing the data consultation on the 2013-14 local government finance settlement. The consultation sets out the majority of data that may be used in calculating the provisional baseline funding levels and revenue support grant allocations from 2013-14. This release will enable local authorities to begin checking the indicator data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; can be found on the local government finance website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-council-tax-support"&gt;Local Council Tax support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for the introduction of local Council Tax support schemes in April 2013, the government consulted on aspects of the funding arrangements to support authorities to offer Council Tax support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I will publish an update on these arrangements, including on the government’s approach to addressing budget pressures to ensure all authorities have a fair starting point. Final funding allocations will be included in the provisional local government finance settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be publishing the Council Tax base regulations and the government response to the consultation on providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the final versions of 2 key Council Tax support regulations (first published in July) have been made and are soon to be published and laid before Parliament - the prescribed requirements scheme and the default scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the regulations will be available on the GOV.UK website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16085</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:54:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/asian-fire-service-association-afsa-conference"/>
    <title>Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Brandon Lewis to the Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be invited to speak here today and to see so many others here to support you. I understand that this is the fifth AFSA national conference, and my predecessor Bob Neill has spoken at the last 2. I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Bob, who has a deep understanding of the issues you face, as well as a great knowledge of the sector. I know that Bob, when he was Fire Minister, greatly valued the close and positive relationship he had with AFSA. I very much hope to be able to continue that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-afsa"&gt;The importance of AFSA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of groups such as AFSA cannot be underestimated. You provide a forum for people to come together to discuss key concerns, to support each other’s development, and provide an opportunity for challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of challenge, AFSA continues to perform a vital role in terms of ensuring that equality, diversity and fairness are mainstreamed in the Fire and Rescue Service. Events such as this provide excellent opportunities for the exchange of ideas, and for lively debate. I know that a regional AFSA group has been set up here in the West Midlands, supporting professional development and progression, sharing learning experiences, building a solid network of mutual support for employees, and supporting charities and fundraising. All of this shows the excellent work that the association is doing both at the national and local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="promoting-equality-and-diversity"&gt;Promoting equality and diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that Sir Graham Meldrum, when he was Chief Fire Officer in the West Midlands and again as Chief Inspector of Her Majesty’s Fire Service Inspectorate did a great amount of work to promote equality and diversity in the service, and this excellent work has been carried on by Vij as Chief Fire Officer of the West Midlands, and in his presidency of the Chief Fire Officers Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to say, on a personal note, that I am deeply committed to advancing equality of opportunity to one and all, not only in the fire and rescue service, but also in the communities they live in and serve. I am also of the firm conviction that this is best driven locally. And I say this because I want each fire and rescue authority to be responsible for reaching out to minority groups, and ensuring that they recognise that the service is for them - not as an add on - but for them along with everyone else in the community. I want fire and rescue services to go out into their communities, find the right people, engage with them and draw them into the heart of the fire and rescue service family. I want the entire community to be so integrated into the fire and rescue service that we no longer have to think in terms of equality and diversity - it will just happen automatically. I know that this is at the core of what AFSA is working for, and you have my full support in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt, a lot is already happening, and I would like to highlight some of the work going on here in the West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service. They have Welcome to the West Midlands, an education programme for new migrants to promote safety, well being, community understanding and citizenship. This has been developed in consultation with migrants to meet the information gap which can occur when someone arrives in this country. The West Midlands also has active employee engagement through the local AFSA group, working with them to target under represented operational and support staff to develop essential skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my short time as Fire Minister I have been very impressed by the wide range of local initiatives such as these, which not only reach out to the under represented, but also to the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, the fire service is leading a community project with the Asian Development Association of Bury. This project, which provided employment opportunities for local people, has already seen the production of a fire safety video that can be heard in eight of Manchester’s most commonly used languages. It will be the main communication tool used in community education sessions, facilitated by fire and rescue service volunteers recruited by the association. There will also be a series of workshops for the &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; business community designed to raise awareness of how the fire and rescue service can help them meet their responsibilities under the Fire Safety Order. This project will be rolled out across all of Manchester’s ten metropolitan boroughs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage young people from a community they have previously found hard to reach, and to respect religious beliefs, they have established a cadet scheme in Hyde for young women from the Bangladeshi community, and they are hoping to use this as a model to engage many ethnic communities in similar activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is being driven forward at the local level - not by central target or quotas, but by responding to the demands of their local communities. And to be able to respond to these, each fire and rescue service needs to make full use of the human resources at their disposal - and to do this equality and diversity has to be at the core of any organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to delivering the best service to the local community is to have a diverse, representative workforce, equipped to understand and meet the needs of those it serves and capable of delivering a first class service to everyone. This will also support the service’s aim to create a better understanding of its preventative role and of the support and advice it is able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire service must ensure that every employee is valued; that there truly is equality of opportunity for all, and that the working culture is such that unfair discrimination, unacceptable behaviour, bullying and harassment are not tolerated. I strongly believe that the fire and rescue service has gone a long way to achieve this goal and together with partners like AFSA they can continue to work to create an even more open and inclusive service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-kills"&gt;Fire Kills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also like to take this opportunity to thank AFSA for your continued support of the Fire Kills campaign. The Fire Kills campaign has had a focus on &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; groups since 2005 - and for good reason. Research has shown that certain &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; communities are at a potentially greater risk from fire. Smoke alarm ownership amongst Asian communities is ten per cent lower than the national average.  Recent analysis of accidental dwelling fire victim profiles has suggested that Asian communities are potentially more vulnerable than African communities. This has led to our 2012 campaign focussing solely on the Bangladeshi and Pakistani communities. With smoke alarm ownership levels lower in these communities the primary message will be on the importance of working smoke alarms. Two bursts of advertising will run - one which began this week, and another in March 2013. The new campaign will focus on blessings. As you know blessing of wellbeing, health and a long life are delivered on important occasions in these communities. The new campaign will encourage people to make their blessings count - ‘when you give a blessing, make it count: test your smoke alarm’. There will be radio advertising to demonstrate the fire consequences of not having a working smoke alarm, linking it back to a blessing that was given. I have no doubt that this campaign, targeted primarily at first generation Pakistani and Bangladeshi communities, will be a powerful tool for you and all those in fire and rescue services seeking to reduce deaths and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-position"&gt;Economic position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of this conference is ‘advancing equality during austerity’. I think that it is important to note that there are signs of improvement in the economy. Jobs are being created, manufacturing and exports have grown as a share of our economy, our trade with vibrant, emerging economies such as China and Brazil is improving, and the world is once again investing in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we face many challenges. The debts built up over many years will take time to work our way through, not helped by a decline in our competitiveness which was effectively masked by unsustainable borrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to cut the national deficit, fire and rescue, as a frontline emergency service, has been given funding protection with reductions back-loaded to give more time for sensible savings to be made, and reductions applied to fire and rescue authorities have been less than those applied to local authorities in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been heartened to hear how many fire and rescue authorities have risen to the challenges that the spending review has posed. However, I know some of you have concerns that fire and rescue services may disproportionately reduce funding on equality and diversity activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this is not the case. But if you see this happening, then you must speak up. It is vital that fire and rescue services do not make decisions that will impact on their ability to deliver on their statutory duties as required under the Equality Act 2010, and transparency and accountability are at the heart of our approach towards local government generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing I would like to thank you once again for giving me this opportunity to speak to you today. I do hope that your organisation goes from strength to strength, and that you remain and important and influential voice in the British fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to extend my congratulations to all the award winners who will be honoured at this evening’s event, well done, keep up the good work and have a great night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15610</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:23:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates--2"/>
    <title>Business rates</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Brandon Lewis on business rates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 October, the government announced our intention to postpone the next business rates revaluation in England from 2015 to 2017. Clause 22 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; currently before the House of Commons will deliver upon this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recent Westminster Hall debate on business rates and during the second reading debate on the Bill, ministers committed to provide more information on the analysis which has informed the government’s position to assist parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full assessment would require a revaluation, which in itself would cost £43 million and take a significant amount of time. However, the Valuation Office Agency have today published their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/corporate/News/2012/newsRelease_November_2012.html"&gt;high level estimates of non-domestic rental and rating assessment movements for England&lt;/a&gt; as at January 2012; it provides an illustration of the potential impact those rateable values would have had on business rate bills. The Agency’s analysis is based on professional judgements informed by limited rental market evidence up to January 2012. The analysis has been prepared independently of ministers and published in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last revaluation was based on April 2008 valuations and rents set at the height of an unsustainable property boom. Since then, the economy and property market have faced exceptional changes. Rents have fallen since that property boom. Some groups have assumed that falling business rents would entail falling business rates. However, this is not the case. While aggregate rateable values have fallen, this would automatically be offset at the revaluation by a higher rating multiplier. Firms would just be required to pay a higher proportion of their rateable value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency’s estimates are based on an increase in the multiplier of 16%. My department has actually forecast an increase of 20%, as a consequence of inflation and the adjustment required to the multiplier for appeals; in this context, in practice, the losers would be likely to be even greater than those presented in the Agency’s paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Agency’s analysis suggests that 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates at a 2015 revaluation. This compares to 300,000 seeing reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectors would have faced big hikes including petrol stations (+28% tax paid), the self-catering industry such as caravan parks (+29% paid), hotels (+6% tax paid), theatres (+25% tax paid), and pubs (+11% tax paid). The retail sector overall would have seen a tax rise of 1% above inflation, and food retail and convenience stores in particular would have faced significant tax increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given business rates are the third biggest outgoing for local firms after staff and rent, such changes would invariably feed through to more expensive prices for family’s weekly shop, more expensive pints in pubs and a significant hit on Britain’s tourism trade. Indeed, as Community Pubs Minister, I am very aware of the concern expressed by honourable members on the pressures being faced by local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revaluations should be revenue-neutral, and equally, postponing the revaluation will be revenue-neutral. Overall the revaluation would not change the total business rates paid in England, so some sectors and locations would have seen reductions at 2015. During recent parliamentary exchanges, it was unfairly suggested that that this change was being done to assist southern parts of England at the expense of other parts of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that offices in central London would have seen by far the greatest reductions in tax paid if the 2015 revaluation had gone ahead (a fall in aggregate rateable value that is one of the reasons why the multiplier has to be increased by so much to make up for the lost revenue). There are complex variations by both locality and by sector in different parts of the country, but what is clear is that there would be far more losers than winners across the country as a whole. In making this decision, ministers are seeking to support the national interest and the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that as a very direct form of taxation, business rates are not popular. Local government finance is too often opaque and confusing. However, we are acting in an open and transparent manner. This independent evidence shows that by postponing the 2015 revaluation, we will protect local firms and local shops from sharp changes in business rates bills at a time when we want to ensure the economy is growing. It will provide business with a stable economic environment in which to invest and support jobs for the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the document will be placed in the Library together with a copy of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"&gt;Impact Assessment for the Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
