<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-for-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-for-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Skills (BIS)</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47571</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/association-of-colleges-annual-conference-2012"/>
    <title>Association of Colleges annual conference 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, in this hall, the Prime Minister gave a speech about the need for Britain to compete in the global race.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He talked about how every one needs to reach their personal best. And how we must not leave anyone behind. He reminded us that our young people must be equipped to compete. Not just with our European neighbours, but with ambitious, innovative, and determined countries all over the world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very specific challenge for everyone in this room. And it is that challenge that I want to talk about today.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over these past months, I have been hugely impressed by the go-getting and dynamic leadership of the best FE and sixth- form Colleges. I know that you are among the most innovative and responsive of any delivery arm of Government. I know that in this room there is the capacity to do so much more.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a very clear view about what my main role has to be as Minister of Skills. It is not to complain or be a constantly niggling critic. Instead, I want to be the unequivocal champion of Further Education.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m quite unusual in politics.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my school didn’t offer the A levels I wanted, I went along to West Cheshire College instead. You were there for me when I needed you. So I will celebrate, eulogise, proclaim and publicise the triumphs in Colleges every day across our land, not just because it is my job to do so, but because I know the value of what you do from my own personal experience.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wouldn’t be doing my job if I didn’t also tell it straight when I think things need to change.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I don’t want any change for change’s sake. But I know you sense a deep unfairness. You feel it in your hearts. I feel it too. It’s a sense of injustice that you deserve a better press, deserve the same recognition as schools and universities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well let me say this - I passionately believe that can happen.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no reason set in stone why technical education should not be seen as on a par with or even more virtuous than university, like it is in Holland or Germany.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also believe this: there is only one way to make that happen. The route to recognition is for every college to be as good as the most outstanding college is today. It will come only when teaching in FE is uniformly high quality. Only when every college is as enterprising as the Gazelle group. When every college reaches for the stars.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outstanding education is the route to outstanding acclaim. I want to see every college an outstanding college. I want to see all teaching as inspiring as the best. I will work with you, support you, stand up for you, and yes, challenge you in that goal. And together we can get there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the public at large, the most trusted sign of excellence in education is a positive Ofsted report. School inspection has existed in England since the year Queen Victoria came to the throne. And I am at one with Sir Michael Wilshaw when he reminds us that “Satisfactory is not satisfactory as it’s not good”.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ofsted is challenging. I know that. It’s meant to be. But the response must surely be: to raise standards. To improve teaching. To perspire. To aspire. To inspire. And I am at your side. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen for myself what our best Colleges can achieve: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with engineers in Sheffield to train world class nuclear technicians &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing inspiring Peter Jones Enterprise Academies &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;joining employers and universities to sponsor new innovative Studio Schools, UTCs, and Academies. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have seen for myself at the Skills Show here in Birmingham the amazing talent on display, honed and thriving through competition.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I see excellence I want to spread it. When I see innovation, I want to learn from it. When I see barriers to progress, I want to break them down.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past two years, under reforms pioneered by my brilliant predecessor, you have taken hold of the freedoms and flexibilities you now have. From next year, a reformed funding system will, I hope, have given you yet more flexibility in how to provide outstanding education.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we all know there is more to do. So I want to outline plans in four priority areas where i see the need for further reform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;apprenticeships &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;traineeships &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;qualifications &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;standards. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me briefly take each in turn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="apprenticeships"&gt;Apprenticeships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, apprenticeships.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, over a million Apprenticeships have been started, half a million of them in the last year. And while this increase in quantity is very welcome, we must ensure they are higher quality, more rigorous, and focused on what employers need. I hope that employers come forward with innovative proposals for higher quality Apprenticeships in the second round of the Employer Ownership Pilot we launched yesterday. And Doug Richard will before Christmas say how we can go further, in a report I hope we can embrace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="traineeships"&gt;Traineeships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, as we raise the standard of Apprenticeships, that will leave a gap. Around the country I have been impressed by the work of many Colleges to give young people the skills they need to get and hold down a job, with Work Pairings, and joint ventures with the Youth Contract and JobCentrePlus. But we must do more.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will bring forward a new traineeship, combining a rigorous core of work preparation, work experience, Maths, and english, with a great deal of flexibility around everything else. I want this to support the best of what’s available, help raise the participation age, and give a clear sense of progression into an Apprenticeship.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside Traineeships, we must also improve the way our skills system and our benefits system interact. How can we justify a system in which we pay people, so long as they don’t train, rather than support people so long as they do? It’s bad for the economy, it’s unfair on young people, and it has got to stop. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="qualifications"&gt;Qualifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, high quality education needs stretching and valuable qualifications.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The QCF is here to stay as an organising framework post-19, but we must be more rigorous about what’s on it, and about what we in Government are prepared to spend scarce resources on. For vocational education to be valued and held in high esteem we must be uncompromising about the value added of vocational education.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we are publishing a revised list of approved vocational qualifications for 14-16 year olds, covering courses taught from next September.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting the work of the Royal Academy of Engineers on new engineering qualifications that will both fit the new system and be stretching and rigorous. I’d like to see more august, employer-led bodies like the Royal Academy step up and design the qualifications employers need. And as you know, as well as reforming qualifications at 16, are we are working on plans for colleges directly recruiting pupils aged 14 and 15 to be directly funded.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whatever the age of the learner, I share with Alison Wolf the view that we must encourage the use of the most rigorous and valuable vocational qualifications. And I also share her view that far too little genuinely occupational education takes place among 16-18 year olds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the route for academic kids is straightforward. But those who choose not to take the academic route too often are encouraged into a general applied qualification, instead of properly considering the value of an Apprenticeship or a rigorous occupational qualification.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the coming weeks we will publish a consultation on how to identify the highest value vocational qualifications for 16 to 18 year olds, just as we have done for 14-16 year olds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In it we will also consider what more we can do to encourage the take up of Apprenticeships and occupational - as opposed to general applied - qualifications. And of course we must consider what this means for adult qualifications too.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For vocational qualifications to be seen to be stretching and strong, they must be stretching and strong, and that’s what I hope to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="standards"&gt;Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, standards.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already set out proposals for a guild, led by you, to build up inspirational teaching and a stronger sense of professionalism and pride.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am setting out plans for high quality colleges to achieve a Chartered Status for Colleges.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course raising standards means tackling poor provision too. We need to be firmer in tackling educational and financial failure, and turning underperforming colleges around.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so students and employers alike can see performance for themselves, I can confirm that, from this year, we will introduce common standards and measures of performance between schools and colleges. Both will be expected to meet minimum standards.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A levels and vocational qualifications are different, so they will be judged separately from each other. But each will be judged in the same way for all institutions. We said we’d introduce a level playing field, and we will.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is one area where Britain should lead the world, but where sinfully we have allowed ourselves to fall behind. Here in these islands, we invented the English language that now dominates the globe. It is the global language: of trade, of culture, of diplomacy, and of the arts. And our history is littered with many of the advances in mathematics too.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet too many of our young people cannot read or write, or add up properly. This is a scandal and it must change.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are reforming schools, and exams at 16, to make this happen. That great revolution will take a generation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we don’t have a generation. And it often falls to you to pick up the pieces.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to show the value we attach to English and Maths, and to make sure you’ve got the resources to deliver, today I’m announcing we are doubling the amount we pay for adult English and Maths functional skills, and for English and Maths within an Apprenticeship. English and Maths are the foundation of learning and we must succeed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four priorities: traineeship, apprenticeships, standards, and qualification reform, they are all aimed four-square at raising the value, the esteem, and the regard of further education and skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognising only the best vocational qualifications. Increasing support for English and Maths. Stronger Apprenticeships. And new traineeships to help young people into a job.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will do what it takes so every one can play their part.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, I am a young man, and honoured to be your Minister. And while this job is hard, it is hugely motivating too. For I am passionate about giving everyone in our country the best possible start. I am passionate about what you do for your students every single day.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have not been dealt an easy hand of plenty. And I can’t pretend the road ahead is not tough.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that the innovation, dedication, and inspiration in this room can get us to our goal. And along that road, I am at your side, every step of the way. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47093</id>
    <published>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/skills-minister-unveils-new-investment-in-skills-in-key-industries"/>
    <title>Skills Minister unveils new investment in skills in key industries</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GIF was set up to help employers overcome barriers to growth within their sectors and industries. So far the government has committed over £15 million to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boost innovation and productivity &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enable industries to set new professional standards &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support new or extended national skills academies. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="support-for-nuclear-skills"&gt;Support for nuclear skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclear.nsacademy.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy (NSA) for Nuclear Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; will receive government investment of more than £920,000. This will enable the Academy expand its activities into nuclear manufacturing to help UK manufacturers take advantage of the opportunities offered by the new nuclear build programme. It will also collaborate with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.semta.org.uk/"&gt;Sector Skills Council for Science, Engineering and Manufacturing Technologies (SEMTA)&lt;/a&gt; and the Sheffield-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://namrc.co.uk/"&gt;Nuclear Advanced Manufacturing Research Centre&lt;/a&gt; to create a focal point to boost companies’ capability to develop skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within its first three years the expansion aims to deliver a more skilled workforce, with an increase of 3,500 learners taking up programmes, including more than 500 apprenticeships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="support-for-creative-and-cultural-skills"&gt;Support for creative and cultural skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nsa-ccskills.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural&lt;/a&gt; will receive around £1.5 million. This will enable it to expand and open up opportunities for more than 1,200 new apprenticeships and craft training for young people across the jewellery, design and cultural heritage sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NSA Creative and Cultural also plans to reach around 1.2 million young people through their careers information, advice and guidance material over the next 5 years. It will work with a number of leading organisations and employers, for example the Goldsmiths’ Company, Holts Academy and the British Jewellers’ Association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is businesses themselves that are best-placed to identify the skills they need to drive growth. This investment is very good news for the UK nuclear and creative industries and will help them to overcome the skills gaps that stand in the way of them meeting their full potential. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new centre for excellence for nuclear manufacturing will increase the number of opportunities for technicians and skilled workers and ensure that UK firms can source the skills they need to grow their market share in an expanding market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural has already demonstrated its success in working with more than 200 employers in the theatre and live entertainment business. I am delighted that investment will allow them to increase opportunities in the design, cultural heritage and jewellery sectors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both nuclear manufacturing and for creative and cultural, government funding will be matched by business and delivered over three years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Skills-Minister-unveils-new-investment-in-skills-for-key-industries-67af8.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Skills Minister unveils new investment in skills for key industries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/gif"&gt;About the Growth Innovation Fund from the UK Commission for Employment and Skills (UKCES)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclear.nsacademy.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Nuclear Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nsa-ccskills.co.uk/"&gt;National Skills Academy for Creative and Cultural&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further education and skills at BIS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18371</id>
    <published>2012-04-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-04-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-national-careers-service-launched"/>
    <title>New National Careers Service launched</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Hayes also hosted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Apr/Ask%20John%20Hayes%20-%20Tweet%20your%20skills%20and%20careers%20questions"&gt;Twitter chat at 10.30am this morning&lt;/a&gt;, answering questions on the new service. Follow the conversation using #askhayes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-careers-service"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining face to face to face local advice with a new interactive website, the new &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt; will: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide information and advice for approximately 370,000 young people through the use of the helpline and website. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer face to face advice to 700,000 adults each year in a range of locations in local communities. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide detailed sector by sector labour market information so people can discover which industries are growing in their area. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide tools such as a CV builder and a Skills Health Check on the website to help people identify their skills strengths and gaps. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow people to open a Lifelong Learning Account, which gives them clear information and advice on skills, careers and financial support in a single, personalised online space. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Hayes said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Careers Service, universally available to people at all stages of their careers, has the very best interactive tools on its website and the highest-quality advisers, committed to the noble cause of helping others fulfil their aspirations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Making available the right advice at the right time and in the right places is to strike a blow for social mobility, social cohesion and social justice - a society that encourages people from wherever they start to journey to the destination of their dreams.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model turned Chef, Lorraine Pascale is an Ambassador for the service. Speaking from the launch she said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“After modelling, choosing my next career move was a big decision. I knew I wanted to find something that I was really passionate about, but I tried courses in hypnotherapy, auto repair and interior design before I found the thing that really makes me tick: cooking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having independent careers advice can really help you find the thing you want to do. I’d encourage everyone to make the most of the National Careers Service to find out how to take their career forward, and realise their ambitions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her view was echoed by Record Producer Pete Waterman. He said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I know from my own experience that it’s never too late to learn a new skill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I learnt to read and write much later in life than many people, but this opened up a whole new world for me.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s one of the reasons why I’m so passionate about helping people to get the skills they need to fulfil their ambitions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the National Careers Service: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/12-677-national-careers-service-right-advice-right-time.pdf"&gt;The right advice at the right time (PDF, 2.2 Mb) &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18372</id>
    <published>2012-04-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-04-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-standards-for-apprenticeships"/>
    <title>Better standards for Apprenticeships</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes has announced that Apprenticeships will last for a minimum of 12 months, guaranteeing improvements in training and workplace learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new standards will come into force for all age groups from August 2012, subject to consultation with providers and employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those aged 19 and over, apprenticeships will last between one to four years unless prior learning or attainment has been undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the new measures, Mr Hayes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The momentum we have created by building the apprenticeship brand has brought about unprecedented success for the apprenticeship programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The majority of apprenticeships are the gold standard in vocational training. They boost individuals’ life chances and build the skills that drive growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They also provide a great return on public money. This has been independently recognised with the National Audit Office finding that apprenticeships generating £18 for the economy for every £1 spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we must be relentless in our drive to ensure all apprenticeships are as good as the best, to identify and root out any instances of poor quality provision, and to raise the bar on standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are taking strong and decisive action to tackle short duration so all apprentices receive high quality training and workplace learning setting them on the road to a long, rewarding career.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="grants-for-small-businesses-employing-their-first-apprentice"&gt;Grants for Small Businesses Employing Their First Apprentice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Monday 2 April small businesses (employing less than 250 employees) &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/News-Media/Latest-News/Article135.aspx"&gt;will be able to apply for a grant, up to a value of £1,500,&lt;/a&gt; when they recruit their first apprentice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service &lt;/a&gt;(NAS) is offering up to 40,000 Apprenticeship Grants to businesses who take on an apprentice aged 16 to 24 years old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those businesses interested in employing their first apprentice can contact one of the quality assured training providers or colleges approved to deliver Apprenticeship training by visiting the National Apprenticeship Service, or if they are ready to recruit, can call 08000 150 600 to speak to a NAS Apprenticeship Adviser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-minimum-12-month-duration-for-all-apprenticeships-6782c.aspx"&gt;Press Notice - New minimum 12 month duration for all apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/News-Media/Latest-News/Article135.aspx"&gt;Press Notice - Grants for Small Businesses Employing Their First Apprentice - Now Available!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18345</id>
    <published>2012-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/banks-boost-uk-jobs-with-new-apprenticeships--2"/>
    <title>Banks boost UK jobs with new apprenticeships</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcements were made at a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.newsroom.hsbc.co.uk/articles/apprenticeship_week_-_hsbc_hos"&gt;financial services sector roundtable, held at HSBC&lt;/a&gt; in Canary Wharf, as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Feb/apprenticeships-week-2012"&gt;National Apprenticeship Week&lt;/a&gt;. The focus was on the creation of new apprenticeship routes into employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks taking part include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Barclays - 1000 new apprenticeships across England and Wales with a major programme in April.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HSBC - an extra 688 apprentices bringing the total number of employees within its apprenticeship scheme to 1,000 by the end of 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Santander to launch an apprenticeship scheme that will see up to 50 people offered places at the bank. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the event, Skills Minister John Hayes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that these banks are investing in apprenticeships which will help them secure the high-quality skills they need to create economic growth and provide new pathways to excellence for the brightest and best young people.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Creating a highly skilled workforce that can take on the best in the world means seeing apprenticeships as an access route to the professions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=423209&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On February 7 the Prime Minister announced &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2012/Feb/apprenticeships-government-funding"&gt;round two of the Higher Apprenticeship Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//sitecore/service/notfound.aspx?item=web%3a%7b6604A760-C720-42F1-AD9A-6100618CD4EF%7d%40en"&gt;Apprenticeships at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18331</id>
    <published>2011-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/building-engagement-building-futures"/>
    <title>Building Engagement, Building Futures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills/youth-participation"&gt;Building Engagement, Building Futures&lt;/a&gt; sets out the Government’s strategy to improve the opportunities for young people so they gain the skills they need to secure an Apprenticeship or employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes radical reforms to schools, vocational education, skills and welfare provision, and has five priorities for action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raising attainment in school so that young people have the skills to compete in the global economy. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping local partners provide services that support all young people, putting us on track to achieve full participation for 16-17 year olds by 2015. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging employers to offer more high quality Apprenticeships and work experience places. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensuring that work pays and giving young people the personalised support they need to find it, through Universal Credit, the Work Programme and the Get Britain Working measures. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Putting in place a new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/1-billion-package-tackle-youth-unemployment"&gt;Youth Contract &lt;/a&gt;worth almost £1 billion over the next three years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re taking action to get our young people into education, training and work, helping them get on the path to a fulfilling life, providing the right advice and guidance through a new National Careers Service and restoring a sense of responsibility and purposeful pride in our communities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having built the largest apprenticeships programme our country has ever seen we are now incentivising employers to offer more high-quality apprenticeships. We are also aligning welfare and skills reforms to better support young people without basic skills get up to speed and progress on to jobs and apprenticeships.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building Engagement, Building Futures has been published jointly by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/a00200853/building-engagement-building-futures"&gt;DfE&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://dwp.gov.uk/publications/policy-publications/building-engagement.shtml"&gt;DWP&lt;/a&gt; - more detail on those Department’s policies as outlined in the strategy can be found on those websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Participation Strategy follows the recent publication by BIS of key reforms to Further Education in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/fe-and-skills-new-challenges-new-chances"&gt;New Challenges, New Chances&lt;/a&gt; on 1 December 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="priorities-for-action"&gt;Priorities for action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt;, the Chancellor set out how the Government will create the conditions for economic growth and recovery. Building Engagement, Building Futures sets out the Government’s offer for young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the priorities for action, the Government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing £4.5 million over the next two years to give more 16-19 year olds access to work experience. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging employers to take on an 18-24 year-old from the Work Programme by making available 160,000 job subsidies worth up to £2,275 for each business. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reforming the Apprenticeships programme and, as part of the Youth Contract, ensuring funding for at least 40,000 incentive payments for small firms to take on 18-24 year old apprentices. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing an extra 250,000 work experience places over the next three years for young unemployed people across the UK as part of the Youth Contract. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funding charities and businesses to help the most disengaged 16-17 year olds get skills and jobs. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transforming vocational education following Professor Wolf’s review, with new 16-19 programmes of study, including meaningful work-experience and a focus on English and maths. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joining up the welfare and skills systems. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching a National Careers Service in April 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=422504&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further Education and Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://dwp.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Work and Pensions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18305</id>
    <published>2011-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-interactive-careers-and-learning-tool-launches--2"/>
    <title>New interactive careers and learning tool launches</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new free online service launched today, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/LifeLongLearningAccount/Pages/default.aspx"&gt;Lifelong Learning Accounts&lt;/a&gt;, will help people to get improved access to jobs and career development opportunities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Account holders will have free access to a number of online tools, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A skills diagnostic tool to identify their interests, strengths and needs. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Localised course and job searches. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A CV builder. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An ‘eligibility checker’ to identify Government funding available to them &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A facility to store all their personal learner information - CVs, skills tests, job and course searches - in one easily accessible place they can share with a careers adviser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Further Education, Skills and Lifelong Learning, John Hayes said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lifelong Learning Accounts will encourage individuals to learn, and keep on learning. I want the accounts to help build a national community with the desire to seek out knowledge and skills and invest in their own success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All young people and adults should have the chance to learn and to excel in their chosen skill, getting into work and progressing in their chosen career.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="lifelong-learning"&gt;Lifelong Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as improving access to careers information and personal data, the accounts will encourage users to link up with other learners to share knowledge and experiences. Account holders will be signposted to relevant learners’ forums and communities via social media such as Facebook and Twitter.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accounts will also enable training providers to respond better to what learners want and help careers advisers to deliver targeted advice and support based on an individual’s interests.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lifelong Learning Accounts offer will continue to develop in 2012 and beyond to provide account holders with the information they want in a way that best suits them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421453&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find Find careers, learning and skills advice at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/index.htm"&gt;Directgov &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt; [](http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18291</id>
    <published>2011-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-cuts-apprenticeship-red-tape"/>
    <title>Government cuts apprenticeship red tape</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes has announced a package of new measures to make it easier for employers to take on large numbers of apprentices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payments will be simplified, contracts streamlined and a number of data returns and audit requirements will be eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hayes said that firms that contract directly with the Government to train apprentices will now benefit from simplified payment, reporting and assessment requirements.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also receive better guidance to help them manage the recruitment, training and assessment of apprentices more efficiently and cost effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Apprenticeships are proving an increasingly effective training route for young people and companies. They are a proven way to fill skills gaps in our economy. That’s why we are boosting the number of apprenticeships and putting them at the heart of our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/further-education-skills/skills-for-sustainable-growth"&gt;Skills for Growth strategy.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But for far too long too many businesses have been put off by overly complex procedures and unnecessary layers of paperwork. We’ve worked with business to cut bureaucracy and ensure the benefits for employers, learners and the economy are maximised”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="action-plan-for-cutting-red-tape"&gt;Action plan for cutting red tape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announcing the measures at a summit hosted by the CBI today, Mr Hayes said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m determined that more employers and learners than ever should have the opportunity to benefit from our unprecedented investment in apprenticeships. Where red tape and bureaucracy deters employers from taking on apprentices, we’ll sweep it away.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That will give more firms access to the skills they need to thrive, creating new jobs and new growth, and it will give many more individuals better prospects and the chance to gain a real stake in society.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for cutting red tape for employers include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pilot for over 20 large employers who have volunteered to trial “payment by outcomes” which will eliminate a number of data returns and audit requirements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing an online plain-English toolkit for employers that clearly explains the end-to-end processes employers need to undertake for apprenticeships. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streamlining contracting arrangements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A commitment to no “in year” changes to contracting arrangements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A more proportionate approach to audit and inspection - reducing preparation time for employers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater use of electronic information, thus reducing paperwork. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A more streamlined certification process. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These measures follow the recommendations of a review led by the Employer Reference Group, the Confederation of British Industry (CBI) and large companies, including BT and TUI Travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susan Anderson, the CBI’s director for education and skills policy, said: “Cutting bureaucracy will support even more businesses to become involved and these recommendations set out the right path for reform.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They recognise that employers are primarily concerned with the day-to-day running of their businesses, and that they are committed to offering high quality training as their reputation and business success depends on this.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421064&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;Apprenticeships UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further education and skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/fe-and-skills-new-challenges-new-chances"&gt;New Challenges, New Chances: Next Steps in Implementing the Further Education Reform Programme&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18285</id>
    <published>2011-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-challenges-new-chances-for-adult-learning"/>
    <title>New Challenges, New Chances for adult learning</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation published today represents the next phase of the Government’s plans to implement its radical reform of adult learning and skills provision in England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take part in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/fe-and-skills-new-challenges-new-chances"&gt;New Challenges, New Chances.&lt;/a&gt; The consultation will close on Friday 21 October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets out proposals that will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote high quality teaching and learning for adults. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow colleges to respond more effectively to the needs of their local communities. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen the skills system by securing a fairer balance of investment between learners, employers and taxpayers.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe that the further education and skills sector is at the heart of our economic and educational policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With better informed, more empowered learners and providers freed from petty bureaucracy, post-school adult learning will take its rightful place at the heart of our communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-consultation"&gt;The Consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation covers measures to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide greater freedoms and flexibilities and further reduce the burden of bureaucracy on further education and skills providers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve the quality of teaching and learning for adults. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen further education and skills providers’ capacity to offer training at higher education level. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review and improve basic literacy and numeracy provision for adults. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refocus Government support for informal adult and community learning. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduce loans from the 2013/14 academic year providing access to advanced and higher level courses. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop the further education landscape and shape of the sector.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Further Education, Skills and Lifelong Learning, John Hayes, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our proposals describe the next steps towards a more confident, vibrant further education sector, ready to meet the challenges and seize the chances that a rebalanced, high skill economy will present.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Government knows that skills change lives, nourish social renewal and feed economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals give more detail on how key parts of the Government’s strategy for further education and skills, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2010/Nov/skills-for-sustainable-growth"&gt;published last November,&lt;/a&gt; will be implemented.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420821&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/further-education-skills"&gt;Further Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18271</id>
    <published>2011-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/10-000-higher-apprenticeships-to-help-business"/>
    <title>10,000 Higher Apprenticeships to help business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting Jaguar Land Rover in the Midlands, Prime Minister David Cameron today announced a £25 million fund that will support up to 10,000 Advanced and Higher Apprenticeships. This will give firms in sectors such as advanced manufacturing, information technology and engineering the hi-tech skills they need to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/employers/the-basics/higher-apprenticeships.aspx"&gt;The Higher Apprenticeships Fund&lt;/a&gt; will support the expansion of apprenticeships up to degree equivalent in companies, particularly SMEs, where there is unmet demand for the higher level skills that are necessary to create additional jobs and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry representatives are invited to bid to the fund, which will be delivered via the National Apprenticeship Service, from today.  The new apprenticeships will commence from October 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am determined that this government should be the most pro-business there has been, with one purpose and one goal: creating jobs and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is therefore crucial that we build up the skills in this country that our businesses need and that will fuel long term growth. That is why despite some difficult decisions on spending we are increasing the number of apprenticeships to record levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are investing in apprenticeships because we know they work - they are good for people who want to get ahead, good for business and good for the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As I work with the business community to rebalance and grow the economy, apprenticeships will increasingly deliver not just basic training, but also the high level, high tech skills that drive growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Higher Apprenticeships Fund is a crucial step towards placing vocational learning on a par with academic study, giving bright youngsters the opportunity to work with and build the most dynamic firms in the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister John Hayes said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government is on track to deliver the biggest and best apprenticeships programme our country has ever seen.   But we’re determined to do more to give smaller firms, especially in high skill industries, the help they need to reap the benefits of world class training.  With every £1 the Government spends on an apprenticeship delivering a return of some £40 to the wider economy, this fund is a sound investment in the country’s future.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420541&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Growth Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
