<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--23</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--23.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48079</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa hails Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’ following successful elections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the National Electoral Committee announced the Presidential election results, Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I congratulate John Dramani Mahama on his election as President of Ghana and on elections that were widely recognised to be free, fair and transparent. Ghana has now seen six successful elections since military government ended in 1992 and it is rightly seen as a beacon of democracy in the region. I commend the Ghanaian people, political parties and civil society on the peaceful environment in which the elections were held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The relationship between the UK and Ghana is strong and vibrant. It is rooted in our long-standing economic, political and cultural connections, our shared values, and the deep links between our peoples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to continuing a constructive and productive working relationship with President Mahama and his government, one that continues to bring our countries closer together.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18772</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-the-overseas-territories-and-overseas-territory-leaders-issue-joint-communique-following-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Minister for the Overseas Territories and Overseas Territory leaders issue joint communiqué following Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council, chaired by Minister Simmonds and attended by Premiers, Chief Ministers and other elected representatives from Britain’s Overseas Territories, closed today with the agreement of a joint communiqué which sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the second day of the Council also saw the Prime Minister welcome Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said in his foreword in the White Paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom’s 14 Overseas Territories are an integral part of Britain’s life and history. This Government is ambitious for our Territories as we are ambitious for the United Kingdom.  We want to see our communities flourish in partnership, with strong and sustainable local economies. We see an important opportunity to set world standards in our stewardship of the extraordinary natural environments we have inherited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out a very positive vision for the Overseas Territories. This first meeting of the Joint Ministerial Council has helped us identify an ambitious list of priority areas for action, such as encouraging economic growth; protecting the environment and making government work better. We will work closely with the Territories in the coming year to achieve what we have together set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of my Ministerial colleagues from across Government took part in the Council this week, demonstrating that the UK Government as a whole is committed to supporting the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17781</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-simmonds-visits-africa-to-support-efforts-to-end-crisis-in-goma"/>
    <title>Mark Simmonds visits Africa to support efforts to end crisis in Goma</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds will first visit Uganda and then travel on to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo. During his trip, he will meet regional leaders to discuss the political work underway to resolve the crisis and the humanitarian situation. He will urge leaders to use any influence they have to bring an end to the crisis and limit its impact on civilian populations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am travelling to the region at short notice to show that the UK is focused on the serious and urgent crisis unfolding in Goma and to show my support to the people of the DRC. I am deeply concerned by the current crisis and I urge the M23 militia to stop their offensive and for all external support to the M23 militia to stop.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On my visit I will be meeting with government ministers from across the region and will ask them all to find, first and foremost, a resolution that will swiftly end the fighting and produce a sustainable long term plan that will ensure peace and stability for the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/44286</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/skiiers-avoid-injury-and-expensive-medical-bills"/>
    <title>Skiers: avoid injury and expensive medical bills</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are launching a campaign aimed at Britons visiting European winter sports resorts this winter to explain the dangers of attempting slopes beyond your level of ability, or going off piste without the correct safety equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re heading off a ski or snowboarding holiday this winter, please don’t put yourself at risk by trying to keep up with more experienced members of your party. The number of reported accidents on French slopes in 2012 was high, including seven deaths out of 12 serious incidents*. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="research"&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to new research from the FCO**, of those British nationals that go on winter sports holidays the majority class themselves as beginner or intermediate. Only 1% of respondents classed themselves as expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly two thirds (65%) of winter sports travellers admitted they would ski or snowboard on slopes above their experience in order to stay with a group. More than half (53%) also said they would follow a group of mates off piste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventy per cent admitted they do not always wear a helmet when skiing or snowboarding, and one in five (21%) said they wouldn’t wear a helmet if others in their group weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor, Consul, based in Marseille, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we saw a high number of British nationals end up in hospital with serious injuries. Sadly this included a number of deaths. Many of these accidents can be prevented by taking simple precautionary steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of assuming you’ll be fine if you’re with more experienced skiers or snowboarders. It is significant that a large number of cases we have dealt with have involved off piste skiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those lucky enough to survive an accident and end up in hospital can face months of recovery, so it is important to think carefully beforehand about the very real risks out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="insurance"&gt;Insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third (38%) of winter sports holidaymakers admitted that they don’t always take out travel insurance. One in three (31%) also said they don’t always check their policy to ensure they are covered for winter sports activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many people will be unaware that failing to wear a helmet or skiing off piste can invalidate some insurance policies, so if something does go wrong you could end up with hefty medical bills. In many cases family members then have to help with funds which can put a huge strain on families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The FCO cannot pay for hospital treatment or for medical repatriation back to the UK, which is why it is so important to check your insurance covers you for everything you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="top-tips-to-stay-safe-on-the-slopes"&gt;Top tips to stay safe on the slopes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take out insurance – and check what it covers. It might not cover off piste skiing unless you are with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a check-up before you ski - one of the major causes of hospitalisation and death on the slopes is heart attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t drink and ski. Alcohol can affect you more quickly at high altitudes and dangerously limits your awareness of risk and cold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most skiing injuries are caused by collisions with other skiers – watch your speed and distance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t attempt slopes you’re not experienced or fit enough to tackle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to go off piste, go with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If going off piste carry a shovel, a probe and a transceiver in case of an avalanche. Also remember that you need proper training on how to use a transceiver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are going out on a glacier, you must wear a harness. If you fall into a crevasse, this will help the rescue team get you out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure someone knows where you’re going and tell them of any changes to your plans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only go off piste skiing or climbing with someone you have met previously and can trust. You need to know his/her capabilities, what you’ll be doing and where.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For further tips and advice on preparing for travel abroad, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.fco.gov.uk/travel" title="FCO Travel Advice"&gt;www.fco.gov.uk/travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Figures taken from FCO 2011/12 consular assistance data &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Survey conducted by ICM. Total sample size was 2,023 UK adults aged 18 and over. Fieldwork was undertaken in November 2012. The figures have been weighted and are representative of all UK adults aged 18 and over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17809</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>UK and Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds, has opened the first annual Joint Ministerial Council, bringing together political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers to drive forward implementation of the vision and strategy set out in the June 2012 White Paper &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/overseas-territories/overseas-territories-white-paper/" title="Overseas Territotories White Paper"&gt;The Overseas Territories: Security, Success and Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council aims to agree priorities and plans for the UK and the Territories to work together on wide range of issues including: building successful and resilient economies; harnessing support from the Commonwealth and the EU; cherishing the environment and creating green growth; working together for better government; building stronger, healthier and safer communities; health; and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister will welcome elected leaders to Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister. Ministers and senior officials from wide range of UK Departments will take part in the Council, demonstrating the commitment from across government to working with the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the meeting Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to welcome elected leaders from the Overseas Territories to the Joint Ministerial Council. This is an opportunity for us to strengthen our work together to build flourishing communities, proudly retaining aspects of their British identity, creating new opportunities for young and future generations and protecting natural environments to the highest international standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year, we have demonstrated our commitment to preserving the astounding natural environment in the territories, by establishing a new Marine Protected Area in South Georgia &amp;amp; the South Sandwich Islands and launching Darwin Plus, the new Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
