<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-planning</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-planning.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Planning</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56622</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/guidance-will-help-support-development-and-get-infrastructure-built"/>
    <title>Guidance will help support development and get infrastructure built</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance has been revised with the active participation of councils and developers to provide certainty on key issues. It has been updated to reflect reforms to the planning system and will help councils looking to introduce the levy, as well as providing clarity to those paying the levy about how it works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; ensures there is no double charging to developers by clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance reflects existing best practice and ensures councils in the process of developing proposals do not need to start their levy setting process from the beginning. Support will be available to councils who choose to review their levy as a result of the new guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ensures a robust evidence base is used for assessing levy rates and provides advice on the 2012 regulations that improve the operation of the levy. The guidance also makes clear that there is no obligation for councils to charge the levy, and that they can set a low or zero rate if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Government has worked actively with councils and developers to get this guidance right and make clear how we expect the levy to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The guidance ensures that councils who have already adopted their levy will not need to do anything new and only councils developing levy rates will need to consider this new guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will continue to listen to issues being raised, such as the need for greater clarity at an earlier stage on how the levy will be spent. We will also be considering the suggestion to move the 2014 date when councils will be limited in their use of pooled Section 106 planning obligations for infrastructure that can be funded by the levy. The government expects to consult on further regulatory changes in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy has the potential to raise an estimated £1 billion a year of funding by 2016 to support growth locally. It gives councils more choice and flexibility in how they fund the infrastructure that their communities want and need, and provides developers with much more ‘up front’ certainty about the amount of money they will be expected to contribute for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Peace from the British Property Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development industry has raised a number of concerns about the Community Infrastructure Levy. We have been closely involved in the development of this document and are pleased that it clearly sets out what local authorities must do when they are looking to charge the levy. These revisions should help support development by ensuring the levy is being implemented effectively. We look forward to continuing our work with the department on other Community Infrastructure Levy issues next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Mike Jones, Leader, Cheshire West and Chester Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils are keen to continue work with the development industry in a positive and productive way that enables much needed development to take place in a way that is fair and equitable to developers and to local people. Discussions on the Community Infrastructure Levy have been conducted in this spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Builders Federation Executive Chairman Stewart Baseley said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been closely involved in the process to improve the Community Infrastructure Levy guidance. We are pleased that it assists in clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations and sets out the importance of robust evidence and transparency when deciding on levy rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recently introduced changes to ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged the Community Infrastructure Levy. Applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents (via a Section 73 planning application) without having to pay another levy on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17243</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/town-and-country-planning-association-conference-speech"/>
    <title>Town and Country Planning Association conference speech</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;England is famous for the beauty of its landscapes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Yorkshire Dales to the South Hams, from the Weald of Kent to the Cumbrian Lakes, England glories in countryside of which generations of man and nature are joint authors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes - together with the greater drama of their Celtic cousins - that draw visitors to these islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes that our most popular institution and your sister organisation, the National Trust, was set up to preserve in perpetuity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of England is its finest asset and, for each of us, our most precious inheritance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative in both name and spirit, as a West Country boy and a Lincolnshire MP, as the son of a former director general of the National Trust and the brother of 1 of its conservation managers, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that nothing would do more to improve the health and happiness of the British people than if more of them got to spend more of their lives surrounded by beauty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty lifts, calms, excites, inspires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more intoxicating than any narcotic, more soothing than any therapy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Britain becomes more prosperous, we must insist that it becomes more beautiful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the beauty we seek, and the landscapes we treasure, are not only to be found in our open spaces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the loveliest scenery in Britain is to be found in our villages, cities and towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take you on a journey, which starts in my constituency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, the river Welland has snaked its way through the low contours of Lincolnshire from its source in Northamptonshire’s Hothorpe Hills.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enters Lincolnshire at the point where 4 counties meet and passes through countryside that is pleasant but hardly memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wandering painter or poet would not give this stretch of the Welland valley a second look, were it not for the landscape of Lincolnshire limestone that is the town of Stamford.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is not just 1 of England’s most beautiful towns; it is 1 of its finest bits of scenery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man-made. Built from stone and timber frames and slate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the aesthetic equal of our most splendid hills, lakes and rivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did this landscape come from?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it spring fully formed from the mind of some 17th century master planner, the brainchild of a Lincolnshire Haussman?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is, as the Royal Commission for Historic Monuments pronounced, ‘a town of discrete buildings’, each 1 unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earls of Exeter from nearby Burghley House provided long leases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the local community of wool, leather, cloth and hemp merchants, apothecaries and solicitors indulged themselves with a great variety of stone window surrounds, doorways, eaves, corner and chimney details.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did so within a broad set of rules set out in the London manuals of Rome educated James Gibbs but almost always used local architects and builders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford was the spontaneous product of human initiative, haphazardly executed and totally unplanned, motivated by the desire for profit, the love of God and that age-old urge that keeps makeover shows in business, the desire to make your house nicer than your neighbours’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop is north of the border, in Great Britain’s first New Town.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by contrast, was an example of municipal town planning at its boldest and most inspired.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the economic stagnation into which Edinburgh had slipped after the Act of Union, in 1752 the Provost, George Drummond, launched an architectural competition to design a new cityscape of wide streets, crescents and squares, featuring symmetrical terraces of town-houses as well as purpose-built shops and public gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-six year old James Craig won the competition and, in 4 stages between the 1760s and the 1850s, he, Robert Adam, William Chambers and William Playfair all stayed loyal to the original vision and developed their own variations on a Greek revival theme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In building their New Town, Edinburgh’s town councillors not only restored commercial and cultural vigour to Scotland’s capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also created 1 of the most beautiful landscapes in the British Isles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who can resist the melancholy charm of a walk in the rain around Charlotte Square and through Ainslie Place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would wager that the Facebook pages of recent visitors to Scotland contain at least as many photographs of Bute House and Moray Place as they do of Loch Lomond or Glencoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Stamford in the early 1600s, and in Edinburgh 150 later, beauty came about as a result of the natural human urge to get together with one’s neighbours to build a place in which it would be a pleasure to live and work, to raise a family and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same generous set of instincts that, another hundred and fifty years later, inspired Ebenezer Howard to build Letchworth Garden City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I am skating on very thin ice telling members of the Town and Country Planning Association anything about the Garden City movement, when your association was founded to promote just that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do want take a moment, as a layman, lacking all planning qualifications, to say why, like the Prime Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister, I believe that we have so much to learn from Ebenezer Howard and his garden cities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genius of Letchworth, like so many of the most appealing towns and cities, lies as much in the spaces between the buildings as in the buildings themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By resisting the temptation to cram as many houses as possible onto the available land and adopting their golden rule of twelve houses to the acre, Letchworth’s architects, Barry Parker and Raymond Unwin allowed room for the organic intermingling of nature and architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings are buttressed by front and back gardens, the roads are lined with broad verges and trees, the town is criss-crossed with footpaths and patchworked with allotments and parks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ebenezer Howard himself put it, “Parks and gardens, orchards and woods, are being planted in the midst of the busy life of the people, so that they can be enjoyed in the fullest measure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letchworth and the other garden cities work as living, breathing urban communities because, as an Ebenezer Howard put it, they combine “the advantages of the most energetic and active town life, with all the beauty and delight of the country.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way most English people want to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find a way to build places like this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has been holding us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only been planning minister for a few months but I have observed the debate about housing and planning for over ten years and I think I know what is wrong.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trapped in a vicious circle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at the new housing estates that have been bolted on to their towns and villages in recent decades and observe that few of them are beautiful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not to put too fine a point on it, many of them are pig-ugly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Harrisons Wharf in Purfleet that I visited last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure the flats inside are nice enough but they occupy an overbearing and unbroken slab of dismal brickwork that is an insult to the community it borders, cutting it off from a stretch of the River Thames which, in Victorian times, attracted day-trippers from London keen to take a pleasant walk along banks of the river.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since new housing estates are all too often soulless and formulaic, and those who will inhabit them will add to the pressure on local roads, primary school places and doctor’s appointments, existing residents oppose any proposal to build new houses on green field sites, even when the land is of low environmental quality.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities respond to the wishes of local voters by putting too few sites into their local plans. And this drives the cost of development land up to stratospheric levels (roughly £3 million an hectare in the South East and East of England by 2010.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers respond by stuffing as many units as they can onto any site and, in an attempt to make the properties affordable, skimp on room size, architectural features, vernacular materials, communal spaces and landscape design.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, because we don’t build beautifully, people don’t let us build much. And because we don’t build much, we can’t afford to build beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the coalition, and my personal mission as planning minister, is to help us break out of this vicious circle once and for all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get back on to that confident, progressive path, which created Stamford, Edinburgh New Town and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to build beautiful and affordable places once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have we done to bring this about? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles’ first step, in June 2010, was to scrap John Prescott’s blanket density target of 30 dwellings per hectare and to stop the garden grabbing that was destroying the precious green spaces that make Britain’s cities so pleasant to live in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government then embarked on a root and branch reform of the planning system and the creation of the National Planning Policy Framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mammoth task which had to be masterminded by a minister with a mammoth brain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my predecessor, Greg Clark, is blessed with exactly that - as well as the unfailing patience and politeness required to bring the good ship Reform to dock with most of those interested in planning and development still on board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Framework establishes a few clear principles, which it is now my job to drive through.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That local councils should take charge of development in their areas by drawing up local plans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that alongside the power to plan comes the responsibility to provide new houses to meet people’s aspirations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their local plans, councils must bring forward enough land to meet the objectively assessed housing needs of their area over the next 5 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they do so, they will be able to protect precious open spaces against speculative development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Secretary of State and I will back them to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they fail to take their responsibilities seriously, the presumption in favour of sustainable development will fill the vacuum and make the vital decisions that they are ducking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Framework, Grant Shapps introduced the New Homes Bonus, which gives local councils additional money for every new home for which they give planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in what I believe will turn out to be our most revolutionary step, the government launched neighbourhood planning through which villages, parishes and other neighbourhoods can take control of their future and decide for themselves how and where development should take place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be talking more about our ambitions for neighbourhood plans after the Autumn Statement.
So the government has acted to ensure that more land is brought forward for development and that local communities have an incentive to welcome new housing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now for planners, architects and developers, large and small, to seize the opportunity we have created and start designing beautiful places, which local people will welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, on the edge of Bishops Castle in Shropshire, Bob Tomlinson and Carole Salmon set out to create a new, contemporary village, a friendly place that people would want to live.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was The Wintles, 1 of the most exciting and enchanting collection of new houses anywhere in England.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses are all different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are unashamedly contemporary but incorporate vernacular features in a bold and imaginative way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a wide range of both natural and manufactured materials and make a priority of the spaces between the buildings (both private and communal) and the planting of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wintles did not get everything right first time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which experiment ever does?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not as integrated into the rest of Bishops Castle as some long-standing residents would like. And, to replicate it on a large scale, one would need to find a way to build houses that are just as beautiful and just as sustainable but cost less to build.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Bishops Castle I believe that the Living Village Trust created a model for our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which Ebenezer Howard would be proud.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which, once again, we build beautiful new urban landscapes full of affordable houses surrounded by green spaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be our goal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16956</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/measures-to-reduce-bureaucratic-barriers-to-growth-and-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Measures to reduce bureaucratic barriers to growth and infrastructure</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;, currently being considered in Parliament, will help the country compete on the global stage by introducing a comprehensive series of practical reforms that will reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals in the Bill include reducing the number of different consents infrastructure developers require. The government is also consulting on a new streamlined ‘one-stop-shop’ service and on reducing the number of bodies developers need to consult on every application. The proposed reforms will deliver a swifter, more efficient planning process while ensuring interested parties can continue to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms will also open up the fast-track planning process used for nationally significant infrastructure projects to additional types of nationally significant development. It will be open for the first time to business and commercial projects that are important to delivering growth and prosperity and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new types of developments that could be considered under the nationally significant infrastructure system include: manufacturing and major tourism and leisure proposals, office development such as research and development facilities, and warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers would be allowed to request that their application for these nationally significant business projects be determined through the infrastructure planning system which ensures decisions are made within 12 months from the beginning of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations on these two proposed reforms to the major infrastructure planning process were issued today. (See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects"&gt;extending the regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents"&gt;expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital we secure investment in new nationally significant infrastructure and commercial development, and that quicker and better planning decisions are made, if we are to help boost the economy and create the new jobs we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning delays help no one. They bring uncertainty for local people and local firms and can deter new investment all together. By streamlining the planning process to make it quicker and easier for these national significant projects to be decided we can ensure sustainable development gets underway without delay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reforms have already given significant additional powers to councils and communities so they can decide on the scale and location of development in their areas. With this power comes a responsibility to ensure that local planning decisions are efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will also give planning applicants the ability to apply directly to the Planning Inspectorate where there is clear evidence that a council’s planning service is performing very poorly and failing to administer a proper service for both applicants and local residents.  A consultation recently published sets out how these proposals would work, including the basis for assessing performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16487</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nick-boles-attends-launch-of-national-business-competition"/>
    <title>Nick Boles attends launch of national business competition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting Westminster City School, Nick Boles spoke to the winners of last year’s competition and saw the how they invented a winning product by taking part in an online business game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt=" Nick Boles with students" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1125/mosaicwinners2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Nick Boles speaking to students from Southfields Community College, winners of last year’s competition&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;School teams are supported by specialist business mentors to compete through the game, which places them into a realistic business situation in which they must develop and market a new product and respond to simulated business competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The competition aims to promote entrepreneurship and inspire knowledge and enthusiasm about business among young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mosaicnetwork.co.uk/en_gb/portal/enterprise-challenge"&gt;Enterprise Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the department, will this year involve over 3,000 students in 80 schools who will be supported by more than 300 mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Apax-Mosaic Enterprise Challenge is an excellent way of enabling pupils to learn practical business skills such as sales, marketing and finance from within the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fantastic to speak to last year’s competition winners and hear how they have benefited from taking part and how much they enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the Department is supporting this for another year and wish everyone taking part the best of luck.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632046112497/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16040</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-inspectorate-essential-to-new-planning-measures"/>
    <title>Planning Inspectorate essential to new planning measures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government recently announced a number of new measures in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; to reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New planning measures will put the Planning Inspectorate centre stage in ensuring we have a swift and effective planning system that helps boost local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By expanding permitted development rights, cutting red tape and streamlining the planning process we can save householders money and help businesses create jobs and compete.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his first visit to the Inspectorate in Bristol on Thursday, the minister discussed the work of planning inspectors with Inspectorate Chief Executive Sir Michael Pitt and toured the National Infrastructure Division and Planning Appeals Division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14731</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-applicants-no-longer-face-threat-of-double-charging"/>
    <title>Planning applicants no longer face threat of double charging</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New changes to planning laws will ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged a costly planning levy for local infrastructure, Planning Minister Nick Boles has confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possible double charging has been identified by builders and developers as disproportionate and making key development and regeneration proposals unviable that would bring locally-supported homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposed change, applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents to make them feasible without having to pay another &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/planningsystem/communityinfrastructurelevy/"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading British developer Land Securities has announced it will proceed with an estimated £350million scheme that will deliver 2,500 jobs as a result of the proposed changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Stopping this unnecessary double charging is an important step in the Government’s bid to do all it can to get the economy growing by supporting locally-led sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This is just one of many measures we have committed to in order to unblock barriers to growth and to make the planning system simpler and more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy helps support growth by contributing to essential infrastructure.  Funds are raised from developers undertaking new building projects and can be used to fund a wide range of infrastructure that is needed as a result of development, including new or safer road schemes, flood defences, park improvements, green spaces and leisure centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft regulations laid in parliament - and soon to be debated - include measures to stop applicants being charged the levy twice, if they amend existing planning consents through Section 73 of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1956365.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1956365.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16918</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lord-taylor-to-review-practical-planning-guidance"/>
    <title>Lord Taylor to review practical planning guidance</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A government review of planning practice guidance is being undertaken by former MP Lord Taylor, Planning Minister Nick Boles announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor of Goss Moor will lead an external group that will look to streamline some 6,000 pages of practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor has invited Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones to join the group. They will be sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large amount of planning practice guidance currently used - added to over the years and often contradictory - makes it difficult for residents and businesses to engage effectively with the planning system. This review will streamline that practical guidance to make the planning system swifter and more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clearer, reduced set of planning practice guidance will better support growth, help create the homes and jobs that the country needs, protect and enhance our natural and historic environment, and help put power back into the hands of communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review follows the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-planning-policy-framework--2"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; which distilled around 1,000 pages of planning policy into a streamlined, easy-to-understand 47-page document. This guidance review will not involve any changes to national policy set out in the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am very pleased to accept the role of Chair of the review of planning practice guidance. I am determined the review will make a significant contribution to the wider work on planning reform, and the aim to make planning simpler, more transparent and accessible for everyone involved in delivering sustainable development.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The planning system needs to be supported by practical guidance that is clear and easily accessible if it is to be effective. Even planning experts struggle to navigate the 6,000 pages of guidance that currently supports the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Lord Taylor has agreed to lead this review of practice guidance and I look forward to reading the recommendations of his expert group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds,&lt;/a&gt; Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation,&lt;/a&gt; Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/speeding-up-the-planning-process"&gt;terms of reference for the review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
