<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-for-employment-relations-and-consumer-affairs</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-for-employment-relations-and-consumer-affairs.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Employment Relations and Consumer Affairs</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57049</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-boost-for-business-as-government-sets-out-plans-to-update-employment-legislation"/>
    <title>Press Release: Boost for business as government sets out plans to update employment legislation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to collective redundancies rules to help employees and businesses were announced by Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government announced it plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the current 90 day minimum period, before very large scale redundancies can take place, to 45 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legislate to make clear that fixed term contracts which have reached the end of their natural life are excluded from obligations for collective redundancies consultation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce new non-statutory Acas guidance to address a number of key issues affecting collective redundancies consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK has a labour market that is flexible, efficient and fair but some of our laws need reform to respond to an ever changing employment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to improve the quality of consultations by making sure that there are tools available to help employers manage this process fairly and successfully to deliver the best possible outcomes for all parties.  Acas will be working with stakeholders to produce non-statutory guidance that will be designed to help improve the quality of consultations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have listened to stakeholders and there is a strong argument for shortening the minimum period which is backed up by hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The process is usually completed well within the existing 90-day minimum period, which can cause unnecessary delays for restructuring, and make it difficult for those affected to get new jobs quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our reforms will strike an appropriate balance between making sure employees are engaged in decisions about their future and allowing employers greater certainty and flexibility to take necessary steps to restructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement responds to a consultation launched in June and to calls for improvements to the way collective redundancies rules operate and for the processes involved to be made easier to understand. It also forms part of the Government’s commitment to review employment law to support business and concentrate on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replacement of the current 90 day period to 45 days will still allow full employee engagement and offer employee representatives a statutory right to contribute to the process. The new 45 day period will be a minimum period, and businesses may consult for longer where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will be made through secondary legislation. Draft regulations will be laid in the New Year and the changes are expected to be made by 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition government started a systematic review of employment law in 2010. This Employment Law Review (ELR) is now half way through its work and aims to provide clarity, certainty and give businesses the confidence to manage their workforce effectively. The Review sits alongside the Employment Law-related Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulatory burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the government’s response to Collective
Redundancies can be found at
&lt;a href="/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill sets out a comprehensive series of reforms aimed at supporting businesses, developers, and first time buyers by slashing red tape that delays or discourages business investment, development or job creation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe
Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39717</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:53:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/groceries-adjudicator-to-have-power-to-fine-supermarkets"/>
    <title>Groceries Adjudicator to have power to fine supermarkets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Groceries Code Adjudicator is to be given new powers to fine large supermarkets who deal with suppliers unfairly.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competition minister Jo Swinson has today announced that the Groceries Code Adjudicator will be given greater powers to enforce the Grorceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a change likely to be widely welcomed by suppliers and farmers, the government listened to the concerns from stakeholders to give the Adjudicator more teeth to protect suppliers from unfair treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Adjudicator finds that retailers are breaching the Groceries Code and treating their suppliers unlawfully or unfairly, he or she will be able to apply a range of sanctions. In most cases, this would consist of recommendations or ‘naming and shaming’ but, if the breach is serious enough, the Adjudicator will have an immediate power to fine the retailer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Adjudicator is being established after the Competition Commission identified competition issues in their 2008 market study. The Adjudicator will be able to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrate disputes between retailers and suppliers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate confidential complaints from direct and indirect suppliers, whether in the UK or overseas, and from third parties.* &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hold to account retailers who break the rules by ‘naming and shaming’ or, if necessary, imposing a fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jo Swinson said, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The food industry plays an important role in economic growth, and the Groceries Code Adjudicator will help to ensure that the market is operating in a fair and healthy way. Large supermarkets form a big chunk of this industry, and generally provide consumers with low prices and variety whilst providing business for farmers and suppliers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But where supermarkets are breaking the rules with suppliers and treating them unfairly, the Adjudicator will make sure that they are held to account. We have heard the views of the stakeholders who were keen to give the Adjudicator a power to fine, and recognise that this change would give the Adjudicator more teeth to enforce the Groceries Code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We expect fines to be used as a last resort, but the fact that the Adjudicator has the power to impose them will send a strong message to retailers that compliance with the Code is not optional. I am confident that these changes will mean that the Adjudicator is able to ensure fair play in the food supply chain and keep the industry growing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Adjudicator will publish guidance within six months after the Bill comes into effect to propose the maximum amount he or she will be able to fine. Retailers would have a full right of appeal against any fines imposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Groceries-Adjudicator-to-have-new-power-to-fine-supermarkets-68464.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Groceries Adjudicator to have new powers to fine supermarkets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/groceries-code-adjudicator-bill"&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/market-studies/cc-market-investigation-on-the-uk-supply-of-groceries"&gt;Competition Commission Market Investigation on the Supply of Groceries in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/groceriescodeadjudicator.html"&gt;Follow the progress of the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill on the Parliament website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47154</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data"/>
    <title>New power to boost consumers access to data</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Jo Swinson announces new powers for consumers to request their personal customer data from business, under the midata programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;19 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers will be given new powers to request their personal customer data from business, helping them manage their money better and make better lifestyle choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/next-steps-making-midata-a-reality"&gt;consultation this summer&lt;/a&gt;, the Government will announce that it will look to legislate if companies fail to comply with the voluntary release of consumers’ electronic data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;Read the government’s response to the consultation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under new plans, companies would have to release data they hold relating to a consumer’s consumption or transactions in an electronic machine readable format, upon request. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with the power to legislate will be focussed on three ‘core’ sectors: current accounts and credit cards, mobile phones and energy, with further powers to extend the legislation to other sectors if appropriate.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment and Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“‘midata’ is all about putting power into the hands of consumers. Many businesses reap huge commercial benefits from the information they gather from consumers’ daily spending patterns. Why shouldn’t consumers also benefit from this by having access to their own data to enable them to make better choices?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great when your energy provider tells you how much gas or electricity you’re using at any point in the year or when phone companies tell you which one of their tariffs suits you best. But it’s even better when consumers can use that information to get better value for money deals or adjust their lifestyles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is just one of many ways ‘midata’ can help, as businesses increasingly recognise sharing data as a means to deliver a better service for their customers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data/midata-future-10-ways-it-could-shape-your-choices"&gt;A midata future: 10 ways it could shape your choices &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data-68373.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New power to boost consumers’ access to data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;m&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data"&gt;idata - access and control your personal data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;midata review and consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47128</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/next-steps-making-midata-a-reality"/>
    <title>Next steps making midata a reality</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government highlights latest proposals for the groundbreaking midata programme, which aims to give consumers access to their data.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;22 Aug 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;midata is a partnership between the UK government, consumer groups and major businesses. It’s aimed at giving consumers access to the data created through their household utility use, banking, internet transactions and high street loyalty cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing people to access and use this personal data has the potential to open up a wealth of opportunities for consumers and businesses, promoting growth across the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to putting the UK at the forefront of this rapidly developing market. It is currently consulting on introducing a power that, when exercised, would give new rights to consumers to access their personal transaction data in an electronic, portable and machine-readable format. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data/midata-future-10-ways-it-could-shape-your-choices"&gt;A midata future: 10 ways it could help shape our future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer Minister, Norman Lamb said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“midata will allow consumers greater insight into their everyday consumption and lifestyle habits by using applications and intermediaries to analyse their actual behaviours and thereby empower them to make better spending choices and secure the best deals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will boost competition between companies in terms of value and service, and stimulate innovation in new data management tools and systems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We want the UK to be at the forefront of the data analytics and information services market that is rapidly growing with huge international potential. However, it’s crucial that we engage with business and consumers to ensure that we do this in the right way.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2011 the government launched its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2011/Nov/midata"&gt;vision for midata&lt;/a&gt;. 26 organisations signed up to help achieve that vision and today’s review shows that important progress has been made, with participants agreeing core principles about data release, publishing research into customer attitudes and beginning work on important questions of privacy and security.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy sector has blazed the trail, with many suppliers already giving customers electronic access to their transaction data and others to follow soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are encouraging developments but the government believes that the significant advantages on offer for consumers and the economy mean that faster progress to achieve midata’s vision is crucial.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=open"&gt;The midata consultation&lt;/a&gt; explores the option of taking an order-making power to ensure government has the flexibility to act if the voluntary approach proves too slow. We are looking for information to help us get the details right so we can have an effective implementation of midata that will remain relevant in the future. Further consultation would be needed before the power could be exercised through secondary legislation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government welcomes responses from business, consumer groups, regulators and members of the public by 10 September 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Next-steps-making-midata-a-reality-67ef5.aspx"&gt;Press notice: next steps making midata a reality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=open"&gt;midata 2012 review &amp;amp; consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data"&gt;Midata - access and control your personal data&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47563</id>
    <published>2012-07-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-future-of-employment-law"/>
    <title>The Future of Employment Law</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Norman lamb tells the CIPS why the government is changing employment law to benefit both businesses and employees.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for asking me to speak today. I’m sorry I can’t be with you in person, but the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill is currently passing through Parliament and I have to be at today’s Committee session to debate the Government’s plans for reforming employment law.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to begin by paying tribute to the fantastic work the CIPD does to foster high standards in HR management. In a former life I was an employment lawyer and I spent a lot of time working with excellent HR professionals.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, you don’t always get the recognition you deserve, but your work helps to underpin the success of the UK economy in a very real sense. Investing the time and effort that’s required to nurture positive relationships between employers and employees - as all of you do every day - generates real benefits for a company’s bottom line.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis by Aon Hewitt, for example, found that organisations with employee engagement levels above 65% outperformed the total stock market index, and posted total shareholder returns around 22% above average. This indicates that companies which recruit well, treat people properly and invest in developing their employees’ skills will reap the rewards of greater productivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-reforms"&gt;Government reforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Government has an important role to play, too, in ensuring that the UK’s employment law regime operates as flexibly and as effectively as possible. That’s why we are introducing a series of reforms, which safeguard workers’ rights while streamlining the system to reduce the sometimes onerous and unnecessary demands made on employers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexible labour markets are a critical part of a successful economy. It’s essential they function in a way that gives employers the confidence to create new jobs, so people out of work can get that vital first foot in the door.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the framework we inherited contains perverse incentives that can dissuade responsible employers from hiring new staff for fear of the costs and time incurred if it doesn’t work out.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to overstate the problem - according to the OECD, the UK labour market is among the most flexible in the world - but we can’t afford to be complacent, and where we can make it better we should.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller businesses, in particular, have told us the fear of ending up in an employment tribunal is a real disincentive to hiring new staff. The decision to expand is one of the most important steps a growing business ever takes, so if we are serious about job creation we have to strike the right balance between security for the worker and flexibility for the employer.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have doubled the period of time a staff member must have been in post before they can claim unfair dismissal, from one year to two. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="encouraging-recruitment"&gt;Encouraging recruitment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as importantly, we have to ensure that all parties have accurate information about their current rights and responsibilities. No employer should be put off recruiting new staff because of misconceptions about the obligations they would be taking on.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the reason we launched the Employer’s Charter, a simple one-page document that sets out for employers the rights and options they have for dealing with various staff management issues.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also launched an online toolkit for first-time employers which provides a guide to their obligations. It includes information on setting pay, getting the right insurance, understanding tax requirements, and checking a new employee’s right to work in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ending-the-employment-relationship"&gt;Ending the employment relationship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that the vast majority of businesses treat their staff with respect - it is in their commercial interests to have motivated staff and a culture of mutual respect in the workplace.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, however, there will be times when it becomes clear a member of staff is not right for their role. And in those circumstances we want to reduce the number of disputes that go to an employment tribunal each year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be aware that the Government launched a call for evidence on the concept of compensated no-fault dismissal for micro businesses. The CIPD responded to this call, and was by no means alone in highlighting the problems associated with such an approach. We are currently analysing the evidence to see if there might be a case for change, but I have to say I am not persuaded of its merits.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, tribunals are a costly, stressful and time-consuming process for everyone involved. So we are encouraging greater use of mediation as a means of resolving disputes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are setting up two mediation networks in pilot form to explore the potential benefits of this approach. And, in future, all prospective claimants will have to contact Acas before they can lodge a tribunal claim, thereby maximising the chances of an early and agreed solution. The aim is to preserve the employment relationship, wherever possible.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But where relations have broken down, we want to enable all parties to reach an agreed solution, at an earlier stage. Settlement Agreements will allow for no-fault arrangements without the fear that the deal, or the discussions around it, can subsequently be used as evidence of unfair dismissal in a tribunal claim.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will provide employers with model letters, templates and guidance enshrined in a Statutory Code of Practice to encourage the use of Settlement Agreements. However, I want to be clear that no employee can be forced out - agreements will only be binding if they are genuinely voluntary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="employment-tribunals"&gt;Employment tribunals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, however, there will always be those cases that cannot be settled through negotiation. Even in these instances, we believe there is substantial scope for improving the current unwieldy, expensive and delay-ridden system of employment tribunals.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average claim now takes 24 weeks. No wonder some employers, especially smaller firms, choose to settle rather than sacrifice the time and expense required to defend themselves.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are introducing a range of measures to streamline and speed up the tribunals system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judges can now sit alone in hearings for unfair dismissal cases, rather than having to convene a tripartite panel. Witness statements no longer have to be read in full at a hearing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judges can award costs of up to £20,000 to either party. And judges can order the claimant to pay a deposit of up to £1,000, where they consider that claims have little chance of success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Government has consulted on introducing fees for Employment Tribunals. For those with a genuine claim, fees will not be a barrier to justice. But their introduction will encourage claimants to consider their cases carefully, leading to more realistic expectations for individuals and greater certainty for employers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tribunal reforms will mean that employers can once again have the confidence to hire the staff they need to grow and thrive. Of course, that doesn’t mean that all the issues associated with being an employer have been solved at a stroke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="europe"&gt;Europe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the UK’s labour law originates in Brussels, so we are examining whether there is scope for removing or simplify laws that implement European Directives.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this work, we have been examining the rules governing collective redundancies. Lengthy consultation periods are not always necessary, and cause stress, uncertainty, and low morale for employees. Businesses also need flexibility to react to changing market condition. Moreover, it’ clear the UK is out of kilter with most other EU countries, with a much longer consultation period   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have just launched a consultation on a set of proposals, which include developing a new Code of Practice and reducing the minimum timescale from 90 days to 30 or 45 days. Any changes will be implemented from April 2013.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also reviewing the TUPE Regulations, which preserve employees’ terms and conditions when a business is transferred to a new employer. These are complex rules. But we want to see whether we can make improvements whilst remaining compliant with the Acquired Rights Directive. We are currently analysing responses to our call for evidence and will respond soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, we are working hard to ensure proposals from Brussels do not jeopardise the UK’s growth prospects. That includes taking a close look at the existing EU rule book.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An obvious example is how the European Court of Justice has interpreted the Working Time Directive. Most employees do not seriously expect to be given extra annual leave if they happen to fall ill while on holiday. But the court has ruled they have this entitlement.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions of this sort merely pile more burdens on employers and hamper their ability to expand and create new jobs. At a time when businesses are already feeling the pressure this is not a sensible way forward.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as a Government, we are determined to do everything we can to help businesses grow and create new jobs and new economic opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="modern-workplaces"&gt;Modern Workplaces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same commitment- helping people to find work and keep it - also underpins our plans to extend the right to request flexible working, and to modernise maternity leave so it becomes shared and flexible parental leave.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family life has been transformed in recent decades. Most women now go out to work and men shoulder more of the duties at home. As roles and responsibilities have changed, our lives have become increasingly complex.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms will help millions of people juggle their commitments at work with their responsibilities at home. They will also ensure employers are able to recruit from the widest possible pool of talent.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also the thinking behind the decision to abolish the Default Retirement Age, doing away with the outdated notion that anyone who reaches the age of 65 has nothing to contribute economically.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflexible rules that fail to keep pace with the profound shifts we have seen in society serve no one, least of all employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am conscious that I have focused on legislative changes in my remarks today. But I’d like to finish by emphasising that this is just the beginning. We want to see a wider change in the employment relations culture in this country.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A culture that establishes dialogue rather than confrontation as the norm between employers and employees. That trusts people to do the right thing rather than relying on regulation to deal with every single issue that may arise. And that ensures businesses have the confidence to hire the talented and committed workforce they need in order to thrive.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have a way to go to get there. So the expertise of the CIPD and its members will be invaluable, as we work together to modernise employment relations and fuel the economic recovery we are all striving to achieve.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47119</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/modernising-copyright-to-help-strengthen-contribution-to-growth"/>
    <title>Modernising copyright to help strengthen contribution to growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government has announced new legislative measures to update and strengthen the UK’s copyright licensing system.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 Jul 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;New clauses will be included in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform (ERR) Bill to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow the creation of a future ‘orphan works’ scheme to open access to valuable material that currently can’t be licensed or used &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put in place a voluntary regime for extending collective licensing to help reduce complexities in the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reserve a power to introduce statutory codes of conduct for collecting societies if they fail to operate to minimum standards. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government also plans to introduce a power to implement a recent EU Directive on the term of protection for sound recordings in a way that keeps the UK’s current strong criminal penalties for copyright infringement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Norman Lamb said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital that we make the most of our creative industries, boosting their contribution to the economy while ensuring protection of the rights holders. The copyright licensing system has been behind the times and we need to modernise and make it fit for the 21st century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The measures we plan to introduce as soon as possible would make it easier for those seeking access to, and use of, copyrighted works. Freeing up so-called ‘orphan works’ will allow use of works for the first time, making the most of untapped economic and creative potential. Extending licensing arrangements for collective societies, whilst ensuring rights holders are protected, will also help maximise the benefit for the UK’s world-class creative industries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government developed these measures in response to recommendations from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview.htm"&gt;Hargreaves review of intellectual property&lt;/a&gt;. The draft clauses will be published shortly, and will be subject to scrutiny as part of the ERR Bill’s progress through Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the value and making the most of the UK’s intellectual property is a vital element of a vibrant and modern economy. The measures outlined today will form an important part of the Government’s growth strategy, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;Plan for growth&lt;/a&gt;, making sure the UK is one of the best places to start, finance and grow a business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/response-2011-copyright.pdf"&gt;Government’s policy statement: Consultation on modernising copyright&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Modernising-copyright-to-help-strengthen-contribution-to-growth-67c37.aspx"&gt;Full press release: modernising copyright to help strengthen contribution to growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual Property Office &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/pro-policy/consult/consult-closed/consult-closed-2011/consult-2011-copyright.htm"&gt;consultation on proposals to change the UK’s copyright system&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/enterprise-bill/"&gt;Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47101</id>
    <published>2012-06-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/collective-redundancy-rules-to-be-changed"/>
    <title>Collective redundancy rules to be changed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Employment Relations Minister Norman Lamb has published proposals to reform rules for consulting staff about large scale redundancies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;21 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new measures propose a more flexible regime and better consultation with staff. They seek to help companies respond to changing economic conditions. They also improve communication between managers and their staff to reduce uncertainty during the collective redundancy process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation-on-collective-redundancies"&gt;Consultation on collective redundancies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has published a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/c/12-808-collective-redundancies-consultation.pdf"&gt;consultation on collective redundancies (PDF, 298 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;. This outlines the proposed measures and seeks views on a number of proposals by 19 September 2012. The proposals include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing a new, non-statutory, Code of Practice to give clearer information on how to conduct good quality consultations &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reducing the 90-day minimum consultation period for large scale redundancies (over 100 staff) to 45 or 30 days &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the guidance for employers and employees on the support on offer from government &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The changes will mean that employers can restructure more effectively whilst ensuring that employees have access to good quality consultations. This should lead to better decision-making and limit the uncertainty and stress of the redundancy process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister Norman Lamb, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is never easy for employers or employees when redundancy is a possibility, but it’s clear that the current arrangements are not working in the best interests of either staff or managers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our reforms are about improving the quality of consultations - this really is a case of quality over quantity. The call for evidence showed that the current arrangements are not fit for purpose for the modern labour market and I would encourage people with an interest to get involved in the consultation. At present fear and uncertainty can hang over a workforce for three months, sometimes resulting in some of the best employees choosing to leave, even if they would not have ultimately been made redundant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some elements that government proposes to leave unchanged, including the Protective Award. This Award currently stands at a maximum of 90 days’ pay for each employee affected by a failure to consult and is paid by the employer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Collective-redundancy-rules-to-be-changed-A-more-flexible-regime-and-better-consultation-with-staff-a-must-says-Lamb-67b9f.aspx"&gt;Press release: collective redundancy rules to be changed&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;Consultation on collective redundancies: changes to the rules&lt;/a&gt;  - submit your views by 19 September 2012 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/call-for-evidence-collective-redundancy"&gt;call for evidence on collective redundancy&lt;/a&gt; ran from 23 November 2011 to 31 January 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47555</id>
    <published>2012-05-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/post-office-mutualisation"/>
    <title>Post Office Mutualisation</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Norman Lamb provides an update on government progress in implementing its postal services policy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is a great honour to be invited to address your annual conference today. I also welcome the opportunity this has provided for me to meet many of you on an individual face to face basis - last night at the President’s dinner, this morning over breakfast and I hope during the course of the day until I leave after lunch.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still a relative newcomer to my role as Postal Services Minister - having been in post just over three months. Though I feel I am now well up the post office network learning curve, I hope you will bear with me if one or two gaps do emerge during the course of the day.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in my previous Opposition role, I argued strongly for the policy that the Government is now implementing for Royal Mail and Post Office Ltd, in particular their separation to allow each to focus on their complementary, but distinct issues.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very aware that Ed Davey did some terrific work as my predecessor. I am very keen to continue that work and I want to make it clear from the outset that I fully share his commitment to working with the Federation, Post Office Ltd and other key interested parties and to investing in the post office network to safeguard its future.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get into the substance of what I want to say I would like to pay tribute to the important contribution which the Federation has made and continues to make both through its willingness to work with Government to secure a better future for the network and its visionary work to build a mutual post office: To George Thompson - a very effective and tough advocate for sub postmasters and micro businesses; I also enjoyed sitting next to Kym Ledgar and would like to thank her for her year as President and would like to wish Bhavna Desai all the best in her year ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="overview-of-the-last-year"&gt;Overview of the last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year since Ed Davey spoke at your Conference last May has been another significant and eventful one for the post office network.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Postal Services Act received Royal Assent last summer. The Act enables two key steps relating to the network: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the separation of Royal Mail and Post Office Ltd which took effect on 1 April 2012; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scope for mutualisation of Post Office Ltd. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another crucial development in the last year was the signing in January of a new long term agreement between Post Office Ltd and Royal Mail. This agreement cements the commercial relationship between the two businesses for the next 10 years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the framework is now firmly in place to implement the network strategy set out by Government in 2010, backed by the £1.34 billion network funding package.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am Member of Parliament for North Norfolk and therefore fully understand the vital importance of the post office in a rural area. I am also very much aware, from discussions with subpostmasters in my constituency, that many of you still have concerns and uncertainties about the future of the network, your own branch or both. I take those concerns seriously. Just like Ed Davey I have a determination to make this work. I believe in the vital importance of the network - which brings me on to the Government’s policy for the network: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-network-policy"&gt;Government Network Policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s network policy is based on the important social and economic role post offices, and sub post offices in particular, play in the communities they serve.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationally, 20 million people a week visit post offices across the length and breadth of the comprehensive national network, to access vital services. Many of these people - particularly in rural and urban deprived areas - greatly rely on the convenient access to services that their local post office provides.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many communities the Post Office is also the only shop: without the income the Post Office provides that shop would close.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without Government funding, a purely commercial Post Office network would be far smaller than it is today and its services more limited.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the very tough public spending review in 2010, we secured a £1.34 billion funding package to modernise and safeguard the network’s future. Now we have a strategy seeking to put the business on a sustainable footing, where it can develop new business and grow its revenues.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to previous network funding deals under the last Government, this one is not focused on closing branches and shrinking the network. We have ended the culture of managed decline.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made it absolutely clear that there will be no closure programme under this Government. The funding deal requires Post Office Ltd to maintain a national network at around its current size.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The separation of Post Office Ltd from Royal Mail - as provided for in the new Postal Services Act - took effect on 1 April 2012. Post Office Ltd is no longer a subsidiary of Royal Mail but a sister company with equal status under Royal Mail Holdings.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for this separation, a much strengthened Post Office Board was appointed under Alice Perkins as the new Chair. There is now a wide range of commercial and financial expertise reflected among the Post Office’s Non Executive Directors to complement the extensive skills and experience of Paula Vennells and her executive team. So the new Board will be able to provide extremely valuable support and challenge to the management of Post Office Ltd.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separation gives both of the businesses the opportunity and freedom to pursue their individual, and different, business needs and priorities in the future.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said this, the importance of Post Office Ltd and Royal Mail continuing to work closely together is clear. In January, Royal Mail and Post Office Ltd signed a new long term commercial agreement which ensures that the full range of Royal Mail products will continue to be available over Post Office counters throughout the country. This landmark agreement reflects both the clear continuing commitment of each business to the other and also a clear campaigning success for the Federation and your General Secretary’s high profile advocacy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="network-strategy"&gt;Network Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a broad consensus among Government, the Federation and Post Office Ltd, that modernisation and strategic investment is essential to address the underlying economics of the network, and to meet changing customer expectations and market developments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this there are two further core elements to the network strategy: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the building of new sources of revenue from developing financial services and products that people want to use, and winning new work from large customers - particularly Government. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a reduction in operating costs, notably elimination of Crown office losses by 2015, to improve competiveness in bidding for new and repeat contracts. I know many of you feel very strongly about this. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our key objective is the creation of a sustainable financial future for POL and subpostmasters. One new encouraging sign, which I hope augurs well for the task ahead, is that in the year to end March 2012, the net decline in the network was just 2 branches - the lowest reduction in over 25 years. I understand that the option of introducing the Post Office Local model has been a significant factor in this welcome outcome in enabling services to be successfully re-established in communities where there had been a temporary closure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in stark terms, there is now a pressing need for change as the current network model is no longer fit for purpose. But the Government is clear that this must be change where it makes sense - not change for change’s sake. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-reinvigorated-network"&gt;A Reinvigorated Network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compete effectively in a highly competitive and fast changing retail environment, the network must adapt to customer and market demands - longer opening hours, quicker service, and accessible locations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve financial sustainability, the high legacy costs of operating the network and the lack of flexibility in the sub post office operating model are being addressed through two key strands: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main post offices, which will benefit from overdue investment, in larger town and city branches; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Post Office Local concept which offers a more flexible operating model with both customer and retailer benefits. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="network-transformation"&gt;Network Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicle for these changes will be the Network Transformation programme, with rollout planned to start during the summer. Participation in the programme is wholly voluntary for subpostmasters and Post Office Ltd will follow a customised approach on a branch by branch basis. This will provide for face to face discussion of the options available under the programme. Government fully supports this approach. Suggestions of a ‘one size fits all’ approach being adopted for conversion to the new operating models are totally wide of the mark.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federation has played a key role in shaping the structure and terms of the transformation programme - in particular in ensuring its wholly voluntary nature and in the negotiations with Post Office Ltd on the compensation and transitional remuneration terms for those who choose to participate.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do understand that for many subpostmasters there is still a genuine uncertainty about the best choice for their branch. And this may not have been helped by the ‘spoiling tactics’ reflected in the campaigning and lobbying around a parliamentary Early Day Motion which called for a moratorium on conversions to Post Office Local model until after a full national consultation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Early Day Motion and the associated lobbying included misinformation and misrepresentation:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example it was claimed that the Post Office Local model has not been trialled in on-site conversions; and that a much reduced range of services is offered at a Post Office Local.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there has been extensive piloting of Post Office Local over three years and there are now over 170 in total and more than 70 on site conversions &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locals offer 85% of the total network product and service range, accounting for over 95% of total customer transaction volumes &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pilots are continuing - currently there are over 200 operating - and lessons continue to be learned and changes made&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Independent research on the ‘Local’ pilots is showing positive customer and operator responses to date and the continuing pilot phase provides scope for development and improvement of the model. Similarly, much of the media reporting around the Post Office Local model and network transformation, associated for example with Consumer Focus reports have been ill-informed and misleading.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against this background, I am glad that the Federation and Post Office Ltd are continuing to work closely together to progress the network transformation programme. And I very much welcome the role which the Federation will play in programme implementation and your Commercial and Network Director, Mervyn Jones’s membership of Post Office Ltd’s newly established Network Transformation Programme Board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-way-ahead"&gt;The way ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of the network is crucial to the Government’s network strategy and the Post Office business plan which underpins it. But it will clearly be challenging. It involves very substantial changes and it incorporates an unprecedented, but necessary, scale of change covering 6,000 branches over two and half years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore absolutely essential that we get the new operating models and all the details right. So Government fully supports Post Office Ltd’s strategy of extensive and extended pilots to identify what works well and what needs improvement or modification before programme rollout begins.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also recognise that there will be branches for which the new operating models will not be appropriate - including some of those serving very small communities or with only a very limited retail offer. So we are looking carefully with POL and NFSP to see what additional support can be offered to such branches in the way of business development and business consultancy to maximise the opportunities available to them. I believe Paula Vennells in her speech will shortly be stressing how keen she is to ensure that all sub post offices are in a position to tap into future sustainable growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would also emphasise that network subsidy will continue to be available to support branches which can never be profitable but which serve a valuable social purpose. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="network-as-front-office-for-government"&gt;Network as Front Office for Government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting alongside Network Transformation is Post Office Limited’s clear ambition to become a Front Office for Government - a convenient place for citizens to access a number of different Government services, and I, like Ed Davey, fully support the Post Office in this ambition.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a newly expanded, dedicated team in place, Post Office Limited is continuing to work hard to develop competitive, innovative services targeted at both local and central Government that will help them to win new business.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, Government at both the central and local level is looking to make savings whilst maintaining quality services - by putting the user at the centre of its services. A key part of Government’s strategy is to move towards the digital delivery of more services. This is no small task and individual Departments, and the Government Digital Service, have continued to develop their plans over the previous year. Post Office Ltd is rightly engaging with this process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Post Office Ltd’s approach - namely to work with rather than against the inevitable changes in how people access services - is the right one. There is clear potential to build on the existing strengths of sub postmasters to develop new Government services - a great example of this is the need for better, more consistent ID verification that will allow access to online services. Post Office Ltd is working closely with Government’s ‘Identity Assurance’ project to develop the role the network could play in this market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need to help people to access digital services who are currently not confident in doing so - again Post Office Ltd is working with the Cabinet Office, individual departments and others to help scope the role they could play. There will also sometimes be the need to ‘step-out’ of a digital process - for example to check evidence or to capture data as part of an application. Post Office Ltd already plays this role in some processes - for example 10-year-renewals of driving licences - and there is scope to increase this role further.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will also remain important to explore the opportunities for more traditional services, such as those undertaken on behalf of local authorities, for example council tax payment. Post Office Ltd is building on good work jointly undertaken with the NFSP in Sheffield. There are now further pilot studies with 25 local authorities in England and Wales, with Scottish authorities to be added soon, that are examining the scope for working together on more effective and rewarding service delivery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-made-on-front-office-for-government"&gt;Progress made on Front office for Government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building up new revenues, particularly through developing and winning new services, will take time. But Post Office Ltd has made significant progress, and it needs to continue to build on this momentum.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last year’s conference Post Office Ltd had already secured some new contracts. Since then I am pleased that they have gone yet further. For example they recently launched a new service to provide electronic Criminal Records Bureau checks for Care Quality Commission employees. This includes both online and in-branch elements, illustrating the ‘step-out’ role for the post office that I mentioned earlier. Post Office also secured a significant contract to capture electronic data for UK Borders Agency biometric permits.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do appreciate that it has not all been plain sailing - for example the decision made by NS&amp;amp;I to withdraw a number of their products from sale - but am pleased to see the start of a generally positive trend in this direction. Of course, it is vital that we continue to see the Post Office winning more business and there are a number of clear opportunities on the horizon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post Office Ltd will also continue to engage with national Government as it develops its own service delivery plans - for example pilots with Department for Work and Pensions and Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs will feed into wider thinking around how Government can best deliver Universal Credit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there has been much progress at local government level too. There is a new team and fresh thinking at Post Office Ltd who are working hard to prove that the Post Office can help to maintain and improve council services at a time when council budgets are being squeezed. Not only is this good for councils, and the people who use those services; it is good for subpostmasters too, who are benefitting from new work and new customers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last six months, subpostmasters in Westminster have been providing six new services on behalf of the council. And the Post Office was recently successful in winning a competitive tender to provide front office services such as ID validation, bill payment and cash payout services in Hammersmith and Fulham. This particular contract is important as it is a so-called framework contract, meaning that all 32 London Boroughs - covering nearly 700 post offices - can now use the Post Office to provide services without needing to run further procurement processes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am hopeful that the 25 local authority pilots that I mentioned earlier - which are due to conclude later this year - will demonstrate that engagement with local authorities yields real opportunities and value for both the Post Office network and for individual subpostmasters.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keen to hold events around the country next year bringing the Federation and the Post Office together with more Councils to try to apply the lessons and best practice from the current local authority pilots. My ambition is to unlock the ‘triple win’ of savings for local authorities, better access to services for consumers and new services and revenues for subpostmasters.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond Government services, I know that Post Office Ltd is also focused on developing its financial services offering. I share my predecessor, Ed Davey’s view that this is important. The Post Office is a trusted brand, with unparalleled reach into communities. Developing economically viable products that meet customers’ needs will be an important part of the Post Office’s overall strategy. I also believe it is important that customers of all major banks are able to access their accounts over Post Office counters. Last September, access for RBS account holders went live across the network. Demand for that service has been very encouraging. We will continue to make our views clear to the remaining banks - HSBC and some parts of the Santander group - that their customers would greatly benefit from this service.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has rightly also been a focus on whether it is possible for the Post Office to build upon its existing links with a number of credit unions. This makes sense on many levels. To a degree, whether and how the Post Office is able to achieve this will depend upon how the credit union sector itself develops over the coming years. The Department for Work and Pensions recently published a report investigating the possible expansion of the sector. While there is a long way to go, this is an important next step towards understanding how the sector could develop to enable stronger links and more credit union transactions through post offices in the longer term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-a-mutual-post-office"&gt;Building a mutual Post Office&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between us, a huge amount of work is going into making the long term future of the business a sustainable one. Both the prospects of the network transformation programme and the shift to a business strategy focussed on growth and services, give me confidence that the Post Office will have a more positive financial outlook by the end of this Parliament. Which brings me onto my final point: mutualisation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employee ownership is something I am passionate about. Indeed I am grateful to you for allowing the Government to temporarily poach Graeme Nuttall - who I know has in the past advised the NFSP on Post Office mutualisation - to undertake a Government review of employee ownership within the private sector. Graeme will report this summer with recommendations for the promotion of employee owned business that I believe can foster a more sustainable economy that serves the many, not the few.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Postal Services Act requires the Post Office to remain in public ownership or eventually be transferred to a mutually owned structure whose ultimate purpose must be to act for the public benefit. At the end of last year, we consulted the public on proposals to convert Post Office Ltd to a mutual model of ownership. The consultation built on Co-operatives UK’s independent report, proposing a mixed membership mutual of ‘producers’ and ‘consumers’ - so sub-postmasters and staff, but also involving customers or those who represent them, such as Consumer Focus or Age UK.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A response to that consultation will be published shortly, setting out the next steps in developing the model mutual. We recognise that a lot must happen before ownership is transferred. A return to financial stability and commercial sustainability, which will rely upon the success of the network transformation programme and on the Post Office winning more profitable business. And the approval of Parliament, involving a further report by Government and then a vote in both Houses, is required.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But many of the benefits of mutualism can - and I believe should - be adopted by Post Office Ltd in advance of any formal change to the Company ownership structure, if they can support the delivery of the network transformation. And the input of those with an interest in the Post Office, who would form the ultimate membership of a mutual, will be an essential ingredient of that cultural shift.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce today that Post Office Ltd will be setting up a Stakeholder Forum to begin the next steps on the path to mutualisation. It will consist of the key interest groups - bodies representing subpostmasters, staff and consumers - identified in the consultation. Its particular focus will be to work with the company to define the purpose of the Post Office, around which a future mutual could be built. It will be the first example of the Post Office’s stakeholders working collectively to develop the future of the business. And if it is successful it will augur well for the potential of mutual ownership in the long term. The NFSP will have a crucial role to play in representing sub-postmasters within this group. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always held the view that the post office network is quite remarkable - a precious national asset which we have long under-exploited - in the best sense of the word. The network reaches into the most rural locations and the most deprived communities. Our collective challenge is to grasp the potential for the network and to make it a reality   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I am very pleased to have had this opportunity to speak to you all today to provide an update on the progress that has been made in implementing Government policy towards the network over the last year and to set out our ambitions and objectives going forward. I look forward to working with you on all in bringing these to fruition. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47089</id>
    <published>2012-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-groceries-code-adjudicator"/>
    <title>New Groceries Code Adjudicator</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Bill to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets is published in the House of Lords.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 May 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The creation of a new Adjudicator will beef up protection for farmers and suppliers. It will ensure that large retailers treat them fairly by lawfully adhering to the Groceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, it will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrate disputes between retailers and suppliers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate confidential complaints from direct and indirect suppliers, whether in the UK or overseas, and from third parties, to end the ‘climate of fear’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hold to account retailers who break the rules by ‘naming and shaming’ or fining supermarkets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Norman Lamb said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The large supermarkets have a lot of buyer power, and with power come responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Supermarkets will still be able to secure the best deals and to pass the benefits on to consumers, but they should also treat farmers and suppliers fairly and lawfully. This means paying them on time or not being able to scrap arrangements with farmers and suppliers at the drop of a hat.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Free and fair competition is the key to a healthy market and by preventing retailers from transferring excessive risk to their suppliers we will support investment and innovation in the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the long-term, that’s in the best interests of everyone, especially the consumer.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill was introduced into Parliament on 10 May. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/groceriescodeadjudicator.html"&gt;Follow the progress of the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill on the Parliament website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="groceries-code-adjudicator-gca"&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator (GCA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new body is being established to enforce the Groceries Code after the Competition Commission identified competition issues in their 2008 market study. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular it concluded that the market dominance of big supermarkets led to some suppliers being treated unfairly in the UK and overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a retailer is found to have breached the Groceries Code then the Adjudicator would have wide ranging powers to effect remedies such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issuing recommendations to solve the dispute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naming and shaming the offenders by publishing information. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imposing fines (if the Secretary of State considers that the other solutions aren’t working and grants the Adjudicator this power).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-Groceries-Adjudicator-to-protect-suppliers-from-unfair-treatment-by-supermarkets-679e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New Groceries Adjudicator to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/market-studies/cc-market-investigation-on-the-uk-supply-of-groceries"&gt;Competition Commission Market Investigation on the Supply of Groceries in the UK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/food-farm/food/food-industry/"&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs - Food industry, supply chain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18374</id>
    <published>2012-04-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/help-in-hiring-your-first-employee"/>
    <title>Help in hiring your first employee</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New online toolkit provides first-time employers with a step-by-step guide on hiring staff.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.improve.businesslink.gov.uk/resources/tools/taking-employee?furlname=employ&amp;amp;furlparam=employ&amp;amp;ref=http%3A//www.bis.gov.uk/common-employment-myths&amp;amp;domain=www.businesslink.gov.uk"&gt;The Taking on a Employee toolkit&lt;/a&gt; on Business Link takes employers through the process of hiring their first member of staff. It also explains their core legal obligations, and guidance on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information on setting pay. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting the right insurance. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding tax requirements. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking a new employee’s right to work in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;** _ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/employment-matters/employment-law-review/common-employment-myths"&gt; ** &lt;em&gt;Find out about more common myths when employing someone for the first time.&lt;/em&gt; ** &lt;/a&gt; _ **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new tool is part of the Business in You campaign, to encourage more people to start or grow their business throughout 2012 using a range of existing support services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister Norman Lamb welcomed the new guide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For many one-person businesses there is a belief that the process for taking on their first member of staff can be a daunting and overly complicated process. And with no one easily accessible source of guidance it can really feel burdensome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taking on an Employee toolkit aims to tackle this problem and will help empower our sole-traders, our one person businesses, to take that next step.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Red Tape Challenge and the online toolkit we are launching today are just two of the many measures we are taking to tackle employment regulation and to make sure it doesn’t act as a deterrent in hiring staff. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If we can provide the advice and information in a simple format, showing first-time employers that taking on staff can be a simple process, this will ultimately help in our efforts in creating jobs and encouraging growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback during the employment theme on the Red Tape Challenge highlighted that previous guidance and information was too complex and not readily available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Taking on an Employee toolkit aims to tackle these problems, by clearly outlining what an employer must do, why they must do it and how they can comply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Online-tool-simplifies-hiring-demands-for-first-time-employers-678f6.aspx"&gt;Press Notice - Online tool simplifies hiring demands for first-time employers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.improve.businesslink.gov.uk/resources/tools/taking-employee?furlname=employ&amp;amp;furlparam=employ&amp;amp;ref=http%3A//www.bis.gov.uk/common-employment-myths&amp;amp;domain=www.businesslink.gov.uk"&gt;Business Link - Taking on an Employee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/employment-related-law/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge - Employment related law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/employment-matters"&gt;Employment Matters at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
