<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--20</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--20.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and the Lords Spokesman on Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T17:26:33+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45369</id>
    <published>2012-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:26:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-02-norwegian-army-conference"/>
    <title>2012/10/02 - Norwegian Army Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State in Oslo, Norway on Tuesday 2 October 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister, Generals, Madam Chair, Ambassadors, Ladies and Gentlemen, god morgen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be given the opportunity to speak directly to you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing me to stress in person, on behalf of the government of the United Kingdom, how highly we value the defence relationship between our two countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an ex-Army officer myself, I am doubly delighted to be addressing a Norwegian Army audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My old regiment used to train in Norway and valued their experience enormously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand how valuable private to private, officer to officer links are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am particularly keen that our army-to-army relationship flourishes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norway is one of the United Kingdom’s closest and most important partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, Norway is the perfect ally: strategically located, reliable and highly capable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our geographical proximity and our intertwined history means we share significant cultural bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Harold Hardrada to Jens Christian Hauge, the Norwegians from the past who have helped shaped the Britain of today, and helped to maintain our freedom, are many. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We developed our constitutional monarchies and our democracies side by side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cultural similarity has led us to develop similar national values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just constitutionally with our monarchies and democracies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in our shared respect for human rights, freedom of expression and the rule of international law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These concepts are central to our foreign and defence policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the globe is interconnected, and that we cannot live free in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when al Qaeda sheltering in Afghanistan, attacked the US, Norway and Britain answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When piracy staged from Somalia became rife, Norway and Britain answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, when a brutal dictator was murdering his own people in Libya, Norway and Britain answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no doubt that, when future crises emerge, which threaten our national interests and our shared values, Norway and Britain will answer again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this recent cooperation has taught Britain that Norway can be relied upon to contribute to international operations, and that you shoulder that burden with the utmost competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your capabilities are world leading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your central involvement in the Libyan campaign proved this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 3000 mission hours flown and 588 bombs dropped you set a pace that Colonel Ghadaffi couldn’t keep up with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These capabilities make you valuable expeditionary allies and trusted guardians of NATO’s North Eastern flank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when people ask why the UK is so interested in its defence relationship with Norway, I answer them - why wouldn’t we be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the Memorandum of Understanding that our two Defence Ministers signed earlier this year has cemented our bilateral relationship, and provided an important springboard to its future development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being a statement of intent, this agreement also highlights the central tenets of our view of NATO’s Smart Defence initiative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU talks about enhancing interoperability for joint action, coordinating resources to achieve cost-efficiency and sharing knowledge and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In otherwords, working together and saving money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence that is our vision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For in a world of ever-shifting threats, we simply cannot predict what the next mission will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in a world of tightened resources, we cannot afford to independently maintain all capabilities to face all possible missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Smart Defence is not a luxury, it is a necessity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practically, what does it mean? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What actual capabilities might we sensibly consider sharing? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there is a dialogue going on between our two Ministries about this putting meat and muscle on the bone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you a flavour where collaboration can enhance our combined security and should be explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chair of the Standing Committee mentioned our Maritime Patrol Aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is currently looking at options to replace these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might make sense for our two nations to think about pooling resources with regards to this capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do after all patrol some of the same area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least we should consider maximising interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Royal Marines currently make very good use of your winter training facilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts of the British Army also take advantage of the facilities and environment you are able to offer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be that this army-to-army relationship could be developed further by expanding the British Army involvement in this training, particulalry upon the conclusion of the Afghan mission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norway and Britain both have highly trained armies.  We both understand our responsibilities to the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why an obvious area for joint working would be capacity building of developing nations’ armies, particularly in some of the coutries of Sub-Saharan Africa, where we have seen the instability that can arise from security vacuums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my mind capacity-building is also Smart Defence - creating the indigenous capability to prevent problems before they occur, saving lives and money in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take on board the General’s reservations about the Smart Defence Initiative.  We are determined that it must, at its heart, address practical co-operation in the land domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true for Norwegian and British cooperation is also true for collaboration within the Northern Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government sees this group of committed and like-minded defence powers as central to our own plans for Smart Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to take this opportunity to thank Norway for the instrumental role it has played in providing drive and leadership within this group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the Northern Group can provide a critical mass for the modernisation agenda within NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working within this non-institutionally bound framework we can achieve real progress and establish a model for practical cooperation and deployability that others will want to copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think the Northern Group can be used as a forum for sharing best practice and developing new capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country has a monopoly on innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we begin to contemplate our drawdown in Afghanistan, the collective memories of the Northern Group can help to maintain the tough lessons we have learned from that battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, we must sensibly prepare for a post-ISAF environment, we should also think about the future challenges we might be presented with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever operations we are involved in they are likely to require rapidly deployable capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in this area that I think the Northern Group can also take a lead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European members of NATO have rightly been criticised for lacking deployable capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The members of the Northern Group are starting to counter this criticism with deeds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By developing interoperability and allocating our defence resources in a coordinated fashion, we can ensure that Europe is better able to look after its own security needs and take the lead in operations in our sphere of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, the Northern Group strengthens NATO just as the leading group in a cycle race spurs on the rest of the chasing pack to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future I believe the Northern Group will be central to building coalitions of not just the willing, but also the able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aspiration means that the forces of the future must be dynamic and flexible, even if they will possibly be smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings me onto my next topic, the UK’s plans to modernise its armed forces - a project we call Future Force 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because this is an army conference I will go into a bit more detail on the army specific elements of this - or Army 2020 as we refer to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review set out the blueprint for our Future Force 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It analysed the threats that the UK may face in the future and considered how our military would need to be structured to deal with those threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It determined that the UK’s future forces would need to be agile and interoperable across services and with allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, however, it also concluded that those forces and the equipment they used would have to be sustainable - in personnel terms, but also in funding terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to be able to say, that after some very hard decisions, we have now achieved a balanced equipment budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we can manitain and with confidence, the powerful, adaptable and agile Armed Forces that our national security demands.  And that our role in the international community requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within that, Army 2020 is the blueprint for our new Army. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will deliver a new structure designed to meet the needs of a smaller, but more flexible Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well trained, well equipped, and crucially, fully funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a smaller Army will necessitate some changes in structure, and some units will be merging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have done everything we can to maintain the Army’s traditions and sense of its own history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will remain one of the very few countries able to deploy and maintain a brigade-sized force almost anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key elements of this new structure are the Reaction and Adaptable Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reaction Forces will comprise three Armoured Infantry Brigades and 16 Air Assault Brigade, trained and equipped to undertake the full spectrum of intervention tasks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be responsible for generating a Lead Armoured Infantry Battlegroup and Lead Air Assault Group, capable of undertaking short notice contingency tasks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the high readiness nature of the Reaction Force, it will comprise mainly Regular Forces with approximately 10 per cent coming from the Reserve Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reserve Forces will play a more important role across our Future Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade some 25,000 members of the reserve have served in Iraq or Afghanistan, including over 18,000 members of the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to integrate Reserve Forces more fully into our Regular structures, growing Reserve capabilities and investing an additional £1.8bn in over the next ten years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these changes will take time to implement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the process we will have a leaner and formidable Army. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have maintained the ability to act unilaterally, but we also intend, as a matter of priority, to seek opportunities to work with the Norwegian Army and other partners, particulalrly in the areas of training, capability development and resource sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conlcusion let me say this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norway has been a steadfast ally to the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brothers in arms on the ground in Afghanistan, at sea off the Horn of Africa and in the air over Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust is at the centre of all strong alliances, and Norway has demonstrated time and time again that it is more than worthy of our trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK hopes to continue to repay that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK sees Norway as a vital defence partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, and as members of the wider Northern Group, I believe we can turn Smart Defence from theory into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in today’s multipolar world, with unpredictable threats and unpredictable markets, it is essential that we do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18760</id>
    <published>2012-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T10:48:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-22-the-maritime-security-challenge"/>
    <title>2012/03/22 - The Maritime Security Challenge</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at the Jakarta International Defence Dialogue on Thursday 22 March 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom has long historical connections and many close partners here in Asia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me these connections are personal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young officer in the British Army I served here in the Far East in the late nineteen sixties. And have returned many times since with my family to visit and explore this fascinating region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen with my own eyes how much has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen the dynamism of the people channelled into the economies of the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen rapid change, skyscrapers grow, and the region take its rightful place as a key centre of global power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some in Europe like to talk rather patronisingly about ‘developing’ economies here - but there are twice as many of the top 30 richest cities in the world in this region compared to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This region as an economic powerhouse and the countries here are now taking up the global responsibilities that this economic clout brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because with power comes responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this era of interconnectedness and volatility, no country, no matter how rich, can hope to provide for the security of its citizens by working alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnership is a necessity not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the responsibility of power is a responsibility to collaborate and find shared solutions to shared problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some areas we need to work together are contemporary - such as Cybersecurity, which I am glad to see on the Conference agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others - such as maritime security - are enduring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-maritime-security-matters---global-economic-dependency"&gt;Why Maritime Security Matters - Global Economic Dependency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an island nation like Britain, with a long maritime history, just like many of the nations in this region, the sea is our blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intrinsically recognise the reliance we have on a rules-based management of our use of the High Seas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in this digital age of fast, cheap air travel, 90% of world trade by value and 95% by volume is carried by sea, as is over half the world’s oil production. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in South East Asia an estimated 50,000 vessels are passing through the Malacca Strait every year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And 40% of the world’s trade passes through the South China Sea -and set to increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National, regional and, indeed the global, economies continue to be dependent upon the freedom of the seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the tyranny of geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such is the global dependence on goods and energy passing through the region that if the critical sea lanes were disrupted for any significant time, the effect would be catastrophic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Peter Hinchcliffe - the Secretary General of the International Shipping Federation said, ‘half the world would starve and the other half would freeze’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the case for working together is self- evident - we all require security and no-one can provide it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upholding the Rule of Law is absolutely key. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a country’s trade transcends its strategic reach, it relies on international norms of behaviour for planning and reassurance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those norms are provided for under the UN Convention of the Law of the Seas - UNCLOS - whether by demarking territorial limits, economic zones, international straits, lifesaving responsibilities or rights of innocent passage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those norms are disregarded to the peril of us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the sea can bring us all prosperity, failing to resolve our differences in accordance with those norms, can only bring strife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how should we manage security in the High Seas? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="collaboration-with-a-purpose"&gt;Collaboration with a Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we should look at what works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in South East Asia you have shown the world how well co-ordinated action can prevent pirate attacks on global shipping. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade ago the Straits of Malacca were a popular hunting ground for pirates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indonesia, Malaysia, Singapore and Thailand came together to implement a range of collective measures, such as intelligence sharing and co-ordinating sea and air patrols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the situation has vastly improved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Off the Horn of Africa, the international community is learning from your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contribution from this region to tackling piracy there has been fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coalition Task Force 151, which is combating piracy through the Gulf of Aden and the Eastern Indian Ocean, has previously been commanded by New Zealand, Pakistan, the Republic of Korea and Singapore. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ten days Thailand will assume command of Coalition Task Force &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s Royal Fleet Auxiliary Fort Victoria is proud to serve as the command platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy plays an active role in both CTF 151 and the EU’s Task Group and it plays a command role in the Coalition Forces Maritime Component Command in Bahrain, where many nations, whether part of the coordinated activity or acting unilaterally, have lodged liaison staff. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the success of the Multi-national Straits Security Initiative and the international action to tackle piracy in other waters has shown that collective action delivers results. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Regional Co-operation Agreement on Combating Piracy and Armed Robbery Against Ships in Asia (ReCAAP) has been similarly successful in safeguarding merchant shipping; I am pleased to see that its tenure has been renewed  for another 5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Membership continues to grow beyond the region and the UK has joined Norway, Denmark and the Netherlands as extra-regional members. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of co-operation extend beyond security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional security operations help build trust and encourage communication and information sharing between nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="multi-layered-security"&gt;Multi-layered Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mature organisation, designed to promote co-operation, ASEAN has the potential to be a platform developing consensus and to help drive regional security collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But such organisations are simply an expression of the political will of the nations who are members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the political will of its members to build capacity that is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the United Kingdom is keen to do to provide practical help in the development of a cohesive and proactive ASEAN. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do not believe that security is served by an approach of putting all your eggs in a single basket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that an approach which provides for multi-layered security -multilateral organisations like ASEAN supported by smaller group co-operation and bi-lateral relationships that can be swifter to act, more flexible in approach and generate real deployable capabilities in a crisis situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A building block approach to security, including maritime security, will ensure that collaboration is not held back by the lowest denomination but driven forward by best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the UK is a proud member of the Five Power Defence Arrangements which is the cornerstone of our defence engagement in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t just about old friendships, as important as they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about new friendships too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why Britain is increasing its defence engagement around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 18 months, we have signed three Defence Treaties and 33 Memoranda of Understanding, including with traditional partners like Australia and New Zealand but also with Asian powers such as India and new friends in this region such as Vietnam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a measure of the importance the UK places in our defence relationships and in the region as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion, we in the United Kingdom are natural allies for any country who seeks to bring security to the sea lanes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the well spring of our own prosperity, and our security, is stability in the High Seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, in the Royal Navy, we continue to invest in some of the best and most capable ships ever to have graced the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we recognise that no man is an island - and security can only be guaranteed by working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this region of economic dynamism and power countries are co-operating as their interests demand, in maintaining the freedom of the seas and protecting the free movement of goods upon which our citizens rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is part of that collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we recognise that how the nations of this region manage their security, stability and prosperity will impact far and wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the 20th Century has been called the “American Century” increasingly people are calling the 21st Century the “Asia-Pacific Century”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens here matters - not just for the region but for the world as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier - with power comes responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this region consolidates as a global power centre, so will the nations of the region have to shoulder their share of upholding international security and stability - based on the rule of law and peaceful co-existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to maritime security, the world needs YOU - it is YOUR future, just as much as it is ours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18745</id>
    <published>2011-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:51:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-25-sultan-of-oman-s-armed-forces-association-annual-dinner"/>
    <title>2011/11/25 - Sultan [of Oman]’s Armed Forces Association Annual Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at the Army and Navy Club, London on Friday 25 November 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your Excellency, General Achmed, My Lord, members of the Sultan’s Armed Forces Association and honoured guests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a privilege to say a few words at tonight’s annual dinner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet at a time of great change and great uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War in Afghanistan; revolution in North Africa; unrest in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bin Laden and Gaddafi are dead; Mladi? and Mubarak are on trial. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has faced nuclear disaster in Japan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s confronting financial disaster in Europe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times like these, it is only natural to look to one’s allies and friends for support - for reassurance - for solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and Oman have been tried and trusted friends for many years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have shared values, shared interests, and shared history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Association is a fine example of the links that bind us together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m proud to have a strong, personal connection to Oman through my late godfather, Colonel David Smiley. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you will know, David was the first Commander of the Sultan’s Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His stories of British servicemen and Omanis fighting side by side made a deep and lasting impression on me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It taught me that there is nothing like shared sacrifice to bind people together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s what makes this Association so special. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the Association was formed in 1968 at a time of great difficulty for Oman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A time when the country was seeking a new unity and a modern identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A time when the struggle against the Dhofar rebels and communists was going badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A time when Oman needed the support of its friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What turned things around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enlightenment of His Majesty Sultan Qaboos bin Said in the progressive policies he pursued; the transformation of the Sultan’s Armed Forces; and the support of friends like Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the foundations of the modern, peaceful, and prosperous Oman the world sees today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the process of reform and modernisation rarely lets up - political stagnation is just as dangerous as social and economic stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the responsible way that His Majesty is responding to the Arab Spring is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But tonight I want return to that successful struggle in Dhofar, because the lessons of 40 years ago do have strong resonance with the security challenges we face today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many factors contributed to that success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me pull out just three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there was an active, reforming, modernising Government which recognised it had to earn people’s loyalty, not just expect it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it was accepted that fighting an insurgency is about people not territory - hearts, minds, and livelihoods were the key to making sure that the Jibalis looked to the Firqat not the Adoo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, it was imperative that the counter-insurgency was progressively led by Omanis for Omanis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this sounds familiar, it’s because many elements of the counter-insurgency strategy pursued by the SAF in Dhofar read across to Afghanistan today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Stirrup made much the same point in his excellent article in the latest SAF Association Journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From your own experience, you know that a successful counter-insurgency requires mass which can only be provided by an outside force for so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it requires indigenous security forces that are effective and trusted by the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires a re-integration and reconciliation process that can only be successful if it truly addresses people’s legitimate hopes for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And most of all counter-insurgency requires patience - and an ability to keep faith during the difficult periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons of the past continue to influence the warfare of today, even as the character of modern warfare evolves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just as it was 40 years ago, the requirement for friends, allies and partners remains essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we in Britain value our friendship with Oman as highly as we ever have. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years both sides have acted to boost the already high levels of interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Queen’s hugely successful state visit to Oman last year to the delegation we received in London this week and the attendance here tonight of so many friends from Oman -relationships are blossoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Achmed, you know how much my wife and I enjoy visiting the Sultanate and catching up with our friends there - it really is a stunningly beautiful place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And General, I treasure the COSSAF cuff links and tie that you gave me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wear them often and proudly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence co-operation remains the underpinning foundation of our friendship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many Omanis attend prestigious courses such as RCDS; Dartmouth; Cranwell; and Sandhurst, as His Majesty the Sultan did before them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They typify the professionalism of the Omani Armed Forces - well trained and highly motivated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Loan Service Personnel in Oman, our largest team deployed anywhere in the world, now advise and discuss issues, rather than instruct or implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not just about personnel exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We train together; we collaborate on equipment; we share views on emerging threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent successful cyber conference in Muscat is an example of the new thinking for the new security environment that is taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain listens with great attention to what Oman has to say. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation in Yemen or Iran, security in the straits of Hormuz, and tackling the scourge of modern piracy, to name but a few areas of joint concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent pirate attacks, almost within hailing distance of the port of Salalah, show what a direct threat this poses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both our countries have worked hard to maintain and build on the firm relationship we now enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friendships like ours are sustained by renewal each generation, by the constant exchanges of people, ideas, and goods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the personal contacts that make for good business and good relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only with those face-to-face relationships that we can share ideas, be honest and open, confront and resolve misunderstandings, and deal with any difficulties that might cloud even the best of friendships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank everyone here tonight for your contribution to that process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular I would like to pay tribute to the hard work of the SAF Association, not only for keeping memories alive, but by forging new relationships with new generations and boosting links at government and at a social level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the camaraderie born out of service in the Sultan’s Armed Forces will continue to enrich all your lives and ensure that the unbreakable bonds between our two great nations flourish long into the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18741</id>
    <published>2011-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:14:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-07-armed-forces-parliamentary-scheme"/>
    <title>2011/11/07 - Armed Forces Parliamentary Scheme</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at the Palace of Westminster, London on Monday 7 November 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Sir Neil [Thorne, Founder of the Armed Forces Parliamentary Scheme] for that kind introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to see some familiar faces - not least Lord McColl and the former Defence Minister, Lord Bach - and to see so many new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted to see Colonel Bob Stewart, who’s brought his distinguished military background to bear on the House of Commons Defence Committee with such aplomb. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s vital that the relationship between our Armed Forces and the communities they’re drawn from is as strong as possible.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s vital that Parliamentarians understand and appreciate the work our Armed Forces carry out on behalf of the nation so they can convey that message to the general public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Parliamentary Scheme - led by Sir Neil and Lady Neil and now in its 23rd year - can help with both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first take the relationship our Armed Forces have with the rest of society.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one level, our Armed Forces are rooted in local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the British infantry system of county regiments helped to forge deep ties between those who serve - often alongside neighbours and friends - and the communities they left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At another level, our Armed Forces are woven into the fabric of our nation’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson on the quarterdeck; the Pals on the Somme; the SAS on TV as they stormed the Iranian Embassy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage, sacrifice, excellence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the British public have a deep respect for, and pride in, our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But respect and pride are not the same as understanding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces Community may be an integral part of our society, but in recent decades that link has declined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When World War II ended in 1945, there were around five million men and women in uniform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone in the country knew someone close who had served. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up learning about my father’s service in that war, just as he grew up learning about his father’s service in World War I; my son hopes to follow in my footsteps.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Service generation added to this huge number of people with direct experience of military experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our Armed Forces have been a professional, volunteer force for many years while the older generations have inexorably dwindled. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public understanding of our Armed Forces has declined as a result. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this matters hugely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces rely on the support they receive from the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They look to you, as Parliamentarians, as a weather vane. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when they see the benches deserted during Defence debates, they inevitably see indifference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when they see Parliament welcoming home units of the Armed Forces - as we did last week with 3 Commando - they are re-assured that Parliament genuinely does care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps them stand tall as they deal with the daily challenges they face. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the Armed Forces Parliamentary Scheme really comes into its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your participation will inevitably enhance the quality of debate, regardless of political hue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will mean a more informed Parliament making more informed decisions about Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if this results in positive outcomes for our Armed Forces -  such as the principles of the first ever Armed Forces Covenant being recognised in law - then that’s a win-win situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s in everyone’s interest that our Armed Forces are understood and appreciated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces, their families, and veterans look to all of us in public leadership for strong advocacy of the sacrifice they’ve made on our behalf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They need Parliamentarians to understand and appreciate the high operational tempo and the rapidly evolving threat environment in which they operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They require and deserve informed Parliamentary oversight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on behalf of the Ministry of Defence, I want to thank all of you for making the effort and sparing the time to take part in the Armed Forces Parliamentary Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18740</id>
    <published>2011-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:13:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-03-wolfe-society-dinner"/>
    <title>2011/11/03 - Wolfe Society Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State in 
Westerham, Kent on Thursday 3 November 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr President, thank you for that kind (and accurate) introduction - I was once introduced as Lord Astor of Heaven! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the names of peers do sometimes make good stories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lord Hart was given a peerage, he received many letters with suggestions for his new title. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was from a Scottish football fan who asked him to include Midlothian, so there would be constant references in Hansard to his team, Heart of Midlothian!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to see so many Officers representing the Naval and Military members of the Wolfe Society.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m very grateful to John Rawlinson for helping me with some of the General Wolfe aspects of this speech. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discussed possible themes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Remembrance Sunday just round the corner, John suggested a comparison might be made between two well-known Generals, Wolfe and the First World War leader, General, later Field Marshal, Haig. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe’s father was an elderly half pay Lieutenant Colonel who had moved south seeking influence at the heart of government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both parents lived to old age, the General’s father dying at 72, just six months before the death of the young General at Quebec. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young man never achieved financial independence; throughout his life his letters are interrupted with frequent requests to his parents to send more money!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe was closest to his mother, Henrietta. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never escaping her influence, the only rift between them came with the search for a suitable bride. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pragmatic mother seeking a financially advantageous match with Miss Hoskins of Croydon, the romantic Wolfe seeking a love match, first with Elizabeth Lawson, and later with Katherine Lowther. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Wolfe was never to marry, travelling to Quebec shortly after his engagement to Miss Lowther.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although lost to Wolfe, Miss Hoskins wasn’t lost to Westerham, marrying the eldest son of the Warde family, our President this evening being one of her descendents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does James Wolfe - a hot-headed, young maverick given command of an expeditionary force of 12,000 men sent to unlock the gateway to North America - connect with the Field Marshal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the face of it the differences outweigh the similarities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douglas Haig was the establishment General, entrusted with command of the biggest military undertaking our nation had known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to Wolfe’s pecuniary difficulties, Haig was from a wealthy family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both parents died when Douglas was just 18, leaving him an independent wealth but without the guidance and support of strong parents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young man looked to his elder sister, also called Henrietta. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years his senior, she provided this support and guidance, and in later life lobbied to promote her brother’s career.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Romantically, the independent Haig did better than Wolfe, marrying the daughter of Lord Vivian. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had four children, one of whom was my mother.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig was educated at Clifton and Oxford, and went on to Sandhurst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His room-mate there, General Sir Walter Congreve, VC as he would become, was already a man not to be trifled with - he had been sent down from Oxford for shooting at his don with an air-gun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fellow cadet later shot his mother-in-law and her lawyer in a drame passionel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast Wolfe’s education was less formal, initially here in Westerham and, after the family moved to Greenwich, at an academy for the sons of naval and military officers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe was to feel his lack of education throughout his life, taking time whilst on garrison duty in Glasgow to study Latin and mathematics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later he successfully sought special leave to travel to Europe to undertake military studies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not unaware of his lack of social graces he spent time in Paris, in an attempt to ‘round his character’, visiting Versailles and being presented to Louis XV and Madame Pompadour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig learnt his profession in the wars at the edge of the empire, in the Sudan, South Africa, and India. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe learnt his skill fighting on the battle fields of Europe very much at the birth of the empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the similarities between Wolfe and Haig are also striking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig’s criticism of Kitchener’s strategy during the Sudanese war, and Wolfe’s private comments on Mordant’s performance at Rochefort, suggest that, as young soldiers, neither was afraid to voice their opinions of inadequate leadership, and both were confident in their own military knowledge.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both earned rapid promotion for meritorious war service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe rising to the rank of Major General aged just 32.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig was the youngest Major General in the army when he was promoted to that rank aged just 43.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig understood the importance of the welfare of his troops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just in later life when he lobbied for rights for demobbed soldiers and set up the British Legion and the Haig Poppy Fund. Even in the darkest days of the First World War, tiny details didn’t escape him; he was responsible for ensuring dentistry services were available for the men.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe also knew the importance of welfare, ensuring his troops brewed spruce beer to avoid scurvy; issuing detailed instructions on camp layouts to prevent the spread of disease and ensure the men were fit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his death, Wolfe’s mother also took a hand in soldier’s welfare, creating a fund for the children of injured veterans of the Quebec campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The residue of this fund was used to help found the Hibernian Military School.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe stood his ground against established military doctrine; despite the threat of a court martial adopting the Prussian drill to train his infantry soldiers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst these tactics were to prove decisive at Quebec - just two volleys seeing off the enemy - his success came more through innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the aborted raid on Rochefort in 1757, he set out the principles needed to launch a combined operation, emphasising the importance of army and navy commanders working in unison. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He understood the need for new landing craft to allow rapid disembarkation of troops and, most important, that his soldiers be drilled in the use of these boats.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering 3,600 well-trained, well-equipped, disciplined and motivated men to a battlefield 3,500 miles away from home was no easy task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing so two and a half centuries ago would mark Wolfe out for immortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His finest hour was no accident. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quebec was a victory built on an understanding of what the troops were capable of, how to deploy new technology on the battlefield, and the co-operation between arms.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig also had to bring new understanding to the battlefield at the darkest hour of WW1 - the German advances of March 1918 and the ‘backs to the wall’ speech. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as at Quebec, the 100 day offensive - the advance to the Hindenburg line and ultimately the German surrender - was also no accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the infusion of American troops was an incredible tonic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the development of military doctrine within Haig’s forces was also critical.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gone was the idea of going over the top without aerial reconnaissance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more would men advance beyond the artillery barrage and armour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanks would now support the advancing infantry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly-arrived Americans, eager to make their mark, would learn these lessons the hard way, as the French and British had done over the previous four years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite political resistance and pressure to stop his advance Haig fought on, ensuring the war in France and Flanders did not extend into 1919.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Haig would be associated with the earlier strategy of attrition and the huge loss of life on the western front as much as final victory and post-war benevolence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But both Wolfe and Haig left positive legacies too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfe - for his understanding of combined operations and his ability to discipline and train his men to new tactics and technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haig - for his ability to adapt and develop a strategy of attrition into one of co-operation between artillery, aeroplanes, tanks, and infantry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now turning to the period in which we are living, despite the reasons for his resignation, I think that Liam Fox will leave a lasting legacy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked closely with Liam, both in Opposition and in Government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has always been a passionate and intelligent advocate for the Armed Forces, and for the robust defence of our national security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He showed decisive leadership - not just in Libya where our forces have made a magnificent contribution in the liberation of that country.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also in taking many of the tough decisions required to put our Armed Forces on the road to a sustainable future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was under no illusions: if you want first class Armed Forces you need a first class economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no future for a big military supported by a small economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was one of the central lessons of the Cold War. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the new Armed Forces we are developing and equipping must be built on firm foundations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, with a force structure that is fit for the challenges of future warfare and the real world risks we are likely to face. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, with a Defence programme that is affordable now, and sustainable into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why unpicking last year’s Strategic Defence and Security Review is simply not an option.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why our new Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, has been clear that he looks forward to the challenge of completing what Liam started. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liam Fox was able to secure agreement from the Treasury that we could plan on the equipment and support budget being increased by 1% a year in real terms between 2015/16 and 2020/21. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing so has allowed us to place contracts knowing we will have the money to pay for them - an obvious notion I know, but sadly lacking in recent years! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, last week we announced a £1 billion upgrade of the British Army’s Warrior armoured vehicles, which will extend their service life to 2040 and beyond. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, military effectiveness is built not only on economic success; it is built on people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us in the Ministerial team are lucky to be working with the bravest, most selfless and professional people the country has to offer - the men and women of our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are supported by some of the most dedicated people in the wider public service, the most highly skilled workforces in British industry, and some of the most committed people in the charitable sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is a very human endeavour, and the consequences of service life are very human too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time we’ve brought into law the Armed Forces Covenant which sets out formally what all of us here know to be true. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces are the greatest assets we have, and the whole nation owes them a lifelong debt of gratitude. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your President asked me to end on a lighter note. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was kind enough to mention my father. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things I inherited from him was a file with amusing stories for every occasion he would encounter as Lord Lieutenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try out a couple of these about Foreign Secretaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First Austen Chamberlain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a luncheon given in his honour, things began to go amiss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chamberlain did not notice that the butler was drunk but his hostess did. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She scribbled a note and gave it to the butler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It read ‘You are disgustingly drunk. Leave the room at once.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The butler read the note, smirked, placed it on a silver salver and, walking unsteadily, handed it with a deep bow to the Foreign Secretary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He read it with some surprise, but, being a perfect gentleman, did as instructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another is about Lord Curzon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foreign Secretary he attended the 1922 Lausanne Conference accompanied by a new valet, who turned out to be drunk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His antics culminated in the ballroom of the Beau Rivage Hotel in which, wearing Lord Curzon’s evening clothes, he reeled around with delegate’s wives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly the valet was sacked on the spot and ordered home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In revenge he made off with all the Foreign Secretary’s trousers, leaving him in his pyjamas just one hour before the beginning of this important conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, the first person I sat next to at lunch in the House of Lords was Lord Franks or Sir Oliver Franks as he was when Ambassador in Washington after the war. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after his arrival, he was asked by a local radio station what he would like for Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Oliver was very touched. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being a man of frugal tastes he said it was very kind of them to ask and what he would really like would be a small box of crystallised fruit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Christmas Day, the radio station broadcast the results of its enquiries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked what he would like for Christmas, the French Ambassador replied, “peace for all mankind.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Soviet Ambassador, “freedom for all people enslaved by injustice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There then came the polite voice of Sir Oliver - asking for a small box of crystallised fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me tonight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18716</id>
    <published>2011-06-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:32:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-06-25-armed-forces-day--3"/>
    <title>2011/06/25 - Armed Forces Day</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at Lingfield Park Racecourse, Surrey on Saturday 25 June 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Lord Lieutenant, High Sheriff, Chairman of Tandridge DC, President of Surrey RBL, Chairman of Surrey RBL, Canon Peter, thank you Peter for those kind words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an honour to be here at Lingfield Park Racecourse to celebrate Armed Forces Day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With members of our Armed Forces who represent the very best that this country stands for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With their friends and family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with veterans whose service we will never forget and always honour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I particularly want to mention the Royal Anglians by name. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I congratulate them on their turn out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are based in Pirbright, Surrey and will be going out on their second tour of duty to Afghanistan early in the New Year, and I wish them the best of good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the day when the rest of us can show our patriotic support for all these heroes, and their outstanding contribution to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because in this country, the respect we have for our Armed Forces is deeply embedded in our national make-up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up learning about my father’s service in the Army, just as he grew up learning about his father’s service in the First World War. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few families who are not touched in some way by our Armed Forces - even simply by taking pride in the work they do to defend us.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what all of us recognise - and what links the generations -  is that those who serve stand for honour and sacrifice; they put themselves after others; their country before self. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South East of England has a proud military tradition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portsmouth is the historic home of the Royal Navy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aldershot is the home of the British Army. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skies above the South-East were our front-line during the Battle of Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, many of those from all three Services in the South-East are on the front-line once more - in operational theatres worldwide, often in difficult and dangerous conditions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So behind the flags, parades, and other events up and down the country to mark Armed Forces Day, we should remember that, as we speak, in this country and overseas, these brave people are putting their lives on the line - on the ground, in the air, and on the oceans - to keep us safe and to build a better world for our children. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also remember that each one of our soldiers, sailors, and airmen is also a wife or a husband; a father; a mother; a son or a daughter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do not choose this vocation for an easy life, and the pressure on their families is considerable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank all those who support their loved ones in the Armed Forces - through good times and bad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget that 15% of today’s Armed Forces are Reservists who, time after time, have come to Britain’s aid, and remain integral to the future of Britain’s Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor should we forget the Cadets, or the adult volunteers behind them to show the virtue of commitment and the rewards of success as our youngsters prepare for life as responsible citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, those serving in our Armed Forces will one day move into the larger family of veterans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Day is a celebration of our veterans’ community too, whatever their age. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means everyone from the 20 and 30 year-olds who have returned from operations in Afghanistan in their prime of life and are seeking new challenges, to the older veterans who are part of our nation’s living history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They all have so much to offer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are a constant reminder to younger generations that preserving our way of life and the things we hold most dear is sometimes hard won, and never guaranteed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the marks of any civilised nation is the way it supports and respects those who fight for their country, and their families. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are an integral part of who we are as a nation, and an inspiration to us all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us honour that commitment by showing our support today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18705</id>
    <published>2011-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T14:20:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-03-10-sandhurst-foundation-dinner"/>
    <title>2011/03/10 - Sandhurst Foundation Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at the Sandhurst Foundation Dinner, Goodenough College, London on Thursday 10 March 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commandant, ladies and gentlemen, good evening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Patrick, thank you for that kind introduction - Lord Astor of Heaven! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the names of peers do sometimes make good stories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lord Hart was given a peerage, he received many letters with suggestions for his new title. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was from a Scottish football fan who asked him to include Midlothian, so there would be constant references in the House of Lords to his team, Heart of Midlothian! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to thank the Sandhurst Foundation and the Inspirational Development Group for organising tonight’s event, and for the wonderful hospitality we’ve all enjoyed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We look to Sandhurst - and to Dartmouth and Cranwell too of course - to mould and inspire the men and women who will be the future leaders of Defence; and to the Foundation as a treasure house of sought-after experience and wisdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And IDG, working in partnership with Sandhurst, enabling them to combine commercial awareness with the operational expertise that the Army has been honing for over 200 years, to develop leadership, fellowship and partnership skills within individuals and organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, we have just had a Strategic Defence and Security Review - the SDSR - and the challenge now is, with fewer resources, to use all the available talent to transform Defence -  while fighting hard in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Achieving these things requires real leadership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that just getting into Sandhurst is often a stern test of initiative and resolve for our future military leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Henry Wilson, who was later to become Chief of the Imperial General Staff, failed the entrance exam three times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General JFC Fuller - perhaps one of Britain’s few great military theorists - was sent to a crammer to learn off-by-heart the answers to 12 questions that were likely to come up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They came up, and he posted a record score of 497 out of 500, perhaps underlining how time spent on reconnaissance is seldom wasted! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Montgomery barely scraped in - a fairly undistinguished record he shared with my grandfather - Field Marshal Haig. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earl Haig, as he would become, also took the crammer option, spending six months in one before going to Sandhurst. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there he found himself having to spend long periods ‘swotting’ - the word originated at Sandhurst and was apparently a modification of ‘sweating’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he went on to pass out first, winning the Anson Memorial Sword, later to become the Sword of Honour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandhurst transformed him, like so many others before and since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the instructors, when asked who was the most promising cadet, replied, “A Scottish lad, Douglas Haig, is top in almost everything - books, drill, riding, and sports; he is to go into the Cavalry and, before he is finished, will be top of the Army.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That early promise was fully realised as Haig later led the British Army to arguably its greatest victory in unarguably the most gruelling war in its history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Sandhurst has been home to many colourful characters with wildly varying leadership styles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time he arrived at Sandhurst my grandfather’s room-mate at Sandhurst, General Sir Walter Congreve, VC, as he would become, was already a man not to be trifled with - he had been sent down from Oxford for shooting at his don with an air-gun!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fellow cadet of my grandfather’s later shot his mother-in-law and her lawyer in a drame passionnel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to visiting Sandhurst twice in the next two months, including the Commissioning Parade in May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are hugely emotional events. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only time I ever saw my father lose his composure was when I was commissioned from Mons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope one day that I’ll have a good blub if my son makes it to Sandhurst!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most famous face to pass through the hallowed portals of Sandhurst was Winston Churchill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He narrowly passed on his third attempt, after a miserable time at Harrow, where he was bottom of the school. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after a ‘hard but happy experience’ he passed out with honours - eighth out of 150 in 1893. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His one regret was when he was invited to dine at the Staff College, where strategy was being discussed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘This was thrilling’, he wrote in My Early Life. ‘It did seem such a pity that it all had to be make-believe and that the age of wars between civilised nations had come to an end forever.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How wrong he would turn out to be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He continues, ‘the world was growing so sensible and pacific - and so democratic too - the great days were over.’  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He adds, ‘Luckily, however, there were still savages and barbarous peoples. There were Zulus and Afghans, also the Dervishes of the Sudan. Some of these might, if they were well-disposed, “put up a show” one day.’!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who’ve passed out of Sandhurst this century would testify that some Afghans still are putting up a show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International forces from 48 nations, including of course our own Armed Forces since 2001, are currently in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reasons for being there and the challenges we face are a world away from the 19th century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 9/11 the world was forced to confront how terrorism had the potential to change the global strategic landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could suddenly see the clear and present dangers that state-sponsored terrorism might inflict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the mission of international forces there is to prevent terrorists, including Al-Qaeda, from again using Afghanistan to plot and launch terror attacks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is only since August last year that we have had the number of troops and the right level of equipment to fulfil our strategy set for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge lies in having the patience and will to see the mission through. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still a great deal to do - which is why current operations in Afghanistan is one of the two main priorities for Defence in the SDSR - but I believe there is also cause for cautious optimism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw that for myself when I visited Afghanistan two weeks ago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other main priority is building a Future Force for 2020 and beyond that will be among the most versatile and capable in the world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But getting there will be undeniably difficult, given the financial mess we inherited. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving a financial mess reminds me of one of my favourite figures from history, the 19th century eccentric - who briefly served in the British Army - John “Mad Jack” Mytton. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been thrown out of both Westminster and Harrow, he tormented a succession of tutors, including leaving a horse in one poor tutor’s room. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horses were clearly an important part of Mad Jack’s life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He managed to kill one of his horses, Sportsman, by making it drink a bottle of port…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A luckier horse was his favourite, Baronet, who had full and free range inside his home, Halston Hall, and would lie in front of the fire with Jack…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a result of a bet, he is said to have ridden his horse into a hotel in Leamington Spa, up the grand staircase and onto the balcony, from which he jumped, still seated on his horse, over the diners in the restaurant below, and out through the window!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But apart from the sheer mayhem of life with Mad Jack, his obliviousness to reality saw him spend his inheritance at an unsustainable rate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure about Gordon Brown’s love of horses, but the inheritance he left us is strikingly similar to Mad Jack’s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We inherited the largest budget deficit of any major economy - at 12% of GDP - including a national debt increasing at the rate of £3 billion per week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timid, but perfectly reasonable option, would have been to accept a diminished role in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we reject the notion of “strategic shrinkage”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than some mythological ‘Fortress Britain’ or overcommitted expeditionary forces, our National Security Council decided on an ‘adaptable posture’ which drove our SDSR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows greater flexibility and agility in our Armed Forces so they can adapt to the changing nature of threats - indeed, the evacuations operations in Libya are exactly the kind of task we envisaged in the SDSR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if there was one overriding lesson from the Cold War it is that a weak economy is a national security liability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government have a duty to get public finance under control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we had to take some very difficult decisions - like retiring the magnificent Harrier - that I know have been painful for many people in our Armed Forces, the civil service, and in industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Britain will continue to meet the NATO 2% target for Defence spending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will still have the fourth largest military Defence budget in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also putting that money to better use, focusing on conflict prevention and building more flexible Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the world has changed enormously in a short time, we must all change with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it really 20 years since we, and the rest of the international community, liberated Kuwait in response to Saddam Hussein’s aggression?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long ago that now seems, not least with the turning point in history that 9/11 has come to represent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or indeed current events in the Middle East and North Africa which are moving at such a pace too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These events remind us of the difficulty of predicting the future, and the folly of assuming that future wars will mirror the wars of today, though it would also be foolish to ignore the lessons of history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a new approach to British foreign policy, because we cannot do it alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need genuine long-term partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even with 21st century communications there is no real substitute for having the right person on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who speaks the language, knows the people and has a real handle on their particular cultural sensitivities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional British professionalism, determination, patience, tact, and indeed charm, can still open doors and minds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true diplomat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That reminds me that the first person I sat next to at lunch in the House of Lords was Lord Franks or Sir Oliver Franks as he was when our Ambassador in Washington after the war. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after his arrival, he was asked by a local radio station what he would like for Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Oliver was very touched. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being a man of frugal tastes he said it was very kind of them to ask and what he would really like would be a small box of crystallised fruit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Christmas Day, the radio station broadcast the results of its enquiries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked what he would like for Christmas, the French Ambassador replied, “peace for all mankind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Soviet Ambassador, “freedom for all people enslaved by injustice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There then came the polite voice of Sir Oliver…. asking for a small box of crystallised fruit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is a serious business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I’ve managed to convey some sense of the challenges we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clear leadership will be an essential component. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many leadership styles to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s widely recognised that one of the most effective leadership styles is to lead by example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young Lieutenant in The Life Guards, I was greatly impressed by Field Marshal Lord Templar, who at the time was the Colonel of our sister Regiment, the Blues and Royals.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time he came into the Officer’s mess for lunch, he would single out a different young officer and concentrate his whole attention on him - and find out his ambitions, intentions, concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate enough to have the benefit and privilege of his advice at one lunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That made a lasting impression on me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you know, it’s a huge privilege to lead men in difficult circumstances, and one of the lessons I learned was the importance of getting to know one’s Troop through good times and bad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things do always go wrong. Good leaders prepare for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Sandhurst prepares those leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks - and Britain’s thanks - to the Royal Military Academy, for the vital work it does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18688</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T15:15:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2010-11-01-air-power-middle-east-conference"/>
    <title>2010/11/01 - Air Power Middle East Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State in Doha, Qatar on Monday 1 November 2010.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Phil [Air Marshal Sturley, Conference Chairman] for that very kind introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General, distinguished guests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great privilege to be here in Doha on behalf of Her Majesty’s Government, and I thank our Qatari hosts for the splendid hospitality they have shown us - thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also thank the Shephard Group for organising this important Air Power conference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could not be better timed, or better located.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new British Government is committed to strengthening relations across the Gulf, and is serious about realising results on issues that are of mutual importance, not least Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw early evidence of that last month when several British Ministers and their Gulf counterparts met in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the historic and enduring ties which Britain and Qatar have enjoyed were reinforced when Her Majesty The Queen welcomed His Highness The Emir to Britain during last week’s highly successful state visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference also comes hot on the heels of Britain’s Strategic Defence and Security Review - the SDSR - which sets a path to a coherent and affordable Defence capability in 2020, as well of course, as supporting our main effort in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR has generated great interest in many countries around the world - countries which share similar security challenges, and the need to modernise and reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that the Secretary of State for Defence was grateful for the frank and open discussions when General Al Attiyah visited London. So I want to use this opportunity to reinforce our commitment to British-Qatari Defence relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And use the example of Air Power to discuss how we approached our Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is proud to be counted among Qatar’s friends and allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our historic ties are strong in many areas, not least culturally, academically, and commercially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are both bidding to host the football World Cup, though thankfully in different years; we wish you well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in today’s uncertain world, nowhere are they more important than in the field of Defence co-operation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your continued support to the United Kingdom as we conduct our operations is greatly appreciated.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many Qataris have graduated from Sandhurst, Dartmouth, and our Defence Helicopter Flying School at RAF Shawbury; or attended prestigious British courses such as the Royal College of Defence Studies in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re keen to do much more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to broaden and deepen our co-operation - through our continued participation in Qatar’s Exercise FEROCIOUS FALCON, through training, and long-term industrial ties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I very much hope that British companies will be viewed as “partners of choice” in Qatar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I promise that British Ministers will be regular visitors, because knowing each other personally helps us to understand each other’s concerns and further our shared interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar is important to us, not simply as an oil- and gas-rich nation, or even because of our long-standing friendship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it can hardly escape our attention that, in the last year alone, Qatar’s exports to Britain increased by an incredible 565%, in large part thanks to your Liquefied Natural Gas now flowing through the South Hook terminal in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar has one of the largest GDP per capita in the world, and is a major investor in the United Kingdom, not least as the second biggest shareholder on the London Stock Exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the recent difficulties in the global economy, Qatar has weathered the storm very well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proud that around 11,500 British people are working here, contributing to that resilience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your place on the world stage is growing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now you have more to protect.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the challenge for Qatar, and for all of us who have shared interests, is deciding how, where, and when to engage to contribute to security and stability in the Gulf and around the globe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such decisions will be driven by many concerns: national security, financial, and trade; others by alliance obligations and shared interests, by humanitarian aims and altruism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be candid, how nations see themselves and how they wish to be viewed by others also plays a part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is certain: the world has changed greatly in a short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now decades away from the Cold War, and approaching the end of the post-Cold War era too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s National Security Strategy highlights a complex array of new and growing threats from a variety of sources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our view, the four highest priority risks are those arising from: international terrorism; international military crises; major accidents or natural hazards; and, as long-overdue recognition of the importance of our critical national infrastructure, cyber attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature and character of conflict itself are also changing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are still dealing with the strategic shock of 9/11 when many of our assumptions were shattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The callous and cowardly willingness of terrorists to harness technology to murder large numbers of innocent civilians has emerged as one of the key challenges of our times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, we must not assume that state-on-state conflict has been consigned to history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circle of international decision making has become wider and more multi-lateral as new, increasingly self-confident and potentially powerful nations seek to take their place and assert themselves on the world stage.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has major resonance for the role of military force around the world, not least the way we view Air Power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we have concluded that this requires an adaptive Defence posture to make our Armed Forces among the most versatile in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The means to achieve these ends were set out in our SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And reaching these decisions was very, very difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are legitimate pulls and pushes from every part of Government; from industry; from academia; from the media; from friends and allies; and of course from those that the SDSR is designed to serve - the British people, and our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of these pressures faced up to the realities of the post-Cold War world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because Air Power tends to come at the more costly end of the spectrum, our future requirements for Air Power had a high profile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maintaining a clear sense of purpose has been vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, even with the difficult decisions we had to make, and even with the cuts we had to take, we were clear that our commitment to the Gulf would never waver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this is one of the reasons why we want to increase our engagements with our friends in the Gulf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now that the SDSR has been published, I thought it might be helpful if I explain Britain’s vision for Air Power, and how we reached the conclusions that we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We approached the SDSR with three principles in mind for Air Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, history has taught us that it is always a mistake to base one’s decisions and design one’s policy on the basis of the last war. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, it would be equally foolish to ignore the lessons of history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we have the enduring lessons of the Battle of Britain; the Falkands; and of course Iraq and Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, our ability to project military power over large distances offers political flexibility for any mission we might want to undertake. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gives us built-in military flexibility to adapt our approach - be that deterrence, containment, or lethal force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we should never forget that Air Power provides us with our asymmetric edge, not least the formidable advantage of combat ISTAR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technical superiority has allowed the precise targeting of insurgents and terrorists but, more important, with minimum civilian casualties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know the contained havoc that an Apache helicopter and a missile can cause an adversary on the ground, while sparing the civilians caught in the battle zone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s asymmetric adversary would love to see Air Power taken out of the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with our three principles in mind, the SDSR was clear about the vital role that Air Power will continue to play across all four pivotal roles: Control of the Air; Air Mobility; Intelligence &amp;amp; Situational Awareness; and Attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was equally clear about the need to invest in programmes which will provide flexibility and advanced capabilities, reducing legacy capabilities which we are less likely to need as we move into a world of precision weaponry where the battlespace increasingly involves unmanned and cyber operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what does this mean for Britain’s future Air Power capabilities? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR concluded that we need: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air Defence at home and for our South Atlantic Overseas Territories;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a credible and capable combat air presence to contribute to conventional deterrence and containment;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an expeditionary combat air contribution in support of enduring land operations;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strategic and tactical airlift;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and other Air Power capabilities, including ISTAR, helicopters and RAF Regiment ground units.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will also develop a long-term coherent strategy for the use of UAVs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we concluded that there is a strategic requirement for a future carrier-strike capability that will last well into this century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, we are examining the most efficient means of aligning our logistics support right across the fleet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do so because an organisation delivering Air Power teeth without the tail will not last very long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fast jet component will be provided by our world-beating Typhoon aircraft, capable of air-to-air and air-to-ground missions; supplemented by the Joint Strike Fighter from the end of this decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will be backed up by the most modern air-to-air refuelling aircraft, extending their range and endurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will be complemented by a growing fleet of Remotely Piloted Aircraft in both combat and reconnaissance roles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the enhanced strategic and tactical air transport fleet will allow us to fly our forces wherever they are needed in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, we will continue our long-term investment in helicopters, air launched weapons, and strategic surveillance and intelligence platforms as part of our broader combat ISTAR capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have had to take several tough decisions, not least the decision to remove our Harrier from service and nor will the MRA4 see service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this formidable array of Air Power is only possible because we have re-balanced our investment in technology, equipment, and people to meet the challenge of irregular warfare, while retaining our ability to respond to emerging state-led threats and other military challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that sharing some of our decision-making process and conclusions will help you to inform your own thinking and planning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister and His Highness agreed last week that we will build a new and dynamic partnership for the future, building on the rich shared history between our two countries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I also hope that I have reflected the Defence component of Britain’s strengthened commitment to Qatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I insisted that one of my first overseas trips as a Defence Minister was to Qatar, I am determined to build on the personal relationships that I have begun or renewed and I very much look forward to returning here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason, when you get in touch with us you will always find a friend - someone you know that has Qatar’s best interests at heart - at the other end of the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how I believe true friends show their commitment to a future of even closer Defence co-operation at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18686</id>
    <published>2010-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T15:49:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2010-10-14-anglo-omani-society"/>
    <title>2010/10/14 - Anglo-Omani Society</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at Sackville Street, London on Thursday 14 October 2010.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your Excellencies, Anglo-Omani Society members and honoured guests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Excellency, thank you very much for those very warm words of welcome, and for being with us in London this evening to open the Anglo-Omani Society’s new home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As His Majesty the Sultan and the people of Oman look forward to celebrating the 40th anniversary of the Renaissance, the opening could not come at a more fitting time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also ask Your Excellency to convey to His Majesty, the Society’s deep and sincere thanks for making it possible to acquire this truly magnificent building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will provide a fantastic focal point for the Society’s growing programme of grants and scholarships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am sure that it will be appreciated by the growing number of British friends of Oman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and Oman have been tried and trusted friends for many years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have shared values, shared interests, shared history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I feel this very keenly because of all the stories about Oman I heard from my late godfather, Colonel David Smiley, who I’m sure some of you remember. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was the first C/SAF between 1958 and 1961 who oversaw that truly remarkable military operation at the Jebel Akdur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He played a key role in helping to make Oman the modern, peaceful, and prosperous state the world sees today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he taught me that we are both culturally rich nations, whose traditions have endured for centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when he discussed British servicemen fighting side by side with Omanis, it left an abiding impression on me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was the fulfilment of a life-long ambition when I first visited Oman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was honoured to lead a parliamentary delegation to Oman earlier this year where I made a number of new friends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even more fortunate that my wife was able to come with me, and she also fell in love with Oman and the Omani people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we value Defence co-operation with Oman as highly as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many Omanis attend prestigious courses such as Dartmouth and Sandhurst, as His Majesty the Sultan did before them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They typify the professionalism of the Omani Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re keen to show our commitment to true friends by making far more regular Ministerial visits to Oman, and I insisted that my first overseas visit as a Defence Minister should be to Oman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am very much looking forward to returning later this month, and again, I hope, early next year, where I hope to build on the warm friendships that I have already made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationship is strong in so many areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong academically with many Omanis studying in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong commercially with increased bilateral trade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And strong culturally with British tourists increasingly drawn to that most beautiful part of the Arabian Peninsular. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain will stand by Oman, as we have before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the breadth and depth of our relationship today is our real strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are both culturally rich nations, whose traditions have endured for centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is precisely what the Anglo-Omani Society embodies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And may I wish everyone every good fortune in your new home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18685</id>
    <published>2010-10-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T15:47:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2010-10-12-sanctuary-and-energy-awards"/>
    <title>2010/10/12 - Sanctuary and Energy Awards</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Under Secretary of State at the Ministry of Defence, Main Building, London on Tuesday 12 October 2010.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you David [David Olney, Deputy Chief Executive, Defence Estates] for that kind introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was once introduced as “Lord Astor of Heaven”, so I’m pleased you avoided that trap!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon Ladies and Gentlemen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has said that he wants this to be the greenest Government ever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are absolutely committed to achieving this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the public rarely equate Defence with being environmentally friendly; with nurturing, protecting, and conserving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a farmer, I have always taken a close interest in the management of the Defence Estate, so I know this to be patently untrue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I am delighted to be presenting this year’s Sanctuary and Energy Awards which shine a light into the tremendous work that Defence is doing in these areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Awards recognise the achievements of teams and individuals across Defence who have ‘gone the extra mile’ to make a real difference to heritage, fauna and flora, and conservation management across the estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the inaugural Energy Awards recognise people’s efforts to conserve energy and cut carbon emissions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Award citations will be read out in a few minutes, and I hope you enjoy hearing them as much as I’ve enjoyed reading them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to use this opportunity to say a bit more about the new government’s commitments, and offer some observations on the awards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I do, let me just make some wider observations about the work of Defence Estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that delivering a service can often be a thankless task. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People take it for granted when things are going well, but you will soon hear from them when they’re not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s right not to rest on our laurels - if 95% of surveyed properties in the UK are either Standard one or two, that is excellent news, yet it also means that 5% is not up to standard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t mean that 95% of people are totally satisfied either.&lt;br&gt;
Improving the quality of life for Service personnel and their families matter, so let me thank all those concerned for their efforts to raise the bar still further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Estates also does a great deal for Defence by taking a sustainable approach to our estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the positive PR and income you generate by giving film and television programme makers access to locations, personnel, and equipment - from ‘Songs of Praise’ to ‘Myths of UFOs’!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the Ministerial team, I want to thank everyone connected with the Defence Estates organisation for all that you do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also delighted to launch this year’s Sanctuary Magazine, the MoD’s annual conservation magazine, which for the first time will be solely available online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine is unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The articles are fascinating and show that this Department cares about nature conservation, heritage, and public access to the estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stewardship of the Defence Estate is clearly in good hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’d like to thank the Editor, Clare Backman, for producing another outstanding edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement states unequivocally that climate change is one of the gravest threats we face, and mitigating and adapting to this change is one of the Government’s central priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a challenge which every part of Government must rise to; Defence is no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we are committed to cutting emissions from greenhouse gases and reducing our carbon footprint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has done well, and I applaud all those who helped us to deliver the Government target of a 12.5% reduction in CO2 emissions two years early. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same story with the condition of our Sites of Special Scientific Interest - we’ve met our targets ahead of the formal target date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has talked at length about his vision of a ‘Big Society’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He describes it as being “about government helping to build a nation of doers and go-getters, where people step forward not sit back, where people come together to make life better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no better example than the thousands of people who make up the large and dedicated network of volunteer conservation groups, and whose conservation management skills are widely admired. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or our people and partners working together and taking initiatives towards the goal of a more sustainable environment and a more engaged society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, I am very proud of what’s being done across the estate, but we’re here today to honour the people who have gone that little bit further in conservation and smart energy use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a few themes caught my eye as I read the Award citations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve challenged assumptions, you’ve taken decisions, and you’ve made changes that have led to positive benefits for the environment and, in many cases, saved the taxpayer considerable sums of money! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were told that it was impossible to reduce energy consumption, or improve a Site of Special Scientific Interest in a danger area - yet you went ahead, you found answers, you delivered solutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must have been satisfying - there’s nothing like telling a big business that it’s got it wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need champions who marshal good arguments and who are persuasive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are obviously some strong characters here amongst the award winners!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while most people do want to make a difference, it sometimes needs champions to encourage and enable this change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broad behavioural change is essential if we are to sustain the improvements that you have started. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we need the technology of Building Energy Management Systems, for example, but the changes will only stick if our people modify their own behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they do, the results are impressive: over quarter of a million pounds in reduced energy costs at just one RAF station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we honour the best of the best in the MoD’s approach to the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility, lateral thinking, and responding to change are the hallmarks of today’s winners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with these qualities, I believe that Defence can lead the way across Government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, as the second largest landowner in Britain, we must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some 240,000 hectares, 45,000 buildings, and areas of outstanding natural beauty, we have the raw materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the financial situation we have been left with, we will need to do more with less across Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the work that all of you do, and which we are recognising today, is such an important part of our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you again, and over to you David for the formal presentations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
