<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--31</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--31.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-06T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28769</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/campaign-to-reward-designated-drivers-launched-by-coca-cola-great-britain-and-think"/>
    <title>Campaign to reward designated drivers launched by Coca-Cola Great Britain and THINK!</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designated drivers will be rewarded with a ‘buy 1 get 1 free’ deal on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coca-Cola Zero, this Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the winter period designated drivers across the UK will give lifts to friends and family as they enjoy a festive night out at pubs and bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain and the Road Safety Minister, Stephen Hammond MP, will today celebrate and pledge to reward responsible drivers, at the launch of this year’s designated driver campaign at the Mason Arms pub in Central London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in its 5th year the nationwide designated driver campaign will reward drivers who choose not to drink alcohol with a ‘buy 1, get 1 free’ offer on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and CokeZero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will run for 3 weeks from 6 to 31 December and is part of an ongoing partnership with the THINK! driver friendly campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dedicated website has also been set up to encourage consumers to take advantage of the offer. From the 6 December designated drivers and their friends can visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/"&gt;the Coca-Cola website&lt;/a&gt; to find a participating pub in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hammond, Road Safety Minister, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our THINK! campaign makes it clear that drink drivers risk losing their licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased that THINK! will be teaming up with Coca-Cola and pub chains across the country to reward designated drivers as well as reminding people of the consequences of getting a drink drive conviction. No one wants to spend their Christmas in a police cell.  My message is clear: don’t drink and drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Woods, General Manager, Coca-Cola Great Britain and Ireland said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Designated drivers provide an amazing service to friends and family. They allow people to have a good night and also help keep roads safe, so everyone can enjoy the Christmas period. By rewarding drivers who choose not to drink with a free Coke, Diet Coke or Coke Zero, we hope even more people will be encouraged to do the right thing and become responsible drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kieron Murphy, Licensee, Masons Arms: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We see a lot of people come in over the Christmas period who are responsible for driving their friends and family home at the end of the night. That’s why we are delighted to be participating in Coca-Cola’s designated driver campaign this year.  It will reward our regulars and make sure they still have a good night out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information, images or interview requests please contact Tim Smith.&lt;br&gt;
Telephone: +44 (0)20 7822 01734&lt;br&gt;
Email: &lt;a href="mailto:tim.smith@portland-communications.com"&gt;tim.smith@portland-communications.com&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event will take place on 6 December (7.30-9am) at the Mason Arms, Maddox Street, London. The designated driver campaign forms part of Coca-Cola Great Britain’s pledge to promote the positive role in which soft drinks can play as credible alternatives to alcohol. The designated driver campaign is a key feature of Coca-Cola Great Britain’s overall commitment to responsible marketing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-the-research"&gt;About the research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research was conducted by Populus for Coca-Cola in November 2011 with 2000 adults. Key findings include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;79% of women have used a designated driver at the end of a night out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;men are more likely to abstain from alcohol with 63% having given it up to drive friends/family home before &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;62% of adults plan to go to a pub or bar over the Christmas and New Year period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two thirds of those aged 65+ have been a designated driver compared to just over half of 18 to 24 year olds &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however 18 to 24 year olds will give the most lifts over the Christmas and New Year period, on average taking 5 people &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the majority of those polled never drive home after drinking more than one alcoholic drink on a night out (83%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nearly half of respondents thought that the best thing about designated drivers is that they stop people drink driving, while 3 in 4 believe it is because they ensure people can get home safely at the end of a night out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="about-coca-cola-great-britain"&gt;About Coca-Cola Great Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain is responsible for marketing 21 brands and over 100 products to consumers across Great Britain, focusing upon developing new brands, extending existing brands and protecting trademarks including Coca-Cola (recognised as the world’s most valuable brand). Other Coca-Cola Great Britain brands include Diet Coke, Coke Zero, Fanta, Sprite, Dr Pepper, Oasis, Glaceauvitaminwater, Schweppes, 5 Alive, Lilt, Kia Ora, Relentless Energy Drink and Powerade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coca-Cola Great Britain portfolio is worth £1,998 million with value sales growth of 8.4% year on year.  Within this the My Coke trilogy (Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coke Zero) is worth £1,150 million, growing at 6.4% in value year on year (Neilsen, w/c 11/02/12).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain is committed to developing innovative, responsible and sustainable initiatives that help protect the environment.  Recently the company launched its PlantBottle™ plastic made from up to 22.5% plant-based materials and up to 25% recycled plastic as the latest step on its journey towards petroleum-free plastic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company is also dedicated to recycling, with 97% of site waste recycled or recovered. For more information about Coca-Cola in Great Britain, please visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk"&gt;Coca-Cola website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-the-think-drink-drive-campaign-and-driver-friendly-initiative"&gt;About the THINK! drink drive campaign and driver friendly initiative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of people killed in drink drive accidents has been reduced by over three-quarters since 1979 thanks to more than 30 years of government education campaigns and measures to improve enforcement. However, drink driving is still a problem and provisional statistics show that 280 people lost their lives in drink drive accidents on Britain’s road in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The THINK! campaign has had a long-standing and well supported partnership with the on-trade and soft drinks industry. In December 2009, this was developed into the ‘driver friendly’ campaign which aims to support the designated driver through the provision of promotional offers and ‘rewards’, linked to the purchase of soft drinks, on their night out. Coca-Cola GB is leading the way for Christmas 2012, and their designated driver promotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DfT press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17247</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/institute-of-advanced-motorists"/>
    <title>Institute of Advanced Motorists </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank-you also for asking me along - it’s an absolute pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="not-complacent"&gt;Not complacent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I took up my post I inherited a road safety record second to none. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This country is a genuine world leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that doesn’t mean for a single minute that it’s ‘job done’ or ‘mission accomplished’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, the provisional figures for the year ending June 2012 show a reduction in fatalities compared to the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, it is very welcome news that, for all road users, the numbers killed and seriously injured are down 17% compared with the 2005-2009 average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s also worth remembering that, while the 2011 figures were slightly up on 2010, the 2010 figures were exceptionally low, and that 2011 was still lower than 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in spite of all we have achieved, we should never forget that road deaths are not statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are someone’s mother or father, brother or sister, son or daughter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are real lives cut short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as Simon (Simon Best – &lt;abbr title="Institute of Advanced Motorists"&gt;IAM&lt;/abbr&gt;) reminded us, road accidents also hit the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers and the graphs may change from year to year, but one thing stays constant - accidents carry a heavy human cost and a huge economic price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why this government is not complacent on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we will continue to do all we can to make our roads safer in our ambition to be the safest we can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in the short time I have today I don’t want to talk you through every last dot and comma of the government’s road safety agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I would like to do is give you an insight into my thinking around some of the key priority areas as I see them - a brief but broad overview if you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="localism"&gt;Localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let me touch on an issue Simon mentioned in his speech - the important road safety role of local authorities, especially in terms of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are testing economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recognise that local government, just like central government, faces tough spending choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know that it is local communities, rather than Whitehall bureaucrats, who are best placed to design local road safety solutions to meet local road safety challenges&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that includes deciding where to focus their resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what localism is all about - the power to choose for yourself, backed by the funding to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are giving more than £1 billion to local councils enabling them to improve the transport infrastructure – including the design of better and safer roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re investing £600 million in local transport through the Local Sustainable Transport Fund – which again gives authorities greater power to deliver their own transport projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Transport for Manchester secured £32.5 million from the Fund for their ‘Let’s get to work project’ - a project designed to give people the kind of viable travel options that allow them to make their journey to work in way that is healthier and safer, cleaner and greener, whether it’s walking, cycling or hopping on the local bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport Fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects contain a cycling element – not just providing better routes, but also making roads safer for cyclists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take the issue of cycle safety very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial at a time when thousands of people are taking up bike riding - inspired by the heroics of our Tour de France, Olympic and Paralympic cyclists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the department has recently launched a THINK! cycle safety campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve made £30 million available to tackle dangerous junctions for cyclists across the country&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have made it simpler for councils to put in place 20mph zones - and install Trixi mirrors to improve the visibility of cyclists at junctions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycle safety is about embracing technology and changing behaviour. So we will continue to develop new ideas and initiatives to build on the progress we’ve already made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="drug-driving"&gt;Drug driving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that one of the great successes of road safety over the last 40 years has been the extent to which drink driving has become socially unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the number of drink drive deaths has fallen by more than 75% since 1979. The culture has completely changed from social necessity to social pariah, such is the view of today’s drink drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sadly, people are still losing their lives because of drink drive collisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;280 were killed last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, through our award winning THINK Campaign, we continue to push home the message that people who drive while over the limit risk losing their licence, being fined or even going to prison. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more importantly, they have to be aware that they could injure, or worse kill someone – including someone they love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve also just launched a drink-drive consultation which includes proposals to close down the legal loopholes where some drivers try to avoid prosecution by demanding to replace their breath test with blood or urine tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drink driving kills. Fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in my view, it is just as socially unacceptable and dangerous to drive while impaired by drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we tackled drink driving in the 1980s, now in the 2010s, it’s time to defeat drug driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I believe we have to make sure that drug drivers face the full force of the law, just like drink drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the government is taking three major steps to do just that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type approval will shortly be given to drug testing devices for police stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we expect to introduce road-side drug screeners during 2014&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and the new law to prosecute drug-drivers will also come into come into effect by the summer of 2014 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This government is on the side of the motoring majority who abide by the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to the reckless minority of drivers who think they can take drugs, jump behind the wheel and get away with it, my message is clear and it’s simple - you will be caught and you will be punished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-hard-core-few-and-the-law-abiding-many"&gt;The hard core few and the law abiding many&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now say a few words about the hard core few and the law abiding many. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re targeting enforcement efforts against the dangerous behaviour of the hardcore few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drivers who commit serious, deliberate and repeated offences - the ones with a poor attitude rather than poor skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told you about cracking down on drink drivers. But there’s no hiding place for the uninsured either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, for example, we’re making full use of existing powers to seize an offender’s vehicle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The police seized around 140,000 vehicles for this offence last year, and the level of uninsured driving has decreased from around 2 million drivers in 2005 to 1.2 million drivers in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also introduced the continuous insurance enforcement scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insurance industry estimate that, with the introduction of this scheme - assuming that police enforcement continues at its current rate - the level of uninsured driving could be reduced by up to 40% in the next 5 years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the law abiding many that’s good news, both for road safety and, I hope, for future insurance premiums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I believe it’s absolutely vital to support the law abiding many.
The motorists who want to do the right thing and who just need a nudge in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, that means offering more educational options to drivers who make genuine mistakes, display poor skills or commit occasional low level offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means improving training and testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the reason we’ve made changes to the practical portion of the driving test so that, instead of being taught how to pass a test, people will actually learn how to drive safely on their own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we want to tackle careless driving with proportionate sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 14 June, the government consulted on proposals to make careless driving a fixed penalty offence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorists who commit less severe examples of the offence - such as driving too close to another vehicle - would be offered training to help them improve their safety skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if anyone knows the benefits of driver education and training, then it’s this Institution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You understand the positive impact it can have on road safety by preventing collisions and crashes from taking place in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="older-drivers"&gt;Older drivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also recognise the impact of changing demographics on motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so do I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Simon pointed out, with an ageing population the number of older drivers on our roads is set to increase over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the report you’ve just launched about older drivers is a welcome contribution to the on-going debate about what this might mean for road safety and road users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the overall aim must be to maintain a balance between freedom of movement for older drivers and road safety for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; is not considering compulsory testing for older drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned the crucial factor for road safety is not age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters is skills and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters is the physical and mental fitness of the driver to drive competently and safely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that applies to young drivers as well as older drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise that we have to do everything we can to make sure young motorists are as safe as they can be on our highways, whether they are driving on the motorway, through town or along country lanes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving the safety and ability of young drivers is a key priority for the government which is why we have adapted the driving test to reflect real conditions on the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of ongoing measures to reduce the risks of accidents, the department is working with young people, the insurance industry, and other partners to identify what more can be done - and we are considering several options to ensure that newly qualified drivers are properly prepared and able to drive safely &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the use of telematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In-car technology like this means insurers now have a real time data feed which allows them to see an individual’s driving behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some evidence suggests that young drivers could see their annual premiums fall by 20% more with a black box installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But research so far also shows that telematics can significantly reduce crash rates and levels of risky driving behaviours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome the increasing number of insurers who are making use of this technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are supportive of any measures that make driving safer and also want to see improvements in young driver safety reflected in their insurance premiums. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I was always taught that there isn’t much point in silent gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as well as thanking everyone here for your hospitality today, I’d also like to say a big ‘thank-you’ to the Institute itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you don’t just campaign for safer roads - you actively do something to make them a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more than half a century you have raised driving and riding standards and improved the skills of road users, both on two wheels and four wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the years you have helped to prevent accidents, save lives and make Britain’s highways some of the safest on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as the Road Safety Minister, I want to pay tribute to everyone at the Institute - your hard work and your expertise makes a real and lasting difference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17387</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/speed-limit-exemption-for-life-saving-services"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemption for life-saving services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proposals to allow drivers from a wider range of emergency services to break the speed limit in order to save lives, have been published today for consultation by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance services are already allowed to exceed speed limits in the course of their emergency response duties and this is not changing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3 month consultation exercise will examine the possibility of extending the exemption to other services including those carrying organs for transplant, bomb disposal units and coastguard vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at amending road safety legislation so that emergency drivers would be required by law to complete high-speed training before exceeding the limit. But this will not place any additional burden on police, fire and ambulance services which already run an effective voluntary training scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance service drivers are highly trained individuals who are at times required to exceed the speed limit in order to save lives. It is only right that we look at allowing other services whose duties can mean the difference between life and death to exceed the speed limit when responding to emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also time to look at the legal requirements of emergency vehicle training so we can build on the rigorous standards the police, fire and ambulance services have already applied through their code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While emergency service drivers are not exempt from the offences of dangerous and careless driving, the current legislation allows drivers in some circumstances to break speed limits legally as well as exempting them from certain traffic regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be viewed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"&gt;DfT website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services currently exempt from speed limits include Police, the Fire Service, the Ambulance Service and the Serious Organised Crime Agency (shortly to be replaced by the National Crime Agency)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The full list of services who have expressed an interest in being exempt are listed within section 5 of the consultation document, they include Ministry of Defence bomb disposal units, fire (other than for fire and rescue authorities which are covered), conveyance of human tissue for transplant, blood transfusion, mountain rescue, mine rescue, radiation emergencies, coastguard and lifeboat launching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The emergency services set up a joint emergency services’ speed limit exemption driver training group to develop their procedures. It also includes representatives from the Driving Standards Agency, the Institute of Advanced Motoring and the Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents. It has developed a Code of Practice which is based around current best practice for each of the exempt organisations and reflects what is being taught there, recognising that there are organisation specific competencies. The consultation proposes using this Code of Practice as the basis for the regulated standards for the mandatory training courses to be used following the proposed legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation includes a set of criteria designed to establish the rationale of each request, balancing the operational need for the exemption against any potential road safety risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation proposes amending the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984 and make any legal exemption dependent on drivers attaining the core competencies identified in the Emergency Services’ Code of Practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"&gt;Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles&lt;/a&gt; written statement by Stephen Hammond MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17020</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department has today published a consultation paper on Speed Limit Exemptions for vehicles used for emergency purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper proposes that Section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) is brought into effect. Section 19 allows the Secretary of State for Transport to designate other vehicle purposes as being exempt from speed limits in certain circumstances and if drivers of said vehicles complete successfully a “high-speed training course”.  Section 19 replaces Section 87 of the Road Traffic Regulation Act (1984) in relation to exemptions from speed limits for certain vehicle purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department recognises that there are certain vehicle purposes that the wider public may well consider as having a speed limit exemptions but which do not currently.  These include, for example, vehicles used to carry human tissue for transplant, mountain rescue teams, bomb disposal squads and others listed in the consultation document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branches of the Emergency Services (Police, Fire Service &amp;amp; Ambulance Service) are currently exempt from speed limits and provide appropriate training to their staff.  No additional requirements will be placed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has worked with representatives of the police, fire and rescue, NHS ambulance services, the Serious Organised Crime Agency and road safety stakeholders on the development of standards for driver training.   This led to the creation of a code of practice based on the principles applied in each organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department seeks to identify the core competencies specified in the code of practice and include them in regulations. It also proposes that the Driving Standards Agency (DSA) will take responsibility for the accrediting and quality assuring training providers seeking to provide high speed driver training courses, against the competences identified in the code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further consideration within the consultation document is to exempt paramedics and other medical personnel from the requirements to wear seatbelts in the back of ambulances, particularly when providing emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17003</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"/>
    <title>Tough new measures to tackle drink drivers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers has been unveiled today by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included in the proposals are plans to remove the statutory right to a replacement blood or urine test where a breath test reading is above and close to the legal limit, closing the loophole which allows those testing positive in breath to sober up while they wait for a blood or urine sample to be taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also intends to legislate to allow police the option not to perform a preliminary breath test where roadside evidential breath tests are carried out following the rollout of roadside evidential breath testing devices and give registered health care professionals greater roles in testing drink drivers - both of which options would speed up the enforcement process and deal with more drink drivers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have made great progress in tackling drink drivers and the 2011 fatality figure for drink and drive accidents is the second lowest ever recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, last year 280 people died ruining the lives of families up and down the country so more needs to be done to eradicate this menace. That is why we are taking forward a package of measures to streamline enforcement against drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to make the jobs of those who deal with drink drivers easier and less bureaucratic so that bringing offenders to justice is not left to chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, drivers who record less than 50 microgrammes of alcohol per 100 millilitres of breath have the right to demand a blood or urine test - despite being over the legal limit of 35 microgrammes per 100 millilitres. This is known as the statutory option. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This option dates back to the original introduction of breathalyser technology when there were concerns over reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his review of drink and drug driving Sir Peter North recommended the removal of the right to demand a blood or urine test as evidence showed people were using it as a delaying tactic. The government also believes that improvements in the accuracy of technology means that this option is no longer necessary.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/consultations/enforcement-procedures-against-drink-drivers-and-other-offenders"&gt;consultation also seeks views&lt;/a&gt; on removing the requirement for a preliminary breath test where roadside evidential breath testing is used. At the moment, when a suspected drink driver is pulled over by police, they undergo a preliminary breath test and are then taken to a police station for a further evidential test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results from the evidential test taken at police stations are the only ones used as evidence. Under the new plans, following the introduction of mobile evidential testing devices the police could perform the eventual test at the roadside so the preliminary test would not be required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also want to see a wider range of registered healthcare professionals given the power to take evidential blood samples in hospitals and to assess whether a driver may have a condition due to a drug. This will enable tests to be carried out more swiftly, easing the pressure on doctors who are currently the only professionals with the authority to carry out the tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other proposals within the plans include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commissioning further research into the current process used to decide whether a driver banned due to drink driving can regain their licence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;further exploration of how greater use can be made of vehicle forfeiture powers to get the most dangerous and irresponsible motorists off the road, including drink drivers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation encompasses the legislative changes the government proposed in its response of March 2011 to the reports by Sir Peter North and the Transport Select Committee on drink and drug driving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation period runs until 2 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile breath testing devices are still subject to type approval by the Centre for Applied Science and Technology and have not yet been deployed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100921035225/http://northreview.independent.gov.uk/docs/NorthReview-Report.pdf"&gt;Report of the review of drink and drug driving law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmtran/460/46002.htm"&gt;Report of the Transport Select Committee: Drink and Drug Driving Law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm80/8050/8050.pdf"&gt;Government’s response to the reports by Sir Peter North CBE QC and the Transport Select Committee on drink and drug driving: command paper 8050&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16693</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/consultation-on-changes-to-enforcement-procedures-for-drink-driving-offences"/>
    <title>Consultation on changes to enforcement procedures for drink driving offences</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has today &lt;a href="/government/consultations/enforcement-procedures-against-drink-drivers-and-other-offenders"&gt;launched a consultation on some enforcement issues relating to the current legislation on drink and drug driving&lt;/a&gt;.  This consultation encompasses the legislative changes the government proposed in its response of March 2011 to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100921035225/http://northreview.independent.gov.uk/docs/NorthReview-Report.pdf"&gt;reports by Sir Peter North&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmtran/460/46002.htm"&gt;Transport Select Committee&lt;/a&gt; on drink and drug driving (“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm80/8050/8050.pdf"&gt;the Government’s response&lt;/a&gt;” ).  The changes covered in this consultation should not be confused with the legislation related to driving with a specified impairing drug in the body, which is currently passing through Parliament in the Crime and Courts Bill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation on enforcement of drink driving will cover four potential legislative changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) withdrawal of the right people have to replace their breath alcohol specimens with either a specimen of blood or specimens of urine in cases where the lower of the two breath readings provided does not exceed 50 microgrammes (mcg) of alcohol per 100 millilitres (ml) of  breath (known commonly as the ‘statutory option’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) removing the requirement for preliminary testing where evidential testing is undertaken away from a police station.  This would mean that a preliminary breath test would not to have to be taken in addition to two evidential breath tests, when mobile evidential breath testing devices are used away from a police station.  While such devices are not yet available, it is expected that they may be type approved within the next 2 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) streamlining the procedure for testing drink drivers and drug impaired drivers in hospital so that a wider range of registered healthcare professionals are allowed to take evidential blood specimens.  This would make it consistent with other policing provisions.
4) the consultation asks for views on whether a health care professional other than a doctor should be able to assess whether a driver may be under the influence of a drug prior to evidential testing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislative changes proposed in this consultation would apply to the Road Traffic Act 1988.  Subject to the outcome of the consultation, we intend to legislate as soon as Parliamentary time allows on the matters covered in points 1-4 above.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-proposals-in-the-consultation"&gt;Other proposals in the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Road Traffic Act 1998 (and other parallel legislative provisions) apply similar measures to the drink drive offence to railways, shipping and aviation.  The consultation seeks views about whether any changes here should also apply to these other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation explores how further use can be made of vehicle forfeiture powers to get the most dangerous and irresponsible motorists off the road including those who drive while under the influence of alcohol. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document explores the scope for further research into the processes for reassessing whether a driver banned due to drink driving should regain their licence. The research would develop the evidence base for longer term solutions in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views about the way forward on three as yet un-commenced legislative provisions in the Road Safety Act 2006 relating to the training and punishment of certain road traffic offenders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with the revised guidance on consultations, we propose to shorten the consultation time for this to just over 5 weeks.  We are particularly interested in the views of the healthcare sector on points 3 and 4 and are planning to meet representative bodies for medical professionals in early December. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16643</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/correction-to-the-written-answer-to-parliamentary-question-97198"/>
    <title>Correction to the written answer to Parliamentary Question 97198</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I regret to inform the House that there was an inaccuracy in the answer given by the then Parliamentary Under Secretary of State to Parliamentary Question 97198 on 1 March (Official Report, Column 450W) about Driving: Licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/vosa/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; identifies poor performing MOT testing stations through a transparent and proportionate disciplinary points system published in the MOT Testing Guide. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; cessate individual testers called Authorised Examiners (AEs) from carrying out MOT tests, not the test stations. AEs cessated in the last three years are 111 in 2008-09, 90 in 2009-10, and 89 in 2010-11 all after appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; identifies poor performing MOT testing stations through a transparent and proportionate disciplinary points system published in the MOT Testing Guide. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; can take action against Authorised Examiners (AEs) and Nominated Testers (NTs).  AEs are an individual, partnership or company approved to carry out MOT tests.  NTs carry out the actual tests.  In the last three years, the Agency struck off 111 AEs in 08/09, 90 in 09/10, and 89 in 10/11, all after appeal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16872</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-major-ports-group-annual-parliamentary-reception"/>
    <title>UK Major Ports Group annual parliamentary reception</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Charles (Charles Hammond – Chairman UK Major Ports Group/UKMPG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along - I’m delighted to have this chance to meet with you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="facts-are-stubborn-things"&gt;Facts are stubborn things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Adams, second President of the United States, said, “Facts are stubborn things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me, the stubborn facts prove that Britain’s ports are a national asset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every year more than 500 million tonnes of freight and well over 20 million international passengers pass through our ports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they account for over 95% of our imports and exports by volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and they employ around 130,000 people and contribute close to £7 billion to &lt;abbr title="Gross Domestic Product"&gt;GDP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Oxford Economics Report 2011)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="our-ports-matter-more-than-ever"&gt;Our ports matter more than ever&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, our ports matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with Britain facing the most serious economic challenge in a generation, they matter more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you create wealth, jobs and growth right here at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that contribution is absolutely vital to the health of our national economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But your economic importance doesn’t start and finish at our borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because you connect our country and our companies to new markets and new customers overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody has more experience, or more expertise, in accessing the global economy - seizing its opportunities, maximising its potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working day and night so that Britain is always open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure we’re a top trading nation, as well as a leading maritime nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who you are. It’s what you do - better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why you are key players. The people and the firms who can help Britain out-compete and out-produce the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-evangelist-for-the-ports-industry"&gt;An evangelist for the ports industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I have a tough act to follow in my predecessor Mike Penning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this audience will agree that Mike was a vocal and effective champion for this country’s ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I’m determined to pick up where Mike left off by being an evangelist for your industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So be in no doubt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trust port or private company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small, medium or large enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;north, south, east or west&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will be on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name on the ministerial door may be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our strategy and our policy for the maritime sector remains exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-right-environment-to-grow-and-succeed"&gt;The right environment to grow and succeed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m looking forward to visiting many of the ports you represent, to see for myself how they are coping in what remains a difficult trading climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know these are tough and testing times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as always, your members have been equal to them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the fact that UK ports increased their total traffic by 1.5 per cent last year is a huge achievement when set against the backdrop of continuing worldwide economic difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that suggests your members are well placed to benefit as the economy picks up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, with interest rates at their lowest for generations, now is a good time for stable, profitable businesses to invest for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this government knows that we must play our part too.  And there are 2 main strands to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creating an environment in which ports and maritime-related business of all kinds can succeed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making sure that the infrastructure for which government has direct responsibility complements and supports the work you do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re supporting major container port developments like those already under construction at Felixstowe, London Gateway and Southampton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial if these ports are to welcome the largest container vessels which are coming into service.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ships have the choice not to call in Britain at all if the infrastructure isn’t there.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these investments will help make sure that as many deep-sea boxes as possible are delivered directly to this country.  And that the country is ready for recovery and growth in trade in manufactured goods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which UK port will they come? That’s up to you. I’ll be as interested as anyone to see how the competition in this sector plays out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And others will follow. Liverpool, Bristol, Dover and Teesport also have the necessary consents to expand their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond the container sector, it’s imperative that every port is able to pursue a vision for the future - whether that’s responding to the opportunities brought by offshore energy, or it’s tapping into the potential of the tourism and leisure market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of the business model or maritime market your members choose, I want to make sure the government creates the right environment for them to grow and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="better-infrastructure-less-regulation"&gt;Better infrastructure, less regulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create that environment we’re absolutely committed to investing in the strategic roads and rail infrastructure that serves UK ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes far-reaching improvements to the rail freight network…as part of a £9.4 billion rail investment package announced this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the new initiatives is a high capacity ‘electric rail spine’ running from the south coast ports to the west Midlands and Yorkshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at ways to relieve the congestion on road routes to and from ports&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, we’ve set out a major scheme to boost the capacity of the A14 linking Felixstowe with the Midlands and the North,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most crucial arteries for goods coming into the country and -  together with measures to boost rail freight - this modernisation will help ease the flow of traffic around one of our biggest ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also removing the barriers you face so you can do your job efficiently and profitably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being responsible for ports and shipping, I also have the title ‘Minister for Better Regulation’ within the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I also regard myself as ‘Minister for Less Regulation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So believe me, if I find suffocating red tape that’s getting in your way and slowing you down, I will cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where there are regulations which add no value, I will scrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while we’ve already run through the Red Tape Challenge formalities, here’s a challenge that remains open to you: let me know where there is still any redundant regulation and I will try to get rid of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the case I’ve put this evening is that our ports have a front and centre role in the life of our nation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boosting jobs and growth in Britain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acting as international gateways for trade and travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping us transform our economic prospects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But then you have always been fundamental to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours is the industry that helped turn a small island nation into a major global player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industry with a proud story to tell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also an industry with a great future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it’s a pleasure to be here this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16037</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-to-scrap-motor-insurance-certificates-launched"/>
    <title>Consultation to scrap motor insurance certificates launched</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drivers could benefit from less motor insurance red tape after a government consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates was launched today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8 week exercise will seek the views of the industry, motorists and other stakeholders on the benefits of moving towards a purely online system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under current law, insurance companies must issue a paper or electronic certificate when agreeing a policy. However, many organisations, including the police and vehicle rental companies, already rely on information stored on the Motor Insurer’s Database (MID) as evidence of valid insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More and more people are using technology to organise their everyday lives so it is only right we look at how we can make life easier for motorists and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are launching a consultation to scrap the legal requirement for insurance certificates to be issued and consolidate a system whereby all information is online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has the potential to make significant savings down the line which I hope will be passed on to policyholders. It will also make the lives of motorists and police easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to moving to an online system include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motorists will no longer be forced to retain certificates as details will be accessible online. This will remove the legal requirement whereby vehicle owners are required to return their certificates to insurance companies in order to cancel the policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;police and the commercial motor industry would be better able to check details at source, instead of relying on policyholder documents which can be forged. The Police already use a download of the MID to identify uninsured drivers on the road.
If the consultation is successful then the Department would look to repeal the current law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposal is part of the government’s Red Tape Challenge, which invited the public and stakeholders to give their views on which regulations should stay, be improved, or be scrapped altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"&gt;consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available on the DfT website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department proposes to amend s147 (1) of the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue motor insurance certificates (whether issued as a paper document or electronically)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Association of British Insurers (ABI) estimate the cost of producing each certificate is about £1 and around 34.2 million insurance documents are issued per annum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14942</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T11:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plans-unveiled-to-increase-lorry-speeds-to-boost-growth"/>
    <title>Plans unveiled to increase lorry speeds to boost growth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans to increase the speed limit for some heavy goods vehicles (&lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in a bid to boost economic growth have been announced today by Roads Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current speed limit on single carriageways for &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; over 7.5 tonnes is 40 mph. Under the proposals, this could be increased to 45 mph or 50 mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freight industry say this will help growth by improving journey times, cutting congestion and reducing costs to business and the cost of goods people buy. It could also reduce the number of collisions caused by other road users overtaking slower moving lorries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is committed to doing everything it can to improve conditions for economic growth. We are consulting on increasing the single carriage way speed limit for certain &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; after listening to industry experts who say that this will boost the UK economy and businesses of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While this is likely to lead to more than £30 million a year in benefits for businesses through quicker journeys and reduced congestion, I want to make sure we have carefully considered the evidence of all of the effects on the economy, environment and – of course – road safety before we make a decision. I welcome views from all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; statistics on monitored free-flow roads estimate that around 70% of &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; currently travel over 40 mph and it is argued that these &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; have an unfair competitive advantage over those who stick to the speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed limit for smaller &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; (those between 3.5 tonnes and 7.5 tonnes) is 50 mph. This will remain unchanged. This consultation does not cover any other speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch of the consultation follows a commitment published in ‘The logistics growth review’ in November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 1 February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation is now available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-34"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport estimates that around 280,000 &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt; would be impacted by the changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The maximum speed limit for the road on single carriageways is 60 mph, (unless a local speed limit is in force)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066    &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292   &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/examining-the-speed-limit-for-heavy-goods-vehicles-over-7-5-tonnes-on-single-carriageway-roads"&gt;Consultation on examining the speed limit for heavy goods vehicles over 7.5 tonnes on single carriageway roads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/heavy-goods-vehicle-speed-limit-increase-evaluation-final-report"&gt;Heavy goods vehicle speed limit increase evaluation: final report (PPR 576)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heavy-goods-vehicles"&gt;Heavy goods vehicles, written statement by Stephen Hammond, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
