<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--23</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state--23.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50188</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali"/>
    <title>UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister made his comments following the arrest late on 10 December of Malian Prime Minister Diarra in Bamako by armed men on behalf of the military junta and the subsequent forced resignation of the Prime Minister and his Cabinet earlier today. Mr Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the latest events in Bamako, and particularly by the intervention of the Malian military junta which has forced the resignation today of Prime Minister Diarra and his Cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali. The rapid appointment of a new government of national unity to take forward the political roadmap towards democratic elections and the reunification of Mali is critical to further progress. These events underline the need for coordinated international action, particularly with the United Nations, the African Union and ECOWAS, to achieve stability in Mali.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48079</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa hails Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’ following successful elections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the National Electoral Committee announced the Presidential election results, Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I congratulate John Dramani Mahama on his election as President of Ghana and on elections that were widely recognised to be free, fair and transparent. Ghana has now seen six successful elections since military government ended in 1992 and it is rightly seen as a beacon of democracy in the region. I commend the Ghanaian people, political parties and civil society on the peaceful environment in which the elections were held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The relationship between the UK and Ghana is strong and vibrant. It is rooted in our long-standing economic, political and cultural connections, our shared values, and the deep links between our peoples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to continuing a constructive and productive working relationship with President Mahama and his government, one that continues to bring our countries closer together.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56680</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-the-overseas-territories-and-overseas-territory-leaders-issue-joint-communique-following-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council agree joint communique</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council, chaired by Minister Simmonds and attended by Premiers, Chief Ministers and other elected representatives from Britain’s Overseas Territories, closed today with the agreement of a joint communiqué which sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the second day of the Council also saw the Prime Minister welcome Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said in his foreword in the White Paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom’s 14 Overseas Territories are an integral part of Britain’s life and history. This Government is ambitious for our Territories as we are ambitious for the United Kingdom.  We want to see our communities flourish in partnership, with strong and sustainable local economies. We see an important opportunity to set world standards in our stewardship of the extraordinary natural environments we have inherited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out a very positive vision for the Overseas Territories. This first meeting of the Joint Ministerial Council has helped us identify an ambitious list of priority areas for action, such as encouraging economic growth; protecting the environment and making government work better. We will work closely with the Territories in the coming year to achieve what we have together set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of my Ministerial colleagues from across Government took part in the Council this week, demonstrating that the UK Government as a whole is committed to supporting the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/44286</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/skiiers-avoid-injury-and-expensive-medical-bills"/>
    <title>Skiers: avoid injury and expensive medical bills</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are launching a campaign aimed at Britons visiting European winter sports resorts this winter to explain the dangers of attempting slopes beyond your level of ability, or going off piste without the correct safety equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re heading off a ski or snowboarding holiday this winter, please don’t put yourself at risk by trying to keep up with more experienced members of your party. The number of reported accidents on French slopes in 2012 was high, including seven deaths out of 12 serious incidents*. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="research"&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to new research from the FCO**, of those British nationals that go on winter sports holidays the majority class themselves as beginner or intermediate. Only 1% of respondents classed themselves as expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly two thirds (65%) of winter sports travellers admitted they would ski or snowboard on slopes above their experience in order to stay with a group. More than half (53%) also said they would follow a group of mates off piste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventy per cent admitted they do not always wear a helmet when skiing or snowboarding, and one in five (21%) said they wouldn’t wear a helmet if others in their group weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor, Consul, based in Marseille, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we saw a high number of British nationals end up in hospital with serious injuries. Sadly this included a number of deaths. Many of these accidents can be prevented by taking simple precautionary steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of assuming you’ll be fine if you’re with more experienced skiers or snowboarders. It is significant that a large number of cases we have dealt with have involved off piste skiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those lucky enough to survive an accident and end up in hospital can face months of recovery, so it is important to think carefully beforehand about the very real risks out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="insurance"&gt;Insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third (38%) of winter sports holidaymakers admitted that they don’t always take out travel insurance. One in three (31%) also said they don’t always check their policy to ensure they are covered for winter sports activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many people will be unaware that failing to wear a helmet or skiing off piste can invalidate some insurance policies, so if something does go wrong you could end up with hefty medical bills. In many cases family members then have to help with funds which can put a huge strain on families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The FCO cannot pay for hospital treatment or for medical repatriation back to the UK, which is why it is so important to check your insurance covers you for everything you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="top-tips-to-stay-safe-on-the-slopes"&gt;Top tips to stay safe on the slopes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take out insurance – and check what it covers. It might not cover off piste skiing unless you are with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a check-up before you ski - one of the major causes of hospitalisation and death on the slopes is heart attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t drink and ski. Alcohol can affect you more quickly at high altitudes and dangerously limits your awareness of risk and cold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most skiing injuries are caused by collisions with other skiers – watch your speed and distance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t attempt slopes you’re not experienced or fit enough to tackle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to go off piste, go with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If going off piste carry a shovel, a probe and a transceiver in case of an avalanche. Also remember that you need proper training on how to use a transceiver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are going out on a glacier, you must wear a harness. If you fall into a crevasse, this will help the rescue team get you out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure someone knows where you’re going and tell them of any changes to your plans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only go off piste skiing or climbing with someone you have met previously and can trust. You need to know his/her capabilities, what you’ll be doing and where.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For further tips and advice on preparing for travel abroad, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.fco.gov.uk/travel" title="FCO Travel Advice"&gt;www.fco.gov.uk/travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Figures taken from FCO 2011/12 consular assistance data &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Survey conducted by ICM. Total sample size was 2,023 UK adults aged 18 and over. Fieldwork was undertaken in November 2012. The figures have been weighted and are representative of all UK adults aged 18 and over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17809</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>UK and Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds, has opened the first annual Joint Ministerial Council, bringing together political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers to drive forward implementation of the vision and strategy set out in the June 2012 White Paper &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/overseas-territories/overseas-territories-white-paper/" title="Overseas Territotories White Paper"&gt;The Overseas Territories: Security, Success and Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council aims to agree priorities and plans for the UK and the Territories to work together on wide range of issues including: building successful and resilient economies; harnessing support from the Commonwealth and the EU; cherishing the environment and creating green growth; working together for better government; building stronger, healthier and safer communities; health; and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister will welcome elected leaders to Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister. Ministers and senior officials from wide range of UK Departments will take part in the Council, demonstrating the commitment from across government to working with the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the meeting Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to welcome elected leaders from the Overseas Territories to the Joint Ministerial Council. This is an opportunity for us to strengthen our work together to build flourishing communities, proudly retaining aspects of their British identity, creating new opportunities for young and future generations and protecting natural environments to the highest international standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year, we have demonstrated our commitment to preserving the astounding natural environment in the territories, by establishing a new Marine Protected Area in South Georgia &amp;amp; the South Sandwich Islands and launching Darwin Plus, the new Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35628</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uk-welcomes-the-success-of-sierra-leones-elections"/>
    <title>The UK welcomes the success of Sierra Leone's elections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK welcomes the success of Sierra Leone’s Presidential, Parliamentary and local multi-party elections, which demonstrates growing political maturity and strengthening stability and security. I would like to congratulate President Koroma on winning re-election to a second term in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This was the first Sierra Leonean election since the civil war which ended in 2002 to be run entirely by national democratic institutions. The UK commends the Sierra Leoneans for their commitment to international standards and the efficient running of the elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The large numbers of Sierra Leone’s citizens who turned out to cast their ballots on 17 November have made their voice clear. We call on all political parties to accept the result. Any remaining concerns with the process should be submitted to the authorities and resolved professionally and peacefully. The UK calls on all parties to continue to abide by the rule of law, renounce violence and incitement to violence and respect human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to continuing our work with President Koroma and his Government in support of progress, sustainable economic development and lasting peace in Sierra Leone and the region.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35626</id>
    <published>2012-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-comments-on-agreement-about-eastern-drc-agreed-in-kampala-today"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa comments on agreement about Eastern DRC agreed in Kampala today</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister returned yesterday from an urgent three day visit to Uganda, Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). Violence has been escalating in Eastern DRC and the situation on the ground there has continued to evolve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking today, he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s summit offered a major opportunity for the three Presidents, of DRC, Rwanda and Uganda together with their partners in the region, to once again demonstrate their determination to end this crisis, and to seek new ways to resolve the underlying causes of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased that the summit resulted in a 10-point Communique, specifying long and short term actions to be taken by all parties, but crucially including a renewed call for the M23 to leave Goma without delay. Clearly, an important test will now be whether that happens or not. We will study the Communique and its implications carefully over the coming days, including what more we and the rest of the international community should do to support ongoing regional efforts to resolve the current crisis in a sustainable way”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56698</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T15:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T15:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-simmonds-visits-africa-to-support-efforts-to-end-crisis-in-goma"/>
    <title>Mark Simmonds visits Africa to support efforts to end crisis in Goma</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds will first visit Uganda and then travel on to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo. During his trip, he will meet regional leaders to discuss the political work underway to resolve the crisis and the humanitarian situation. He will urge leaders to use any influence they have to bring an end to the crisis and limit its impact on civilian populations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am travelling to the region at short notice to show that the UK is focused on the serious and urgent crisis unfolding in Goma and to show my support to the people of the DRC. I am deeply concerned by the current crisis and I urge the M23 militia to stop their offensive and for all external support to the M23 militia to stop.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On my visit I will be meeting with government ministers from across the region and will ask them all to find, first and foremost, a resolution that will swiftly end the fighting and produce a sustainable long term plan that will ensure peace and stability for the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35607</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-travelling-to-uganda-rwanda-and-the-democratic-republic-of-congo"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister travelling to Uganda, Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, is travelling to Uganda today. This is the first leg of an unscheduled three stop trip to the region, which will include visits to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit will serve to support international efforts to bring an end to the crisis currently engulfing Goma. During his trip, Minister Simmonds will be meeting with regional leaders to discuss the situation, including political efforts underway to resolve the crisis, and the humanitarian situation. He will be pressing key actors to use any influence they have to bring an end to the crisis and limit its impact on civilian populations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am travelling to the region at short notice to show that the UK is focused on the serious and urgent crisis unfolding in Goma and to show my support to the people of the DRC. I am deeply concerned by the current crisis and I urge the M23 to stop their offensive and for all external support to the M23 to cease.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On my visit I will be meeting with my counterparts from across the region and will call on all to find, first and foremost, a resolution that will swiftly end the immediate fighting and produce a sustainable long term plan that will ensure peace and stability for the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
