<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/prime-minister</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/prime-minister.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Prime Minister</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35559</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-us-presidential-election"/>
    <title>The US Presidential election</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has given his reaction to Barack Obama’s victory in the US Presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister spoke during his visit to Jordan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to congratulate Barack Obama on his re-election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have really enjoyed working with him over the last few years and I look forward to working with him again over the next four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are so many things that we need to do: we need to kick start the world economy and I want to see an EU-US trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Right here in Jordan I am hearing appalling stories about what has happened inside Syria so one of the first things I want to talk to Barack about is how we must do more to try and solve this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Above all, congratulations to Barack. I’ve enjoyed working with him, I think he’s a very successful US president and I look forward to working with him in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27970</id>
    <published>2012-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-and-foreign-secretary-attend-un-general-assembly-ministerial-week"/>
    <title>Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary attend UN General Assembly Ministerial Week</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations General Assembly Ministerial Week, 24 - 30 September brought together Heads of State and Government and Ministers from all 193 member nations to address global issues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreign Secretary discusses UN General Assembly Ministerial Week September 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_OGuSMAbAo" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full coverage:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 29 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816829782"&gt;Ministers take steps to strengthen the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign Secretary William Hague, and Minister of State for the Commonwealth Hugo Swire represented the UK at the Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York today, where Ministers agreed measures to strengthen and modernise the Commonwealth._&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: In the margins of Commonwealth Foreign Ministers meeting, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ow.ly/i/YHt3"&gt;Papua New Guinea Foreign Minister Pato&lt;/a&gt;; Foreign Secretary William Hague and Minister Swire meet &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ow.ly/i/YGGB"&gt;Australian Foreign Minister Carr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday 28 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816800882"&gt;Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security&lt;/a&gt;” - UK Statement by Baroness Warsi at the UN High Level Meeting on Countering Nuclear Terrorism - 28 September 2012&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816794482"&gt;Foreign Secretary statement on the importance of isolating the Assad regime and ending impunity&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign Secretary William Hague spoke after today’s meeting of the core group of the Friends of Syria._   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816718382"&gt;Foreign Secretary welcomes extension of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria&lt;/a&gt; - The UN Human Rights Council today passed a further resolution on Syria which condemned the appalling human rights violations by the Syrian regime and extended the mandate of the UN Commission of Inquiry._   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816566182"&gt;Minister for Africa calls for international condemnation of support for militia groups in eastern DRC&lt;/a&gt; - The Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, attended the UN High Level Meeting on the Great Lakes yesterday which aimed to focus attention on the instability in the region, and encourage a consensus on the way forward._&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: New photos of yesterday’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/sets/72157631644736299/"&gt;Friends of Yemen meeting&lt;/a&gt; co-chaired by Foreign Secretary William Hague.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Foreign Secretary William Hague meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8033891136/in/photostream"&gt;Prime Minister of Ethiopia Hailemariam Desalegn&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8033890599/in/photostream"&gt;Vice President of South Sudan Riek Machar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday 27 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816439682"&gt;Foreign Secretary calls for more action to help Yemen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=Speech&amp;amp;id=816427082"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague’s opening remarks at the fourth UN General Assembly Friends of Yemen Ministerial&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=816428182"&gt;With genuine commitment from all involved, in partnership with the government of DRC, long term sustainable solutions can be achieved&lt;/a&gt;” - Statement by UK Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, at the UNGA Mini-Summit on the situation in Eastern DRC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816393382"&gt;meets Ecuadorian Foreign Minister Ricardo Patino&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816492782"&gt;I congratulate Sudan and South Sudan on bringing these intensive weeks of negotiation to a positive outcome”&lt;/a&gt; - Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds speaks at the High Level Sudan/ South Sudan Consultative Forum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816557082"&gt;signs cooperation agreement with the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031011088/in/photostream"&gt;Tunisian Foreign Minister Rafik Abdessalem&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031010856/in/photostream"&gt;Arab League Secretary-General al Araiby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031010688/in/photostream"&gt;UN Under-Secretary-General Ameerah Haq&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031015521/in/photostream"&gt;Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Trinidad and Tobago Honourable Winston Dookeran&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Baroness Warsi meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031015521/in/photostream"&gt;Secretary General of Organisation of Islamic Cooperation Professor Ekmeleddin Ihsanoglo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesday 26 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816032182"&gt;The UK will provide an additional £10 million to help the new government of Somalia&lt;/a&gt;” - Intervention by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague at the Secretary-General Mini Summit on Somalia&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816037482"&gt;The Arab Spring is a moment of huge opportunity to build peace, security and prosperity for the region and by extension, the world”&lt;/a&gt; _ - _Intervention by the Foreign Secretary William Hague, at the UN Security Council meeting on Peace and Security in Middle East and North Africa&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028570787/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;photo&lt;/a&gt;)  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816028582"&gt;The United Kingdom restates its longstanding commitment to the people of Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt; - Statement of the delegation of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in exercise of the right of reply to the remarks made by the Prime Minister of Spain in the general debate on 25 September 2012&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816014282"&gt;There can be no negotiations on the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands unless and until such time as the islanders so wish&lt;/a&gt;” - Statement of the delegation of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in exercise of the right of reply to the remarks made by the President of the Argentine Republic in the General Debate on 25 September&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816006082"&gt;Statement by the UK Prime Minister David Cameron&lt;/a&gt; to the 67th Session of the UN General Assembly (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028713668/in/photostream"&gt;photo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816016582"&gt;We need to unite to develop effective international action to help the Malian Government restore territorial integrity, democratic legitimacy and national security&lt;/a&gt;” - UK Statement by Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs Mark Simmonds to the Sahel Ministerial Summit&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816001782"&gt;UN Commission on Life-Saving Commodities and contraceptive implants&lt;/a&gt;: Remarks at stakeout by UK Secretary of State for International Development Justine Greening _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Prime Minister David Cameron meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8026643446/in/photostream/"&gt;Egyptian President Mohamed Mursi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8026644869/in/photostream/"&gt;Libyan President Mohamed Yousef El-Magariaf&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8027012697/in/photostream/"&gt;Pakistani President Asif Ali Zardari and Afghan President Hamid Karzai&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Foreign Secretary William Hague meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028511583/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Brazilian Foreign Minister Antonio Patriota&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028506954/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mali Prime Minister Cheick Modibo Diarra&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028511747/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Rwanda’s Foreign Minister Louise Mushikiwabo&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507080/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Minister for Foreign Affairs of Cote d’Ivoire Daniel Kablan Duncan&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507152/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;DRC Foreign Minister Raymond Tshibanda&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Baroness Warsi meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507118/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Afghanistan’s Deputy Foreign Minister Jawed Ludin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 25 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=815183582"&gt;pledges £1 million to tackle sexual violence in conflict&lt;/a&gt;; Remarks by Foreign Secretary William Hague to the open UN General Assembly side-event ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815158082"&gt;Preventing sexual and gender-based crimes in conflict and securing justice for survivors&lt;/a&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815338182"&gt;Peacebuilding: A way towards sustainable peace and security&lt;/a&gt; - Baroness Warsi speaks at UN Peacebuilding debate_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815338582"&gt;We have a clear objective and that is the ending of global absolute poverty”&lt;/a&gt; - Prime Minister David Cameron remarks at media stakeout as a Co-Chair of the Secretary-General’s High-level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda .&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024544363/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mr. Burt meets Dr Abdul Samad Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of the Maldives; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024459099/in/photostream"&gt;Mr. Burt meets UNODC Executive Director Yury Fedotov&lt;/a&gt; at the UN General Assembly; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023843504/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Mr Hoshyar Zebari&lt;/a&gt;, Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affairs; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023619618/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Youssef Amran&lt;/a&gt;, Moroccan Deputy Foreign Minister&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In pictures:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024459623/in/photostream"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague meets Mr Wunna Maung Lwin&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of Myanmar; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024276955/in/photostream"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague recording an interview&lt;/a&gt; on CNN’s Amanpour; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023844685/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague meets with the US President Barack Obama and First Lady Michelle Obama&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monday 24 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=814594782"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Yemeni President Hadi visits UK ahead of Friends of Yemen meeting in New York&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=814670882#.UGDdTctp4Zw.twitter"&gt;Baroness Warsi speaks at the ECOSOC Special Ministerial meeting&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8021315719/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Najib Mikati,&lt;/a&gt; Prime Minister of Lebanon; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8020907586/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mr Burt meets Khalid bin Ahmed Al Khalifa&lt;/a&gt;, the Bahraini Foreign Minister; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8021031172/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Baroness Warsi meets Hamrokhon Zarifi&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of Tajikistan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key issues for Ministerial Week included the situation in Syria, and efforts to support stability in Somalia and Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK hosted the fourth Friends of Yemen Ministerial meeting. Ministerial Week also saw the first meeting of the High Level Panel on the post-2015 development agenda, which was co-chaired by the Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague co-hosted an event on preventing sexual violence in conflict, with the UN Secretary General’s Special Representative and UN Women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find further information and news on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;UK Mission to the United Nations&lt;/a&gt;  website and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/UKUN_NewYork"&gt;@UKUN_NewYork&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27935</id>
    <published>2012-09-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/a-significant-moment-for-somalia-prime-minister-congratulates-new-president"/>
    <title>A significant moment for Somalia: Prime Minister congratulates new president</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a significant moment for Somalia, and an important step towards a renewed political process. I congratulate Hassan Sheikh Mohamud on his victory and welcome the part played by outgoing president Sheikh Sharif, to bring Somalia to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The coming months and years are critical for Somalia’s transition to democracy. Somalia’s leaders must now work together to build a more representative and transparent system, tackle corruption and strengthen security and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The London Conference on Somalia in February brought the international community together to support this process. Britain will continue to support Somalia’s people and leaders, so that Somalia can fulfill its potential as a peaceful, inclusive and prosperous nation.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27922</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-foreign-office-ministerial-team"/>
    <title>New Foreign Office ministerial team</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Affairs: Rt Hon William Hague MP:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall responsibility for the work of the Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy Unit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Honours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intelligence policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyber security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Minister of State: Rt Hon Baroness Warsi  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Afghanistan, Pakistan, Bangladesh&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Central Asia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human Rights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UN, International Organisations and ICC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All of FCO business in the Lords  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Europe: Rt Hon David Lidington MP  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Union (including Gibraltar and SBAs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Europe, including Balkans, Ukraine, Belarus and Moldova &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Russia, South Caucasus,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NATO and European Security &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OSCE and Council of Europe &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FCO relations with Parliament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FCO Finance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estates and Security &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information and Technology  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State: Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP 
  * Far East and South East Asia 
  * India and Nepal 
  * Latin America (including: Dominican Republic, Haiti and Cuba) 
  * Falklands
  * Australasia and Pacific 
  * Commonwealth
  * Migration
  * Emerging Powers Co-ordination 
  * Public diplomacy, Olympics legacy and the GREAT campaign
  * International Economy
  * Prosperity work, including FCO’s relations with British Business, in support of Lord Green
  * Drugs and International Crime  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State: Alistair Burt MP    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Counter Terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Counter Proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Counter Piracy &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North America &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Middle East and North Africa &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maldives and Sri Lanka&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defence policy (except NATO and European Security)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human Resources and Diversity &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ministerial correspondence  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State: Mark Simmonds MP  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Africa&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overseas Territories (not Falklands, SBAs or Gibraltar) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflict Issues &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climate Change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;International Energy &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protocol &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ministerial Oversight for FCO Services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Caribbean (not including Dominican Republic, Haiti or Cuba)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Trade and Investment: Lord Green of Hurstpierpoint  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leading on FCO relations with British Business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commercial Economic Diplomacy Department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economics Unit &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK Trade and Investment (joint Minister with Dept. for Business, Innovation and Skills)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Export Credits Guarantee Department (ECGD) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spokesman for the Government on trade and investment issues in the House of Lords &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business policy  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27890</id>
    <published>2012-08-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-ministers-statement-on-the-death-of-the-prime-minister-of-ethiopia"/>
    <title>Prime Minister's statement on the death of the Prime Minister of Ethiopia</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It was with great sadness that I learnt of the death of the Prime Minister of Ethiopia Meles Zenawi. Prime Minister Meles was an inspirational spokesman for Africa on global issues and provided leadership and vision on Somalia, Sudan and South Sudan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“His personal contribution to Ethiopia’s development, in particular by lifting millions of Ethiopians out of poverty, has set an example for the region. Our thoughts are with his family and with the nation of Ethiopia. He will be greatly missed.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27855</id>
    <published>2012-08-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-brazil-to-co-host-event-to-tackle-global-hunger"/>
    <title>UK and Brazil to co-host event to tackle global hunger</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost one in three of the world’s poorest children cannot reach their full potential due to malnutrition.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday 12 August, Prime Minister David Cameron and Vice President Michel Temer of Brazil will challenge global leaders to step up efforts to improve nutrition and reduce the rate of stunting among the world’s poorest children between now and the next Olympics in 2016.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Global Hunger Event will help to strengthen these commitments by identifying pioneering new ways of working to tackle malnutrition and bringing in new champions to support the global movement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central part of London’s successful bid for the Games has been the legacy it will create for Britain - reinvigorating one of the poorest parts of the country and inspiring a whole generation of young people.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that this event on the closing day of the Games will mean that London 2012 also has a lasting legacy for millions more children around the world by improving their nutrition and giving them the opportunity to fulfil their potential too. A new global target to reduce the number of stunted children by 70 million by 2025 has been agreed by the World Health Assembly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest updates on the Summit:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/DFID/global-nutrition-event"&gt;View the story “Global Hunger Event” on Storify&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27783</id>
    <published>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-ministers-statement-on-the-death-of-president-mills-of-ghana"/>
    <title>Prime Minister's statement on the death of President Mills of Ghana</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was deeply saddened to hear about the death of President Mills earlier today. President Mills was a tireless defender of democracy in West Africa and across the continent, and he will be greatly missed. Our thoughts and prayers are with his wife and family, and all the Ghanaian people on this difficult day.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27764</id>
    <published>2012-07-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/afghan-national-army-officer-academy-agreement"/>
    <title>Afghan National Army Officer Academy agreement</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron and President Karzai have signed a Memorandum of Understanding for the UK to provide mentors and advisers for the Afghan National Army Officer Academy modelled on the Royal Military Academy Sandhurst in the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the signing ceremony, David Cameron said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope [the Academy] will be a lasting contribution from my country to the people of Afghanistan to help with the training and development of your officers and your army.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re building up Afghan forces so they can protect your citizens and keep out violent extremists once the international forces leave. We are strengthening democracy and governance so that all Afghans can play their part in developing a more prosperous country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we’re working with regional partners, because a stable Afghanistan is not just in the interests of Afghans, but in the interests of their neighbours too.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 18 July, Mr Cameron visited British forces in Helmand Province, where he said he was impressed with the huge progress being made.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also spoke about the post-2014 commitment to Afghanistan, and the political process. He spoke about the message the commitment sends to the Taliban:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You cannot wait this out until foreign forces leave in 2014, because we will be firm friends and supporters of Afghanistan long beyond then.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he talked about the vital role that Afghanistan’s neighbours have to play, and the shared interests between Afghanistan and Pakistan. The Press Conference was held before a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=790494782"&gt;trilateral meeting with the Prime Minister of Pakistan Raja Pervez Ashraf&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over the last two months in Chicago and Tokyo, the international community has made clear our commitment to securing Afghanistan’s future and prosperity for decades to come. We are here to work with you to transform the future together.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27759</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-visits-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>Prime Minister visits Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron today arrived in Helmand Province for a tour of Camp Bastion, the UK’s largest Afghan base. Mr Cameron visited frontline troops from the 1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment at the Shawqat base in Nad-e-Ali and saw a provincial reconstruction team in Lashkar Gah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked about major reductions in troop numbers, the Prime Minister said it had been a difficult decision to make but insisted the coalition needed a defence budget which made sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussing the withdrawal of British troops, Mr Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What I will commit to is that we will do this in a sensible, ordered, practical way - 9,500 to 9,000 this year. As Afghan troops take a bigger role we will be able to reduce troop numbers further next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t want to see some cliff edge. I’m confident we are going to have a staged reduction and deliver a safe and secure situation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very pleased to be here because I want to thank our Armed Forces for all the incredible work that they do.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27696</id>
    <published>2012-06-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-congratulates-president-mohamed-mursi-on-his-election-victory"/>
    <title>Prime Minister congratulates President Mohamed Mursi on his election victory</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The British Government has welcomed President Mursi’s statement that he intends to form an inclusive government that governs on behalf of all the Egyptian people. The Prime Minister wished President Mursi success in the task of supporting Egypt’s transition to democracy and building the stable, inclusive and prosperous future which Egyptians deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister emphasised his strong belief that the establishment of functioning democratic institutions which deliver the people’s aspirations for reform and accountability will be important to pave the way to greater stability.&lt;br&gt;
He also underlined the importance of swiftly establishing a government that reflects the breadth of political forces within the new Egypt and agreement over a new Constitution through an inclusive and transparent process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron reiterated that he looked forward to working with Dr Morsi and his government on issues of common interest for the peace and stability of the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
