<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/prime-minister</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/prime-minister.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Prime Minister</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T13:41:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T13:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T13:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16885</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T15:30:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-shines-at-the-civil-service-awards"/>
    <title>MOD shines at the Civil Service Awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Civil servants gathered together yesterday for the awards ceremony at Lancaster House in London. Hosted by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/" title="BBC"&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; TV presenters Jon Sopel and Sian Williams, the event honoured outstanding individuals and teams across government for their contribution to public services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/news/civil-service-awards" title="Civil Service Awards 2012"&gt;The Civil Service Awards&lt;/a&gt; celebrate and promote innovation and improvement across the entire breadth of central government. They recognise people who are leading the way in these areas and champion them as examples of best practice that can be applied across the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/" title="Civil Service"&gt;Civil Service&lt;/a&gt;. This year 850 nominations were received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Awards featured 18 main categories. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; was shortlisted in two of them. As well as the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s civilian Standing Joint Commander [&lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt;] (UK) nomination, Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie were nominated for the Achieving Better for Less Award. The judges accepted the fact that Defence has a unique &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; and opened the competition up to Service personnel as well as civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full citations and a list of all the winners can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://network.civilservicelive.com/pages/view/710933/civil-service-awards-winners-2012" title="Civil Service Awards Winners 2012"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video message at the event Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This summer we showed the world the best face of Britain and your efforts were a big part of that success. So I am very pleased to see a special category tonight recognising achievements in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Britain’s Civil Service is a great source of national pride. Your excellence, innovation and professionalism and your values, integrity and impartiality, honesty and objectivity are rightly respected around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the event, Sir Bob Kerslake, Head of the Civil Service, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s not often we have a chance to celebrate the excellent work we do in the Civil Service. What these nominations demonstrate is that it is a great place to work and what we do matters greatly to the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to sincerely thank all of you for your passion and dedication and innovation; it is truly impressive, it is truly great. You should all feel incredibly proud of your achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympic Team Award was a one-off category created for the 2012 Civil Service Awards to celebrate individuals, teams and volunteers who showed excellence in delivering the &lt;a href="London%202012" title="http://www.london2012.com/"&gt;2012 Games&lt;/a&gt;. Over 100 nominations were received for this category alone. The award was judged by a panel including the new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.teamgb.com/" title="British Olympic Association "&gt;British Olympic Association&lt;/a&gt; Chairman, Lord Sebastian Coe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video message played just before the winners were revealed Lord Coe said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The quality of the London Games was predicated almost entirely on the secure, robust relationships that we formed. And nowhere were those relationships more secure and robust than across government. There were 19 government departments that helped us deliver the Games. No organising committee alone can do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of you I know worked long and hard and put all sorts of things on hold to make sure these Games were the extraordinary success they were. Thank you for being such true and trusted teams to help us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting the award to the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team, Jonathan Stephens, Permanent Secretary at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/" title="Department for Culture, Media and Sport"&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This summer was a summer like no other. It was a great opportunity to put on a show to the world. It was also only made possible by the very best of public service and Civil Service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Staff Sergeants Andy Laurie and Marc Smith" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1181/CSAwards01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Staff Sergeants Andy Laurie and Marc Smith from the Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers Training Wing [Picture: Crown Copyright/&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team is made up of Angie Rogers, Sarah Williams, Kerry Kellett, Sheila Symes, Miles Tooke, Charlie Bird and Jo McKeegan-Brown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking moments after receiving their award, the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are really proud of what we have achieved. We worked so hard over the summer. It’s just recognition of that achievement. The award is not just for us, it’s for our families and friends who put up with us being away from them every weekend for six months and for supporting us when we worked long hours during the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces contribution to the Games was recognised throughout the summer but this award recognises the civilians too. It shows the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; as a team, with civil servants and military working together. It doesn’t matter if it’s in Afghanistan or the UK - we can still do a good job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; team was up against Operation Stepchange from the &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport" title="Department for Transport"&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/a&gt;, which tested travel and business continuity plans across government in readiness for the Games; the UK Wide Operations Olympic and Paralympic Torch Team from the Department for Culture, Media and Sport, which co-ordinated the Olympic Torch Relay across the UK; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalparks.org.uk/" title="Royal Parks"&gt;Royal Parks&lt;/a&gt;, which hosted a number of the Olympic events watched by two million spectators. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Service Awards support the wider Civil Service reform plan. One of the plan’s main priorities is for all government departments to find new ways of delivering services. It aims to transform the Civil Service so that it will have a more innovative and less hierarchical culture, with a much sharper focus on outcomes rather than processes, and will be more flexible and corporate. Many aspects of the plan came from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/tell-us-how" title="Tell Us How"&gt;‘Tell Us How’&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Cabinet Office"&gt;Cabinet Office’s&lt;/a&gt; suggestion scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; itself uses GEMS, its own staff suggestion scheme, to encourage innovation within Defence. The ideas scheme was launched in 1996 and is open to all Defence civilian and Service personnel, including ex-employees, anywhere in the world. It is the third most successful ideas scheme in the world. Those who make successful suggestions receive a financial reward. GEMS is a key part of Transforming Defence. It falls under the Behaviours and Business Improvement workstream, linking closely with the ‘Be A Leader - Think Defence - Do It Better’ behaviour change work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GEMS also glittered at the Civil Service Awards, showing the rest of Whitehall how we in Defence are ‘Doing It Better’. Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie, who were nominated for the Achieving Better for Less Award, earlier this week won the GEMS Idea of the Year Award and a commendation in the Most Operational Benefit category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Armoured Frame Electrical Layout is a training aid for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/reme/reme.aspx" title="Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers"&gt;Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers&lt;/a&gt; vehicle mechanics to fix electrical problems in protected mobility vehicles. This is currently a real problem in Afghanistan, and this innovation will help the mechanics in theatre to learn how to make faster repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two Staff Sergeants were up against the Respiratory Team from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/index.htm" title="Department of Health"&gt;Department of Health&lt;/a&gt;, which in the end won the Achieving Better for Less Award. The team retendered contracts for the regional Home Oxygen Service. The other nominee was the Property Asset Management Unit which is a shared service between the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/" title="Department for Education"&gt;Department for Education&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government" title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;. It maintains the buildings for both departments at a significantly reduced cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although we didn’t win our category we were very pleased to be nominated. We work with civil servants quite closely and it was a privilege to come here and see the recognition they received. We felt the winning nomination deserved it, and we commend them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permanent Secretary Jon Thompson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My congratulations to the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Team for their win, and to Staff Sergeants Smith and Laurie for their nomination. There was fierce competition from other government departments at the Civil Service Awards this year and the bar was set very high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strong performance at the Awards recognises our commitment to ‘Doing It Better’, and shows how highly our innovative work is regarded outside the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50198</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/piracy-ransoms-task-force-publishes-recommendations"/>
    <title>Piracy Ransoms Task Force publishes recommendations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force was established by the Prime Minister, David Cameron, after the London Conference on Somalia in February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14-nation Task Force, brought together policy makers from some of the world’s largest Flag States (countries where vessels are registered), nations whose seafarers are most commonly at risk, and those countries at the forefront of the military response to piracy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Task Force made four recommendations in its final report to the Contact Group on Piracy off the Coast of Somalia in New York:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a new strategic partnership between Flag States, the private sector and law enforcement agencies that brings together those tackling piracy and those subjected to it in a united effort to break the piracy business model;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a more co-ordinated approach to information-sharing to provide evidence to pursue and prosecute all involved in piracy;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen co-ordination between Flag States, the private sector and military responders to prepare for potential hostage situations; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage implementation of anti-piracy measures, including greater compliance with Best Management Practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s conclusions from the Piracy Ransoms Task Force are a welcome step in the right direction. International action, led by the UK, is starting to beat back in the global fight against piracy. The dramatic reduction in pirate activity in the past year shows how important collective action is, and the recommendations of the Task Force should make it harder for pirates to receive, and to profit from, ransom payments. But seafarers of all nations remain at risk, and we must continue to work to break the piracy business model, with the ultimate ambition of bringing an end to ransom payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Government firmly supports and endorses the conclusions of the Piracy Ransoms Task Force. Only through the international community working together to break the pirates’ business model will we reach a position whereby pirates are no longer able to receive or profit from ransom payments. The Government will continue to work as a leading member of the Contact Group and with industry in taking forward the implementation of the task force’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56230</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/life-sciences-strategy-one-year-on"/>
    <title>  Life Sciences Strategy: one year on</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the UK has generated more than £1 billion on industry and private sector investment within 12 months.  This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£500 million from GSK to build its first new manufacturing plant in almost 40 years at Ulverston in Cumbria and invest more in its two sites at Montrose and Irvine in Scotland as a direct response to the introduction of the Patent Box&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£25 million leveraged in from the private sector to bridge the ‘Valley of Death’ adding to a government commitment of £49 million to 64 projects through the Biomedical Catalyst&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£294 million through the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (&lt;abbr title="UK Research Partnership Investment Fund"&gt;UK RPIF&lt;/abbr&gt;) from businesses and charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Real progress has been made working closely with companies across the sector to ensure the measures in the strategy are making a real difference to their work and their decisions to invest in and remain in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes investing £1 billion per annum through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500 million in our translational research infrastructure in the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; to boost networks between academia, industry and the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="revolutionising-the-fight-against-cancer"&gt;Revolutionising the fight against cancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron also announced that the UK will be the first country in the world to introduce to introduce high-tech &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; mapping for cancer patients and those with rare diseases, within the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.  Up to  100,000 patients over three to five years will have their whole genome – their personal &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; code –sequenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genome profile will give doctors a new, advanced understanding of a patient’s genetic make-up, condition and treatment needs, ensuring they have access to the right drugs and personalised care far quicker than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also help to develop life-saving new drugs, treatments and scientific breakthroughs, which experts predict could significantly reduce the number of premature deaths from cancer within a generation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has earmarked £100 million: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to train a new generation of British genetic scientists to lead on the development of new drugs, treatments and cures, building the UK as the world leader in the field. And train the wider healthcare community in harnessing this technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to pump-prime &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; sequencing for cancer and rare inherited diseases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to build the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; data infrastructure to ensure that this new technology leads to better care for patients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="reaction"&gt;Reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Science and Universities David Willetts said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life sciences is one of the most truly international sectors – so if we are to continue to be a world player and compete in the global race we must do everything we can to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past year, our initiatives have attracted more than £1 billion of private sector investment to the UK. We can see clear evidence the UK is succeeding in creating the right environment to attract global investment to our shores and continue to be world leader in life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am announcing today that we are committing a further £100 million to support this sector out of the extra money for science announced by the chancellor in his Autumn Statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;David Willetts speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;Life Sciences at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;a Strategy for UK Life Sciences: One Year On’ report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/dna-tests-to-fight-cancer/"&gt;Notice: &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; tests to revolutionise fight against cancer and help 100,000 &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; patients&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35559</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-us-presidential-election"/>
    <title>The US Presidential election</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has given his reaction to Barack Obama’s victory in the US Presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister spoke during his visit to Jordan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to congratulate Barack Obama on his re-election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have really enjoyed working with him over the last few years and I look forward to working with him again over the next four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are so many things that we need to do: we need to kick start the world economy and I want to see an EU-US trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Right here in Jordan I am hearing appalling stories about what has happened inside Syria so one of the first things I want to talk to Barack about is how we must do more to try and solve this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Above all, congratulations to Barack. I’ve enjoyed working with him, I think he’s a very successful US president and I look forward to working with him in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57550</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-inspects-new-carrier-construction"/>
    <title>Prime Minister inspects new carrier construction</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arriving at 1100hrs on Monday, the Prime Minister met around 200 people working on the project which will see the country’s most powerful ever warship, HMS Queen Elizabeth, handed over to the Ministry of Defence in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge at 280 metres in length, 65,000 tonnes and capable of embarking 40 aircraft - twice the capacity of HMS Illustrious - the aircraft carrier is being constructed at shipyards across the country and assembled at Rosyth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing the workers, Mr Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think this is the success story that the whole of the United Kingdom can take great pride in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just as the Olympics showed what we can do when we come together, you’re showing it right here in Rosyth with this incredible feat of engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has been and still is an immense task and, as soon as you have completed this aircraft carrier, the Prince of Wales will follow, and I am very proud to be standing here and to say thank you to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As was said at the Olympics, we want to make sure ‘Made in the United Kingdom’ is a badge we can be really proud of and I believe that, with these aircraft carriers, you here in Rosyth are making it absolutely clear that it is something we can all be really proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron’s visit coincided with the moving of the aft - or back - section of the hull onto one of the two largest barges in the world at Govan shipyard, ready for its move to Rosyth on 3 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be the final hull section of HMS Queen Elizabeth to arrive at the dockyard where BAE Systems and Babcock are working together to put all the sections together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production of the second carrier, HMS Prince of Wales, has also started at Govan and Portsmouth dockyards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angus Holt, Queen Elizabeth Class Block Delivery Director at BAE Systems, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today marks the culmination of months of hard work and preparation and I am extremely proud of the team’s achievements in successfully loading out the aft section on time and built to an exceptional standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sheer size and complexity of the block both highlights the skill Clyde and the huge amount of progress which we continue to make deliver the nation’s flagships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vessels are being delivered by the Aircraft Carrier Alliance, a partnership between BAE Systems, Thales UK, Babcock and the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57579</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-takes-the-salute-at-royal-naval-college"/>
    <title>Prime Minister takes the salute at Royal Naval College</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 256 Royal Navy personnel were on parade at the Britannia Royal Naval College in Dartmouth to mark the occasion as Mr Cameron inspected the successful cadets, watched by their families and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing the parade, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy is absolutely fundamental to our security as an island nation. And it’s a vital part of our heritage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The challenges you face over the coming years may place demands on you experienced by few others of your age in the world today. Despite the technology of today, being in the Armed Forces is an intensely human business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is based on personal relationships and the ability of people like you to lead your fellow men and women, even in the face of danger. And there is no greater honour that a nation can bestow than the trust to lead your fellow men and women. That is the task you will have. Your training here has given you the best possible start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among those completing training was 21-year-old Midshipman Miles Amery from Torquay, whose father Chief Petty Officer Bill Amery also works at the college. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Completing the maritime leadership exercise on the River Dart was one of the most enthralling weeks of the course. It was challenging, hard work, we were sleep-deprived, but overall it was great fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passing the exercise and being assessed as strong was a huge highlight of training. Training on board HMS York was another exciting part of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPO Amery has served in the Royal Navy for nearly 36 years. He has served both at sea and ashore all around the world; the last six years as an instructor of Officer Cadets at Dartmouth. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be able to stand alongside my son at his passing out parade is the proudest day of my life. Our family’s union with the Royal Navy goes back many generations. To be able to present my grandfather’s naval sword to him was a unique moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Miles has an exciting, challenging and rewarding career ahead of him. Needless to say, I shall be following his every move with envy. My only hope is that I don’t have to bump into him every day and have to salute and call him sir!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new course was introduced in February 2012 and is split into three distinct ten-week phases known as Militarisation, Marinisation and Initial Fleet Time. While the first two phases take place primarily at the college, the third is conducted on board a warship at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new course is two weeks longer than its predecessor and is underpinned by nine core maritime skills that are the foundations of naval life and essential to operational effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Jerry Kyd, the Commanding Officer of Britannia Royal Naval College, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The modern naval officer needs to be robust and able to adapt to whatever the mission demands, from war-fighting and maintaining security at sea to providing humanitarian aid to a community hit by some form of disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This new course involves more time on the water and teaches the cadets how to operate and lead in readiness for the challenges at the front line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is progressive and designed to ensure that the cadets are better equipped to undertake assignments both at sea and on land, working jointly with other parts of the UK Armed Forces and in partnership with other nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also train promising aspirant officers from around 20 allied nations; these personnel undergo the same training as their British counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were delighted to have the Prime Minister as the guest of honour at the parade to celebrate the success of this latest group of Officer Cadets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They have displayed commitment and courage in completing this intensive and demanding course and are fine examples of the quality of people serving in today’s Royal Navy and in the navies of our allied nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new course also delivers improved fitness levels with training provided using a disciplined method of military fitness which focuses on developing co-ordination and individual physical strength and endurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command, leadership and management training is a constant thread throughout the course, with emphasis on coaching, mentoring and development activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27970</id>
    <published>2012-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-and-foreign-secretary-attend-un-general-assembly-ministerial-week"/>
    <title>Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary attend UN General Assembly Ministerial Week</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations General Assembly Ministerial Week, 24 - 30 September brought together Heads of State and Government and Ministers from all 193 member nations to address global issues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreign Secretary discusses UN General Assembly Ministerial Week September 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_OGuSMAbAo" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full coverage:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday 29 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816829782"&gt;Ministers take steps to strengthen the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign Secretary William Hague, and Minister of State for the Commonwealth Hugo Swire represented the UK at the Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York today, where Ministers agreed measures to strengthen and modernise the Commonwealth._&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: In the margins of Commonwealth Foreign Ministers meeting, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ow.ly/i/YHt3"&gt;Papua New Guinea Foreign Minister Pato&lt;/a&gt;; Foreign Secretary William Hague and Minister Swire meet &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ow.ly/i/YGGB"&gt;Australian Foreign Minister Carr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday 28 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816800882"&gt;Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security&lt;/a&gt;” - UK Statement by Baroness Warsi at the UN High Level Meeting on Countering Nuclear Terrorism - 28 September 2012&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816794482"&gt;Foreign Secretary statement on the importance of isolating the Assad regime and ending impunity&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign Secretary William Hague spoke after today’s meeting of the core group of the Friends of Syria._   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816718382"&gt;Foreign Secretary welcomes extension of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria&lt;/a&gt; - The UN Human Rights Council today passed a further resolution on Syria which condemned the appalling human rights violations by the Syrian regime and extended the mandate of the UN Commission of Inquiry._   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816566182"&gt;Minister for Africa calls for international condemnation of support for militia groups in eastern DRC&lt;/a&gt; - The Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, attended the UN High Level Meeting on the Great Lakes yesterday which aimed to focus attention on the instability in the region, and encourage a consensus on the way forward._&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: New photos of yesterday’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/sets/72157631644736299/"&gt;Friends of Yemen meeting&lt;/a&gt; co-chaired by Foreign Secretary William Hague.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Foreign Secretary William Hague meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8033891136/in/photostream"&gt;Prime Minister of Ethiopia Hailemariam Desalegn&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8033890599/in/photostream"&gt;Vice President of South Sudan Riek Machar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday 27 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816439682"&gt;Foreign Secretary calls for more action to help Yemen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=Speech&amp;amp;id=816427082"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague’s opening remarks at the fourth UN General Assembly Friends of Yemen Ministerial&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=816428182"&gt;With genuine commitment from all involved, in partnership with the government of DRC, long term sustainable solutions can be achieved&lt;/a&gt;” - Statement by UK Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, at the UNGA Mini-Summit on the situation in Eastern DRC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816393382"&gt;meets Ecuadorian Foreign Minister Ricardo Patino&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816492782"&gt;I congratulate Sudan and South Sudan on bringing these intensive weeks of negotiation to a positive outcome”&lt;/a&gt; - Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds speaks at the High Level Sudan/ South Sudan Consultative Forum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=816557082"&gt;signs cooperation agreement with the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031011088/in/photostream"&gt;Tunisian Foreign Minister Rafik Abdessalem&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031010856/in/photostream"&gt;Arab League Secretary-General al Araiby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031010688/in/photostream"&gt;UN Under-Secretary-General Ameerah Haq&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031015521/in/photostream"&gt;Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Trinidad and Tobago Honourable Winston Dookeran&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Baroness Warsi meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8031015521/in/photostream"&gt;Secretary General of Organisation of Islamic Cooperation Professor Ekmeleddin Ihsanoglo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesday 26 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816032182"&gt;The UK will provide an additional £10 million to help the new government of Somalia&lt;/a&gt;” - Intervention by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague at the Secretary-General Mini Summit on Somalia&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816037482"&gt;The Arab Spring is a moment of huge opportunity to build peace, security and prosperity for the region and by extension, the world”&lt;/a&gt; _ - _Intervention by the Foreign Secretary William Hague, at the UN Security Council meeting on Peace and Security in Middle East and North Africa&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028570787/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;photo&lt;/a&gt;)  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816028582"&gt;The United Kingdom restates its longstanding commitment to the people of Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt; - Statement of the delegation of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in exercise of the right of reply to the remarks made by the Prime Minister of Spain in the general debate on 25 September 2012&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816014282"&gt;There can be no negotiations on the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands unless and until such time as the islanders so wish&lt;/a&gt;” - Statement of the delegation of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in exercise of the right of reply to the remarks made by the President of the Argentine Republic in the General Debate on 25 September&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816006082"&gt;Statement by the UK Prime Minister David Cameron&lt;/a&gt; to the 67th Session of the UN General Assembly (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028713668/in/photostream"&gt;photo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816016582"&gt;We need to unite to develop effective international action to help the Malian Government restore territorial integrity, democratic legitimacy and national security&lt;/a&gt;” - UK Statement by Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs Mark Simmonds to the Sahel Ministerial Summit&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=816001782"&gt;UN Commission on Life-Saving Commodities and contraceptive implants&lt;/a&gt;: Remarks at stakeout by UK Secretary of State for International Development Justine Greening _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Prime Minister David Cameron meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8026643446/in/photostream/"&gt;Egyptian President Mohamed Mursi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8026644869/in/photostream/"&gt;Libyan President Mohamed Yousef El-Magariaf&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/8027012697/in/photostream/"&gt;Pakistani President Asif Ali Zardari and Afghan President Hamid Karzai&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Foreign Secretary William Hague meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028511583/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Brazilian Foreign Minister Antonio Patriota&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028506954/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mali Prime Minister Cheick Modibo Diarra&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028511747/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Rwanda’s Foreign Minister Louise Mushikiwabo&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507080/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Minister for Foreign Affairs of Cote d’Ivoire Daniel Kablan Duncan&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507152/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;DRC Foreign Minister Raymond Tshibanda&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_In pictures: Baroness Warsi meets &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8028507118/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Afghanistan’s Deputy Foreign Minister Jawed Ludin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 25 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=815183582"&gt;pledges £1 million to tackle sexual violence in conflict&lt;/a&gt;; Remarks by Foreign Secretary William Hague to the open UN General Assembly side-event ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815158082"&gt;Preventing sexual and gender-based crimes in conflict and securing justice for survivors&lt;/a&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815338182"&gt;Peacebuilding: A way towards sustainable peace and security&lt;/a&gt; - Baroness Warsi speaks at UN Peacebuilding debate_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=815338582"&gt;We have a clear objective and that is the ending of global absolute poverty”&lt;/a&gt; - Prime Minister David Cameron remarks at media stakeout as a Co-Chair of the Secretary-General’s High-level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda .&lt;br&gt;
_&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024544363/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mr. Burt meets Dr Abdul Samad Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of the Maldives; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024459099/in/photostream"&gt;Mr. Burt meets UNODC Executive Director Yury Fedotov&lt;/a&gt; at the UN General Assembly; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023843504/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Mr Hoshyar Zebari&lt;/a&gt;, Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affairs; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023619618/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Youssef Amran&lt;/a&gt;, Moroccan Deputy Foreign Minister&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In pictures:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024459623/in/photostream"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague meets Mr Wunna Maung Lwin&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of Myanmar; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8024276955/in/photostream"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague recording an interview&lt;/a&gt; on CNN’s Amanpour; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8023844685/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague meets with the US President Barack Obama and First Lady Michelle Obama&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monday 24 September&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=814594782"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Yemeni President Hadi visits UK ahead of Friends of Yemen meeting in New York&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=814670882#.UGDdTctp4Zw.twitter"&gt;Baroness Warsi speaks at the ECOSOC Special Ministerial meeting&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt; _&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In pictures: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8021315719/in/set-72157631615264683/"&gt;Mr Burt meets Najib Mikati,&lt;/a&gt; Prime Minister of Lebanon; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8020907586/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Mr Burt meets Khalid bin Ahmed Al Khalifa&lt;/a&gt;, the Bahraini Foreign Minister; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ukun_new_york/8021031172/in/set-72157631615264683"&gt;Baroness Warsi meets Hamrokhon Zarifi&lt;/a&gt;, Foreign Minister of Tajikistan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key issues for Ministerial Week included the situation in Syria, and efforts to support stability in Somalia and Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK hosted the fourth Friends of Yemen Ministerial meeting. Ministerial Week also saw the first meeting of the High Level Panel on the post-2015 development agenda, which was co-chaired by the Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague co-hosted an event on preventing sexual violence in conflict, with the UN Secretary General’s Special Representative and UN Women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find further information and news on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukun.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;UK Mission to the United Nations&lt;/a&gt;  website and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/UKUN_NewYork"&gt;@UKUN_NewYork&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27935</id>
    <published>2012-09-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/a-significant-moment-for-somalia-prime-minister-congratulates-new-president"/>
    <title>A significant moment for Somalia: Prime Minister congratulates new president</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a significant moment for Somalia, and an important step towards a renewed political process. I congratulate Hassan Sheikh Mohamud on his victory and welcome the part played by outgoing president Sheikh Sharif, to bring Somalia to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The coming months and years are critical for Somalia’s transition to democracy. Somalia’s leaders must now work together to build a more representative and transparent system, tackle corruption and strengthen security and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The London Conference on Somalia in February brought the international community together to support this process. Britain will continue to support Somalia’s people and leaders, so that Somalia can fulfill its potential as a peaceful, inclusive and prosperous nation.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
