<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Secretary of State for Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39704</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-launched-on-the-future-of-britains-reserve-forces"/>
    <title>Consultation launched on the future of Britain's Reserve Forces</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation, ‘Future Reserves 2020: Delivering the Nation’s Security Together’, proposes more training for reservists, a ‘kitemark-type’ award for supportive employers, and the idea of changing the Territorial Army’s name to reflect their enhanced role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals there will be a new relationship between reservists, employers and government, and a transparent approach whereby employers are given more certainty about the timing of possible mobilisations and more notice when they occur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures will create a fully integrated force of regulars and reservists, using similar equipment and training together. It will mean that the Reserves not only provide individual augmentees to regular units, but also deploy as formed units and sub-units. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Royal Marines Reserve" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1435/Consultation_launched_on_the_future_of_Britain_s_Reserve_Forces2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Royal Marines Reserve received a rare opportunity to form the Guard at Edinburgh Castle recently
[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of trained Reserves will grow to around 35,000 across all three Services by 2020, aligning the mix of regular and reserve components with many of our closest allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army will see the biggest change, with 30,000 trained Reserves, creating a total land force of about 120,000. And the plans are backed by an extra £1.8bn in funding over the next ten years for new equipment, uniforms and training for the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• increasing the number of days Army reservists are required to train from 35 to 40 days a year  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• a change of name from Territorial Army to Army Reserve - better reflecting the future role and tasks  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• encouraging more ex-regulars to become reservists - making it easier for them to transfer to the Reserves and developing incentives for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This transformation of the Reserves will see a radical shift in the way in which we use them, with units deployed as formed units or sub-units as well as delivering individual augmentees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Increased training, better equipment and extra investment in our Reserves are all integral to our vision of a formidable, adaptable and flexible Armed Forces, with a reserve/regular balance more in line with our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government has committed £1.8bn to rebuilding our Reserves. The consultation I have launched today is about working with reservists, their families and employers to use that money to design the Reserve Forces of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir Nick Houghton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since 2003 there have been over 25,000 reservists mobilised, fighting alongside their regular counterparts. 29 have paid the ultimate price for their country and just this summer we saw 2,000 reservists provide a pivotal security role at the London 2012 Games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the future we will become even more reliant on our Reserves. But this increased reliance means that there are key issues that we have to tackle - like our relationship with employers and the notice period ahead of mobilisation - to get this right. I want to encourage everyone to get involved in this consultation and have their say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 18 January 2013 and following this we will publish a White Paper in Spring 2013 setting out this new relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39691</id>
    <published>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/work-on-afghan-officers-academy-underway-as-herrick-17-begins"/>
    <title>Work on Afghan officers' academy underway as HERRICK 17 begins</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The building of the future &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt;, marked today, 10 October, by an earth-turning ceremony at its site in the Afghan capital, underlines the UK’s long-term commitment to a secure Afghanistan after combat operations cease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once fully operational, the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt; will train up to 1,350 male students and 150 female students each year. Based on a model resembling the Royal Military Academy Sandhurst, it will help to sustain the ongoing progress being made in building a capable and professional Afghan National Army. This work will take place during and after the transition of security responsibilities to the Afghan Government post-2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event coincided with the transfer of authority between British brigades in Helmand with 4th Mechanized Brigade taking command of Task Force Helmand from 12th Mechanized Brigade which is now on its way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Doug Chalmers (left), Commander of 12th Mechanized Brigade, and Brigadier Bob Bruce of 4th Mechanized Brigade " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1479/Work_on_Afghan_officers__academy_underway_as_HERRICK_17_begins2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Brigadier Doug Chalmers (left), Commander of 12th Mechanized Brigade, hands over command of Task Force Helmand to Brigadier Bob Bruce of 4th Mechanized Brigade [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transfer of authority marks the start of Operation HERRICK 17 which will oversee the drawdown of 500 UK Service personnel already announced to take place by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six months will see 4th Mechanized Brigade working in support of the Afghan National Security Forces to ensure they are capable of assuming full security responsibilities by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In July, the [UK] Prime Minister [David Cameron] and President Karzai signed a Memorandum of Understanding to reaffirm UK and Afghan dedication to the officer academy project in Kabul which is one of the UK’s commitments to an enduring partnership with Afghanistan after our combat operations cease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The academy will present a real opportunity for us to help generate a well-trained cadre of junior officers to bolster the leadership within the Afghan Army for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both the commencement of the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt; project and the planned drawdown of 500 personnel from 4th Mechanized Brigade by the end of the year demonstrate significant steps forward in a transition process that is well on track and will see us hand over full security responsibility for Afghanistan to its own security forces in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the earth-turning ceremony in Kabul, Deputy Commander of the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF), Lieutenant General Adrian Bradshaw, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The training that will take place here will develop the next generation of military leaders in a brand new Afghan National Army Officer Academy. This is yet another example of how ISAF and the Afghan National Security Forces are sustaining the progress we have made in building a capable and professional force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very proud of our achievements and the turning of the earth marks not only the start of the main construction effort but also the beginning of the academy itself. It is a truly historic occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel from 4th Mechanized Brigade will work alongside the Afghan Army and the Afghan National Police in a co-ordinated effort over the forthcoming winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander of Task Force Helmand for HERRICK 17, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our focus throughout this deployment will be on assisting our Afghan allies to deliver security to their people. We are superbly well trained and equipped to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Real success has been achieved. As the Afghan security forces continue to grow in capability and confidence we will reduce our profile. I am planning to send 500 troops home by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17418</id>
    <published>2011-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bank-holiday-rail-services"/>
    <title>Bank holiday rail services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond has welcomed the news that the rail industry will be keeping more trains running this August bank holiday weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 49,903 trains will be carrying an expected 5 million rail passengers to destinations across the country - 1,700 more trains than were operational during last year’s bank holiday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail’s engineering teams will still be out working hard to deliver the vital improvements to the railways over the holiday weekend, but 95 per cent of normal train services will be running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bank holiday weekends are always a busy time to travel, but a great deal is being done to ensure that travellers get to their destinations as smoothly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While Network Rail will be carrying out important improvement works in some areas, 95% of normal train services will be running this weekend which is around 1,700 more trains than ran last August bank holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course everyone should still allow plenty of time for their journeys and plan well in advance, but a lot of work is going into keeping Britain moving this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of intense pressure on the public finances the government is undertaking one of the biggest programmes of rail improvements since the Victorian era. These include a green-light for Crossrail, Thameslink and a programme of additional carriages for our most rail crowded lines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most travellers there should be no disruption because of the improvement works. But, as always, travellers should check with their train operator or national rail enquiries before they travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7494</id>
    <published>2011-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-enforcement-and-education-to-cut-road-deaths"/>
    <title>Better enforcement and education to cut road deaths </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans to improve road safety education while taking tough action against the small minority of dangerous drivers were set out by Transport Secretary Philip Hammond today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Careless driving will be made a fixed penalty offence to allow the police more effectively to tackle reckless driving that puts other road users in danger, while disqualified drivers face having to take a new test before regaining their licence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be more educational courses that can be offered in place of a fixed penalty and points in appropriate cases as well as a new post-test qualification for novice drivers, under plans set out in the new ‘Strategic framework for road safety’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as new analysis shows, 3,500 deaths and serious injuries could have been prevented in a year if the successes of better local authorities and police forces had been matched across the country. Local people will be given the information they need to have a real say in road safety priorities on their local roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This report marks a sea change in how we tackle road safety in this country. We are determined to differentiate between wilfully reckless drivers and the law abiding majority who sometimes make honest mistakes, or who have allowed their skills to deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will focus relentlessly on cracking down on the really reckless few who are responsible for a disproportionately large number of accidents and deaths on our roads. By allowing the police to focus resources on dealing with these drivers, we can make our roads even safer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our vision is to ensure Britain remains a world leader on road safety. We will only do this is if we bring people with us. This means cracking down on the most dangerous drivers without waging war on the law abiding majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new ‘Strategic framework for road safety’ sets out the government’s plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make careless driving a fixed penalty offence to allow the police more effectively to tackle the wilfully reckless driving that puts other road users in danger. Guidance will ensure that that the circumstances in which a fixed penalty notice is appropriate are clearly defined.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Require offenders to pass a test before they regain their licence after a serious disqualification.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make greater use of powers to seize vehicles to keep the most dangerous drivers off the roads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the level of fixed penalty notices for traffic offences from £60 to between £80 and £100 and penalty points. Levels have fallen behind those for other fixed penalty offences, which risks trivialising the offences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve enforcement against drink and drug driving, as announced in the response to the ‘North report’ in March.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the use of police-approved educational courses that can be offered in place of fixed penalty notices to encourage safer driving behaviour. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launch a new post-test qualification for new drivers, including an assessment process to give insurers confidence that it will create safer drivers who can expect to pay lower insurance costs. This will replace the current Pass Plus scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue to improve the driving and motorcycling training processes, including introducing film clips into theory test.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a new website to allow local people to easily compare the road safety performance of their local area against similar areas, as well as a new portal to help road safety professionals share information. The framework published today also includes maps which show the recent road safety records and improvements of local authorities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launch an annual road safety day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The framework also sets out the roles and responsibilities of local authorities, road safety professionals and other stakeholders in improving road safety and the increased freedom that is being given to local authorities in assessing and acting on their own priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s long term vision is to ensure that Britain remains a world leader on road safety and the Department will monitor its performance against indicators in a new road safety outcomes framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic framework for road safety’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s response to the ‘North report’, covering what steps will be taken to tackle drink and drug driving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maps showing the road safety performance of individual local authorities are included on p27-28 of the ‘Strategic framework’. These are based on figures published in ‘Reported Road Casualties Great Britain’. And here is the detailed local authority data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New analysis of these figures, included in the strategy, shows that if lower-performing local authorities were to increase their road safety performance so that their killed or serious injured (KSI) casualty rate per billion vehicle miles for 2007-09 was no higher than for the median (mid point) local authority, we might have expected the number of KSIs to be 14 per cent lower than observed - or around 3,500 fewer KSI casualties per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport has also today published summaries of the responses to two consultations: the ‘Road safety compliance consultation’ and ‘A safer way’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The UN has proclaimed 2011-2020 as the Decade of Action for Road Safety with a goal of stabilising and then reducing global road deaths. The launch of the road safety framework has been scheduled to coincide with the launch of this decade of action. The UK is a world leader in road safety and the framework demonstrates our commitment to contribute to the further reduction in road deaths envisaged globally by the UN.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3118&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14226</id>
    <published>2010-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-not-bigger-hammond-creates-south-east-airports-taskforce"/>
    <title>Better not bigger - Hammond creates South East airports taskforce</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A drive to reduce long queues and the number of delayed flights was announced today as Transport Secretary Philip Hammond unveiled a new group tasked with improving operations at the major South East airports.  It will be made up of key players from the aviation world and chaired by Aviation Minister Theresa Villiers, with the initial focus on Heathrow, Gatwick and Stansted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This marks the start of a new chapter in our aviation policy.  I have a clear vision for our airports which sees greater reliability, shorter queues, less hassle and better services for passengers.  It is absolutely crucial that we get this right as aviation is vital to our national economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been clear in our opposition to additional runways at Heathrow, Gatwick and Stansted, so the challenge we face now is making them better within existing runway capacity constraints.  Working together with key partners within the aviation community, this group will look at how to secure the successful future of aviation in the Southeast and Heathrow’s hub status within the constraints of the existing runways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our vision is for better not bigger airports, with new investment targeting improvements in reliability and passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group features representatives from airlines, airports, passenger groups, business, environmental groups and other industry bodies such as the Civil Aviation Authority and NATS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement complements the government’s separate commitment in the Queen’s speech to reform the economic regulation of UK airports, which should help to drive investment in existing airport facilities and improve performance to benefit passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Members invited to take part in the group are:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minister of State for Aviation, Theresa Villiers (Chair)  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BAA Heathrow  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;GIP Gatwick   &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BAA Stansted  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CAA (Civil Aviation Authority)   &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NATS (National Air Traffic Services)   &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BA (British Airways)  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Virgin Atlantic  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EasyJet  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ryanair  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;London First  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AUC (Air Transport Users Council)  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AOA (Airport Operators Association)  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AEF (Aviation Environmental Federation) &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first meeting of the group is expected within the next month, at which the precise terms of reference will be agreed.  These will then be available on the DfT website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3118&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
