<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Secretary of State for Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16671</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-defence-secretary-on-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>The Defence Secretary on delivering value for money and innovation in Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking yesterday, Mr Hammond used his speech to talk about how, over the last two-and-a-half years, the Department has set about reforming the way Defence is managed in order to deliver improved efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began by recapping the scale of the reform challenge faced by Defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will rematerialise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two-and-a-half years of the transformation project, the Defence Secretary said we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture so that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said that while Defence needed a solid financial foundation, it was the people that really mattered and made the difference, and therefore an attractive employment package to attract and keep the best was needed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them. And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis. So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life. So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that a new employment model was needed and this would need to be flexible to meet the varying and individual needs of Service personnel: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term and attractive to Service personnel and fair to the taxpayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall, designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that this ‘New Employment Model’, or NEM, isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges, and it is not about overnight transformation but will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer: towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And more stability to Service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners, and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On housing, Mr Hammond said that, in a 22-year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want this to change. As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, the Defence Secretary said we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation. Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence Budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability. That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task, but neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43707</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-2-billion-contract-awarded-for-new-attack-submarine"/>
    <title>£1.2 billion contract awarded for new attack submarine</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Audacious" title="Audacious"&gt;Audacious&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth of 7 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class" title="Astute Class"&gt;Astute Class&lt;/a&gt;  submarines being built for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt;. They are the most technologically-advanced the Royal Navy has ever sent to sea and offer a step-change in capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.www.baesystems.com/" title="BAE Systems"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; will safeguard 3,000 skilled jobs at Barrow-in-Furness in Cumbria and represents a significant step forward in the Astute submarine programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 2 boats, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/HMS-Astute" title="HMS Astute"&gt;Astute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Ambush" title="Ambush"&gt;Ambush&lt;/a&gt;, are currently undergoing sea trials to rigorously test their systems. Astute has conducted deep dive trials and successfully fired Tomahawk land attack missiles and Spearfish torpedoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambush’s ability to dive and surface has been successfully tested, as has her propulsion system, and the third boat, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Artful" title="Artful"&gt;Artful&lt;/a&gt;, is reaching the final stages of her construction at Barrow shipyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD can also confirm today that a further £1.5 billion has been committed to the remaining 3 submarines in the class. This has enabled early build work to start on the next boat (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Anson" title="Anson"&gt;Anson&lt;/a&gt;) and long lead items to be ordered and bought for the as yet unnamed boats six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This £1.2 billion contract marks an important step forward in the progress of the Astute programme and moves the Royal Navy closer to adding more of these highly advanced and powerful attack submarines to its fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce today that the MOD is committing more than £1.5 billion for boats five, six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Astute " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1735/45150807.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Astute sails up the Clyde estuary (library image) [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) J J Massey, Crown Copyright/MOD 2009]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding demonstrates our commitment not only to a key Royal Navy capability but also to the submarine industry in Barrow which will play a vital role in Astute for decades to come. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD’s Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Astute Class will become the jewel in the crown of the Royal Navy’s Submarine Service and boasts much greater firepower and more advanced sonar and communications than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These submarines represent a huge leap forward in technology and will operate all over the world with the Royal Navy. These boats provide the optimum capability a submarine can offer in land strike, strategic intelligence-gathering, anti-submarine and surface ship warfare, and protection of the strategic deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Featuring the latest nuclear-powered technology, the Astute Class never need to be refuelled and can circumnavigate the world submerged, manufacturing the crew’s oxygen from seawater as they go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 7,400-tonne Astute Class are quieter than older submarines, and can operate covertly and remain undetected despite being 50% bigger than the Royal Navy’s current &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class" title="Trafalgar Class"&gt;Trafalgar Class&lt;/a&gt; submarines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45359</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-21-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>2012/11/21 - Delivering Value for Money and Innovation in Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces exist to protect our country and provide the ultimate guarantee of its security and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be the first duty of Government, and everything we do in Defence is directed at supporting that objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating the military capability required to meet the needs of national security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And delivering that capability on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most fiendishly complex tasks of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the most expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With resources as tight as they are, the obligation to deliver value for money is paramount:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure every pound of taxpayers’ money spent on Defence has a tangible impact on delivering capability to the front-line and on the security of the nation;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, enhancing the efficiency of Defence delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today I want talk about how, over the last two and a half years, we have set about reforming the way Defence is managed to deliver that improved efficiency:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restructuring the MOD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Re-configuring our Armed Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balancing the budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting the equipment programme on a sustainable course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And because none of this would be possible without the people who make up Defence, I want to say a bit about how we will modernise the offer that we make to the men and women of our Armed Forces, so that their terms and conditions, while they will never look like those associated with civilian employment, better reflect lifestyles in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to start by re-capping the scale of the reform challenge we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review kick-started one of the biggest change programmes taking place anywhere in the Western world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change programme essential to ensuring that our Armed Forces can continue to defend our country, protect our interests and project our values abroad;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of a complex range of threats in a rapidly changing environment; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the powerful, adaptable and, crucially, sustainable Armed Forces we require;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipped with some of the best and most advanced technology in the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all at a cost that the country can afford and on a scale that we can sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this change programme isn’t just about meeting the Future Force 2020 structure set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also about changing the way we deliver Defence to make sure we don’t repeat the mistakes of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this Government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene’s Defence Reform Review set out clearly what the problems were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A focus on short-term affordability at the expense of long-term value for money and a lack of financial rigour throughout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Head Office, which was trying to micro-manage from the centre, disempowering the people who actually deliver in the Service Commands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confusion over who was accountable for what&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Few levers for those who wanted to innovate and change behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An over-complicated and fragmented structure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And an unbalanced relationship between the Department and its suppliers - with poorly aligned incentives driving sometimes perverse behaviours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting these problems resolved is every bit as important as eliminating the inherited black hole in the budget if we are to deliver sustainable, long-term change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will re-materialise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are getting on with implementing Lord Levene’s recommendations which we accepted in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the behaviours so that we do not repeat the same mistakes again;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focussing on long-term value, not short-term cash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering value for money by making sure we have modern, innovative ways of doing business;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where people accept responsibility for decisions and have the power to make them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing us to weed out duplication, red-tape, perverse incentives, waste and delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken as a whole, this is a 10 year reform plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, halfway through this Parliament, and half way between two SDSRs; a year and a half on from the Defence Reform Review; it is worth reflecting how far we have come already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the Department, many of the tough decisions on force structure had already been taken: to shrink the size of the MOD; to rationalize our equipment programme; and to reduce the size of the Navy, Army and the Air Force, while increasing investment in the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They just needed implementing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the senior management was beginning the process of changing the way Defence was managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make no apologies for the fact that I chose to focus on the money first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no option of continuing the ‘finger in the dam’ approach to Defence budgeting, which had resulted in the MOD lurching over a decade from budget crisis to budget crisis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salami-slicing each year in the hope that “something would turn up” to fund the programme in the next;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing projects further and further to the right in an unsustainable and ever-expanding bubble;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeting based on fantasy rather than reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ill-served the tax-payer, who ended up paying more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ill-served the Defence Industry, who found it impossible to invest with any certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it ill-served our Armed Forces, who could not plan with confidence politicians promised them would be delivered on time, to requirement and in the numbers expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have instituted an integrated financial and military capability planning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming prudently rather than optimistically, so that we can focus on value rather than on cash management; with a proper centrally held contingency reserve against the equipment programme, and (an innovation in MOD terms) an annual Departmental Unallocated Provision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving from a culture of spending first and working out how to afford the long-term costs later to one of only committing to what we can be confident that we can deliver;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living within our means, rather than systematically planning beyond them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our new cost controls in place, no project can be committed without a 10-year budget line to cover not only its procurement, but also its support costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we allocate projects to the committed core programme only at the point when they need to be committed in order to be delivered on time, and only in accordance with the military assessment of priority at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ending a long-established “conspiracy” between the industry and the Department to “lock in” unaffordable projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By maintaining these simple disciplines, sensibly managing in-year budgets, and forecasting prudently, we are changing the dynamic in the equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we still have to live with the legacy projects - against which we have now made prudent provision of financial contingency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will continue to have a negative effect on the Department’s public reputation for project management as their original fantasy budgets and timelines are exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can now make choices, based on military priorities, about which new capabilities we can afford, rather than which bits of the programme we have to cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by delivering this budgetary discipline we are already demonstrating the benefits to the Armed Forces and to Industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding projects when it is safe to do so, not cutting them because we have run out of cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I announced in May that we had achieved a balanced budget, I have been able to give the go ahead to some half a billion pounds of further investment in Equipment and Support, including targeting pods for fast jets, better protection systems for Tornado GR4, enhancements to MERLIN Helicopters and new FOXHOUND vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And further announcements are imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is, I am told by old lags in the Department, the first in living memory that the MOD has not had to sit down in September and decide which programmes need to be cut or delayed in order to remain within spending control targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major step forward for the MOD and for the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Reform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sustainability is considered in every decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building-in a focus on value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing structures and incentives to change behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging innovation to improve delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locking in the significant reductions in running costs we are achieving by making the organisation more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already on course to save approximately £2bn in non-frontline costs in the year 2014/15, compared to 2010/11 baseline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of this saving will be sustainable reductions, so we can expect to maintain high-levels of savings in following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a ten year period we expect to save around £15bn of non front line costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how"&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we are pushing authority and accountability down the chain of command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Top Level Budget holders the freedoms and incentives they need to drive efficiencies and improve delivery in their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head Office is becoming smaller, on course to shrink by 25% by 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly constituted Defence Board, which I chair, has been meeting regularly over the last year, providing strategic direction to the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delegated operating arrangements for Service Commands will go live in April 2013, including for the new Joint Forces Command which was stood up in April of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Service is doing detailed work on its own operating model, identifying which activities are to be modified or stopped, and where to prioritise resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the bottom line is that they will have much greater control over planning for future capability requirement;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding where to concentrate resources to provide maximum effect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking responsibility for living within the means provided, but with the freedom to innovate and establish better ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing we are doing is bringing in private sector skills where we judge it necessary to help change behaviours and drive efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Business Services has been set up in a partnership with SERCO, who are providing the external management team to transform the organisation into a lean and effective shared services centre, building on best practice outside the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Infrastructure Organisation brings together all aspects of Defence infrastructure asset management and facilities management under one organisation for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now in the process of recruiting a strategic partner to help transform its business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps most significantly, the work to overhaul procurement, the Materiel Strategy, is developing fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms of the acquisition process in the Defence Reform Review were anticipated by Bernard Gray’s report for the previous Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, Defence has lacked the right business skills and capabilities to manage what are some of the largest capital and infrastructure projects being undertaken in today the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the MOD has, too often, been a poor customer for industry - and in some cases, a soft touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are setting out to create a proper interface between the Defence Equipment &amp;amp; Support organisation and the Defence customers it serves enabling it in turn to be a more effective customer for its suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will require the recruitment of a private sector partner to deliver the high-level commercial and management skills that we currently lack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently testing the value for money case for a Government Owned, Contractor Operated - or GOCO - entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final decision on the precise structure will be made in due course, but the bottom line is that the reformed DE&amp;amp;S, supported by a strategic partner, will be better by design at negotiating and managing contracts for the benefit of the tax-payer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the private sector partner injecting key disciplines, processes, skills and management freedoms into MOD’s procurement activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By refocusing the Head Office to providing strategic direction rather than micro-management, by empowering the Service Commands and other parts of Defence to deliver and to innovate, and by bringing in private sector partners with the skills and flexibilities to help them, this programme will deliver behaviour change from the bottom up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people"&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive change agenda: In the Armed Forces, in the MOD and across the support organisations like DE&amp;amp;S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And change is often uncomfortable for the people at the heart of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me say unambiguously that our people in Defence are our biggest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces - Regular and Reserves; the civilians who support them; and the people who work in the industries which supply them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to rebuild the trust of all of them after a period of sometimes traumatic change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to say something this morning specifically about how we will address the challenges of recruiting and retaining for the Armed Forces once the lure of deployment on operations is gone as we withdraw from our combat role in Afghanistan by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, hopefully, against the challenge of a healthier civilian economy as a competitor for talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="service-personnel"&gt;Service Personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my big learning curves over the last year has been understanding the unique nature of what the military call the “moral component” of Defence; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that provides the “will to fight”, and the determination to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that allows us to recruit some of the best people the country can provide to preserve the unique attributes of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gives us our edge over other countries, many of whom have larger Armed Forces and similar equipment to us, but very, very few of which can come close to matching our military capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our people that give Britain’s Armed Forces their special quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that some of them feel, perhaps many of them feel, they have taken a bit of a pounding over the last couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redundancies; downsizing; re-structuring; relocation; re-roling for the post Afghanistan world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all while fighting a long and difficult counter-insurgency and stabilization campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must often have felt like the perfect storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future Armed Forces will continue to offer careers that are exciting, challenging and rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we want to continue to recruit and retain the best people, both Regulars and Reservists, that may not be enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service Personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-employment-model"&gt;New Employment Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in doing so, we need to achieve three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to secure for Defence the people it needs - both in terms of quality and quantity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recruiting to preserve the unique attributes of the Armed Forces by drawing adventurous, spirited and committed people to the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we need to reflect the changes in social, demographic and economic conditions in our society and the complexities of modern family life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no identikit Service career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a young recruit wants from the package may be very different from an NCO in his late 20s with a wife and small children - and we have to make sure that what we provide is an attractive offer for both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attractive to Service personnel and fair to the tax-payer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me be clear: this is not a cost cutting exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call this project “the New Employment Model”, or NEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about overnight transformation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to meet the expectations of a generation that has yet to join the Service, as well as our current Servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some elements are capable of being delivered relatively early while others will take longer to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more stability to service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="housing--spousal-employment"&gt;Housing &amp;amp; Spousal Employment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodation lies at the heart of this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of our Regular Service personnel rely on publically provided accommodation because the job currently demands a very high degree of mobility around the UK - and sometimes beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 22 year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want this to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enabling the children of Service personnel to be settled in one area and to avoid frequent changes of school;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making it easier for partners of Service personnel to find work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we do must of course be done in a way which continues to support operational capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our goal is to enable Service Personnel more freedom to make the choices that other people make:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About where to live;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about whether to rent or buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, home ownership rates among current and former members of the Armed Forces are comparatively low, suggesting an element of systematic disadvantage - something which the Armed Forces Covenant commits us to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, alongside a steady improvement in the quality of service accommodation, we want to increase access to home ownership for Service personnel, providing realistic lifestyle choices to our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways this could be achieved and we will look at developing a range of options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark fact is that people in the Armed Forces, with a generous, non-contributory pension scheme, are accumulating significant wealth during their service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a significant part of their total remuneration package cost that wealth creation but without them being able to access it to facilitate house purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that disadvantages them compared to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the challenge we have set ourselves is to explore models that would allow our people either to directly access some of that accumulating wealth or to use it to collateralise mortgage borrowing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting forces home ownership;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And removing an important element of disadvantage service people face relative to their civilian counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would not, of course, remove the need for Service accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially for younger, single service people, this will often be the right choice, or indeed, the only one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces will continue to provide subsidised accommodation for those who require it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whether you are in the Forces or in a civilian job, taking on the responsibility of homeownership these days often requires two reliable incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So making it easier for the partners of service people to find and keep work is a critical precondition to boosting home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making military basing more settled will be a big step forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also recognise that some bases, by necessity, are in relatively remote locations with limited employment opportunities for partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the areas I want to explore urgently in 2013 is how we could use parts of the military estate to stimulate local economic growth and employment generation around garrisons - by providing incentives for business relocation to land that we hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus creating conveniently located job opportunities for the Armed Forces community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a whole, the New Employment Model will include everything from the accommodation and home ownership issues which I have discussed today, to overall pay structure, training and education needs, career management and manpower control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NEM will support both Regular and Reserve personnel - and will build on the Whole Force concept and the integration of Regular and Reserves which I set out earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, we will begin consulting with Service personnel, and testing some of the ideas we are developing on the people they are designed to benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have set out this morning, the progress we have made on one of the most ambitious transformation programmes ever undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programme necessary to ensure that our Armed Forces are affordable and sustainable, as well as flexible and effective in the face of both fiscal challenges and strategic uncertainties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not undervalue what we have already achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have defined the new structure of our forces and the shape of the MOD that will support them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have developed our plan to bring the army home from Germany;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And an Equipment Programme which can be delivered and afforded;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms to maintain budget discipline are in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that is, relatively speaking, the easy bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that requires a motivated and engaged workforce;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that recognises the challenges we are facing;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shares our vision for the future of Defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understands the plan for delivering it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And feels a valued part of that plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of redundancy and pay restraint, that is a big challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the one we must now address;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through greater empowerment, both personal and professional;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through better delivery of value to the individual from the remuneration package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45365</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-08-future-reserves-2020"/>
    <title>2012/11/08 - Future Reserves 2020</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Michael [Michael Prescott, BT Director of Corporate Affairs], for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BT has been a prime mover in the Partnering for Talent initiative over the last 12 months and a proud track record of supporting the men and women who serve in our Armed Forces - both Regular and Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BT has recruited over 800 ex-service personnel in the last couple of years, and will be recruiting another 250 in the coming months - People who will serve the company well in the years to come, just as they have served the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of their induction, BT is actively supporting the maintenance of military links through service in the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is the Reserves that I’ve come here want to talk about today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I am publishing the MOD’s consultation on the future of the United Kingdom’s Reserve Forces, entitled ‘Future Reserves 2020: Delivering the Nation’s Security Together’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades, our Reserves have fought alongside their Regular colleagues, in the Balkans, in Iraq, in Afghanistan, taking the same risks, making the same sacrifice, decorated with the same honours and deserving the same recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like our Regular Forces, they have been stretched, but have risen to the challenges they have been set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time, the structure of our Reserve Forces has been allowed to wither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite six reviews since the Cold War, their true potential remains unrealised, particularly that of the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declining in number, starved of resources, with training cut, opportunities reduced, and morale suffering - they have had many years of a raw deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long, the Reserves have been the forgotten part of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today marks the beginning of a fresh start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fresh-start"&gt;Fresh Start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re setting out our commitment to a larger Reserve, both absolutely and as a proportion of overall service manpower;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better resourced, with an injection of £1.8bn over the next 10 years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means better equipped and better trained, using the same kit as their Regular counterparts and becoming the sole repository of some specialist skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, in the future they will be part of a fully integrated force of Regulars and Reserves, able to deploy as formed units and sub-units, as well as continuing to augment Regular forces as individual Reservists where required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes I am proposing today, amount to a paradigm shift in the role of Reservists’ in delivery of the nation’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shift which will see Reservists routinely sharing responsibility for activities once the exclusive domain of Regular Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this shift, wider society will need to play a larger part in the delivery of national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Security is everyone’s business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new relationship is required between the State and Armed Forces on the one hand and individual Reservists, their families and their employers on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exciting new proposition bringing with it new opportunities, and new challenges for Reservists, and for their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Reservist - more responsibility, bringing with it more support, more respect, and more reward;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the employer - an open relationship based on mutual benefit, better exploiting the skills and motivation Reservists offer as employees, with appropriate packages, for different types of employer, of accredited training, recognition and impact reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for employers, Reservists and their families alike, greater predictability of liability for call-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this Green Paper will affect all Services: the Maritime Reserve, the Royal Marine Reserve, the Royal Auxiliary Air Force, and the Territorial Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will be most keenly felt by the Army, who, on the basis of the plans set out this year for Army 2020, will need to fully integrate their Reservists into the very fibre of the force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will concentrate most of my remarks today on the challenge facing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very nature of the TA’s new role will require a step change in organisation and approach to force generation, as well as in the relationship with employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change that, I believe, should be reflected in a change in name to ‘The Army Reserve’ - and that is one of over 30 propositions that we will be consulting on over the next two months as part of a process leading to a white paper published in the Spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I put some flesh on the bones of these proposals, let me set the transformation of our Future Reserves in the context of the wider changes taking place in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review called for redesign of our Forces to meet the new security challenges which will face them post-Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Future Force 2020, we are building an adaptable, integrated Whole Force fit for a more uncertain world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer focussed on the Cold War model of mass territorial defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor the predictable pattern of deployment to enduring operations in Iraq or Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But configured instead to project power and respond to a diverse set of contingencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile, high-tech, structured to allow rapid reaction and expeditionary warfare;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capable of conducting the full spectrum of operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to command as part of a coalition and more interoperable with our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller, but better equipped;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because now that we’ve a balanced budget, with a sustainable equipment programme, our Armed Forces can be confident that they will receive the cutting-edge equipment that has been promised as we build the formidable capability that Future Force 2020 represents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation is necessary to prepare our Armed Forces for the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to deal with the legacy of the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multi-billion pound black-hole in the Defence Budget that had to be filled, before we started to make a contribution to reducing the overall fiscal deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant some very tough decisions: relinquishing some capabilities, to invest in new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting smaller numbers, to ensure we can equip people properly for the job we ask them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-reserve-legacy"&gt;The Reserve Legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the SDSR implementation process, the Prime Minister set up an Independent Commission to provide an authoritative picture of the state of our Reserves and recommendations for optimising their use in the context of modern threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report they published in July last year makes for sobering reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They found that individual Reservists had made, and continue to make, an essential contribution to national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At their peak, Reservists made up 20% of our Forces in Iraq and 12% in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best trauma unit in the world - the Camp Bastion Hospital - has been staffed, on average, 40% by Reservists and has nearly 50 Reservist medics currently on its staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 25,000 Reservists have deployed on operations overseas in the last 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;29 have paid the ultimate price, with many more injured, sometimes seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, given that this is remembrance week, I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to all those who have sacrificed so much to preserve our national security and protect our national interests - serving and veteran; regular and reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the amazing efforts of individual Reservists to make a difference, and the hard work of many unsung Reserve Units up and down the country from all the services, the Commission found an organisation in institutional decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting smaller, getting older, less well trained, less motivated;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not matched to the new security environment - with major units of the TA still configured to provide mass reinforcements to counter the Soviet threat; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not able to be mobilised for routine deployments - with the legal position not supporting the use of Reserves for standing tasks;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not matched to the new configuration of the regular Armed Forces;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forming too small a part of our overall military capability, both in comparison to our closest allies of similar tradition - and indeed by our own historic standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even during the last decade of enduring operations, to which the TA made such a contribution, its nominal strength fell by almost a third with the Reserves Commission reporting some estimates of genuine trained strength as low as 14,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long, the Reserves were considered a soft target by the last administration as they desperately tried to find in-year savings measures to cover their failure to control the spiralling cost of the equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restrictions on live round firing;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of equipment curtailed;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, the then Government tried to cut the TA’s annual budget by 30% with a reduction in drill nights and weekend training, to balance the in-year budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of all of this has been Reserve Forces failing to realise their potential; failing to recruit to requirement, with a proposition that is simply not attracting enough potential Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A diminishing return on capability and a diminishing return to Defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So change is not just desirable, it is essential for the future of our Reserve Forces and the contribution they make to the Defence of our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that change is required not only in the organisation, structure and role of Reserve Forces - and how they are integrated with Regular Forces - but it is required in the proposition we make to Reservists and in the relationship we have with their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what will the Future Reserve of 2020 look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this mean for what we ask of our Reservists, their families and their employees?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is the fresh start we are proposing today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-reserves-2020"&gt;Future Reserves 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is fully committed to delivering the Reserve Forces the country needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investing an additional £1.8bn in the Reserves over the next 10 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support an increase in our Reserve Forces…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…to a trained strength in the Army Reserve of 30,000;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maritime Reserve of 3,100;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Royal Auxiliary Air Force of 1,800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in 20 years the planned trajectory is up, not down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the effect of this investment is already beginning to show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already reversed the decline in the Army Reserve in terms of recruitment and total strength - with enlistments this year 3% up against the rolling average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New training and new equipment is being rolled out progressively, with delivery of new uniforms, new vehicles and new radios, in line with those used by Regulars, already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening, I was at Fulham TA Centre visiting the Royal Yeomanry to see their new light reconnaissance vehicles and Bowman radios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more money, higher numbers and better equipment, however welcome, will not alone turn our Reserves into the efficient, effective, and deployable Force our national security requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Whole Force concept of full integration between Regular and Reserves will require us to redefine the role that Reserves will play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to restructure them to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Forces will continue to deliver specialist capabilities which cannot be cost-effectively held in Regular Forces, particularly in the medical field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we intend to extend the range of specialities, drawing on skills from the civilian workforce, such as intelligence, information technology and cyber. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also provide functions that do not require complex unit-level training to maintain readiness, such as some aspects of logistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reserves will fulfil a general role in homeland security, such as the support they provided to the Olympics, and to national resilience tasks, such as flood relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will provide, as they do now, vital support to short-term high impact operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will provide resilience to longer term stabilisation operations, like the Balkans and Afghanistan - providing a higher proportion of the committed force than is currently the case, increasing the longer the operation goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual Reservists will continue to be mobilised as augmentees for regular units as now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be deployed as formed units and sub units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Reserve Forces will be expected to fulfil new roles too, including contributing to standing commitments such as the Falklands and to defence engagement work abroad, such as conflict prevention and capacity building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This financial year, over 20 new overseas training exercises will take place for the Army Reserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hundred Reservists from the 6th Battalion, the Rifles recently spent two weeks in Germany training alongside their Regular Regimental colleagues from 5 Rifles in Exercise Leopard Star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise centred on the Warrior Armoured vehicle and was designed to develop the kind of integration between regular and Reserve that will be necessary to meet the demands of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such exercises were rare in the past; they will be more common in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists will routinely be part of deployments at home and abroad and will routinely train with the Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will require a change in legislation, redefining the circumstances in which Reserves can be mobilised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, they will be a fundamental part of how we provide military capability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of a ‘Whole Force’, alongside their Regular counterparts, the civilians who support them and the Defence Industry which supplies them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘Whole Force’, designed to ensure the nation’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are some who have questioned whether we can achieve the growth in Reserve Forces that we have set out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these new levels are well within historic norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1990, the TA was 72,500 strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army Reserve we are proposing is modest in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the new targets are ambitious, they are clearly achievable, and I am determined to deliver them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, we will need the support of employers, as well as potential Reservists and their families to deliver this ambition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="proposition-for-reservists"&gt;Proposition for Reservists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying respective Reservists, we’re looking for people who are going to turn out when they’re required to turn out, who are going to do the training they need to do and who are available for deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Army Reserve, they will be expected to undertake an extended training regime of around 40 days a year after basic training is completed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will be structured as one 16 day deployment and the balance at weekend and evenings, avoiding any added burdens on employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the message to future Army Reservists is clear: promise us you will make the commitment; turn up regularly to train and be prepared to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in return, we promise to equip you, train you, fund you and use you as an integral part of the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because you will be integrated with the Regulars and deployed more routinely, there will be greater opportunities for promotion and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balanced package of remuneration and support will be developed for Reservists and their families and provided as part of the ‘New Employment Model’ the MOD is developing for our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will support an integrated approach to pay and allowances and enable a much closer alignment of regular and Reservist careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will provide a much better deal for the families of Reservists, with help to access the support and networks available to Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outwith a genuine national emergency, we will also provide predictability to deployment, which will help at home as well as at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Routine liability in the Army Reserve will be for no more than one six month deployment in 5 years - although the total period of mobilisation would be longer - in some cases up to a year - to encompass operation specific training and post-operation recuperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some mobilisations will be much shorter - for example the Reserve element of the contribution to Olympics was only mobilised for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will be able to indicate in advance when the potential period of deployment will occur for any individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all these changes, this is an exciting proposition for Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenging, yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the Reserve Forces of the future, we need people who genuinely want to serve their nation and are committed to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this proposition will be appealing to those leaving the Regulars, as well as to the Volunteer Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an average year, over 18,000 people leave the regular forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, they have a liability for reserve service for a time limited period after they leave the regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few serve actively in this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could make better use of this asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making an attractive offer to departing regulars to remain voluntarily engaged in the Reserve we will do two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll help ourselves with numbers - just 10% of departing regulars taking up active Reserve Service would take us a significant part of the way to meeting our target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will also strengthen the resilience of the Reserves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more ex-regulars we have in the Reserves, the easier it will be for the Reserves to integrate with the Regulars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-relationships-with-employers"&gt;New Relationships with Employers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this proposition for Reservists themselves is only one part of the jigsaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often in the past we’ve recruited the Reservist and then left him or her to worry about how to tell the employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though our plans call for a Reserve that will represent only 0.1% of the total UK workforce, I do not believe that we can achieve our ambitions without the active cooperation of employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this fresh start for the Reserves is also a fresh start for the relationship between the Armed Forces and the businesses who employ their Reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to work with employers, building partnerships that deliver mutual benefit from Reserve Service;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joint approach to leadership and management training;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration on skills training;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to develop potential in students before they graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All will require a genuinely open relationship between Employer, Reservist and the Military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the employer understanding the Reservist’s liability and the Reservist confident that his service will not prejudice employment or promotion prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And underpinning this new relationship will be a tailored approach for different types of employer, reflecting the different benefits and impacts Reserve Service can have on companies in different sectors and of different sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that Reserve Service will affect small employers differently from large ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the truth, of course, is that with the growth of statutory leave entitlements - and other flexible working practices - employers of all sizes are becoming much more used to managing periods of absence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it is likely that public sector and large private sector organisations will be best placed to manage Reservists in their workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I see a real opportunity to work with major employers, like BT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employers who are already engaging through the Partnering for Talent Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies take great pride in supporting our Reservists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They see it as part of their corporate social responsibility; a great way of showing commitment to society at large&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are leading the way and helping us shape an adaptable and flexible Defence Force with an increased role for the Reserves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only right that we recognise these companies and the Green Paper suggests a new ‘Kitemark’ type award for Reserve-friendly employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not just about Corporate Social Responsibility: it must also be about mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many employers see very clearly the benefit that Reserve training and experience brings to them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering motivated, skilled, talented employees representing the values of the wider Armed Forces - integrity, application and commitment;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership training that is different from its civilian counterpart, adding a dimension to the skills of the work force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will consult on expanding the accreditation of skills and experience gained in reserve service through recognised civilian qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing direct benefit to employers through reduced training costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will consult, too, on the scope for linking apprenticeships and Reserve service in a package. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable this open relationship we are proposing to introduce a voluntary charter for employers of Reservists, recognising the contribution that good employers make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we will also consider anti-discrimination legislation if we see evidence of systematic disadvantage to the Reservist in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the shape of the fresh start for our Reserve Forces and our proposition to employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Reservist: an exciting opportunity to be an integrated and respected part of the Defence of the nation - at the centre, not sidelined - with greater opportunities and better rewards - but with more responsibilities and commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the employer: a new relationship of mutual benefit - with packages designed for specific types of business - helping them to make better use of the skills, talents and training of Reservists - as well as an opportunity to support our Armed Forces and be recognised for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for Reservists, their families and employers alike - greater certainty and greater predictability to Reserve Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the investment we are making, the Reserves are no longer the forgotten part of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we go forward, they will be at its very heart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39704</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-launched-on-the-future-of-britains-reserve-forces"/>
    <title>Consultation launched on the future of Britain's Reserve Forces</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation, ‘Future Reserves 2020: Delivering the Nation’s Security Together’, proposes more training for reservists, a ‘kitemark-type’ award for supportive employers, and the idea of changing the Territorial Army’s name to reflect their enhanced role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals there will be a new relationship between reservists, employers and government, and a transparent approach whereby employers are given more certainty about the timing of possible mobilisations and more notice when they occur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures will create a fully integrated force of regulars and reservists, using similar equipment and training together. It will mean that the Reserves not only provide individual augmentees to regular units, but also deploy as formed units and sub-units. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Royal Marines Reserve" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1435/Consultation_launched_on_the_future_of_Britain_s_Reserve_Forces2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Royal Marines Reserve received a rare opportunity to form the Guard at Edinburgh Castle recently
[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of trained Reserves will grow to around 35,000 across all three Services by 2020, aligning the mix of regular and reserve components with many of our closest allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army will see the biggest change, with 30,000 trained Reserves, creating a total land force of about 120,000. And the plans are backed by an extra £1.8bn in funding over the next ten years for new equipment, uniforms and training for the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• increasing the number of days Army reservists are required to train from 35 to 40 days a year  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• a change of name from Territorial Army to Army Reserve - better reflecting the future role and tasks  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• encouraging more ex-regulars to become reservists - making it easier for them to transfer to the Reserves and developing incentives for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This transformation of the Reserves will see a radical shift in the way in which we use them, with units deployed as formed units or sub-units as well as delivering individual augmentees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Increased training, better equipment and extra investment in our Reserves are all integral to our vision of a formidable, adaptable and flexible Armed Forces, with a reserve/regular balance more in line with our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government has committed £1.8bn to rebuilding our Reserves. The consultation I have launched today is about working with reservists, their families and employers to use that money to design the Reserve Forces of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir Nick Houghton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since 2003 there have been over 25,000 reservists mobilised, fighting alongside their regular counterparts. 29 have paid the ultimate price for their country and just this summer we saw 2,000 reservists provide a pivotal security role at the London 2012 Games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the future we will become even more reliant on our Reserves. But this increased reliance means that there are key issues that we have to tackle - like our relationship with employers and the notice period ahead of mobilisation - to get this right. I want to encourage everyone to get involved in this consultation and have their say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 18 January 2013 and following this we will publish a White Paper in Spring 2013 setting out this new relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45349</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-01-air-power-partnership-in-the-21st-century"/>
    <title>2012/11/01 - Air Power: Partnership in the 21st Century</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;101 years ago today, on the first of November 1911, an Italian pilot threw four hand-held bombs out of a plane, from all of 600 feet, on Ottoman positions in what is now part of modern day Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although no-one was reported killed, and the only Ottoman response was, I’m told, a complaint of ungentlemanly conduct, this is generally regarded as the first bombing mission undertaken by aeroplane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, the Royal Flying Corps was formed, and over the last century, air power has moved from a peripheral role in military strategy, to a central one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Air Force today is integral to the defence of the United Kingdom and an indispensible part of operations to protect national security:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, helping to provide the Libyan people with the protection, and indeed the courage, they needed to overthrow the brutal dictator who had oppressed them for so long;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, policing the skies over London to ensure the delivery of a safe and secure Olympics; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I speak now, in the skies over Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all of these operations, air-power alone would not be enough; but in none of these operations could success have been achieved without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk today about the future development of the Royal Air Force and its contribution to the security of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as the theme of this conference suggests, I will do so in the context of partnership - international and domestic - military and civilian - government and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships that the RAF will need to enhance if it is to continue to assure the delivery air power in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A century in which space and cyber space will emerge as increasingly important domains of the overall strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in which the evolution of technology is already changing how air power can be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that the pilot of an aircraft need not be sitting in a cockpit, but can be in a bunker 3,000 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me first set out the overarching framework within which the Royal Air Force will continue to transform its capability, structure and infrastructure over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transformation"&gt;Transformation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I became Secretary of State just over a year ago, the campaign in Libya was entering its final phase - with Gaddafi and his family expelled from Tripoli and holed up in Sirte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first day on the job was partly taken up with targeting decisions for air strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any notion that Defence was ‘just another Government Department with a budget problem’ was quickly dispelled.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I was having to navigate my foundation lesson in “military speak”, that impenetrable language designed to repel outsiders, and to underline just how different Defence is from other parts of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw at first hand, literally on my first day, that of course the first priority was then and will remain, success on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the very raison d’etre of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that our country is defended, our national security interests protected at home and abroad, and our values projected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan we are clear that we will end combat operations by December 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime, we must complete the mission: training and preparing the Afghan Forces to take on the burden of security, so that we can bring our personnel home, while protecting the gains that we have so expensively made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we and our ISAF partners draw down, we will be more dependent than ever on the air-bridge, and the RAF’s work in sustaining this link is critical to delivering success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of the Royal Air Force’s strength is currently contributing directly to operations and standing commitments -  in Afghanistan and on other tasks defending the UK and our dependent territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF is an integral part of the front-line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just as I am clear on the priority of operations, I am equally clear that without budgetary discipline, the need for the kind of reductions and tough decisions taken as part of the 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review, would come upon us again - and we will have gained nothing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, budgetary discipline has to be the supporting foundation of the transformation to Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence equipment programme needs to be balanced and sustainable if the Armed Forces are to have the confidence that the capabilities promised will actually be delivered, on time and to requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now half-way through this Parliament and I can confirm that we in the Ministry of Defence now have a balanced budget with an affordable equipment programme, backed by, although you might not realise it reading the British media, what will still be the fourth largest Defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this changes the dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By maintaining discipline, sensibly managing in-year budgets, and tightening our long-term projections, we can begin to release the contingencies that we have built into the budget, to support further investments in capability, confident that there is a sustainable funding stream to deliver them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, since the beginning of this financial year, the new discipline in our budgetary regime has allowed us to give the go ahead for a series of equipment projects for the air environment over and above the committed equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes targeting pods for fast jets, better protection systems for Tornado GR4, and enhancements to MERLIN Helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The powerful, adaptable RAF of Future Force 2020 is taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The re-formation of 13 Squadron at RAF Waddington, announced last week, will double the RAF Predator capability in the skies over Afghanistan, flying these remotely piloted air systems from ground stations in the UK for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was proud earlier this year, to be in Fort Worth to take delivery of the UK’s first F-35 Lightning II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning II is one of the clearest examples of Britain’s determination to stay in the top rank of military powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the clearest examples of our determination to maintain an advanced, powerful and flexible combat air capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of our regeneration of Carrier Strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A world-class capability, able to deploy anywhere in the world and jointly operated by the Royal Navy and the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With land based initial operating capability in 2018, allowing the platform to deploy as part of the UK’s contingent combat air capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And initial flights off HMS Queen Elizabeth in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a decade away, as our critics complain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just over 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deployed outside home waters, the new Carrier will routinely have Lightning II jets embarked with personnel from both Services, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been speculation in the media, much of it, as usual, ill-informed, around our intentions for operating the Carrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be absolutely clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF and the Royal Navy are working together to deliver a joint force that can operate from land bases in the UK, from the carriers when they are at sea, and from forward operating bases when deployed abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the direction of the Chief of the Defence Staff, the concept of operations for carrier enabled power projection is being developed in line with the adaptable posture set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concept of operations that will embrace both carrier strike and littoral manoeuvre operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is a substantial process, and dependent in part on decisions due to taken as part of the next SDSR in 2015 on the use of the second carrier to produce continuous carrier capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a joint asset, Lightning II will provide us with a flexible capability that will out-perform anything we’ve been able to put in the air before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with the UK enjoying a 15 % share of the industrial work, the peak production period is likely to sustain 25,000 jobs in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Strike Fighter project was conceived as a multi-national programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s tier one status in the programme speaks eloquently of the UK’s close partnership with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to turn now to the theme of international partnerships - because that relationship with the US is the UK’s most important, but by no means only, relationship upon which we rely to deliver our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-partnership"&gt;International Partnership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;100 years on from that very first aircraft bombing mission in Libya, NATO’s Operation Unified Protector last year proved the versatility of the RAF’s combat capabilities in the very same skies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just the precision weapons in the arsenal like Storm Shadow, dual-mode Brimstone and Paveway IV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also in the employment of Typhoon in its first multi-role contribution to operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the mission critical ISTAR assets such as Sentinel and E3-D Sentry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the strategic level, the mission demonstrated once again how air power can provide politicians with political choices short of intervention on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as the Chief of the Air Staff has previously said, Libya is not the archetype for conflict, anymore than Afghanistan is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can learn the very valuable lessons of both campaigns as we work to deliver adaptable Armed Forces, best configured to deal with the contingencies of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The striking feature of both campaigns is the breadth of the coalition taking part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libya operation saw 260 aircraft from 16 countries flying 26,500 sorties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of cooperation, in particular, between the RAF and the French Armee de l’Air during the campaign, was a potent demonstration of the new momentum in UK-French defence cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, the International Security Assistance Force is now some 50 nations strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAF assets operate alongside those of our fellow ISAF partners…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… the Tornado GR4 force at Kandahar airport shares Tango Ramp with F16s from the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camp Bastion airfield in Helmand, controlled by the RAF, ranks as one of the busiest multi-national airfields in the world, handling up to 450 movements a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level and sophistication of the integration between coalition partners, forged in campaigns such as Afghanistan and Libya, needs to be maintained and then taken forward long after those campaigns are behind us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the RAF, this interoperability with allies has become second nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last century, from the Allied air campaigns of the 2nd world war, through the Berlin Air Lift, to the Gulf War, Balkans and Kosovo campaigns of the 1990s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this century in Iraq, Afghanistan and Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF has honed its understanding and interoperability, operating as part of multi-national coalitions over many, many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wide international audience that I see before me today, is testament to the strength of the relationship that the RAF has forged with its fellow military aviators from across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That operational experience is now being built upon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tornados from RAF Marham have deployed to the Middle East for a series of exercises to work with partner nations on Exercise SHAHEEN STAR - and soon Typhoons from RAF Leuchars will be joining exercises in UAE and Oman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Typhoon has also been flying with allies from the Five Power Defence Arrangement as part of Exercise BERSAMA LIMA 11, in Malaysia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all part of putting into practice the kind of interoperability we will need in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-partnership-challenge"&gt;The Partnership Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there is another strategic lesson we can draw from recent operations, particularly Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the one hand, Libya showed the strength of our the NATO alliances and our partnerships, the operation also, to be frank, cruelly exposed the imbalances and weaknesses in NATO and thus the scale of the task facing European NATO nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as former US Defence Secretary Robert Gates pointed out at the time, “The most advanced fighter aircraft are little use if allies do not have the means to identify, process, and strike targets as part of an integrated campaign”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could argue this is the very nature of coalition operations, with each partner providing the skills and assets that it can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of Libya it shone a bright light on relative military and political capabilities in terms of who “could but wouldn’t”; and who “would but couldn’t”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the United States reflecting, in its strategic posture, the growing importance of the developing strategic challenge in the Pacific, the nations of Europe must find the political will to take on more responsibility for our own back yard, and fund the capabilities to allow that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly that means, shouldering the major burden in the Balkans and the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also being prepared, if necessary, to take a bigger role in relation to North Africa and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that Europe, as a whole, needs to do more, at a time when the reality is that, across the continent, aggregate defence expenditure is certain to fall in the short term and, at best, recover slowly in the medium term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the challenge is stark: if we can’t spend more, we must do things differently;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maximising the capability we can collectively squeeze out of the resources we have; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing interoperability, closing capability gaps through joint working and greater specialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the UK is overhauling its ISTAR, strategic lift and combat air capabilities as part of the transition to Future Force 2020 with the new Atlas and Voyager fleets operating alongside the C17, Sentry, Sentinel, and Airseeker as well as a range of remotely piloted air systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These forces will allow us to offer capacity to share with our international partners in new, innovative and mutually beneficial ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, for the time being at least, we will depend on others for support with maritime patrol aircraft, when we need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is not just about smart behaviour by NATO members per-se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Britain, Smart Defence is also about making the Alliance more flexible, encouraging collaboration among groups of allies within the Alliance, and with partners outside the Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Libya and Afghanistan have shown how agile NATO can be in incorporating the contributions of outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should capitalise on this experience in making it easier for non-NATO nations and key potential partners to contribute to NATO’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The partnership challenge encompasses more than just bi-lateral and multi-lateral government-to-government or military-to-military relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also encompasses those who supply and support our equipment too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partnership-with-industry"&gt;Partnership with Industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With shrinking Defence budgets in many advanced countries, and ever greater appetite and capability for involvement in design, development and production of sophisticated military equipment in the emerging economies, it is a tough business environment out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition will be intense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic challenges involved in maintaining a high tech, highly capable, air force now and in the future are considerable -and the technical challenges equally high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success will require a genuinely transparent collaboration in aerospace, between industry and government to keep overheads down, to maintain essential R&amp;amp;D, and to build healthy export order books while making sure the unit cost is affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are embarking on some major changes to make the MOD a more capable and intelligent customer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restructuring equipment acquisition and through-life support;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing in private sector management skills through a partnership to re-inforce the military and civilian specialists who form the backbone of the Defence equipment and procurement organisation;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at how the acquisition processes can take better account of the commercial landscape - building in exportability - making sure the wider package on offer to potential customers is as attractive as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those years of over-programming in Defence created a climate of uncertainty that was beneficial neither to our Armed Forces, nor to industry - with neither side able to plan properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide industry with as much information as possible to plan, we will be publishing a summary of the equipment plan in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide greater granularity than ever before about how money will be spent across the breadth of capabilities by breaking down spending for equipment and support alongside the judgement of the National Audit Office on the robustness of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong aerospace sector in the UK - manufacturing, servicing, and crucially exporting - is a vital part of the Government’s strategy for rebalancing our economy so it can return to sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also an onus on our suppliers to provide better value for money for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need our partners to be lean and flexible, capable of operating in a more competitive defence marketplace, responsive to the needs of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry support for air operations in Libya last year shows what can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering and sustaining capability - as well as supplying equipment and developing new technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently 5,000 contractors directly supporting our operations in Afghanistan, including the vital role played by the RAF. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Total Support Force’ concept, set out in the White Paper, seeks to integrate more fully the contribution of the private sector to operations. Industry, the Armed Forces, MOD, civilians and industry working more closely than ever to achieve their mutual goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Future Force 2020, we are building a force fit for a more uncertain world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we may not know in advance what conditions we will be fighting in;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we can only hope to meet the challenges of modern conflict and protect national security by exploiting all the advantages we possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of our advanced technology and industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of our international alliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the advantage of our highly trained, highly capable people -  working together as a total force to deliver the world’s most effective expeditionary military capability outside the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF brings unique capabilities to the delivery of joint effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid reaction, speed, agility and precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control of the air and the ability to exploit that domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategic lift to project power at range;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactical manoeuvre and re-supply on the battlefield;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the real-time intelligence and awareness that airborne ISTAR provides of the battle space as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the people of the RAF that deliver this effect. Our people are our principal asset. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just the pilot; the air crew, the engineers, the planners, the whole edifice of the RAF that supports the delivery of British air power at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as we enter the remembrance period, and honour those who have sacrificed so much for the freedom of this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us express our confidence in the men and women of today’s Royal Air Force; in their determination to demonstrate the same spirit and commitment to duty as their illustrious forbears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that our skies will continue to be safe in their hands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45362</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-15-ssafa-annual-defence-industry-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/10/15 - SSAFA Annual Defence Industry Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kevin [Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, SSAFA Chair] for that introduction; and for your kind invitation to make the address this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Royal Highness, Chief of the Defence Staff, my Lords, Ladies and Gentlemen, it’s a great pleasure to be back here at SSAFA’s annual dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I spoke at the Annual Dinner last year it was my first speech as Defence Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After just days in the job, I was confidently asserting all sorts of things with very little direct personal knowledge of whether they were true or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year on, a little more au fait with the military jargon, and a lot more familiar with the challenges facing our troops and their families, I can pay full tribute to the vital work that SSAFA does, based on a personal understanding of the need you are meeting and the difference you are making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week, I heard at first hand at Queen Elizabeth Hospital in Birmingham how facilities such as SSAFA’s Norton House allow visiting families to focus their energies on their injured loved one without having to worry about finding and paying for accommodation close to the hospital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the range of activities, outlined by the Chief of the Defence Staff earlier, the work you do is hugely appreciated and highly valued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on behalf of all of us in Defence, let me say “thank you” to you and the industry who support you so magnificently, for everything that you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is one year to the day since my first day in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an old civil service legend that’s told about Sir Alec Douglas-Home when he was appointed Foreign Secretary under Ted Heath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first weekend box, he was confronted with a two-inch thick report on Icelandic fisheries and a note from his Private Secretary, which read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Secretary of State may care to read this over the weekend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Alec returned the report the following Monday with his own note, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A kind thought, but wholly erroneous.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I arrived in the MoD, I had been prepared for the worst: a stereotypical bureaucracy seeking to frustrate ministerial intent at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have to say, my experience has been very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into a Department as complex as Defence has been quite an eye-opener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly wasn’t appointed because of my knowledge of fighter jets or aircraft carriers or armoured vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if I’m honest, I probably came into the Department with a focus on the budget challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly understood that, while the budget is crucially important, Defence is about much more than a set of balanced books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="afghanistan"&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first day in post, one of the first duties of my Military Assistant was to inform me of the death in Afghanistan of Rifleman Vijay Rai of the 2nd Battalion, the Royal Gurkha Rifles, and to explain to me the process of kinforming and repatriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a very sober introduction to my new responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to the reality of our operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those operations remain, of course, the first priority of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we come towards the end of our mission there, it’s important for us to remind ourselves why our troops are there; how much they’ve achieved; and how we are going to get them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we are in Afghanistan is simple: to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the only reason, in my book, to ask our troops to put themselves in harm’s way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is clear: training the Afghan Forces to take on the burden of security so that we can bring our troops home while ensuring the gains that we have made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And coming home they will be: another 500 by Christmas, and we expect to make further, significant reductions by the end of next year, with all UK combat operations finishing by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="balancing-the-budget"&gt;Balancing the Budget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move towards the end of our mission, we need to plan now for the post-Afghanistan environment and the Transformation of Defence to meet the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has been dominated by the urgent need to eliminate the black hole in the MoD budget; to learn lessons from the failures of the past; and to ensure that our forces are prepared for the very different challenges they will face in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has meant taking some tough decisions: to shrink the size of the MoD; to rationalize our equipment programme; and to reduce the size of the Navy, Army and the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-way through this Parliament, we now have a balanced budget with an affordable equipment programme and a deliverable plan Future Force 2020, backed by what will still be the fourth largest Defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people---the-future-of-our-armed-forces"&gt;People - The Future of our Armed Forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the budget is crucially important, but it is not an end in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a means to enable us to deliver, sustainably, the Defence of this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the key to doing that - what really delivers Britain’s battle-winning edge - is the people that make up Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces - Regular and Reserves; the civilians who support them and the Defence Industry which supplies them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my big learning curves over the last year (and there have been a few) has been understanding the unique nature of what the military call the “moral component” of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is that provides the “will to fight”, and the determination to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes our people so special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of our people feel they have taken a bit of a pounding over the last couple of years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also know that I have got a big job on my hands to build their trust and win their confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having fixed the budget problem and begun the process of Transforming the Department, it is now time to focus on our people, and their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I cannot avoid the need for change, what I can do is give people clarity and certainty about their individual futures as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already completed the Armed Forces Pension review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering a new, non-contributory scheme that remains one of the very best pension offers anywhere in the public or private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the end of the year, we will announce the re-basing plan, so that families will know where their future homes will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will do everything we can to minimise the number of compulsory redundancies as we bring the Army to its future size over the next couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that our service men and women want certainty that at the end of these changes, they will be part of UK Armed Forces that remain amongst the very best and most respected in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many countries will have more people in their armed forces, and some may even have similar equipment, very few will be able to begin to match the military capability of our people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this process of transformation, I am confident that we will have the most capable, deployable armed forces outside the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strengthening--the-covenant"&gt;Strengthening  the Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want our servicemen and women to know that the Government and society as a whole recognises the debt of gratitude we owe to them and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have enshrined the key principles of the Armed Forces Covenant in law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Covenant is now becoming entrenched across Whitehall - so much so that Ministers in other departments are now coming to me asking how they can do their bit to support our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor, with £35 million from banking fines redirected to service charities;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Education Secretary, increasing and extending the scope of the service pupil premium;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And across Government, a commitment to give Reservists a minimum 10 days’ additional paid leave each year for their training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud that upholding and strengthening the Covenant is taken so seriously across Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have more work to do, but the process is now irreversibly established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-year-ahead"&gt;The Year Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the year ahead, as well as the proper priority that we will give to our operations in Afghanistan, we will make progress on three important parts of Defence transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, working to build our new Reserve capability and integrate the Reserves with our Regular forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, we’ll publish our Reserves Green Paper, setting out our new offer, backed by an additional £1.8 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In return for properly equipping, training, and funding our Reserves we will expect them to turn up regularly to train, and to be prepared to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite thousands of them having served in Afghanistan and operations around the world, too often our Reserves have been the forgotten part of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer: in the future, they will be more vital to our force projection than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will treat them as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we will accelerate work on the New Employment Model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making service terms and conditions more flexible, better reflecting the complexity of modern family life and delivering our goal of higher levels of home ownership among members of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And third, restructuring our equipment and support acquisition, bringing in private sector management skills to support the military and civilian specialists who form the backbone of DE&amp;amp;S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined that the MoD will be a much better customer in the future - an organization with which the Defence industry can do business far more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in return, we need the industry to be leaner, more cost-conscious suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that with shrinking Defence budgets in many countries, it is a tough environment out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by working together to create the equipment our Armed Forces need, at a cost we can afford and at a price that makes it exportable, we can continue this country’s proud tradition of excellence in Defence manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last couple of years haven’t been easy for anyone in Defence, least of all for those in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the budget back in balance and the bulk of the tough decisions taken, we can now look ahead to the future with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handing over security in Afghanistan to the Afghan;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming our Armed Forces for the future;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the battle-winning platforms and weapon systems our forces need;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforming procurement;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And building our integrated Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most importantly, we can begin the process of rebuilding confidence in the future among our people after years of uncertainty and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a challenge for me and for the Department - indeed for the whole of Government and society as we build on the commitments of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is one that we will be hugely better able to rise to with the magnificent support of the fantastic service charities such as SSAFA and your generous supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you again for everything you do - and please, keep up the good work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39691</id>
    <published>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/work-on-afghan-officers-academy-underway-as-herrick-17-begins"/>
    <title>Work on Afghan officers' academy underway as HERRICK 17 begins</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The building of the future &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt;, marked today, 10 October, by an earth-turning ceremony at its site in the Afghan capital, underlines the UK’s long-term commitment to a secure Afghanistan after combat operations cease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once fully operational, the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt; will train up to 1,350 male students and 150 female students each year. Based on a model resembling the Royal Military Academy Sandhurst, it will help to sustain the ongoing progress being made in building a capable and professional Afghan National Army. This work will take place during and after the transition of security responsibilities to the Afghan Government post-2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event coincided with the transfer of authority between British brigades in Helmand with 4th Mechanized Brigade taking command of Task Force Helmand from 12th Mechanized Brigade which is now on its way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Doug Chalmers (left), Commander of 12th Mechanized Brigade, and Brigadier Bob Bruce of 4th Mechanized Brigade " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1479/Work_on_Afghan_officers__academy_underway_as_HERRICK_17_begins2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Brigadier Doug Chalmers (left), Commander of 12th Mechanized Brigade, hands over command of Task Force Helmand to Brigadier Bob Bruce of 4th Mechanized Brigade [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transfer of authority marks the start of Operation HERRICK 17 which will oversee the drawdown of 500 UK Service personnel already announced to take place by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six months will see 4th Mechanized Brigade working in support of the Afghan National Security Forces to ensure they are capable of assuming full security responsibilities by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In July, the [UK] Prime Minister [David Cameron] and President Karzai signed a Memorandum of Understanding to reaffirm UK and Afghan dedication to the officer academy project in Kabul which is one of the UK’s commitments to an enduring partnership with Afghanistan after our combat operations cease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The academy will present a real opportunity for us to help generate a well-trained cadre of junior officers to bolster the leadership within the Afghan Army for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both the commencement of the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army Officer Academy"&gt;ANAOA&lt;/abbr&gt; project and the planned drawdown of 500 personnel from 4th Mechanized Brigade by the end of the year demonstrate significant steps forward in a transition process that is well on track and will see us hand over full security responsibility for Afghanistan to its own security forces in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the earth-turning ceremony in Kabul, Deputy Commander of the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF), Lieutenant General Adrian Bradshaw, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The training that will take place here will develop the next generation of military leaders in a brand new Afghan National Army Officer Academy. This is yet another example of how ISAF and the Afghan National Security Forces are sustaining the progress we have made in building a capable and professional force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very proud of our achievements and the turning of the earth marks not only the start of the main construction effort but also the beginning of the academy itself. It is a truly historic occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel from 4th Mechanized Brigade will work alongside the Afghan Army and the Afghan National Police in a co-ordinated effort over the forthcoming winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander of Task Force Helmand for HERRICK 17, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our focus throughout this deployment will be on assisting our Afghan allies to deliver security to their people. We are superbly well trained and equipped to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Real success has been achieved. As the Afghan security forces continue to grow in capability and confidence we will reduce our profile. I am planning to send 500 troops home by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27962</id>
    <published>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-important-relationship-between-uk-and-poland"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes "important relationship" between UK and Poland</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The British Ministers discussed a range of issues of mutual importance to our two countries with Poland’s Foreign Minister Rados?aw Sikorski and Defence Minister Tomasz Siemoniak.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a huge pleasure to be in Poland again. The United Kingdom and Poland share an important relationship. We are close allies within the EU and NATO and share a similar outlook on many international issues. Today we had a valuable discussion on issues which matter to both our countries. Of course the situation in Syria was foremost in our minds. Britain and Poland stand together with the Syrian people as they face a shocking humanitarian situation brought about by the violence of the Assad regime. We also discussed a wide range of other topics including NATO, European defence and bilateral defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This morning we also discussed Europe’s Eastern Neighbourhood. The United Kingdom will continue to support the Eastern Partnership and I would like to pay tribute to Minister Radek Sikorski for his efforts in encouraging the EU to reach out to our Eastern neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Eastern Partnership has the potential to transform the EU’s relationship with our eastern partners and with it the prospect of meaningful integration. Any such integration relies on a genuine commitment by all parties to a set of common values. These common values must be the foundation stone of the Eastern Partnership, just as they are for the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We want to offer strong support to our partners to carry out reforms and will help them to succeed; but there can be no backsliding on democracy. In this respect, the Ukrainian and Georgian Parliamentary elections in October will be of paramount importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On Belarus, we call - once more - for the release and rehabilitation of all political detainees as a first step towards the normalisation of relations. We hope that this weekend’s parliamentary elections will be conducted to international standards, and that there will no repeat of the violence against peaceful protesters that marred the 2012 Presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We also discussed many other issues including economic growth, the single market and increasing trade.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreign &amp;amp; Defence Secretaries visit Warsaw&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/slideShow/index.gne?group_id=_groupid_&amp;amp;user_id=ukinpoland&amp;amp;set_id=72157631574464324" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary attended a commercial diplomacy event in the British Embassy. The event was planned as an exhibition of UK strategic competency and live exhibits which are available in Poland and the broader region, showcasing the UK experience in energy sector power generation and engineering, and the potential of Poland as the leading market in Emerging Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quadrilateral meeting: statements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/VPNUE3Di4hE" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top British automotive and construction engineering brands, including Aston Martin, Jaguar, Land Rover, Lotus and JCB, were on display in the Embassy garden. The visit of the Foreign and Defence Secretaries concluded with a meeting with Poland’s President Bronis?aw Komorowski. It was an excellent opportunity to build on the ministerial discussions held earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second quadrilateral meeting between the UK and Poland on diplomacy and defence issues. The first one had been held in London in October 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45361</id>
    <published>2012-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-23-address-to-the-royal-college-of-defence-studies"/>
    <title>2012/07/23 - Address to the Royal College of Defence Studies</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me here to speak to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as you approach the end of your course I know you will have made the most of the opportunity presented here at the Royal College Of Defence Studies to get to grips with some of the very complex issues facing defence and defence diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of which are common to the United Kingdom and its allies and partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international nature of this course is one of its strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your generation of leaders will have a key role in addressing these challenges; and in forging the bi-lateral and multi-lateral defence relationships that the Defence and Security arrangements of every country, even the United States, is likely to rely on in the future to protect its national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to talk this morning about some of the strategic challenges we’re facing in UK Defence and more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And pose you some of the questions that will have to be answered during your generation’s tenure in the top jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strategic-picture"&gt;Strategic Picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategically, the world is a far less certain, and in some ways, a less threatening place than it was 25 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we faced an adversary with the means, and the intent, if an unpredictable and paranoid leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, at least, the paranoid leaderships are still struggling to obtain the means!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly technology is racing ahead; changing the way we protect critical infrastructure more likely to be rendered inoperable through a computer virus than a bombing raid; requiring multi-level C4ISTAR - capabilities which are not as obvious to the public and an aircraft carrier, a tank or a jet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of ‘invisible’ capabilities like this presents a challenge to politicians who need to demonstrate to the public who are paying for them, how we are spending their money and how we are keeping them safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a geo-political level, the dispersion of power that began as the Berlin Wall crumbled has gathered pace with the emergence of new potential military powers and greater strategic competition between growing economies, both regionally and globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, the impact of globalisation means there are diminishing levers available to individual national governments to effect change, manage their economies, and protect their national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic realities facing the mature economies show how linked we are; how easily contagion can spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the medium term, those charged with the task of protecting national security, in economies set for relative decline as the pattern of wealth adjusts, will have to do so in an environment of constrained resources &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the future in which you will lead in your respective services and in your respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And although this future will be unpredictable and volatile, we can clearly see some of the issues that will dominate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-means"&gt;Economic Means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - The economic backdrop. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic strength underpins national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a requirement for generating military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at what is driving the changed pattern of military power today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at what settled the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without strong economies and public finances it is impossible to build and sustain, in the long-term, the military capability required to project power and maintain strong defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, today, the debt crisis should be considered the greatest strategic threat to the future security of western nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is also why, although NATO has often talked of distributing the burden of collective defence more equitably, in the current fiscal climate, it is essential that we no longer talk, but begin to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that too many member states are failing to meet their financial responsibilities to NATO, and so failing to maintain appropriate and proportionate capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many are opting out of operations or contributing but a fraction of what they should be capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have to be realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic and fiscal circumstances in which most developed countries find themselves, makes this problem difficult to fix in the short term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the alliance, aggregate defence expenditure is certain to fall in the short term and, at best, recover slowly in the medium term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So more money is not going to be the answer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the challenge is to maximise the capability we can squeeze out of the resources we have available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="political-will"&gt;Political Will&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to my second point: alliance structures are only as strong as the political will of individual nations to meet their responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It matters that NATO countries meet their commitments on funding Defence - to ensure the means to protect our collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is no good having the means if you lack the will to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya showed what can be achieved when many of the stars are in alignment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Security Council, NATO, regional powers, the political will of those with the capabilities to act, and of course the will of the majority of the Libyan people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also showed quite starkly the imbalances in NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imbalances in the hardware (and increasingly software) available to the Alliance from national contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also imbalances in the will to act, the will to deploy, the determination to take part and commit nationally owned capabilities that have absorbed many billions of taxpayers’ cash in order to make us all collectively safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are untapped reserves of resource in European NATO which need to be tapped to support our collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few years, the United States will put into practice its ‘tilt’ to the Asia-Pacific theatre - a focus that is very much in our interests as the US rise to meet the strategic challenge set by the emergence of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US will expect Europe to do more to of the heavy lifting to ensure security in our own region, and our near abroad - the Middle East, North Africa, and the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How European nations respond to this pivot will set the context for the multi-lateral environment British Armed Forces and others will operate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my third point: cohesion of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="meeting-threats"&gt;Meeting Threats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to confront head on a real tension within the NATO alliance: basically to answer the question, what is NATO for in the 21st Century?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threat from a monolithic Soviet Union no longer exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the approach to Russia differs across the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us further back, west of the old iron curtain, the threat is no longer a territorial, but global terror and rogue states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a passive defence of national territory is no longer adequate protection for our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are starting from a reality that it is much better to fight in the space of our adversaries rather than at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this is relatively easier to do if your adversary is a terrorist, rather than a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this requires rapidly deployable, adaptable, agile, flexible, expeditionary forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is what the UK’s Strategic Defence &amp;amp; Security Review was all about; responding to these three drivers - the economics, the evolving alliance pattern, and the evolving threat pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaping the spread of capabilities we will maintain, in the face of fiscal restraint, to the future character of warfare - and to maintain national security by acting at distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future posture of Russia is by no means certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with political change sweeping across North Africa and the Arab world, change that is far from at an end, far from predictable, and has the potential to leave a less secure and less safe neighbourhood, we cannot rule out the return of a strategic threat to territorial Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this has been about striking the right balance between our own direct national needs and those of the NATO alliance upon which we continue to rely for collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recognising the likely future shape of operations in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future-shape-of-operations"&gt;The Future Shape of Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have had the opportunity during your course to look at current operations and to draw lessons from them for the future character of warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya showed the utility of precision weapons in an era where minimising collateral damage and civilian deaths will be part of the strategic objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it also exposed shortfalls in the European contribution to NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Libya has tested another concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The utility of air-power as an alternative to ‘boots on the ground’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya has shown how air power can provide politicians like me with political choices short of intervention on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have not drawn the conclusion that ground intervention will be unnecessary in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a ground campaign in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could not have proceeded without NATO airpower support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was decisive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was undertaken by Libyans, not NATO troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 10 years of enduring campaigns, you do not have to be a political sage to recognise that the public’s future appetite for open-ended interventions is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we do not yet know the end outcome of the Libya intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Displacing the old regime was, relatively, the easy bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what comes after is not yet completely clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So modern warfare requires firepower and political sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that requires a deep understanding of the situation on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, our troops have had to wear the face of both the warrior and the diplomat - fighting one moment - and taking tea with the elders the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political dimension of warfare is crucial to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can win the battle but lose the war unless you are focussed on what you really want to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will usually be the case that force of arms alone cannot deliver victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is certainly the case in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the comprehensive approach - marrying politics, finance, military capability, diplomacy, development - not just across national government, but internationally too - will be so important in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, against that backdrop, let me bring this discussion closer to home and say something about the future shape of the UK’s Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future-shape-of-uk-armed-forces"&gt;The Future Shape of UK Armed Forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is still very much the priority in terms of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the end of the combat mission is now in view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, intellectually, we have moved on to look beyond 2014 at the shape of the Forces we will need for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The needs of the mission in Afghanistan, and before it Iraq, have dominated for a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the dangers and complexities of those missions they have provided some predictability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have known, often two years in advance, when they are going to be deployed; they know how long they are going to be deployed for; often they have known exactly where they are going to be deployed to before they go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have bent our military, our Army in particular into the shape required for this six month rotational enduring conflict in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the process, we have lost some contingent capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post 2014, the move from enduring campaign to contingency, signals an end to the predictability of the roulement cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It heralds a Future Force geared toward being ready to deal with the unexpected and unplanned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we make this change against a background of fiscal constraint driven by the economic health of the country as a whole, and the legacy of mismanagement in the defence budget in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation we are undertaking is challenging - probably the most complex change programme being undertaken anywhere in the western world at the current time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The black hole that existed in the defence budget, the weakness of the equipment programme, and the shape of the country’s finances, have militated against simply bailing the budget out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be hard to justify excluding the Defence Budget, the fifth largest call on the public purse, from the programme to exert fiscal control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the books and creating a sustainable forward Defence programme has meant reducing personnel numbers, retiring some capabilities, and taking some calculated and managed risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I told an audience in Washington last week - it is far better to have a smaller but well-equipped and well-trained force; with an equipment programme that offers a high level of confidence that we will deliver it; giving our Armed Forces the ability to plan for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the announcements I have made over the last couple of months on the Defence Budget, the Equipment Programme, Army 2020 and the Reserves we have put in place the vision set out in the SDSR of sustainable Armed Forces, equipped with some of the most capable and most technically advanced platforms in the world, configured to respond to the unexpected -  and to go anywhere to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have also set out a blueprint for the reform of the management of defence;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renewing the way strategic direction is provided;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing authority and accountability down the chain of command;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging innovation and budgetary responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And developing a new strategy for the procurement of defence equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeking to instil private sector skills and disciplines to our acquisition process, driving up productivity, by bringing a private sector partner into the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And creating clearer and harder relationships between the different functions in the Defence procurement chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To read some of the comment in the media, often fuelled by retired officers whose view of the world was shaped in the Cold War era, you would think that Britain was getting out of the force projection business altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing could be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when this programme is complete, we will still expect to have the fourth largest defence budget in the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceeding the NATO standard of 2% of GDP; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending £160bn on our equipment programme over the next 10 years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering the next generation of military technology and platforms that will help provide a battle-winning edge;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller Armed Forces but better equipped and confident that they will receive the equipment that has been promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile, high-tech, Capable of conducting the full spectrum of operations;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structured to allow rapid reaction and expeditionary warfare;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to deploy overseas and sustain a Brigade-sized force indefinitely, or a Division-sized force in time of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to command in the coalition context and more interoperable with our main allies;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully integrated between Regular and Reserves, with predictable obligations for the Reservists that will require a real commitment to service;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a more systematic use of contractors for support and logistics; allowing greater focus of military manpower on fighting tasks;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, structured to be able to generate mass and capabilities if the threat picture changes or the fiscal position eases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the British Armed Forces that some of you will be leading in - or for our partners overseas - the British Armed Forces you will be operating with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many of you who are from overseas will be seeing similar transformations in your own militaries over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you are here because you have been identified as having the qualities needed for top level responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the moral component of leadership is one of the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this transformation is to be realised, and national and collective security to be guaranteed, you will need to be focussed, positive, full of ideas, prepared to change, to challenge convention, and willing to drive change in others, inspiring those around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is a challenge at a political level too, for people like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Secretary of State, I have responsibility for Defence but as a Cabinet Member, I have responsibility to look wider and help to balance national priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an immediate or existential threat shrinks, the public appetite to fund Defence shrinks with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are lucky in the UK, particularly compared to other European nations, that the public feels a strong affinity with our Armed Forces and has a greater inclination to give defence a higher priority than many of our neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the legacy of Iraq and Afghanistan has undoubtedly left us a public which is without appetite for enduring campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And politicians need to think carefully about how we are going to maintain public support for Defence spending in the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially when more and more of the capabilities we are investing in will not be traditional military assets - and indeed will often be invisible to taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many actions in hand to manage the transition from a period of enduring campaigns to one of contingent readiness; and I have described a few today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have answered by no means all the questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the future focus of NATO;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About how we maximise the military effect that we get from limited budgets across the Alliance;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the balance of capabilities between traditional kinetic effect and investment in C4ISTAR, cyber and space;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the type of warfare we need to prepare to fight;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about the future of European Defence industries in the face of rapidly changing export markets and shrinking domestic purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, and many other questions, will form the challenges that the next generation of military and political leaders will face over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I look forward to hearing your thoughts on them!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
