<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-transport.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Secretary of State for Transport</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-20T14:38:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17395</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T14:38:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T14:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/crucial-road-improvements-to-be-delivered-twice-as-fast"/>
    <title>Crucial road improvements to be delivered twice as fast</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and hauliers will benefit from increased capacity on England’s motorways by spring 2015 thanks to the acceleration of 3 upgrades, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be delivered in this spending review period rather than the next, as the government introduces major improvements to the way road schemes are planned and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new way of working should in future see lanes added to motorways in up to half the time it normally takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three schemes being accelerated are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vital improvements to A160/A180 route to the port of Immingham will also start construction sooner than originally planned in the summer of 2015 and completed autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half by dismantling procedures that have slowed us down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Together these schemes will increase capacity for millions of road users by 72 miles. My ambition is that in future all major road schemes will be accelerated, tackling congestion more quickly and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a keynote speech to the &lt;abbr title="Confederation of British Industry"&gt;CBI&lt;/abbr&gt; yesterday, the PM announced that “it’s our ambition to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Highways Agency has looked hard at how to speed up the decision making process and the time it takes to have roads ready for use by motorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1km of managed motorway (using the hard shoulder as extra lanes and variable speed limits) can be built every 2 weeks, instead of every 4. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected more complex, traditional capacity improvements on non motorway routes, such as the A160/A180 Immingham improvements, will be delivered up to 25% quicker/a quarter more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to faster delivery means this government will bring forward £75 million of investment forward into this spending review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There are four schemes in the programme where this new approach to road upgrades will be piloted, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A160/A180 Immingham dualling scheme - improving access to the port of Immingham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 rather than during 2016. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £159 million (minimum) to £223 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is located on 13.4 miles of the M3 Motorway between Junction 12 of the M25 (M3 J2) to the A327 (M3 J4a) in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide more reliable journeys from London and Heathrow to Solent ports – important for both leisure and business commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn is expected to start 2013/14 instead of 2014/15 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £140 million (minimum) to £201 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is located on a 9.6 mile stretch of the M6 between junctions 10a and 13, to the north west of Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support the economic development in and around the M6 by increasing business efficiency and improving reliability for business travellers, freight and logistics operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will add extra capacity on the M1 near Sheffield, between junctions 28 and J31 (18.9 miles), which is the primary strategic link between Nottingham and Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity improvement will support the economic development in the 7th and 8th largest urban areas in the United Kingdom by increasing business efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Immingham A160 and A180 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme is expected to start in summer 2015 instead of during 2016 and complete by autumn 2016 instead of during 2018 - this is subject to the successful completion of statutory processes, and the construction budget being agreed (for the next spending review period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an original 5 and a half year programme, our ambition is to cut 18 months off the completion date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £89 million (minimum) to £132 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to improve the A160/A180 by upgrading it to a dual carriageway and improve access to the port of Immingham. The A160 is approximately three miles long and has sections of both single carriageway and dual carriageway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the A160 carries around 13,000 vehicles per day, including approximately 5,700 heavy goods vehicles (44%) with road users experiencing severe congestion at times, particularly along the single carriageway sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Road schemes can be delivered more quickly by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undertaking concurrent planning, design and construction preparation activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking more work off-site and bringing to site as pre-fabricated/pre-assembled units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving toward a 24 hour operation with more people on site working on multiple phases at once &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15629</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/caa-board-members-reappointed"/>
    <title>CAA board members reappointed</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin has reappointed 2 members of the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) board for second terms in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Gray and Michael Medlicott joined the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; as non-executive Members in November 2009 and February 2010 respectively. David Gray has particular expertise in economic regulation including a period at Ofgem, where he was responsible for gas and electricity price control reviews. Michael Medlicott has many years’ experience in the transport and tourism sectors, including senior roles in the airline and airport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will serve for second terms of 3 years each at their existing salaries of £22,000 per annum for a time commitment of 1 day per week, with additional remuneration for chairing committees and participation in appeals hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A successful, safe and efficient aviation sector is vital to the UK’s success on the global stage. These reappointments recognise the contributions that both individuals have made to ensuring the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; remains an effective, reforming regulator in what has been a challenging period for the aviation sector. I wish them well as they continue in these important roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Authority is responsible for the regulation of civil aviation in the United Kingdom and is the government’s principal advisor on aviation matters. It has specific responsibility for aviation safety, consumer protection, airspace policy and the economic regulation of the industry. It is based mainly in London and Gatwick and has approximately 950 employees. The great majority of the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s funding comes from the charges it imposes on the industry, rather than the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both members were originally appointed following an open competition regulated by the Office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments. The appointments were made on merit and political activity plays no part in the selection process. They have both declared that they have undertaken no relevant political activity during the past 5 years and that they hold no other current public appointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15068</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/driver-and-vehicle-licensing-agency-13-november-2012"/>
    <title>Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency 13 November 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has recently run a competition to procure a front office counter service provider for its face to face motoring services from next April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will award Post Office Ltd® a contract to build on the existing counter operation to provide a wider range of services and better accessibility for motorists. The contract will run for 7 years with an option to extend for up to another 3 years. This contract will allow the Post Office to fully develop better services with the requirements of customers at the heart. Under the contract Post Office Ltd® will offer &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; services at over 4,700 outlets for road tax and vehicle transactions, 750 of which will also cater for driver licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new contract provides value for money for the taxpayer resulting in savings of between £13 million and £15 million a year. The contract also gives scope for the Post Office to provide front office counter services for other government departments, to increase efficiencies across government and provide better value for the tax payer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16470</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/campaign-to-protect-rural-england-annual-lecture-transport-and-the-countryside"/>
    <title>Campaign to Protect Rural England - Annual Lecture - Transport and the Countryside</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great pleasure to be here with you in this extraordinary museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A place that shows us how transport built London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the world’s first underground trains in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the Routemaster bus in the 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the cablecars and Boris bikes of today.
Transport is what makes London tick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s easy to see why people sometimes think transport only matters to big cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I know – and you know – they’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="derbyshire-dales"&gt;Derbyshire Dales&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, because I represent the Derbyshire Dales in Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I’m the first Secretary of State for Transport with a really rural constituency since John MacGregor in the early 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m afraid you are going to hear quite a lot about it today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derbyshire Dales is not just the most beautiful part of the Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the back garden for half the cities in England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birmingham, Manchester, Sheffield, Derby and Nottingham - all just a short trip away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They put huge pressure on our rural transport system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But transport doesn’t just matter for visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a necessary part of country life, too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The further you are from towns, services, jobs and friends, the more important transport becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why rural Britain needs good transport just as much as urban Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at a map of stagecoach routes for Derbyshire in the eighteenth century and you’ll also be looking at a map of bus and car routes today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s another thing that’s just as evident in rural life today as it was in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take my local branch line from Derby which ends at Matlock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 1968, this was a busy mainline from Derby to Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that year, Barbara Castle made the mistake of closing the route between Matlock and Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we regret that closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a century ago, when it was first built, people protested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Headstone Viaduct was built through Monsal Dale, John Ruskin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The valley is gone! Now every fool in Buxton can be in Bakewell in half an hour. And every fool at Bakewell in Buxton.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, as now, you’ll always find people ready to question whether we need more capacity, or better links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the truth is, we did then. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has happened in the intervening years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fundamental requirements of our economy are exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need better transport to connect people with the workplace and goods with the marketplace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not enough to close our eyes to the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, Ruskin was wrong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beautiful Monsal Dale not only survived the construction of the line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was enhanced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viaduct is now a listed structure and the old railway has become the Monsal Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s so popular even I have cycled on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s just the sort of thing I’d like to see more of. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you accept that we need good transport to live our lives and expand our economy then two questions come to mind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you provide it so that rural people can benefit too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how can you make sure the beauty of Britain doesn’t suffer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t easy questions to answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that there are a couple of ways to look at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either you try to freeze progress, put up with what you have got already…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and condemn rural Britain to a nasty mix of stagnation and congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can be confident, see transport as a good thing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and do what it takes to make sure that transport helps the countryside, not harms it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cars-and-community-transport"&gt;Cars and community transport&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that takes me directly to cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people, cars are rural transport – and dare I say it, that includes many &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; members too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not apologetic about supporting drivers, rural garages, rural roads. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And rural Post Offices, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With today’s good news that the &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s new £450 million, seven-year contract will stay with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know that running a vehicle has become more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly in rural regions where people have fewer options and tend to do higher mileages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just the cost of rural driving that matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cars have a growing impact on the countryside too. Rural traffic is rising fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s affecting the tranquillity of the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I want people to be free to drive…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…I also want to protect what they come to the countryside to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means ideas like the “quiet lanes” we have in Derbyshire…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and it means making sure there are good alternatives to driving too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of rural people and visitors don’t have access to a car, or don’t want to drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have got to help rural bus services, and support alternatives like community transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re keeping the Concessionary Travel Scheme which allows older and disabled people to travel for free on local bus services after the morning peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a new approach to subsidising buses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re putting £600 million into the Local Sustainable Transport Fund. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve also increased funding to boost community transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community rail, in particular, has been a great success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rural branch lines – the lucky ones that survived Dr Beeching – have shown outstanding growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the St Ives Bay line, just over four miles long…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…to the 88-mile route along the Cumbrian Coast…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…. and my local line through Duffield to Matlock, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-signs"&gt;Road signs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So transport plays a fundamental role in the rural economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s something else I want to talk about today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How the countryside looks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many country roads carry a reminder of how insensitive planners can be to aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugly and unnecessary signs clutter up the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signs seem to sprout like weeds, without any apparent consideration of what’s already there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often what we’re left with is not just a blot on the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s confusing and potentially dangerous too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are those ‘temporary’ signs saying “New Road Layout Ahead” that are left to rot for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or near me in Derbyshire there’s an ugly big sign by a beautiful medieval church that just says: “No Footpath”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s on a small country lane. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there isn’t a path. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need a huge sign to tell us that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m determined to do more to sort this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a traffic signs review in 2011, and we’ve relaxed rules that used to insist on two signs by the road side when one would do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re working on revised Traffic Signs Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined effect of these changes will be to give authorities and designers much greater freedom to simplify and use fewer signs at country junctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to make sure that they use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my message today to highways engineers is: if in doubt, don’t do it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save your money for something that really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-safety"&gt;Road safety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something, for instance, like road safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, around two-thirds of fatal traffic accidents happened on rural roads. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re looking at ways to give councils a greater say over speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, creating 40 &lt;abbr title="miles per hour"&gt;mph&lt;/abbr&gt; zones in national parks or areas of outstanding natural beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; for responding to the consultation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ll issue guidance by the end of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hs2-and-the-countryside"&gt;HS2 and the countryside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve spoken about some of the immediate challenges facing rural transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also my job to prepare our country for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next 30 years, for instance, passenger demand for rail is set to double…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…while vehicle traffic will rise rapidly too, especially outside cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a country, we are travelling more and more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet many of our roads and railways are already overcrowded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a railway system conceived in the 19th century straining to support a 21st century economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I want to get cracking on High Speed Two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just to get faster journeys. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to free up space on the rest of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get freight onto rail, and trucks off our roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know it’s controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people here today will oppose the line strongly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I respect that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also want you to hear the case for going ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My argument today is that we need good transport and more of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question is how we provide it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think HS2 is the right way to do it for our countryside as well as our cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High speed, high capacity stations in city centres will encourage new housing and business on brownfield sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means fewer big new roads through the countryside and less urban and suburban sprawl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s vision for 2026 makes clear, the sustainable cities will preserve and energise rural England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put it another way: a better Manchester and a better Sheffield can also mean a better Peak District.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our objective with HS2 is not just to make sure it isn’t just the south-east that benefits from growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also to deliver it in the most responsible way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, what’s good for the economy and what’s good for the environment have been seen as polar opposites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s assumed you have to make a straight choice between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also an attitude that favours division over dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I reject that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I welcome the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt;’s constructive – but challenging – input to High Speed Two. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start, we have sought to consider the views of rural communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their evidence was carefully weighed up after one of the largest public consultations ever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a result, we announced alterations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than half the route between London and Birmingham will now be in tunnels or cuttings…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including a longer, continuous tunnel under the Chilterns from Little Missenden to the M25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 13 miles through the Chilterns area of outstanding natural beauty, less than 2 miles will be at or above the surface. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means less impact on ancient woodlands and heritage sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is still a lot to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So HS2 Ltd will keep working hard with you and others as the scheme develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we consult on the best route for HS2 north of Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="design-and-compensation"&gt;Design and compensation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly keen to ensure high quality design for structures along the route &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ones that are sensitive to the character of their setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I can confirm today that I have asked HS2 Ltd to look at establishing an independent HS2 Design Panel – just as we did for the Olympic Park and Crossrail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made up of experts in architecture, engineering, town planning and transport, it will work with local people, councils, environmental and countryside groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than that, those whose homes are affected will be recompensed over and above what the law requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those living closest to HS2 will be able to sell their home to the government – whether they are required for construction or not – at any time after the route is safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will receive its full value. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will also receive a 10% additional home loss compensation up to a value of £47,000.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’ll be reimbursed for reasonable moving costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rural areas we will establish a voluntary purchase zone which will go out as far as 120 million from the railway line, within which homeowners will have the option to sell their properties to the government for the full value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there will be a long term hardship scheme to help those further afield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also believe that the impacts of HS2 will be considerably less than many fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we expect property values to recover over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example of HS1 in Kent suggests this is more than a hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fear-of-change"&gt;Fear of change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings me back to something I mentioned at the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear of change in the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows what would have happened to our green belt over the decades had the countryside lobby not protested and made its voice heard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have moved on from the days when Swampy was headline news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve learnt from massive advances in green technologies and construction techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve learnt that it’s neither environmentally or morally acceptable to build new infrastructure without careful consideration of the surrounding landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve learnt that offering either an effective transport system or a clean and green environment is a false choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those road protests were against schemes designed more than a quarter of century ago, by a generation of road builders whose careers began when the very first motorways were being created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we’re investing around £2 billion in a programme of fourteen managed motorways schemes across the country &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than hugely expensive widening programmes, we’re making the most of our existing infrastructure through use of the hard shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with HS2, projects have to fit into the existing landscape, matching the topography, where necessary using false cuttings and planting new trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use quieter tarmac, and noise barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We build boxes for bats and tunnels for badgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we sometimes build entire substitute habitats for protected species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of how much progress has been made is the A3 Hindhead Improvement scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opened last year, this project not only protects the surrounding countryside – but makes it much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tunnel was built to bypass the village of Hindhead and remove a notorious traffic bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the scheme also reunited two commons previously split by the road, creating the largest area of lowland heath in Southern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers also planted 200,000 trees and shrubs to provide a magnificent haven for wildlife and lovers of our countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that isn’t a one-off. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when we improved the A30 in Cornwall we bought land with Natural England to create new moorland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a 670 hectare wetland nature reserve – the largest of its kind in Europe – is being created on Wallasea Island…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…from almost 5 million tonnes of earth excavated from beneath London as part of the Crossrail project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schemes like these are not isolated examples of good practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re a pointer to the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; – and the broader environmental lobby – can certainly take credit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know you’ve got an even bigger role to play in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not proposing to emulate China, which over the next three years will build 70 new airports…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and ten massive new transport routes crisscrossing one of the largest countries in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do have to modernise key parts of our transport system if the UK is going to be able to compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what HS2 will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new transport network for the 21st century that will meet rigorous environmental standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So. A final thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just oppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider what’s needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And work with us to get it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14868</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-headquarters-for-rail-accident-investigators"/>
    <title>New headquarters for rail accident investigators</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today officially opened the new premises of the Rail Accident Investigation Branch (&lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt;), the independent investigators working to make the railways safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southern team of the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is now based at Cullen House, near Aldershot, Hampshire, on the same site as the Air Accident Investigation Branch (AAIB). Previously the team were based in Woking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail is significantly safer now than in previous years because the industry has ensured safety issues have been identified and safeguards introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is helping to ensure that our safety record continues to improve by carrying out thorough investigations when something goes wrong and identifying what needs to change to prevent it happening again. The new premises at Cullen House give the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; an excellent base from which to carry out their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Inspector Carolyn Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cullen House provides a continuing presence for the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; in the south east which together with its northern team in Derby provides a balanced coverage for the geographical territory we investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To date since becoming operational in 2005 we have completed 196 investigations The industry has implemented 95% of recommendations from those investigations, bringing about real changes that improve safety for passengers and those who work on the railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cullen House, Patrick McLoughlin met &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and unveiled a plaque marking the official opening of the new premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new premises are named after Lord Cullen who in 2000 led a public enquiry into the Ladbroke Grove rail crash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sole purpose of &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; investigations is to prevent future accidents and incidents and improve railway safety - the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; does not establish blame, liability or carry out prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For media enquiries, please call 020 7944 3248&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3248  &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14406</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T11:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T11:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/airports-commission-membership"/>
    <title>Airports Commission membership</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A panel of 6 experts will take forward vital work to examine how the UK’s status as a leading global aviation hub can be maintained, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State announced on 7 September that the Airports Commission would be chaired by Sir Howard Davies. Today the terms of reference for the Commission were announced alongside the appointment of the group of leading academics and aviation experts who will help Sir Howard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aviation is vital to the UK economy and we need to have a long term aviation policy which meets the challenges of the future. Sir Howard and his team will now take forward this vitally important work for the Government and bring a much-needed fresh perspective to the debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Howard Davies, Airports Commission chairman, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am announcing a team with the range of skills and experience required to drive forward the important work the Commission is undertaking.
&amp;gt; With open minds, we will take time to explore the evidence, consider the options and aim to develop a lasting solution to the nation’s aviation needs.   Our ambition is to do a thorough piece of work that will ensure aviation continues to support this country’s economic, social and environmental ambitions.
The experience of recent years shows we need a robust evidence base which has the support of a broad consensus of opinion. We aim to put the next government into a position in which rapid and implementable decisions can be soundly made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commissioners who will support Sir Howard Davies are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir John Armitt CBE, the former Chairman of the Olympic Delivery Authority and former Chief Executive of Network Rail. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Ricky Burdett, Professor of Urban Studies at the London School of Economics and director of the LSE Cities research centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vivienne Cox, the former CEO and Executive Vice President of BP Alternative Energy and a former member of the BP Executive Management Team. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Dame Julia King, Vice Chancellor of Aston University and a member of the Committee on Climate Change, with a background in the aerospace industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Muirhead CBE, the former CEO of the Manchester Airport Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commissions-terms-of-reference"&gt;Commission’s terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s terms of reference are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission will examine the scale and timing of any requirement for additional capacity to maintain the UK’s position as Europe’s most important aviation hub; and it will identify and evaluate how any need for additional capacity should be met in the short, medium and long term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should maintain a UK-wide perspective, taking appropriate account of the national, regional and local implications of any proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should engage openly with interested parties and members of the public, providing opportunities to submit evidence and proposals and to set out views relevant to its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should seek to engage with a range of stakeholders, including with local and devolved government as well as the Opposition, to build consensus in support of its approach and recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission should report no later than the end of 2013 on: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;its assessment of the evidence on the nature, scale and timing of the steps needed to maintain the UK’s global hub status; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for immediate actions to improve the use of existing runway capacity in the next five years – consistent with credible long term options;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assessments and recommendations in the Commission’s interim report should be underpinned by a detailed review of the evidence in relation to the current position in the UK with regard to aviation demand and connectivity, forecasts for how these are likely to develop, and the expected future pattern of the UK’s requirements for international and domestic connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its assessments of potential immediate actions should take into account their economic, social and environmental costs and benefits, and their operational deliverability. It should also be informed by an initial high-level assessment of the credible long-term options which merit further detailed development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission should report no later than summer 2015 on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;its assessment of the options for meeting the UK’s international connectivity needs, including their economic, social and environmental impact;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for the optimum approach to meeting any needs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for ensuring that the need is met as expeditiously as practicable within the required timescale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission should base the recommendations in its final report on a detailed consideration of the case for each of the credible options. This should include the development or examination of detailed business cases and environmental assessments for each option, as well as consideration of their operational, commercial and technical viability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of its final report in summer 2015, it should also provide materials, based on this detailed analysis, which will support the Government in preparing a National Policy Statement to accelerate the resolution of any future planning applications for major airports infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-short-biography-of-each-of-the-members"&gt;A short biography of each of the members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir John Armitt CBE: John Armitt was appointed Chairman of the Olympic delivery Authority on 1 September 2007. He joined John Laing as a civil engineer in 1966, and was Chairman of Laings International and Civil Engineering Divisions from 1987-1993. In 1993 he was appointed Chief Executive of Union Railways, the company responsible for developing the high speed Channel Tunnel Rail Link. In 1997 he was appointed Chief Executive of Costain and in 2001 Chief Executive of Railtrack plc, a year later he was made Chief Executive of Network Rail a position he held until 2007. John is currently Chairman of City and Guilds (appointed on 25 October 2012), Deputy Chairman of Berkeley Group plc and a non-executive Director of Transport for London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Ricky Burdett: Ricky Burdett is Professor of Urban Studies at the London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE) and director of LSE Cities and the Urban Age programme. His research interests focus on the interactions between the physical and social worlds in the contemporary city and how urbanisation affects social and environmental sustainability. He was Chief Adviser on Architecture and Urbanism for the London 2012 Olympics and architectural adviser to the Mayor of London from 2001 to 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vivienne Cox: Vivienne Cox is a non-executive Director of Rio Tinto plc, BG Group, Pearson plc and Vallourec SA.  She is the Lead Independent Director on the Board of DFiD.  She is also on the Board of INSEAD and an adjunct Professor at Imperial College. In 2009 she retired from BP after spending 28 years in the company.  Her last full time role was as the Executive Vice President of the Gas, Power and Renewables business. She was a member of the Executive Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Dame Julia King: After 16 years as an academic researcher and lecturer at Cambridge and Nottingham universities, Julia King held a number of senior business and engineering posts at Rolls-Royce plc, in both the aerospace and marine businesses, between 1994 and 2002.   Following two years as Chief Executive of the Institute of Physics, Julia returned to academia as Principal of the Engineering Faculty at Imperial College, London, before becoming Vice-Chancellor of Aston University in December 2006. Julia advises Government on a range of education and technology issues and is a member of the Committee on Climate Change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Muirhead CBE: Geoff Muirhead is a qualified civil and structural engineer who spent 22 years in the construction industry prior to joining Manchester Airport in 1988 as their Director of Development and Planning leading the delivery of Terminal 2. Geoff was subsequently promoted to Business Development Director in 1992 and to Chief Executive in 1994, during which time he led the business through the acquisition of Humberside, East Midlands and Bournemouth Airports. Geoff was also responsible for leading the planning and delivery of Manchester Airport’s second runway – the only full length runway constructed in the UK since the Second World War. Geoff retired from the role in October 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15597</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/membership-and-terms-of-reference-of-the-airports-commission"/>
    <title>Membership and terms of reference of the Airports Commission</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 7 September, the government announced its intention to create an independent commission, chaired by Sir Howard Davies, to identify and recommend to government options for maintaining the UK’s status as a global aviation hub. Following discussions with Sir Howard, the government is now in a position to announce the full membership and terms of reference for this body, which will be named the Airports Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In selecting members of the Airports Commission, the government worked with Sir Howard to identify individuals with a range of skills, backgrounds and experience. The commission also intends to appoint a panel of expert advisors, to enhance its capability to address issues that fall outside of the direct experience of the commissioners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Sir Howard Davies, the full membership of the commission includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir John Armitt, the former Chairman of the Olympic Delivery Authority and former Chief Executive of Network Rail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professor Ricky Burdett, Professor of Urban Studies at the London School of Economics and director of the LSE Cities research centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vivienne Cox, the former CEO and Executive Vice President of BP Alternative Energy and a former member of the BP Executive Management Team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professor Dame Julia King, Vice Chancellor of Aston University and a member of the Committee on Climate Change, with a background in the aerospace industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geoff Muirhead CBE, the former CEO of the Manchester Airport Group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The commission’s terms of reference will be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission will examine the scale and timing of any requirement for additional capacity to maintain the UK’s position as Europe’s most important aviation hub; and it will identify and evaluate how any need for additional capacity should be met in the short, medium and long term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should maintain a UK-wide perspective, taking appropriate account of the national, regional and local implications of any proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should engage openly with interested parties and members of the public, providing opportunities to submit evidence and proposals and to set out views relevant to its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should seek to engage with a range of stakeholders, including with local and devolved government as well as the opposition, to build consensus in support of its approach and recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission should report no later than the end of 2013 on: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;its assessment of the evidence on the nature, scale and timing of the steps needed to maintain the UK’s global hub status; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for immediate actions to improve the use of existing runway capacity in the next 5 years – consistent with credible long term options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assessments and recommendations in the commission’s interim report should be underpinned by a detailed review of the evidence in relation to the current position in the UK with regard to aviation demand and connectivity, forecasts for how these are likely to develop, and the expected future pattern of the UK’s requirements for international and domestic connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its assessments of potential immediate actions should take into account their economic, social and environmental costs and benefits, and their operational deliverability. It should also be informed by an initial high-level assessment of the credible long-term options which merit further detailed development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission should report no later than summer 2015 on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;its assessment of the options for meeting the UK’s international connectivity needs, including their economic, social and environmental impact;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for the optimum approach to meeting any needs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its recommendation(s) for ensuring that the need is met as expeditiously as practicable within the required timescale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The commission should base the recommendations in its final report on a detailed consideration of the case for each of the credible options. This should include the development or examination of detailed business cases and environmental assessments for each option, as well as consideration of their operational, commercial and technical viability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of its final report in summer 2015, it should also provide materials, based on this detailed analysis, which will support the government in preparing a National Policy Statement to accelerate the resolution of any future planning applications for major airports infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-document"&gt;Related document&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/airports-commission-membership"&gt;Airports Commission membership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13196</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/statement-on-west-coast-main-line-and-franchising"/>
    <title>Statement on West Coast Main Line and franchising</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, with permission I would like to make a statement on the progress we are making to put right arrangements for the West Coast Main Line and rail franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will update the House on the Laidlaw Inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I will explain how we will ensure not only continuity of service on the West Coast line after December 9 but an enhanced service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 3 October I announced the cancellation of the competition to run the Inter-City West Coast franchise…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;because of the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the procurement process run by the Department for Transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it clear at the time, and do so again today, that this was a very regrettable decision prompted by mistakes that should never have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also launched two independent inquiries, one of which has reported its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/laidlaw-inquiry-interim-report"&gt;interim findings&lt;/a&gt; to me and which I am today delivering to the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the first inquiry, led by Centrica chief executive Sam Laidlaw, to look into what happened and why…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with the aim of establishing the lessons to be learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also asked the second review, led by Eurostar chairman Richard Brown, to focus on any lessons to be learned for the future rail franchising programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I promised that both would conduct their investigations thoroughly, independently and urgently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, given the public interest in this matter the Laidlaw Inquiry was asked to deliver an interim report to me by the 26 October, and a final report by the end of November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to the Inquiry for meeting this first deadline, and working tirelessly to meet the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stress that today’s findings are precisely that - an interim report. There is more work to do. These findings are clearly a first stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Mr Laidlaw explains, they set out what went wrong, and from that basis he will now carry out further investigations into why this happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start, my aim in dealing with this situation has been to be open, and come forward with information for the House at the earliest opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in that spirit that I make this statement today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interests of complete transparency, I am publishing this interim report, with its provisional findings, and placing copies of it in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be blunt, these initial findings make uncomfortable reading but they provide a necessary and welcome further step in sorting this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will need to see the full and finished report before it can comment in detail on any conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial because of the independent nature of the Laidlaw Inquiry and the need for the government not to pre-judge its eventual findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is clear that the Inquiry has identified a number of issues which confirm that my decision to cancel the franchise competition was necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a lack of transparency in the bidding process…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the fact that published guidance was not complied with when bids were being processed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;inconsistencies in the treatment of bidders…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and confirmation of technical flaws in the model used to calculate the amount of risk capital bidders were asked to provide to guard against the risk of default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Laidlaw Inquiry also mentions factors “that appear to have caused or contributed to the issues raised”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will look at these with interest and care, although once again we will need to see the final report before we can comment further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I would like to update the House on the progress we are making to ensure continuity of service on the West Coast Main Line once the current franchise expires on the 9 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said previously, we will ensure that passengers continue to be served by the same trains, with the same frontline staff, the same services, using the same tickets…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and, I am pleased to say, enhanced future timetables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is making good progress in its discussions with Virgin on how they will operate the line for a short period of up to 14 months while a competition is run for an interim agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are discussing their proposals for improved services over this period and an enhanced compensation scheme for delayed passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dealing with this, my department has been frank and open about its mistakes and is absolutely determined to find out exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we will keep delivering for passengers and continue with the unprecedented levels of investment in trains, stations and railway lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combined with our decision to limit train fare rises to an average of inflation plus one per cent, instead of RPI+3, for the next 3 years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this demonstrates this government’s total commitment to Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13588</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-coast-main-line-laidlaw-inquiry-interim-findings"/>
    <title>West Coast Main Line: Laidlaw Inquiry interim findings</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the Department for Transport’s handling of the franchise competition to run the West Coast Main Line has submitted an initial findings report to Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interests of transparency, Mr McLoughlin has today published that report, alongside a covering letter, and this afternoon delivered an update to Parliament about this report and wider progress on ensuring continuity of service on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw, the senior business figure and DfT non-executive director leading this independent review, has asked the DfT to release the following statement on behalf of his inquiry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the limited time available this is necessarily only a preliminary report. What is clear however is that in seeking to run a complex and novel franchising competition process, an accumulation of significant errors, described in the report, resulted in a flawed process.
&amp;gt; These errors appear to have been caused by factors including inadequate planning and preparation, a complex organisational structure and a weak governance and quality assurance framework. The full causes and the lessons to be learnt will be addressed in the final report of my independent Inquiry to be published at the end of November.
&amp;gt; Firm judgments should not be made based upon what are provisional findings or wider conclusions drawn at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Laidlaw Inquiry interim findings and Mr Laidlaw’s covering letter to the Transport Secretary are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/laidlaw-inquiry-interim-report"&gt;DfT website.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Transport Secretary’s oral statement to the House of Commons of this afternoon is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/mcloughlin-20121029a/"&gt;DfT website.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Laidlaw Inquiry team: 020 7922 2402.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15275</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/high-speed-two-assistance-and-compensation-for-home-owners-and-occupiers-on-the-london-west-midlands-route"/>
    <title>High Speed Two - assistance and compensation for home owners and occupiers on the London - West Midlands route</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In January the government announced that we would proceed with plans to build a high speed rail network linking London with Birmingham, Leeds and Manchester. High Speed Two (HS2) will have a transformative effect on Britain, bringing cities closer together and providing the new transport capacity we need to meet the challenges of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to drive forward with this vital national project. In doing so we need to provide support for those facing the disruption that the plans for the railway are causing, while also protecting the interests of tax-payers who will ultimately pay for compensation. We have been clear throughout that we are committed to providing appropriate compensation and assistance for those affected by the building of HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statutory system of compensation already provides fair compensation for the vast majority of infrastructure schemes. However, given the particular circumstances of HS2, in this case I believe it is right to go above and beyond what is required by law. Today I am launching a generous proposed compensation and support package for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals set out today all those living closest to the route of HS2, in the so-called ‘safeguarded area’, will be able to choose to sell their home to the government - whether it is required for construction or not - at any time after the HS2 route is safeguarded, which is currently expected to happen in Spring 2013. Those choosing to sell their homes will receive its full un-blighted value (that is, what the property would have been worth had there been no plans for HS2), a home loss payment of 10% of the value of the property (up to a maximum of £47,000) and be reimbursed for reasonable moving costs, including stamp duty on the purchase of a new property of equivalent value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rural areas we will establish a ‘voluntary purchase zone’, extending out from the boundary of the safeguarded area up to 120m either side of the line, within which homeowners will have the option to sell their homes to the government at their full unblighted value at any time after the HS2 route is safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those living beyond both the safeguarded area and voluntary purchase zone but who need to move house during the development of HS2 and find they are unable to sell their property, there will also be a ‘long term hardship scheme’ under which the government will buy the homes of successful applicants at their full unblighted value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, under the new ‘sale and rent’ back scheme, homeowners whose property will need to be acquired will have the option to sell their homes to the government early and stay in them as tenants until the properties are required for the railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the owners of properties above tunnels may also be concerned about the potential impact of HS2 and therefore we are bringing in a series of measures designed to provide confidence in these properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will work with local authorities, housing associations and affected tenants to agree a joint strategy to replace any social housing which is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must stress that we have already written directly to all those whose homes we currently expect to need to buy in order to build and operate HS2 on the London - West Midlands route. The wide-ranging proposals set out today reflect the significant nature of the concern that currently exists in the property markets near the HS2 line of route, they are not a reflection of what the government believes the long term impacts of HS2 will be. We fully expect that the impacts of HS2 will be considerably less than feared and that property prices will recover over time. However, we recognise that the current property markets near the HS2 line of route may not reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2 will be the backbone of a new transport system for the 21st century, offering the new railway capacity that our country will need to compete and grow. However, we fully recognise that the line will have unwelcome impacts on people living close to the route and I believe that this package of compensation demonstrates the strength of the government’s commitment to provide the right compensation and assistance to those affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the property consultation published today, we are also publishing a consultation on safeguarding directions for HS2. This will set out the proposed area of land considered necessary to protect the line of route from conflicting developments, that is to say planning permission being granted for developments on land that will be required for the construction or operation of HS2. This will also set the ‘safeguarded area’ within which compensation measures will apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both consultations will close on 31 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-property-compensation-london-west-midlands"&gt;High Speed Two: property and compensation for London - West Midlands video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121025a/"&gt;Government unveils generous HS2 compensation package&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;*[HS2] High Speed 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
