<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-environment-food-and-rural-affairs</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/secretary-of-state-for-environment-food-and-rural-affairs.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-11T23:06:16+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/1735</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T23:06:16+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-11T23:06:16+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/250-million-fund-to-herald-return-of-better-weekly-collections"/>
    <title>£250 million fund to herald return of better weekly collections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A fund of up to quarter of a billion pounds to help support councils to deliver better, more environmentally friendly weekly bin collections for residents is now open, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September last year the Government announced its intention to introduce a new weekly collection support scheme for councils that retain or reinstate weekly residual waste and recycling services. The new scheme will deliver benefits to the environment and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe that waste services have become too complex, leaving residents anxious about following the rules and possible penalties. They think councils should focus on 3 things: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better weekly collections&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better contracts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is additional funding to local government, financed from savings made to the Department for Communities and Local Government’s central budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new fund will help support reward schemes (for example, those like Windsor and Maidenhead’s Recyclebank scheme and Birmingham’s Nectar points scheme), where families are rewarded for recycling, delivering on a Coalition Agreement pledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also explicitly intends to tackle ‘bin blight’ and the proliferation of bins, by supporting new technology where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund will promote innovation, better procurement and joint working across local authorities. It intends to support a range of local initiatives to increase recycling and deliver weekly collections. It will seek to prioritise bids which support comprehensive weekly rubbish and recycling collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rubbish collections are the most visible service that people get for their £120 a month Council Tax bill. But barmy bin rules have made putting out your rubbish more complicated than solving a Rubik’s cube. The public are fed up of all the bin do’s and bin don’ts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People just want a comprehensive service in return for their Council Tax, which is why this Government is working with councils to increase the frequency and quality of rubbish and recycling collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caroline Spelman, Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to help people to go green by making it easier for them to do the right thing. This scheme will encourage councils to provide the services we believe residents really want, without sacrificing the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew Farrow, the Environmental Services Association’s Director of Policy, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Waste management companies want to collect and manage waste in ways which are both user friendly for the householder and benefit the environment. So we welcome the way in which the fund prioritises environmental criteria and services that meet the needs of householders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also support the encouragement given to local authorities to think innovatively and to work with the private sector. We look forward to working with their local authority customers to help them make best use of the opportunities the fund provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
