<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/senior-minister-of-state</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/senior-minister-of-state.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Senior Minister of State</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14740</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eid-message-from-faith-minister-baroness-warsi"/>
    <title>Eid message from Faith Minister Baroness Warsi</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Foreign Office Minister and Minister for Faith and Communities, Baroness Warsi, has sent her best wishes to those celebrating Eid ul Adha this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to send my best wishes to Muslims in Britain and across the world who are celebrating the conclusion of the Hajj pilgrimage and the holy festival of Eid ul Adha.
&amp;gt; “Eid gives us a special opportunity to reflect on the links between our faiths, since Islam, Christianity and Judaism share a founding father, Abraham, whose selfless sacrifice we mark during this festival.
&amp;gt; “It is also an occasion for us to give to others and consider those less fortunate than ourselves. Foremost on my mind this Eid will be those suffering in Syria; the people across the world who are persecuted for following their faith; and brave, young Malala Yousafzai, Pakistan’s inspirational campaigner.
&amp;gt; “Eid is a time for peace and happiness and I look forward to celebrating it both at home with my family and in Downing Street.
&amp;gt; “Eid Mubarak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14703</id>
    <published>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-faith-and-communities-meets-with-archbishop-of-westminster"/>
    <title>Minister for Faith and Communities meets with Archbishop of Westminster</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi yesterday met with the Archbishop of Westminster, the Most Reverend Vincent Nichols, for the first time since she became Minister for Faith and Communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Archbishop, who is President of the Bishops’ Conference of England and Wales discussed with Baroness Warsi the central role faith plays within communities and in building a cohesive society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi is also Senior Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, where her responsibilities include human rights and religious freedom, and is holding a series of meetings with faith leaders during her first few weeks in post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ever since I have been in Government I have been making the case for faith and I am delighted to be taking on a dual role in which I can focus on continuing to do so. I will be working closely with religious leaders, and communities of different faiths and none, and I was delighted to see Archbishop Nichols to discuss the opportunities and challenges ahead - particularly on issues of faith and religious freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Archbishop of Westminster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the government’s renewed emphasis on the vital role faith plays in community life and in building a cohesive society. Baroness Warsi has demonstrated strong leadership in promoting good relationships with Religions both domestically and internationally. I look forward to working with her to build on this important work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They discussed building upon the achievements of February’s visit to the Vatican, during which Baroness Warsi led the UK’s largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See alongside the Archbishop of Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631573779371/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 4 September 2012 The Rt Hon Baroness Warsi PC was appointed Senior Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and Minister for Faith and Communities at the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
