<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/senior-minister-of-state</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/senior-minister-of-state.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Senior Minister of State</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48336</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi, will mark International Human Rights Day by hosting the London launch of the United Kingdom’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is standing for election to the UN’s Human Rights Council next year to ensure that the UK is at the forefront of efforts to drive forward the human rights agenda. Calling to account countries that commit the most serious and widespread violations against their own citizens, ensuring the Human Rights Council is at the forefront of the international response to international crises and fighting hard against those who seek to weaken or undermine international human rights mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s campaign will focus on four key human rights priorities: protecting those most vulnerable in societies, working towards human dignity for all, responding proactively to evolving challenges, and keeping human rights at the heart of multilateral priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“International Human Rights Day is a stark reminder that there are still too many around the world who are not able to enjoy fundamental freedoms. It is important to focus on those who are fighting for their rights and the rights of their loved ones, those who are prepared to put themselves in danger for a better future for others and to remember those who have left a legacy to inspire us all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must keep those voices at the heart of our efforts to promote and protect human rights around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am proud of the UK’s commitment to protecting those most vulnerable in our societies. Across the world, too many people are discriminated against on the basis of their race, religion, sexual orientation, disability, or gender-identity. The reasons for discrimination are many, and we must tackle the causes and the acts themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking later today at the reception for the London launch of the UK’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council, Baroness Warsi will say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear. A Council that is not bogged down by politics, but where the rights of the individual are paramount. A body where states are held accountable for their actions against their citizens, where peers review peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe strongly that we have an important role to play, which is why the UK is standing for election. We bring experience, commitment and ambition. We want to play a part in strengthening the Council, as we have since its inception in 2006. In that time the Human Rights Council has grown in status and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through the Council, we have called to account countries who commit the most heinous and systematic violations against their citizens. We have actively supported the Human Rights Council’s international response to the crisis in Syria. We have also run thematic initiatives including through a resolution which used the Olympics to promote awareness on human rights through sport and established a commitment with the future hosts of the Games to do the same.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=842675682" title="Follow @FCOHumanRights "&gt;Follow @FCOHumanRights &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter "&gt;Twitter &lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook "&gt;Facebook &lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+ "&gt;Google+ &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35584</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wilton-park-conference-on-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations"/>
    <title>Wilton Park conference on preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the Foreign Secretary will attend and deliver the keynote speech on the final afternoon of a Wilton Park Conference on “Preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his announcement in May that Britain would set up a specialist team of experts that could be deployed to conflict areas to support UN missions and local civil society to investigate allegations of sexual violence, gather evidence and help build the capabilities of other nations, the Foreign Secretary will today announce that the specialist team now consists of 70 people and is ready to deploy overseas in the near future.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those recruited for the team include police, lawyers, psychologists, doctors, forensic experts, gender-based violence experts and experts in the care and protection of survivors and witnesses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will also announce additional funding of more than £¼ million over a three year period to the UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations and the Department of Field Support to develop policies, guidance and training for use by UN peacekeepers as first responders to incidents of sexual violence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the conference, the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that a critical mass of public opinion has now begun to build up against the use of rape as a weapon of war in many countries. My experience as a politician leads me to believe that this is the moment to mobilise global public opinion and to rally the efforts of nations, in the same way that we have mustered the will to ban the use of landmines and cluster munitions, and are on the verge of securing an international Arms Trade Treaty. Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation. It is a cause whose time has come.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants at today’s conference are drawn from over 25 countries and include ministers and senior practitioners and experts.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference which includes sessions on the international normative framework; addressing impunity; early warning indicators; strengthening justice mechanisms; and communications, was also attended by the following:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mrs Zainab Bangura, UN Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margot Wallstrom, the former Special Representative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Madeleine Rees, Secretary-General of the Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serge Brammertz, a prosecutor from the ICTY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be working with Foreign Secretary Hague again on the United Kingdom’s initiative on Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict. In many conflicts, sexual violence is used as a tactic of war, intended to hurt not only a single individual, but their family, their community, their ethnic group. Today this  has almost become a rule rather than an exception, and we all must work together to combat the impunity and ensure justice for the victims.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35574</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-hails-malala-s-inspirational-activism"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi hails Malala’s inspirational activism</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Highlighting the UK’s role in supporting Pakistan in improving education access, Baroness Warsi reinforced the UK’s support for more support for education for girls in school.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through her inspirational activism Malala has bravely highlighted the need for education to be accessible to all children in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Education is the single most important factor that can transform Pakistan’s future. Currently, half the adult population can’t read or write, and more than twelve million children are not in school. The problem for women is more acute; nearly two thirds of women in Pakistan can’t read or write. Girls’ education is a priority for the UK Government’s programme in Pakistan.  It is important to ensure that girls have an education in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK is supporting up to four million children in school and is training up to 45,000 teachers. All of our programmes a have an emphasis on women and girls and aim to tackle the low levels of girls’ enrolment in primary schools.  Additionally in the part of Pakistan that Malala is from, Khyber Pukhtunkhwa, we support the provincial governments to increase girls’ attendance at school, through the use of stipends and vouchers, the provision of free textbooks, and improving school facilities to make sure they are safe and appropriate for girls.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35560</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-congratulates-burmese-president-on-reforms"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary congratulates Burmese President on reforms</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a meeting with Burmese President Thein Sein on 6 November in the margins of the Asia-Europe Summit in Laos, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was pleased to meet President Thein Sein to follow up our meeting in Burma in January. I congratulated him on the progress Burma has made so far on vital political and economic reforms. I highlighted UK concern at the violence in Rakhine state and the humanitarian situation there, and welcomed what the Government had done to allow our ambassador access to the area. The UK is urging all political parties in Burma to do what they can to end the violence and address the issue of Rohingya citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I encouraged continued cooperation between the UK and Burmese governments to promote responsible trade with and investment in Burma. And I expressed my hope that the President would be able to visit the UK early next year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14740</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eid-message-from-faith-minister-baroness-warsi"/>
    <title>Eid message from Faith Minister Baroness Warsi</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Foreign Office Minister and Minister for Faith and Communities, Baroness Warsi, has sent her best wishes to those celebrating Eid ul Adha this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to send my best wishes to Muslims in Britain and across the world who are celebrating the conclusion of the Hajj pilgrimage and the holy festival of Eid ul Adha.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Eid gives us a special opportunity to reflect on the links between our faiths, since Islam, Christianity and Judaism share a founding father, Abraham, whose selfless sacrifice we mark during this festival.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is also an occasion for us to give to others and consider those less fortunate than ourselves. Foremost on my mind this Eid will be those suffering in Syria; the people across the world who are persecuted for following their faith; and brave, young Malala Yousafzai, Pakistan’s inspirational campaigner.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Eid is a time for peace and happiness and I look forward to celebrating it both at home with my family and in Downing Street.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Eid Mubarak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35485</id>
    <published>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/world-day-against-the-death-penalty-2012"/>
    <title>World Day Against the Death Penalty 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It is the longstanding policy of the UK Government to oppose the death penalty in all circumstances as a matter of principle. There is no evidence of its deterrent value and any miscarriage of justice is irreversible and irreparable.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since the Government launched its Strategy for Abolition of the Death Penalty in October 2011, we have continued to take action against our three goals, and taken all appropriate opportunities to raise the issue with our priority countries. Our work has also included support for civil society projects in different parts of the world, which are helping gather support for worldwide abolition.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There have been several positive developments over the last year: I was particularly pleased to note the ratification by Benin, in July this year, of the Second Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, which aims at the abolition of the death penalty. I was also pleased to see the State of Connecticut repealing the death penalty in April this year, becoming the 17th US state to do so.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the same time I am concerned about the sharp increase in executions during the past twelve months in some of those countries which still apply and implement the death penalty. Later this year, the United Nations General Assembly will for the fourth time debate a resolution which advocates a worldwide moratorium on the use of the death penalty. I would particularly encourage those states which have a long-standing moratorium in force, to consider joining the growing world trend against the death penalty and to vote in favour of the Resolution.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35652</id>
    <published>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nuclear-terrorism-remains-one-of-the-greatest-threats-to-our-global-peace-and-security"/>
    <title>“Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security”</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful attack, no matter where in the world it came, would be catastrophic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism (ICSANT) is one of the cornerstones of the international effort to counter this threat.  It provides a legal basis for international cooperation in the investigation, prosecution and extradition of those involved in the preparation or execution of terrorist acts involving radioactive material or a nuclear device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK ratified the Convention in September 2009, demonstrating our commitment to maintaining the highest possible international standards in countering the threat from nuclear terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the crucial element of co-operation that I want like to focus on today.  International cooperation to combat nuclear terrorism has been tremendous.  The recent Nuclear Security Summit in Seoul once again catalysed the political will and technical expertise necessary to fulfil commitments made in Washington, two years earlier.  53 countries made over 100 new commitments to improving global nuclear security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, at least 14 countries have ratified the convention since the 2010 Summit and a further 15 announced plans to do so in the 2012 Summit to ratify this convention and/ or the Amendment to the Convention on the Physical Protection on Nuclear Material, another essential element of the global nuclear security architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise there are some challenges in promoting universal adherence to the UN Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A  perception among some States that they may not have to implement effective controls on nuclear and other radioactive material if they do not possess nuclear weapons or hold only limited quantities of materials for peaceful purposes; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A  possible lack of awareness within governments of this convention  and its requirements and obligations; and a limited capacity and resource to draft, implement or enforce the necessary laws and regulations;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But against these challenges I would like to offer a brief reminder of the significant advantages of adhering to this convention.  States that adhere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are better able to investigate, prosecute and punish any acts relating to nuclear or radiological terrorism by non-State actors;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will enhance their national security and public health and safety;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demonstrate to others, including potential investors that they are a safe and responsible location for activities involving nuclear and other radioactive material;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;comply effectively with their international reporting requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Co-operation, assistance and advice are available to all States who want or need it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highlight Security Council Resolution 1540 in this context, in particular the [1540] Committee of Experts, whose role is to monitor and assist states in adopting and effecting appropriate laws and activity to better prevent proliferation in or through their territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will also be focussing on the effective implementation of Resolution 1540 as a priority for our 2013 Chair of the Global Partnership against the Spread of Weapons and Materials of Mass Destruction.  Looking ahead, the 2014 Nuclear Security Summit, complemented by efforts such as the Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism, will continue to provide the momentum, political will, co-ordination and expertise, necessary to strengthen nuclear security still further.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encourage countries, where appropriate to do so, to engage with international nuclear security initiatives and Conventions, and for those that have yet to ratify the UN International Convention on the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism, to do so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27969</id>
    <published>2012-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-pays-tribute-to-outgoing-governor-of-helmand-province"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister pays tribute to outgoing Governor of Helmand Province</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This follows the announcement by the Afghan Government of changes in a number of Governors as part of a wider reshuffle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking today Baroness Warsi said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, particularly through the UK-led Provincial Reconstruction Team, has worked closely with Governor Mangal over the past four and a half years. Under his leadership there has been remarkable progress in Helmand. Governance has expanded into previously un-governed areas and its quality continues to improve. People can now access health centres, schools and other services that previously they could not. There is now greater freedom of movement, which has led to increasing trade and access to services. This has all made a huge difference to the lives of the people of Helmand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is of course much more work to be done. We remain committed to supporting further progress in the province as well as in Afghanistan more broadly, and we look forward to working with the new Governor of Helmand, General Mohammad Naeem Baluch, to achieve this.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14703</id>
    <published>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-faith-and-communities-meets-with-archbishop-of-westminster"/>
    <title>Minister for Faith and Communities meets with Archbishop of Westminster</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi yesterday met with the Archbishop of Westminster, the Most Reverend Vincent Nichols, for the first time since she became Minister for Faith and Communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Archbishop, who is President of the Bishops’ Conference of England and Wales discussed with Baroness Warsi the central role faith plays within communities and in building a cohesive society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi is also Senior Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, where her responsibilities include human rights and religious freedom, and is holding a series of meetings with faith leaders during her first few weeks in post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ever since I have been in Government I have been making the case for faith and I am delighted to be taking on a dual role in which I can focus on continuing to do so. I will be working closely with religious leaders, and communities of different faiths and none, and I was delighted to see Archbishop Nichols to discuss the opportunities and challenges ahead - particularly on issues of faith and religious freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Archbishop of Westminster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the government’s renewed emphasis on the vital role faith plays in community life and in building a cohesive society. Baroness Warsi has demonstrated strong leadership in promoting good relationships with Religions both domestically and internationally. I look forward to working with her to build on this important work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They discussed building upon the achievements of February’s visit to the Vatican, during which Baroness Warsi led the UK’s largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See alongside the Archbishop of Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631573779371/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 4 September 2012 The Rt Hon Baroness Warsi PC was appointed Senior Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and Minister for Faith and Communities at the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27949</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-welcomes-vote-in-european-parliament-on-trade-package-for-pakistan"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi welcomes vote in European Parliament on trade package for Pakistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the result of the vote in the European Parliament to implement a trade package for Pakistan. The package will provide substantial benefits for Pakistan’s economy, bringing growth and jobs to people still recovering from the devastating 2010 floods. The UK has been a tireless advocate of improved EU market access for Pakistan, and has worked closely with the European Commission and international partners since 2010 to press for today’s decision. The vote is a further sign of a deeper and more effective EU-Pakistan relationship.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
