<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/ministers/solicitor-general</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/solicitor-general.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Solicitor General</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12394</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/keynote-speech-to-the-world-bribery-and-corruption-compliance-forum"/>
    <title>Keynote speech to the World Bribery and Corruption Compliance Forum </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Thank you Mr Chairman. It gives me great pleasure to open this conference on this hugely important topic. It is also a great honour to speak alongside so many distinguished speakers to so many eminent delegates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The importance of tackling bribery and corruption, at all levels, cannot be overstated. Corruption is corrosive. Like rust, rot and other decay, corruption, once set in, begins to spread, and which, like rust, rot and other decay, must be stopped before lasting and irreversible damage is done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many have written with great power and eloquence of the degenerative effects of corruption at all levels, from the impact of corruption on the person engaging in the corruption, to the wider effects on society as a whole. Some considerable time ago, the writer of Ecclesiastes spoke perceptively of the impact of corruption on the corrupter. The author wrote, ‘Extortion turns a wise person into a fool, and a bribe corrupts the heart’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“More recently, Kofi Annan spoke of the impact of corruption on society as a whole. In his now well-known foreword to the 2004 United Nations Convention against Corruption, the then Secretary General described corruption as, ‘an insidious plague that has a wide range of corrosive effects on society’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the 20 years I spent at the Bar, then later during my time as the minister responsible for benefit fraud prosecutions in the Department for Work and Pensions, more recently working with the Council of Europe’s Group of States against Corruption, as a member of the House of Commons Committee which debated what is now the Bribery Act, and finally, from the unique perspective I now have as Solicitor General, I have seen, and attest to the impact of bribery and corruption - and the importance of ensuring that we share the collective responsibility to ensure that the rot of corruption does not set in, or if it does, it is adequately dealt with and those responsible punished appropriately. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am sure that many here this morning will share those observations. Of course, when I recite these truths, I am saying nothing new. Indeed, the very fact that you are attending this conference underlines the commitment you and your respective organisations clearly have to tackling bribery and corruption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reason, however, I chose to open my remarks this morning by underlining these truths is because it is important to remind ourselves of this context. Bribery and corruption are borderless crimes, neither respecting boundaries nor constrained by geography. For that reason, those seeking to eradicate it or avoid it - and I take that all of us here fall into at least one of those categories - should not be constrained by boundaries or geography either. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Put another way, international crimes require international enforcement strategies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The international community has taken its stand; I have already mentioned the UN Convention; of course, the &lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt; Convention on Combating Bribery of Foreign Public Officials 1997 requires State parties to the Convention to apply penalties which are “effective, proportionate and dissuasive”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So it is absolutely right that a conference such as this - the World Bribery and Corruption Compliance Forum - has senior representation from across the globe. I am delighted that Lanny Breuer, Assistant US Attorney General, will be joining us to speak this afternoon, and I hope to be able to return for his address later today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, it is easy to extol the virtues of tackling bribery and corruption; it is altogether less easy to do so effectively. Many of us will approach the issue of enforcement with different perspectives. For some, the issue will be carrying out the enforcement. For others, the issue will be avoiding the need for enforcement by advising clients on steps to be taken to prevent bribery and corruption from setting in in the first place.For others still, the task will be to defend those accused of engaging in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whatever perspective we bring to the issue of enforcement, it is clear that all involved could benefit from a tool to reduce the complexity and uncertainty of current enforcement powers, and to deal with cases more quickly and in a way which better meets the interests of justice and commands public confidence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why I am delighted to confirm that that the government is introducing Deferred Prosecution Agreements, a new tool to tackle economic crime, through amendments to the Crime and Courts Bill, to be tabled today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Earlier this year, the government consulted on the possibility of introducing &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt;. The response we received to that consultation, which closed in August, was overwhelmingly positive, with 86% of those who responded supporting the proposals. No doubt many organisations represented today are among those who responded. Today the government’s response to the consultation will be published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In broad terms, under a Deferred Prosecution Agreement, organisations will publicly face-up to their wrongdoing and resolve to make things right by agreeing to comply with stringent conditions. Conditions may include the payment of substantial penalties, making reparation to victims, undertaking reform to prevent such conduct occurring again, and submitting to regular reviews and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The process will be scrutinised by an independent judge and the threat of prosecution will remain hanging over an organisation should it fail to comply fully with the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Initially, &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will be available to the Serious Fraud Office and the Crown Prosecution Service, although there will be provision for the Secretary of State to designate additional prosecutors to use the powers. In the case of the DPP and the Director of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;, the power to enter a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; may only be exercised by the relevant director acting personally, as an additional safeguard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am confident that &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will be an invaluable tool for the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;. In cases where a company accepts wrongdoing, and is committed to put things right, a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; will mean that it must comply with stringent conditions to compensate and ensure there are no repeat incidents, whilst avoiding a lengthy and expensive prosecution with the prolonged uncertainty it brings for the victims, blameless employees and others dependent on the fortunes of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When formulating our proposals, we looked to other jurisdictions that deploy similar tools. The United States, for example, has been using Deferred Prosecution Agreements and Non Prosecution Agreements for some 20 years, and a considerable body of jurisprudence and commentary has built up surrounding their use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But as anyone advising on cross-jurisdictional issues will tell you, it is not possible simply to transplant one element of a very different legal regime into our domestic legal and constitutional framework, even if we do have a shared common law heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is much to learn from the US model however; it offers a good example of the effective use of the voluntary agreement approach. We decided to build on the US model by formulating proposals which ensure a greater level of judicial involvement, from an earlier stage, as well as greater levels of transparency in order to command the confidence of the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So a key feature of the new regime will be early, pre-charge judicial oversight. This oversight, from a Crown Court Judge, will ensure that &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; provide both certainty, as required by the prosecutor and the party to the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;; and transparency, as required by the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In recognition of the unique nature of economic crime, &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will only be available for certain economic crimes committed by organisations. They will not be available in relation to offending by individuals, and they will not be available in relation to the criminal law generally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I must stress that this is not because economic crime is in any sense not as serious as other crime - on the contrary. As the Lord Chief Justice said in the 2010 case of Dougall, which involved a plea agreement by the Serious Fraud Office,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For all the respectable and reputable fronts that many fraudsters and corrupt businessmen may present, they are criminals. What is sometimes described as white collar crime or commercial crime taking the form of fraud and corruption in particular is crime. And it is not victimless: sometimes identified individuals are victims, and at others, unnamed, unknown individuals in the entire community are victims, and sometimes the community itself is the victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There will always be cases where the public interest requires a full criminal prosecution - &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will allow prosecutors to focus more of their resources on those cases, and in effect will allow them to prioritise prosecutions. It is highly unlikely, for example, that &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will ever be appropriate for use with companies which have been used primarily as a vehicle for criminal activity: such companies, and the individuals responsible for the criminal activity, can expect to face criminal investigation and prosecution in the normal way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Returning to the new regime, much of the procedure leading to a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; will be similar to the way in which investigations are carried out at present. A criminal investigation will take place, prompted either through self-reporting by the company, or through some other means. The prosecutor will be involved from an early stage, as is the case with most serious and complex investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the prosecutor considers in principle that the offending revealed by the investigation is suitable for a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the views of the organisation in question will be sought. In reality, there is likely to be a dialogue between the prosecutor and organisation from an early stage; we expect there to be an increase self-reporting and &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will rely to an extent on cooperation from organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the certainty provided by the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; process, combined with the possibility to draw a line under past criminal conduct, without the organisation having to face full criminal proceedings will be a strong incentive to engage with the regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The early judicial oversight of which I spoke a moment ago will take place in the following way. The prosecutor, having agreed with the organisation an outline of agreed basic facts, will present those agreed facts to a Crown Court judge, in private, along with details of the alleged wrong doing, a draft indictment, the agreed or contemplated conditions to be attached to the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and an outline of any areas which remain under discussion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It would be at this stage that the prosecutor could inform the judge of any international dimensions to the case, which we hope will be particularly useful in cases where the organisation faces enforcement proceedings in a number of jurisdictions, where both the prosecutor and the organisation need to ensure that whatever is happening domestically correlates with whatever is happening internationally. As such, &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will be a swifter, more nimble way to conduct enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well as speed, we hope that &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide the parties with a degree of certainty that simply cannot be offered by regular criminal proceedings. The judge will, at the early preliminary hearing, be able to give an initial indication as to whether what is proposed by the prosecutor and the organisation is likely to be endorsed by the Court when presented for final approval. Or in the words of the clauses being tabled today, whether, ‘entering into a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;… is in the interests of justice and the proposed terms of the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; are fair, reasonable and proportionate…’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, the judge may decide not to make such a declaration; the court may consider that in the particular circumstances of the case, a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; is not appropriate, or that certain steps must be taken, or further lines of enquiry pursued, before the matter could be considered further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“While this early hearing of necessity cannot be open to the public, details of what took place will be published by the prosecutor in the event that a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; agreed and approved by the court. 92% of those who responded to the consultation considered that it was appropriate for this early hearing - or hearings, for there may be more than one if the parties so require - to take place in private. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are a host of reasons why such hearings should be in private, not least the Article 6 rights of the company to a fair trail in the event that a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; is not concluded and a full prosecution takes place. The same could be said in relation to prosecutions against individuals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And there are, of course, market considerations too - while a commercial organisation may be willing to sustain whatever the impact of an announcement that a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; has been agreed, quite understandably such organisations will be less willing to engage with the process if the early stages of their otherwise confidential discussions with the prosecutor are simply used to fuel speculation and adverse coverage in the media, with all that that will entail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Following the preliminary hearing or hearings, the prosecutor and the party to the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; will return to the Crown Court for the final disposal hearing, in which the prosecutor must apply to the Court for a declaration in similar terms to the initial indication given during the preliminary hearing, but with the crucial distinction that once the declaration is made, the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; comes into force. We propose that the test to be applied by the Crown Court at that stage will be the same as that applied at the preliminary hearing, that is to say,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;entering into a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;… is likely to be appropriate in all the circumstances of the case and in the interests of justice, and the proposed terms of the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; are fair, reasonable and proportionate…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Allow me to say a few words about the terms of the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The regime is intended to be flexible, so neither the legislation nor the statutory &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; Code for Prosecutors that the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; will be required to produce, will be prescriptive as to what the terms should be. Rather there will be a non-exhaustive list of indicative criteria in the legislation that will include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a financial penalty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disgorgement of profits or benefit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reparation to victims&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an obligation to use all reasonable efforts to make available to the prosecutor all relevant non-privileged information or material, such as the factual findings of an internal investigation and to interviews given as part of an internal investigation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an obligation to put in place anti-corruption or anti-fraud policies, procedures or training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the more serious cases, an independent monitor could be appointed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Taking into account the relevant facts, previous discussions and the views of the prosecutor, the financial penalty and other terms would be a matter for the judge to approve. Once the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; and its terms are approved, a voluntary bill of indictment will be preferred and immediately and automatically suspended - suspended, that is, pending compliance by the organisation with the terms of the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Variation of a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; or termination of a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; will not be in the gift of the prosecutor; an application will have to be made to the court for the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; to be varied or terminated as the case may be and the court will apply the same test as when the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; was made, whether “entering into a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;… is likely to be appropriate in all the circumstances of the case and in the interests of justice, and the proposed terms of the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; are fair, reasonable and proportionate…”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; remains in force until its expiry date, the prosecutor will give notice to the court that the proceedings are not to continue, and it will not be possible to bring fresh criminal proceedings against the organisation for the same offence in the future. That restriction is subject to the proviso that if the organisation provided inaccurate, misleading or incomplete information, and knew or ought to have known that that is the case, the bar on fresh proceedings being brought for the same offence no longer applies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, I am aware that a regime such is this will not be without criticism. It has been said that &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; are themselves a fraud; companies that commit criminal acts do so by their human actors; should not the priority be prosecuting such people? Well let me say this: I agree with the conclusion of that statement. The priority should be prosecuting people: where there is evidence, and it is in the public interest (which, given my comments at the outset, it undoubtedly will be), there will be criminal prosecutions of such individuals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope the regime will encourage companies, perhaps as part of a cleansing process, to resolve past misconduct. In doing so, evidence to support full criminal investigations against individuals is likely to be revealed to prosecutors to support prosecutions of those individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It has been said that the rationale of &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; is logically inconsistent; if a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; is available for economic crime, why not for other crimes? Why not offer &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; to gang criminals or drug dealers, for example? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, that criticism fails to address the fact that the &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; regime does not detract one bit from the primacy that should be afforded to prosecuting individuals of serious economic crime. Indeed, by freeing up resources currently consumed by prosecutors engaged in lengthy criminal litigation against companies, more prosecutions of more individuals will be a realistic goal. &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPAs&lt;/abbr&gt; are only available in relation to organisations for the simple reason that you can’t send an organisation to prison, only a financial penalty is available. The same simply cannot be said of the other crimes cited in this criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am aware of cases which are and have been before the courts involving both the company and the directors; in cases where the directors are convicted of criminal charges, there is a very strong argument for using the tailored, bespoke solution offered by a &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreement"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; to deal with enforcement matters against the company in such situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So as I conclude, although I noted at the outset that when I underlined the pernicious effects of bribery and corruption I was saying nothing new, I hope certainly that in the second half of my speech I not only said something new, but that I have kindled your interest in what will be a very effective, and in time vital, enforcement tool. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The programme for the rest of the conference looks fascinating, and I trust that it will be interesting and productive.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12397</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-role-of-the-law-officers"/>
    <title>The role of the Law Officers </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It is a pleasure to be speaking here tonight at Kent Law School. May I first thank Professor John Fitzpatrick for inviting me to do so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Before discussing the role of the Law Officers, can I start by saying how delighted I was that Kent Law Clinic was joint winner of ‘Best New Student Pro Bono Activity’ in this year’s Attorney General’s pro bono awards for its Public Access to Land Project. Both the Attorney General and I are strong supporters of Pro Bono by students and the professions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Kent Law School is a pioneer of student pro bono and a regular winner of the Attorney General’s pro-bono awards. I am delighted this culture of innovation continues and that your Law Clinic is central to the work of the Law School.
There is no better way for young lawyers to engage with the profession. I was involved in the early student committees of the Free Representation Unit, or &lt;abbr title="Free Representation Unit"&gt;FRU&lt;/abbr&gt;, in the 70s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have fond memories of my involvement with &lt;abbr title="Free Representation Unit"&gt;FRU&lt;/abbr&gt; - and not just because it was through &lt;abbr title="Free Representation Unit"&gt;FRU&lt;/abbr&gt; I met my future wife. It was an opportunity to use my legal knowledge and skills to help clients who would otherwise not have been represented. It provided valuable experience for me as an advocate, as a lawyer and for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The constitution is full of old and strange jobs and titles, like that of Attorney General, that of Advocate General for Scotland, and my own, Solicitor General. To most people, even those with knowledge of government and the criminal justice system, the role of a Law Officer is something of a mystery. Indeed to most parliamentarians nowadays and even to some ministers the Law Officers are something of a mystery (perhaps even to some Law Officers). So I am delighted to have an opportunity to offer an insight to the offices we hold and the work we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, a bit of history. The Office of Attorney General is an ancient one, though much changed over the years. Legal historians argue about who the first Attorney General was, with some suggesting the role may go back as far as the appointment of Lawrence del Brok in around 1247, whose function was to sue ‘the King’s affairs of his pleas before him’. While the first person to be called ‘Attorney General’ was John Herbert who was appointed as the King’s principal law officer in 1461.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Writing of my own position, Solicitor General, JP Collier published in 1819 a book impertinently called ‘Criticisms of the Bar’. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If, as was shown when speaking of the Attorney General… of all the officers in the gift of the Crown that of the Attorney General is least to be coveted, that of the Solicitor General is perhaps most to be desired. In point of rank the latter is but just inferior to the former and the Solicitor General is relieved from a great part of the weight of public odium which his co-adjudicator is under the necessity of sustaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over the 200 years since that was written much has changed, though I daresay some recent Attorneys must have felt they have had their share of public odium. The Solicitor General is still essentially the Attorney’s deputy, but since the Law Officers Act of 1997 any function of the Attorney General may be exercised by the Solicitor General, and indeed we share much of the work that falls to be done in the name of the Attorney General. So when I talk of the functions of the Attorney General I mean my own too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Office of Solicitor General itself has a long history. One of my 17th-century predecessors, Sir Francis Bacon, described the role of Solicitor General as ‘one of the painfulest places in the Kingdom’. Yet history also records that Sir Francis made great endeavours to secure appointment to the office of Solicitor General, before later serving as a Law Officer for 10 years, so he must have either liked the pain, or at least thought it worth enduring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some Law Officers have had more reason than others to complain, of course: the most extreme example perhaps was John Cooke, the first Solicitor General of Oliver Cromwell’s English Commonwealth, who in 1649 led for the prosecution in the trial of King of Charles I, only to be rewarded with execution for high treason after the Restoration: the only Law Officer to be hanged, drawn and quartered. So far, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But what history has bequeathed us is an Attorney General who is a Minister of the Crown and Chief Legal Adviser to the Government, who also exercises a number of functions in the public interest. He superintends the Directors of Public Prosecutions and the Serious Fraud Office, as well as overseeing the Government Legal Service. While the role has evolved much, it has some consistencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Law Officers’ are members of the government. The Attorney General is a politician, but he is not just a party political minister: he is also a senior lawyer. He is not a member of Cabinet, though he will attend when his advice is required or when matters within his responsibility come up for consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Indeed, the core function of the Attorney General was and is to make sure that government, that ministers, act lawfully, in accordance with the rule of law. Some of you may find it harder to accept that a politician and member of the government is best placed to ensure that the government acts lawfully in what it does. Some argue that the current office involves too many conflicts of interest. That subject is too wide and deep for me to explore today. The current arrangement, as awkward as it may look on paper, like so many of the eccentricities in our constitution, works because it puts at the heart of government an independent lawyer who is trusted by those he advises because he is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In my approach to the role I have been much influenced by a former Solicitor and Attorney General, Peter Rawlinson. Peter Rawlinson was appointed Solicitor General by Harold Macmillan in 1962. He describes in his autobiography, ‘A Price Too High’, how he was invited to become Solicitor General. The Prime Minister honoured him with a ‘scholarly review of mediaeval office holders’, a review which flowed into the 16th and 17th centuries, embraced approvingly the career of Samuel Pepys, and concluded with the admonition that the loyalties of a Law Officer must be first to the Crown, second to Parliament, and only thirdly, almost incidentally, to the administration. I am struck by the order of loyalties that Macmillan described and regard it as one which I, now a Law Officer, will honour for so long as I hold this office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third UK Law Officer as I mentioned is the Advocate General for Scotland, Lord Wallace of Tankerness &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Jim Wallace is responsible for advising the UK government on matters of Scots law. He also plays a key role in relation to legislative procedure, as I shall explain later. And I should for the sake of completeness mention the similar role played in relation to the devolved administrations by the Lord Advocate in Scotland, the Attorney General for Northern Ireland and the Counsel General in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the role of the Attorney General as the government’s Chief Legal Adviser was neatly summed up by the former Attorney General, Lord Mayhew of Twysden, who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Attorney General has a duty to ensure that the Queen’s ministers who act in her name, or purport to act in her name, do act lawfully because it is his duty to help to secure the rule of law, the principle requirement of which is that the government itself acts lawfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is reinforced by the Ministerial Code issued by the Prime Minister, which requires that the Law Officers must be consulted in good time before the government is committed to critical decisions involving legal considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Departments will often come to us for advice on how policy can be achieved in a lawful or proper way. By longstanding convention, also recorded in the Ministerial Code, neither the fact that the Law Officers have advised or not, nor the advice that the Law Officers have given, may be disclosed. I cannot give you examples of how, in the few weeks I have been in office, I have, if at all, discharged that role. But let me say that I have not been short of things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As law students you can well understand why it is vital that a lawyer must keep his clients’ confidences and I would like to say here a bit about our role of Law Officers but also lawyers more generally. Lawyers and the practice of law are all too often cast in a negative light. There is a perception that lawyers can be a hindrance. That we are the men and women who just say no. We are too cautious, too risk adverse, that we stop things getting done. That is not my experience. Both as a lawyer in private practice and now a Law Officer in government, my experience is that lawyers are enablers. A lawyer does not say no lightly. A lawyer says no with intent, so much of our time is not spent just saying ‘No’, but ‘Have you thought about doing it this way?’ which is what all good lawyers should do for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A good lawyer understands how things get done. The law provides the framework for this. The concept of the rule of law is contested, and now is not the time for an exposition on it. But the law provides the predictability, the stability, the reliability needed to make decisions and enable investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The best lawyers are creative; they help their clients walk the line, to achieve what they want, the property bought, the contract agreed, the deal done, all within the law. Many lawyers explore that line; the best learn to walk it. In government as lawyers we do that too, but sometimes we go further, we redraw the line. We draft the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Law Officers have a particular role in the legislative process, considering each Bill as it approaches introduction into Parliament. The Attorney General or the Advocate General are both members of the Cabinet’s Committee which considers the readiness of government Bills and authorises their introduction. In that role the Law Officers assist the government in its search for a lawful and proper way to achieve its policy objectives. Ultimately we may block a Bill if we have unresolved concerns about its legality or propriety. But our ability to ensure that Bills are legal and proper comes from our relationship with the government lawyers who work on Bills and with the Parliamentary Counsel who draft them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are in fact 3 sets of lawyers involved in preparation of a bill. Firstly there are the departmental lawyers who advise their clients on the legal issues with a policy and consider whether legislation is necessary to achieve it. Where possible the government tries to avoid legislating and adding to the regulatory burden on citizens. Secondly there are the Parliamentary Counsel who draft the actual text of the bill, and finally us the Law Officers who I will say more of later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The role of Parliamentary Counsel as the drafters of legislation is central to this process. Parliamentary Counsel advises departmental lawyers on matters of legal propriety and technical drafting, and refer matters of concern to the Law Officers if they cannot be resolved. They also act as guardians of the rule of law and they can and often do look to the Law Officers for support. This is a useful way of ensuring that the main legal players in the Bill process cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Liaising with Parliamentary Counsel and departmental lawyers serve as a useful guide to the Law Officers to new trends in drafting and legislation, for the drafting of legislation is not immune from innovation, if not fashion. The art of both drafting and legislating is not set in stone, and we do not pursue these activities in a vacuum though you might be forgiven for thinking that; governments legislate to meet or influence events, which throw up their own and new challenges that have to be met. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“However, we need to ensure that the legislative responses to those challenges are appropriate and that the government’s understandable desire to act does not lead to ill considered or inept legislation. Parliamentary Counsel and government lawyers enable us to check this and to offer a guiding hand if we feel that an excitable and excited minister has been touched by a bout of unlawful enthusiasm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The volume of legislation over the last 13 years has been relentless; whether it has been of any public benefit is a matter for you to consider. The Law Officers believe if we are to legislate, we should make good law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Law Officers have a more direct role in relation to 3 aspects of proposed legislation, namely compatibility with the European Convention on Human Rights. When a Bill is introduced the minister in charge in each House is required by section 19 of the Human Rights Act 1998 to make a statement that in his or her view the Bill’s provisions are compatible with the Convention rights. Alternatively, if the Minister is not able to provide that personal assurance, then he or she must state that nevertheless the government wishes the House to proceed with the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Law Officers will consider the Human Rights memorandum that departments are required to produce for the Cabinet Committee. The memorandum sets out an analysis of the convention rights that are engaged by a Bill and an assessment of any interferences and justification for them in &lt;abbr title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;ECHR&lt;/abbr&gt; terms. The department demonstrates its human rights law reasoning with a view to satisfying the Law Officers, and so the committee and the government, that the route by which the department has come to the conclusion that the Bill is compatible is correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Even if I were able to explain to you what matters we had been consulted on, Bills we had commented on or what advice we had given, that would only give a tiny picture of all the legal work that goes in to the development of government policy and legislation. Many of the tricky legal issues that arise in developing policy never come to the Law Officers. The day-to-day guardians of legality and propriety in all that the government does are the lawyers of the Government Legal Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Law Officers enjoy a special relationship with the lawyers working in to government departments. This ensures the professional independence and standards of the advice given by them and their staff. Government lawyers may consult the Law Officers if they have doubts about the propriety of any proposed course of conduct in a matter for which they have responsibility. And from this position of strength, government lawyers can advise ministers on the legality of what they want to do, and they work up solutions when what is proposed collides with the constraints imposed by, say, the Human Rights Act, or by our obligations under EU law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you have found what I have said so far interesting you may want to consider becoming a lawyer in the Government Legal Service, they recruit trainees and pupils every year. It is not all though about liaising with the government. The Law Officers also have particular independent public interest functions. Indeed, as is rather grandly set out on the office’s website, the Attorney General historically has the role of ‘the guardian of the rule of law and the public interest’. I will outline just a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This includes a pivotal part in the contempt of court jurisdiction ensuring that trials are not undermined by any media reporting. There is no desire to censor but solely a need to ensure that a case is decided solely on the evidence that is presented in court. The right to free speech and open justice is of fundamental importance but at times can clash with another fundamental right - that to a fair trial. The contempt of court jurisdiction and the Law Officers’ role in overseeing it is borne of an attempt to strike the right balance between these 2 rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This role is increasing determined by statute, in particular the 1981 Contempt of Court Act. The starting point is, as I believe it should be, in favour of open justice protecting fair and accurate contemporaneous, written in good faith, legal reporting. However the publication of material which creates a substantial risk that the course of justice will be seriously impeded or prejudiced will fall foul of the legislation. In that situation it is for the Attorney General to decide whether to instigate proceedings against the publisher. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There have been high profile examples of this in the past. For instance, you may remember the reporting of the Joanna Yates murder investigation in Bristol last year. There was widespread speculation and copy, across much of the media, about Mr Jefferies who was arrested on suspicion of murder but was later found to be wholly innocent. The coverage in the Sun and Daily Mail newspapers was found to amount to contempt of court as it would have created a substantial risk of serious prejudice if he had been brought to trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Court looked closely at the issue of impediment to the course of Justice. They decided Mr Jefferies had been vilified to such an extent that potential witnesses might have been discouraged or deterred from coming forward and providing information helpful to Mr Jefferies. The Court ruled the articles published by both papers would have been extremely damaging to Mr Jefferies and his defence. They constituted contempt under the strict liability rule. As the Attorney noted at the time, ‘This prosecution is a reminder to the press that the Contempt of Court Act applies from the time of arrest.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Caution, not to say common sense, must come into play when the media are reporting on a case involving an arrested suspect - a suspect who may never be charged. Thankfully prosecutions of this sort are comparatively rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Another power the Attorney exercises as guardian of the public interest is that to refer to the Court of Appeal sentences which he considers to be unduly lenient. This is often thought of as a right for the prosecution, or indeed an interested party, to ‘appeal’ against a lenient sentence, but that is to misunderstand the nature of the power. The power is to provide an exceptional remedy to address those sentences which fall so far below the range of sentences it was reasonable for the judge to impose that they risk damaging public confidence in the criminal justice system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The legislation only covers certain serious offences for which a sentence was passed in the Crown Court. It is subject to a strict time limit of 28 days from the day of sentence. We take advice, as you may expect, including from experienced independent counsel, but the decision is ours personally. It is only where we feel that a sentence was significantly outside the appropriate bracket that we will ask the Court of Appeal to intervene. It is then of course a matter for the Court as to whether it decides to increase the sentence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My experience over the weeks since I have been in office has been that judges do a difficult job very well. The legislation can be fiendishly complex and even with the benefit of sentencing guidelines passing sentence requires the exercise of careful judgement, taking many different and sometimes competing factors into account. It is only a tiny proportion of the sentences passed in the Crown Court which come to our attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By way of example, in 2011 the sentences passed on 263 offenders were drawn to the attention of the Attorney General. Of those 112 were referred to the Court of Appeal and the Court increased the sentence in 95 cases. Bear in mind that each year somewhere in the region of 80,000 cases are sentenced in the Crown Courts and you will see that we really are talking about a fraction of cases. It is nevertheless important that there is a route by which people are able to draw cases to our attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For my part, doing a job in government so closely associated with the law and the profession which has been such a big part of my life for the last 40 years is a reward. The life of the Law Officers, although circumscribed by limitations that many a politician would not tolerate, brings one to the very centre of power even if those at the centre do not realise it. It is not the dry and fusty world of the Dickensian lawyer’s office, still less the Office of Circumlocution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A few weeks ago I swore before the Lord Chief Justice that I would ‘truly minister the Queen’s matters and sue the Queen’s process after the course of the law and after my cunning. For any matter against the Queen where the Queen is a party I will take no wages or fee of any man. I will duly in convenient time speed such matters as any person shall have to do in the law against the Queen, as I may lawfully do, without long delay, tracting or tarrying the Party of his lawful process in that that to me belongeth, and I will be attendant to the Queen’s matters when I shall be called there to.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is the oath Peter Rawlinson took, and that is the oath that Geoffrey Howe, Patrick Mayhew and Nick Lyell took on becoming Solicitor General. As Macmillan told Peter Rawlinson my first duty is to the Crown, secondly to Parliament, and thirdly, to the administration, but if in discharging those duties I can also rebuild the now attenuated links that used to join Parliament and government to the institutions of the Law, I will have achieved something of value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Parliamentarians must understand the role and rule of law and recognise that our constitution has reserved a place for the courts. One of my jobs is to help them do that. Government must also not always stand on its rights when there are better and cheaper ways of achieving an outcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let me give you an example: you may or may not recall that a few years ago a case was brought by a prisoner who claimed that his human rights had been infringed by the prison service for keeping him in a cell where the lavatory was blocked. Rather than allowing the claim to develop, rather than defending the claim at huge public expense, would it not have been more sensible to call a plumber to unblock it? The plumber’s hourly rate of course may have been higher than that of many barristers, but the hours a good deal fewer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17661</id>
    <published>2012-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/prosecuting-human-trafficking-and-slavery-the-law-and-the-uk-response"/>
    <title>Prosecuting human trafficking and slavery: the law and the UK response</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a great pleasure to be able to speak to you today. I would like to thank Professor Neil Cooper and Dr Julia Buxton for inviting me to speak about human trafficking. It is an opportune time to debate this topic as the UK’s Anti Slavery Day was on the 18 October. You have provided me with an excellent opportunity to mark this day and I am delighted to do so at this department which has such an excellent international reputation in the area of peace studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My parliamentary constituency is North East Hertfordshire. Within it, at Wadesmill, there is a monument marking the spot where, in June 1785, Thomas Clarkson rested his horse on the way from Cambridge to London. Clarkson had just won a university prize for an essay on the topic, ‘Is it lawful to enslave the unconsenting?’ He had written about the Atlantic slave trade, and while resting his horse, Clarkson realised that ‘it was time some person should see these calamities to their end’. Clarkson then devoted his life to campaigning for the abolition of slavery. His energy and determination, and that of other ‘abolitionists’ like William Wilberforce and Olaudah Equiano, led first to the abolition of the slave trade in 1807, and then to the Slavery Abolition Act of 1833.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Important as those achievements were, the ‘unconsenting’ are still enslaved today. Human trafficking threatens the human rights of millions every year and represents a new form of slavery. Human trafficking is the second largest organised crime in the world; there are millions of victims at any given time with profits of traffickers worldwide estimated in excess of $32 billion each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the UK, those who are exploited may face years of sexual abuse, forced labour or domestic servitude. They are vulnerable women, children and men who often speak no English and are kept isolated. In many instances they never fully recover from their traumatic experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Anti-Slavery Day was introduced in 2010 through the Anti-Slavery Day Act to raise awareness of the need to eradicate all forms of slavery, human trafficking and exploitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, I will look at the nature of the problem in the UK and give an overview of the UK response to human trafficking. I will then examine the influence of international instruments, such as UN protocols, on domestic legislation. Finally I will comment on the UK criminal justice response both in terms of how prosecutions are handled, and the effectiveness of the criminal justice system in combating human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But I thought it might be helpful to start by explaining something about my role as a Law Officer and how this relates to the subject under discussion. I am deputy to the Attorney General. Together we are known as the Law Officers. The office of Attorney General covers a wide range of functions. In addition to being chief legal adviser to the Crown, and thus to government, the Attorney General is also the guardian of the public interest and a protector of charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As government ministers, we account to Parliament for the 2 largest prosecuting departments: the Crown Prosecution Service and the Serious Fraud Office. (We also have ministerial responsibility for the Treasury Solicitor’s department and Her Majesty’s Crown Prosecution Service Inspectorate.) This superintendence role involves safeguarding the independence of the prosecutors in taking prosecution decisions and, in conjunction with the directors of the prosecuting authorities, setting their strategic direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“While the lead in policy making on human trafficking lies with the Home Office, the Law Officers have a role, together with Home Office and Ministry of Justice colleagues, in formulating criminal justice policy. In particular, we want to ensure human trafficking policy works in practice, when it comes to the prosecution of offences. I am a member of the Inter Departmental Ministerial Group (&lt;abbr title="Inter Departmental Ministerial Group"&gt;IDMG&lt;/abbr&gt;) which acts as the UK rapporteur on this issue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I start with the problem in the UK, human trafficking is, by its nature, a complex and hidden crime and it is difficult to get a full picture of the numbers involved. However, the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) in 2010 undertook a study of sexual exploitation in England and Wales. The report looked at who was being trafficked into the country for ‘off-street’ prostitution, where they came from, and how they were treated. This report estimated that, of the 17,000 migrant sex workers in the off-street sector, there were at least 2,600 female adult victims of trafficking for sexual exploitation in England and Wales, with a further 9,600 considered to be vulnerable, and suspected to have experienced an element of trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“National Referral Mechanism (&lt;abbr title="National Referral Mechanism"&gt;NRM&lt;/abbr&gt;) figures give a more up-to-date picture of those victims who have reported to the police or are brought to the attention of the authorities. The &lt;abbr title="National Referral Mechanism"&gt;NRM&lt;/abbr&gt; is a framework for identifying victims of human trafficking and ensuring they receive appropriate care. A range of agencies may be involved in a trafficking case, such as the police, the UK Border Agency (&lt;abbr title="UK Border Agency"&gt;UKBA&lt;/abbr&gt;), local authorities and non-governmental organisations such as charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="National Referral Mechanism"&gt;NRM&lt;/abbr&gt; makes it easier for these agencies to co-operate, share information and facilitate access to advice, accommodation and support. In 2011, 946 potential victims of human trafficking including 234 child victims were identified in the UK by the &lt;abbr title="National Referral Mechanism"&gt;NRM&lt;/abbr&gt;. Using this data we are also able to explore where victims are trafficked from. The most prevalent source countries were Nigeria, China, Vietnam, Romania and Slovakia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most prevalent type of exploitation for adults trafficked to the UK is sexual exploitation and for children it is labour exploitation. In recent months we have also seen cases in which victims have been brought to the UK to be exploited for the purpose of benefit fraud and other types of criminal exploitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The impact of these crimes is great in terms of harm, both to victims and to society more generally. The numbers of people trafficked and the source, transit and destination countries continue to change and evolve as traffickers seek to exploit new and more profitable opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is therefore crucial that we monitor the constantly changing pattern of human trafficking to and in the UK, in order to support victims and deter and disrupt traffickers. This is why we vigorously review the latest data on trafficking at each of our inter-departmental ministerial meetings on human trafficking.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-uk-government-response"&gt;The UK government response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So, the UK government response to human trafficking is of vital importance. We have made progress. We are improving the identification of, and support for, trafficking victims. And we are working more closely with international partners to deter, disrupt and prosecute traffickers. But there is much more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government published its human trafficking strategy in July 2011 with a focus on victims, and prevention. The aims of that strategy are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, improved victim identification and care - actions have been taken to improve the awareness of front line professionals working in local authorities, health services, the UK Border Agency (&lt;abbr title="UK Border Agency"&gt;UKBA&lt;/abbr&gt;), the police, the Crown Prosecution Service, the Serious Organised Crime Agency (&lt;abbr title="Serious and Organised Crime Agency"&gt;SOCA&lt;/abbr&gt;), charities such as NSPCC and the Gangmasters Licensing Authority, so that they can better identify, support and protect victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The second aim is to act early in source countries. Increased international engagement has begun: to gain a better understanding of human trafficking patterns, to raise awareness of this crime, and to assist in strengthening law enforcement and justice systems in priority countries. The &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; has a number of prosecutors based in ‘strategic threat assessment countries’. They regularly liaise with 2 of the major source countries through the Supreme People’s Procuracy (SPP) from Vietnam and the Nigerian Agency for the Prevention of Trafficking In Persons (NAPTIP) to prosecute traffickers at source, improve cooperation and build the capability of investigators and prosecutors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The third aim is smarter, more effective action at the border - concentrated efforts have been made by a range of agencies to work together to share information and maximise capabilities. The Border Force has been working with the European Border Agency, Frontex, to draw up risk profiles on victims from particular countries, in cooperation with other member states. The risk profiles have been disseminated to UK ports. In this way the attention of frontline staff can be focused on passengers who pose the highest risk and allow the vast majority of legitimate travellers to pass through without delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The final aim is more coordination of UK law enforcement efforts - agencies across the UK work collaboratively and with their counterparts in other countries to share intelligence and collectively target traffickers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tackling human trafficking, no single agency or government organisation alone can provide a comprehensive response. This is why it is crucial that we cooperate together fully at every level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the strategic level, the Inter-Departmental Ministerial Group (&lt;abbr title="Inter Departmental Ministerial Group"&gt;IDMG&lt;/abbr&gt;) draws together ministers of the relevant departments and the devolved administrations. I am a member of this group. You may be surprised at the range of other departments represented: the membership includes ministers from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Communities and Local Government, Department for Education, Ministry of Justice, Department for International Development, Department for Work and Pensions and Department of Health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This group is responsible for developing and reviewing the UK’s counter-trafficking policy. In line with the requirements set out in the 2011 EU Directive on trafficking in human beings, the &lt;abbr title="Inter Departmental Ministerial Group"&gt;IDMG&lt;/abbr&gt; is the UK’s national rapporteur mechanism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="Inter Departmental Ministerial Group"&gt;IDMG&lt;/abbr&gt; published its first annual report on human trafficking on 18 October 2012. The report is an assessment of human trafficking in the UK and work underway to prevent people from becoming victims of this crime. As well as assessing trends the report also provides an update on the UK government’s human trafficking strategy. I would urge you to read this report which is available to download from the Home Office website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At official level, policy on trafficking is consistently reviewed at meetings of both government and non-government representatives - such as the Poppy Project and NSPCC. My officials take a full part in these meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At operational level, the UK Human Trafficking Centre is a multi-agency unit that coordinates law enforcement. UK law enforcement and prosecutors also work in joint investigation teams. These teams tackle the chain of criminals across various countries who are responsible for recruiting, moving and exploiting vulnerable victims.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-role-of-international-instruments-in-shaping-and-influencing-legislation"&gt;The role of international instruments in shaping and influencing legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over recent years, there has been a growing international consensus that there should be a concerted global response to human trafficking. Globalisation has resulted in an increase in transnational crime, and migration provides a fertile field for criminals. In response, international instruments have criminalised human trafficking, put in place procedural safeguards and protected victims. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK’s legal framework has been directly influenced by UN and EU Conventions and Directives. I will refer to just 2 such international instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The first is the ‘Palermo Protocol’. The UN Convention against Transnational Organised Crime, signed in Palermo, Italy in 2000 is the main instrument against transnational organised crime. It provided international and mutually recognised definitions of human trafficking and criminalisation of trafficking including proportional criminal penalties for traffickers. It also, importantly, established the protection to be afforded to victims. The ‘Palermo Protocol’ continues to shape the UK’s response to human trafficking and in particular the care and support afforded to identified human trafficking victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The second international instrument I will refer to is the EU Directive on Trafficking in Human Beings, which the UK opted into in July 2011. The UK was already compliant with the majority of the provisions contained within the directive. However, there were 2 areas identified where primary legislation was required to comply. Steps have already been taken, through the Protection of Freedoms Act 2012, to introduce new legislation in these areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The legislative changes mean that, in future, England and Wales can prosecute UK nationals who commit trafficking offences even where the trafficking has no connection with the UK. The power to prosecute traffickers for non-sexual trafficking offences which occur wholly within England and Wales has also been introduced.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-uk-criminal-justice-response"&gt;The UK criminal justice response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I now turn to domestic legislation and the criminal justice response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cases of human trafficking may be prosecuted under a variety of different legislation. I shall briefly run through some of the relevant legislation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Sexual Offences Act 2003 criminalised the trafficking into, within, and out of, the UK for the purposes of sexual exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Secondly, the Asylum and Immigration Act 2004 criminalised trafficking into, within, and out of, the UK for all other forms of exploitation. This legislation was also sufficiently wide for prosecutors to prosecute traffickers for a wide range of exploitative conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Finally, in April 2010 a standalone offence was introduced under the Coroners and Justice Act 2009 to criminalise those who hold another person in slavery or servitude or require them to perform forced or compulsory labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All these offences attract maximum penalties of up to 14 years imprisonment on conviction and the first 2 are ‘lifestyle offences’ for the purposes of proceeds of crime. This means that the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; can deprive the defendant of the financial benefit that he or she has obtained from criminal conduct through a confiscation order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To give an example of the kind of slavery and servitude offences that are prosecuted: in July of this year 4 members of the Connors family were found guilty of forcing destitute men into servitude. The men were kept in squalid conditions at a caravan park, made to work up to 19 hours a day, 6 days a week for nothing and slept in sheds and horseboxes. They were also verbally abused and beaten and threatened to be killed if they ever tried to leave. Some were alcoholics, drug addicts or had previously been in trouble with the law, and were picked up off the streets, at soup kitchens or in centres for the homeless. One victim said that living at the caravan site was like being in a ‘concentration camp’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cases of human trafficking may also be prosecuted under other legislation. For example offences such as conspiracy to traffic, assisting unlawful immigration to a member state (known as facilitation), and other serious criminal offences such as rape, kidnapping, false imprisonment and threats to kill. These offences are not necessarily lesser charges, as they may carry similar or more serious penalties than human trafficking charges. Importantly, they are used in circumstances where evidence obtained does not support charges of trafficking, or it is not in a form that is reliable and admissible in a court in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In terms of convictions, Ministry of Justice data for England and Wales in 2011 shows that the number of defendants found guilty, on a principal offence basis, for human trafficking offences (this means that the human trafficking count was the most serious on the indictment), was 8. In 2010, it was 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“While these were the numbers of convictions for specific trafficking offences, they do not include all traffickers convicted - this is because many traffickers are convicted for alternative, but related, offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Data from the Crown Prosecution Service’s systems, although less robust, gives an indication of the number of defendants convicted where there was an original charge for trafficking but where that particular charge was subsequently dropped or amended, or where the defendant pleaded guilty to or was convicted of an alternative offence. The data generated by this approach shows that the number of defendants charged was 142 in 2011-12 (in 2010-11 that figure was 103). Two-thirds of those defendants were convicted, which equates to 94 defendants.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protection-and-support-for-victims-in-giving-evidence"&gt;Protection and support for victims in giving evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Central to increasing the numbers and success of prosecutions is the need to encourage victims to support prosecutions. We recognise that many victims and witnesses take significant risks in giving evidence against their traffickers and exploiters. They often fear the consequences of giving evidence - not only for themselves, as often traffickers threaten the lives of close family members who remain in the source country - and may therefore be reluctant to support criminal proceedings. They may worry that they may not be believed. Or they may have a distrust of the authorities because of the culture or their experiences in their home country. Victims may also be facing conflicting interests such as pending applications for asylum which might impact on their willingness to engage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For any of these reasons, they may be apprehensive or frightened about coming to court to give their evidence. Whilst we know it will be difficult for victims, the police and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; work with a range of non-government agencies, and the other agencies in the criminal justice system, to provide victims with appropriate protection and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This support will improve their safety and help them to give evidence. We know that non-government organisations will often have greater experience of victims and their differing needs, and we recognise the important role they play. As I referred to earlier, there is in the UK a single framework, called the National Referral Mechanism, which assists greatly in identifying victims and referring them on to appropriate support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When a victim is going to give evidence at court the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; will consider the range of ‘special measures’ available to support and protect trafficked victims and allow them to give their best evidence. For example, prosecutors can apply to have the victim’s evidence-in-chief video recorded for presentation in court or for the victim to give evidence via a video link from their home country if they wish to return there. Prosecutors can also apply for reporting restrictions to protect victim’s identity in the press.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international"&gt;International&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As I said earlier, human trafficking has a truly international dimension. It is a global problem and investigations for human trafficking usually extend to other jurisdictions, requiring evidence for prosecutions in the UK to be obtained from abroad. The principal mechanism for obtaining or exchanging information between different jurisdictions is through mutual legal assistance (MLA). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“MLA is requested through a letter of request, which is a legal document issued by either a judge or a crown prosecutor, requesting assistance in obtaining evidence specified in the letter for use in criminal proceedings or to support an investigation. Additionally the UK has a number of bilateral treaties with other states. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In seeking the return of a suspect from another jurisdiction, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; can use extradition proceedings and does so to good effect. For example, in a recent prosecution the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2009 extradited an offender from Spain. This was in relation to an unspeakably horrendous case of a father and son trafficking women (some still minors) into Britain from Romania and forcing them to work as prostitutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the women did not comply with the demands of their clients, they were beaten and raped by the 23-year-old son. The victims were forced to work 6 or 7 days a week, with up to 8 or 10 clients a night. It was the father who was extradited and subsequently convicted of 6 trafficking charges for sexual exploitation and 1 of controlling prostitution for gain. Following a trial at Manchester Crown Court, the son was also was found guilty of a wide range of offences including rapes, assaults, sex trafficking and controlling prostitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The successful prosecution of those men means that they no longer pose a threat to women and children.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sentencing"&gt;Sentencing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Before moving on to the topic of UK law influencing other jurisdictions, I must finish by referring to the importance of sentencing. Sentencing Council guidelines have been issued to the judiciary, identify aggravating and mitigating factors which should be applied in ‘human trafficking for the purposes of sexual exploitation’ cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When any human trafficking offence is sentenced in the Crown Court, if the prosecution, or any other interested party, considers that the sentence is unduly lenient - that is, it falls outside the appropriate range suggested by the guidelines or, where there are no guidelines, by previous cases - then they can ask the Attorney General to review the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the Attorney General or I think the sentence is unduly lenient, we may ask the Court of Appeal for permission to refer the case to it. The Court of Appeal decides whether or not the sentence is unduly lenient and, if it is, whether to increase the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By way of an example, the case I mentioned a moment ago was one that was referred by my office in 2011. The sentences that were handed down of 21 years imprisonment for the son and 6 years for the father were assessed as unduly lenient by my predecessor. Lord Justice Hughes, who reviewed the sentences with Mr Justice Treacy and Mr Justice Blake, said the case was a ‘depressing narrative of depravity, callous exploitation and brutality’ and increased both sentences. The father’s was increased to 9 years. The son was assessed as a significant risk of serious harm to the public, making him eligible for an indeterminate public protection sentence from which he will only be freed when - and if - he is considered safe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="role-of-uk-in-influencing-law-in-other-jurisdictions"&gt;Role of UK in influencing law in other jurisdictions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As human trafficking is a global criminal enterprise we liaise with our partners abroad for the purposes of bringing a prosecution in this country, and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; shares their experience with our partners overseas to enable them to strengthen their criminal justice systems and rule of law. This helps traffickers to be stopped and prosecuted before they come to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This work is essential. Many of the source and transit countries for trafficking are targeted by organised criminals due to the perceived weakness of the rule of law in those countries. The &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; has a positive programme of seeking to work in many of these countries to assist them in strengthening their criminal justice systems. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;advising law makers on changes in legislation and policies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with practitioners to train them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identifying and assisting in removing key strategic blockages to successful prosecutions within the court system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Despite the positive steps that have been taken, both at home and overseas, I recognise that there is much to do in combating human trafficking and slavery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To conclude, I would like to reiterate the point I have made before: human trafficking is a global issue. The UK takes the issue seriously and uses the international framework to properly create and apply domestic legislation.
We cannot operate in a vacuum, either domestically (which is why we have the &lt;abbr title="Inter Departmental Ministerial Group"&gt;IDMG&lt;/abbr&gt;) nor internationally (which is why the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; works hard to support other jurisdictions).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are areas which require further attention and which we are addressing through the UK strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Firstly - prevention. Demand for cheap labour, cheap goods and services, and demand for prostitution or sexual services continues to provide a thriving environment for organised criminals to operate in. Tackling demand is therefore vital in the fight against human trafficking and is one of the most challenging areas for the UK to address. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As I have said, prosecutors work with source countries to improve the ability of overseas investigators and prosecutors in case building and prosecution to disrupt human trafficking at source. In 2010 an offence which criminalises those who pay for the sexual services of a prostitute subjected to force was introduced to try and curb demand. In relation to labour exploitation, we work closely with the Gangmasters Licensing Authority and large national hotel groups combat forced labour, trafficking and exploitation in the UK hospitality industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Secondly - ensuring that victims are identified as early as possible. This is especially hard where the issues faced by victims in reporting offences are as complex as those that I described earlier. Under-reporting impacts on our ability to identify the true scale of trafficking in the UK and stops us from being able to help all those who have been trafficked to the UK. It is therefore critical that every relevant agency is able to contribute to the identification, protection and support of potential trafficking victims. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is why we have made training and guidance available for front line staff across the widest range of agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is crucial that our continuing aim is to ensure there are no safe havens for traffickers and that their victims are fully and properly protected. The government is committed to seeing that this is achieved.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8444</id>
    <published>2012-09-04T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/oliver-heald-mp-appointed-solicitor-general-for-england-and-wales"/>
    <title>Oliver Heald MP appointed Solicitor General for England and Wales </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister, the Rt Hon David Cameron MP, has appointed Mr Oliver Heald, MP for North East Hertfordshire, to be Solicitor General. Mr Heald takes up his post with immediate effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General supports the Attorney General across the range of his responsibilities and can lawfully exercise any of his functions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General, Dominic Grieve QC MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome Oliver Heald to my Department. Oliver is an experienced, hardworking and respected colleague with a wealth of experience and I look forward to working with him on the challenges ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I also wish to pay tribute to the outgoing Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP, whose stalwart support and wise counsel have been invaluable to me over the past 2 years. In particular Edward has worked tirelessly and very effectively to improve the tools available to prosecutors in fraud and corruption cases through his work on proposed statutory deferred prosecution agreements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Heald MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am happy and honoured to be appointed to this ancient office with its responsibility to advise and to uphold the rule of law. I believe this is a wonderful opportunity for me to work with the Attorney General and ministerial colleagues to achieve a fairer society and a more effective and efficient justice system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8441</id>
    <published>2012-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/unduly-lenient-sentence-cases-referred-to-the-court-of-appeal-latest-figures"/>
    <title>Unduly lenient sentence cases referred to the Court of Appeal – latest figures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General’s Office has released statistics for 2011 sentences which were considered too low - or unduly lenient - and referred to the Court of Appeal, which can quash a sentence and impose a higher one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, 117 sentences, from 78 cases, were referred to the Court of Appeal by the Law Officers. The Court considered 97 of them were unduly lenient (83%) and 94 sentences were increased (80% of the 117 referred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases are usually referred to the Attorney General by the Crown Prosecution Service, but it is open also to victims, their families, members of the public and MPs to ask for review. In 2011 the sentences passed on 377 offenders were drawn to the attention of the Attorney General and Solicitor General (the Law Officers), compared to 342 in 2010 and 369 in 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General, the Rt Hon Dominic Grieve QC MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The unduly lenient sentence scheme allows anyone to refer a sentence to me for consideration. In the vast majority of cases judges impose sentences which are appropriate to meet the justice of the case, but the scheme provides an important safeguard in those few cases in which the sentence falls significantly outside the proper range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sentencing is not a precise science. It requires judgments to be made about a whole host of different factors, including any aggravating and mitigating features, and how any relevant guidelines should be applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These statistics are only part of the story. Where there have been mistakes, in relation to the acceptance of pleas by the prosecution, these errors are followed up with the lawyers concerned to ensure they are not repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 377 sentences drawn to the attention of the AGO as being possibly unduly lenient in 2011, 299 fell within the scheme and were considered. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8440</id>
    <published>2012-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-tool-to-tackle-economic-crime"/>
    <title>New tool to tackle economic crime </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans for a new tool to tackle economic crime have been published for consultation by Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC and Justice Minister Crispin Blunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Deferred Prosecution Agreements (&lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;), companies would agree to publically admit wrongdoing, and meet tough conditions such as payment of substantial penalties, undertaking internal reform and submitting to regular review and monitoring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole process would be overseen by a judge and the threat of full prosecution would remain hanging over a company should they fail to comply with the agreement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we can encourage companies to self-report and come clean, pay penalties and mend their ways, the time and expense of investigations and prosecutions will be better spent elsewhere, enabling us to bring more individuals and companies to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An important aim of any &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; system would be to allow investigators and prosecutors to focus resources on those cases where a prosecution is in the public interest - and there will always be some where it is the only option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justice Minister Crispin Blunt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Law enforcement agencies have told us that they do not have the tools they need to tackle increasingly complex economic crimes. Investigations can take several years and cost millions of pounds, with no guarantee of success, which means victims wait far too long for reparation. Or indeed receive no payback at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More clearly needs to be done. Deferred Prosecution Agreements will give prosecutors extra tools to tackle this type of crime and bring about a just outcome - which punishes the wrongdoer, ensures the surrendering of any proceeds and makes amends to victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic crime is increasingly complex, making it difficult to tackle effectively. As the complexity and size of commercial organisations grow, so too do the difficulties of identifying criminal activity and of bringing any organisation which commits such crime to justice. This is especially so in the case of organisations that operate, and so may have committed wrongdoing, in more than one country to which more than one set of laws can be applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DPAs would be available for prosecutors to use alongside existing methods, to give them the flexibility to secure appropriate penalties for wrongdoing, at the same time as achieving better outcomes for victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; is an agreement between a prosecutor and a commercial organisation that in return for complying with a range of conditions the prosecutor would defer a criminal prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An independent judge would oversee the development of the agreement to ensure it is fair, in the public interest and that the conditions properly reflect the nature of the wrongdoing. This will include the reparation made to victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, at the end of the deferral period, the prosecutor is satisfied the organisation has fulfilled its obligations, there is no prosecution on the charges laid. If, on the other hand, the commercial organisation fails to meet its obligations, further penalties are available and the original criminal proceedings could be revived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8434</id>
    <published>2012-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/firearms-sentence-doubled-at-court-of-appeal"/>
    <title>Firearms sentence doubled at Court of Appeal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP has welcomed the doubling of the prison sentence originally given to 23-year-old Zephen Rollings for possession of a loaded firearm with intent to enable another to endanger life, from 5 to 10 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor had appealed the sentence to the Court of Appeal as possibly unduly lenient, arguing that as the supply and movement of dangerous weapons around the country was essential to the violent criminal acts committed with them, the punishment of the facilitators should reflect the gravity of the potential ultimate result of their activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Rollings, the weapon - a Smith and Wesson .357 calibre Magnum revolver loaded with hollow-point bullets, was particularly dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In my view the original sentence of 5 years was unduly lenient and did not properly reflect the seriousness of the crime. It was truly shocking that a gun loaded with dum-dum bullets, which expand on impact, was being carried in broad daylight in a residential street. The Court of Appeal agreed and doubled the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The facts of this case painted a stark picture. Criminals carrying guns cause untold misery. The court clearly recognised the seriousness of this crime and I hope the increased sentence of 10 years sends out a clear message that gun crime will be dealt with severely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 6 July last year, police officers searched Zephen Rollings in a mini-cab outside an address in Brockley, South London. He was carrying a small leather bag which contained an American .357 Magnum calibre Smith and Wesson revolver. The gun was loaded with live ammunition which on test firing were found to mushroom on impact. He pleaded guilty to possessing a firearm with intent to enable another to endanger life and to possessing both a prohibited weapon and ammunition. On 10 November at Woolwich Crown Court, he was sentenced to a total of 5 years’ imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case was referred under the unduly lenient sentence scheme to the Court of Appeal and presented by the Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP. Giving judgment today, Lady Justice Hallett, Mr Justice Irwin and Mr Justice Nicol increased his sentence to 10 years’ imprisonment. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12331</id>
    <published>2011-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-2011-legal-wales-conference"/>
    <title>Speech to 2011 Legal Wales Conference </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Ladies and gentlemen, it is a pleasure to be here this afternoon to address the Legal Wales Annual Conference 2011. May I first thank my learned friend, the Chairman of the Legal Wales Standing Committee, Winston Roddick, for inviting me to do so? Whether you will thank him for doing so by the end of this talk is another matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am not Welsh, but I have been to Wales and to Cardiff on many previous occasions as a tourist, a barrister and a politician. My aunt lives in Powys, I have spent many happy days on the north Pembrokeshire coast on holiday with my wife and children, I successfully defended a libel action here in Cardiff some years ago brought against HTV by a caravan company, and masterfully failed to have another libel action brought against its Welsh language service by Daffyd Wigley moved from Caernarvon to English-speaking Mold or Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have conducted cases with and against the late, great Gareth Lord Williams of Mostyn, I have been to Her Majesty’s Prisons at Parc, Cardiff and Swansea, I have visited the South Wales &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, and I was lucky enough to watch England play Wales in the Millennium Stadium last December but 2 more facts connect me to Wales. My cousin, Crispin Masterman, is a circuit judge here in Cardiff although sensibly he is not here this week, and I was educated in that small but noisy part of Wales that sits between the Broad and the High in Oxford: Jesus College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let me tell you a little about my role as a Law Officer, the devolution landscape in Wales, and gazing at the horizon, the challenges for the Justice System in both England and Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="role-of-the-law-officers"&gt;Role of the Law Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The post of Law Officer is one of the most interesting posts for a lawyer to hold. It certainly has a colourful history. For example, one former Solicitor General, John Cooke, was responsible for prosecuting Charles I in 1649 for high treason in Westminster Hall, just a few yards from my own office in just off Central lobby. As we all know, the King was beheaded in Whitehall and went to his death with great dignity and Christian fortitude. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if Cooke though the death of the King and the abolition of the monarchy were the end of his troubles he was wrong - things caught up with the Solicitor General on the restoration of the Monarchy in 1660 when he became the first, and I hope, the last, Law Officer to be hanged, drawn and quartered. I am sure that all of us who practice in the courts of this jurisdiction will have had our good days and our not so good days in front of saintly and not so saintly judges but I trust that you, my audience, will let me get home today with that particular record still intact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney and Solicitor General have 3 main roles: as Chief Legal Advisers to the Crown and the Government, as the Government Ministers responsible for the Law Officers Departments and as guardians of the public interest. We are the political and legal heads of the Government Legal Service; we enjoy a special relationship with the lawyers in every other government department which entitles them to consult us on legal issues affecting their advice to ministers as well as where different departments have differing views on some issue that needs to be arbitrated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We seek to preserve the professional independence, and ensure high standards of advice and professional conduct in departmental lawyers. Of course, many of the legal issues that policy development gives rise to never come to the Law Officers but we remain the protectors of the rule of law and ensure that the government and its ministers conduct their business within the law and with propriety. And in that role we are ourselves lawyers but not just lawyers: as politically appointed ministers who are also lawyers we do not give advice or lead our lawyers with party-political bias nor do we adjust our advice to suit our party’s narrow political interests, but because we are appointed and accepted as fellow ministers, as fellow MPs, as elected politicians, we can speak to our colleagues in government, from the Prime Minister downwards with a confidence, a directness and with an understanding of the environment we operate within. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are there to speak truth unto power and if we do not do that we are failing in our job. It is a role that has taken on a new importance now that the Lord Chancellor is no longer the head of the judiciary but the head of a large spending and political department. The same goes for government lawyers in their departments but they have the comfort of knowing that if their advice is questioned or improperly criticised they can come to us for protection or may consult us if they have doubts about the propriety of any proposed course of action in a matter for which they have responsibility. This means that they can discharge a role in their respective departments that reflects ours at their head, not as politicians but as government lawyers who are also independent professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“From this position of strength they can advise Ministers on the legality of what they want to do, working up solutions when what is proposed collides with the constraints imposed by, say, the &lt;abbr title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;ECHR&lt;/abbr&gt; or by our obligations under EU law. These things are matters of intense political controversy as we have been reminded this week at the conservative Party conference in Manchester and it is our job and our lawyers’ job to steer those politicians who are either over-excited, hasty or in need of a headline through the legal thickets and minefields that can destroy the unwary. Our job is not always to say “No” but to suggest they do it this way rather than that way; not to put up the red light but the amber one, to warn, to cajole and to ask, “have you thought about doing it this way?” which is, I guess, of course, what all good lawyers should do for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney General and I superintend and are responsible to Parliament for the Crown Prosecution Service, the Serious Fraud Office and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Inspectorate. We do not run these bodies, we do not micro-manage their day to day activities but we meet the &lt;abbr title="Director of Public Prosecutions"&gt;DPP&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Director of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Chief Inspector, as we do the Treasury Solicitor, the non-political head of the &lt;abbr title="Government Legal Service"&gt;GLS&lt;/abbr&gt;, to discuss the overall strategy of their organisations, we consider where in the most contentious cases the public interest lies and how it can best be served and we consent or not to those prosecutions that require our consent, and we refer to the Court of Appeal and frequently appear to argue about those Crown court sentences we consider to be unduly lenient as well as prosecuting contempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For my part, doing a job in government so closely associated with the law and the profession which has been such a big part of my life for the last 35 years is hugely rewarding. The life of the Law Officers, although circumscribed by limitations that a real politician would not tolerate, brings one to the very centre of power even if those at the centre do not realise it. It is not the dry and fusty world of the Dickensian lawyer’s office, still less the Office of Circumlocution. Of course, the public only see the capital ships, dressed fore and aft, steaming full steam ahead on the high seas, occasionally firing their guns - even at each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But below the surface and silently, and only known to a few in the law and in Whitehall, are the 2 submarines, HM Attorney and Solicitor. When we go on manoeuvres we do so to have an effect as the controversy over the Attorney General’s advice on Iraq in 2003 perhaps unfortunately reveals but there are happier examples of activities carried out in confidence for governments of both colours where the advice and restraining hand of the Law Officers has been both sensible and well received. When we surface it is usually to resign (or not), to apply to the courts in a contempt case, or to complain of an unduly lenient sentence. But my aim is not to end up like HMS Astute on the shingle bank off Skye, beached, powerless and inoperable; I am, like the man from the Inland Revenue here to help; I am but a humble seeker after truth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="devolution"&gt;Devolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government of Wales Act gives the Law Officers, along with the Counsel General for Wales (Theodore Huckle), the power to refer to the Supreme Court the question whether a Welsh Assembly Bill is within its legislative competence. So far there have not been any references but because we work closely with the Counsel General, the Welsh Government, the Assembly and the Wales Office, and they all with each other, there is no reason to expect references will be a frequent occurrence. In one sense that is a disappointment: as a member of the Bar I would relish the opportunity to argue a Welsh, Scottish or Northern Irish devolution point in the Supreme Court but by and large these difficulties are soluble without recourse to the courts. That is not to say that there may come a time when it will be sensible, indeed imperative, to ask the Supreme Court to arbitrate. No statute can anticipate every contingency so if either Wales or the United Kingdom does have to take a reference let us do so in a spirit of cooperation and willingness to hear each other’s arguments and as evidence of our willingness to make the devolution settlement work as parliament intended. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will act to clarify the limits of the devolution settlement, not to stultify political debate. We would do so to ensure that the boundaries of the devolution settlement here or in Scotland or in Northern Ireland are respected, not out of any desire to interfere with the policy behind devolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The devolution settlement itself has changed over the last 12 years - with powers shifting away from Westminster to Cardiff. In March this year, the referendum result meant further law making powers moving from Westminster to the National Assembly for Wales. The Assembly can legislate in all twenty areas covered by the original devolution settlement, including economic regeneration, education, health, transport and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a significant broadening of the Assembly’s powers, but all the areas not previously devolved remain reserved as the responsibility of the United Kingdom government and Parliament. This new constitutional landscape presents interesting challenges for us all in Westminster, Whitehall, the Welsh government and the National Assembly. We need to work together, talk to each other, correspond with each other and meet face to face to ensure that our working practices take account of the Assembly’s wider powers, understanding their new boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In July the Secretary of State for Wales announced plans to set up an independent Commission on Devolution in Wales. With the help of the Welsh government and cross-party support from the Assembly, we hope to establish the Commission this autumn. It will examine issues of fiscal devolution and accountability in Wales and will look to build a consensus around the recommendations it makes. It will take into consideration the work of the Welsh Government’s Holtham Commission, and will aim to report in the autumn of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Once the government has considered the Commission’s recommendations, it will turn its attention to looking at the boundary between what is devolved and what is not devolved in Wales, and specifically whether to recommend modifications to that boundary in light of the Assembly’s wider powers. The Commission will aim to report on this part of its work in 2013.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes---the-justice-system"&gt;Changes - the justice system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Despite all the constitutional reforms, criminal justice remains one area which is unaffected by the Welsh referendum. We are one jurisdiction. Reforms to our legal system and how we pay for it are implemented from Westminster and Whitehall but whether they came from London or Cardiff, in the current economic climate the Legal Aid reforms emanating from the Ministry of Justice will create real challenges. Publicly funded access to the law, to advice and to the courts is an essential prerequisite of any civilised and compassionate society and it will be even if to a different extent or in different ways than before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The work - work that has been carried out by hard-working, dedicated lawyers with a vocation to assist the less well off, the sick or the vulnerable for generations - will still be available but we must be adaptable and open to new ideas. Much as we would like to spend a growing percentage of public money on greater areas of legal work, we cannot afford to and thus we must face up to change and meet the challenge. It will not be easy, it may not be what we are used to or want, it has led and will lead to arguments and differences between individuals, chambers, firms, the professions, judges, and government as we seek to adapt to the new era of less public money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday ‘Alternative Business Structures’ became part of our life having been introduced by the last Government’s Legal Services Act. ABSs were not universally welcomed then and will not make us all dance in the street now but they will create opportunities by lifting the restrictions on the structure, ownership and management of businesses that provide legal services. They will allow lawyers and non-lawyers to work together in a single enterprise, providing clients with a service that recognises that the solution to at least some of their problems may not always involve recourse to the law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The external investment of funds into the legal services sector and competition will help stimulate growth which should help to maintain and even drive up the high standards of our already first class legal system. What they must not do is suborn professional standards or conduct, interfere with our duties to the court, our clients and to justice or skew our advice to please our financial masters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The role of the Law Society and the Bar Council and of the judges before whom we will appear will become all the more central to the maintenance of the highest standards but equally the independent firm of independent partners, large or small, the barrister in private practice will still have a vital and essential part to play in the justice system and one which I am determined to see survive and thrive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Other changes facing the profession include the introduction of a Quality Assurance Scheme for Advocates. The scheme devised by representatives from the Bar Standards Board, the Solicitors Regulation Authority and &lt;abbr title="Institute of Legal Executives"&gt;ILEX&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide a common and transparent assessment system for advocates in the higher courts whatever branch of the profession they are from. It will allow clients to pick the most appropriate advocate - whether barrister, solicitor or &lt;abbr title="Institute of Legal Executives"&gt;ILEX&lt;/abbr&gt; practitioner- to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There will inevitably be competition between solicitors and barristers for advocacy work but competition is at the heart of our two professions and neither should feel threatened by it. Competition, backed by high standards, properly assessed and regulated, is a good thing. Let us embrace it. These reforms bring into sharper focus the responsibilities of all of us in the legal professions to help shape the change and to adapt to change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The circuits have always been central to the professional and social life as well as the training and development of the Bar. It is through the circuit leaders and presiding judges that we talk to each other and to the judiciary. I am sure the Wales and Chester circuit will play its part in maintaining and enhancing the profession in Wales, and helping those in need of guidance and support as we navigate our way through these difficult economic times and this period of change. The Attorney and I take our roles as Leaders of the Bar seriously and we are there to help, to advise and to speak to government if needed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes---the-crown-prosecution-service"&gt;Changes - the Crown Prosecution Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms to the justice system will not only affect the private sector. The Crown Prosecution Service too is facing change. The inexorable rise in the numbers of in-house advocates at the expense of those outside has ceased as the Attorney and I have required the restoration of a proper balance between the private referral profession and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;. The comprehensive spending review touches every government department, ours included, as we implement the government’s agenda to reduce the massive budget deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This year the Crown Prosecution Service introduced a new scheme for the delivery of prosecution services in court. All advocates undertaking prosecution work from this month onwards must be members of new, quality-controlled &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Advocate Panels. The panels will be open to all barristers and solicitor advocates, and panel members will complement and work alongside &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; in-house advocates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although the overall number of advocates on the panels will be reduced, selected advocates will have more opportunity to undertake prosecution work. This initiative will help maintain the high standards of advocacy amongst prosecutors and ensure justice is delivered in Court. We will not tolerate poor advocacy from either private or employed advocates acting for the prosecution and those who cannot come up to scratch, be they in or outside the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, will not be offered the work - nor should they.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Crown Prosecution Service Wales Area, as part of the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Senior Management Restructuring Plan, was introduced in April earlier this year. There will continue to be eight &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; offices across Wales (Wrexham, Colwyn Bay, Newtown, Camarthen, Swansea, Merthyr, Cardiff and Cwmbran) in order to ensure the effective delivery of services across Wales. We are, however, increasingly working in the digital age and the Wales is one of the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; areas leading the drive towards a more efficient and predominantly digitalised working environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For example, Dyfed-Powys was the first area to use a ‘digital file’. “Advance Information” is now provided ahead of first hearings in the Magistrates’ Court in electronic format both to the court and, where necessary, to Probation and Youth Offending Teams. This will make it easier and faster to get at information, reduce unnecessary adjournments and increase the overall efficiency of the administration of justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Crown Prosecution Service has also developed mechanisms for more effective cooperation with the police. Witness Care Units, for example now operate on a digital basis and have the capacity to move work between Units. Court files are now increasingly being prepared conjointly by the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and the police rather than wasting time and resources on creating multiple files which often never get read.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all facing difficult challenges in the current economic climate. Present circumstances have compelled us to look very hard at the current way of doing things. But reform would be needed even without an eye-watering budget deficit to worry about - to address some of the weaknesses present in the way that the Justice system operates, and to build on its strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s at times like this, when one has a difficult case to make, that I draw comfort from the strength and resilience of the traditional legal hack. Perhaps you know of the case in the Court of Appeal in which the appellant’s counsel was making heavy weather of a pretty hopeless criminal appeal. The presiding Lord Justice, beginning to lose patience but not his manners, stopped counsel in mid-stream.’Isn’t the difficulty you face, Mr Smith, that the evidence before the jury showed that your client was driving the van when it was stopped by the police, that in the back of the van was a large cardboard box all over which were found your client’s fingerprints and inside which was found a vast quantity of Class A drugs?’ Mr Smith replied, ‘Let me put it this way, my Lord. Here on the bench beside me is a copy of Archbold. It is my Archbold and I brought it here. But no one has ever suggested that I know what’s in it.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7968</id>
    <published>2011-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sentences-examined-by-the-attorney-general-in-2010"/>
    <title>Sentences examined by the Attorney General in 2010 </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General’s Office has released figures on Unduly Lenient Sentence cases which were considered too low – or unduly lenient - and referred to the Court of Appeal, which can quash a sentence and impose a higher one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;77 sentences were referred by the Law Officers. The Court considered 65 of them were unduly lenient (84%) and 60 sentences were increased (78% of the 77 referred)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2009, the sentences of 71 offenders were increased out of 108 reviewed by the Court of Appeal (66%). In 2008 52 sentences were increased out of 71 reviewed by the Court (73%).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 sentences passed on 342 offenders were drawn to the attention of both the previous incumbent, the Rt Hon Baroness Scotland QC, (from Jan to May 10,) and the present Attorney, the Rt Hon Dominic Grieve QC MP (from May to Dec 10) compared to 369 in 2009 and 274 in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dominic Grieve said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the Unduly Lenient Sentence scheme plays an important role in maintaining public confidence in sentencing as a vital tool in the criminal justice system, as well as being an important part of our role as guardians of the public interest. It is the only means by which anyone - especially victims or their families - can have an apparently unduly lenient sentence examined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC MP, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unduly lenient sentences are rare. There are tens of thousands of sentences passed each year in the Crown Courts in England and Wales and in the vast majority of cases, the judge’s approach meets the justice of each case. The scheme provides an opportunity for the Court of Appeal to identify how sentencing in certain types of case should be approached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentencing requires judgments to be made about the weight to be attached to all the relevant considerations including aggravating and mitigating factors, and how any relevant guidelines should be applied. It may be reasonable to pass a sentence which is lenient, or which is harsher than the guidelines might suggest, on the particular facts of an individual case. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cases referred to the Court of Appeal in 2010 included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 3 March 2011, the Solicitor General presented 3 cases where the victims were sexually assaulted or raped in their homes or another place where they were entitled to feel safe. In 2 of the cases, the victims were subjected to the added humiliation of having pictures taken of the attack. The Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Henriques and Mr Justice Davis ruled that the sentences were unduly lenient, and issued guidance to sentencing judges that in a case where a violent sexual attack has been committed after or in the course of burglary in a home - even if there are no additional features beyond the rape and the burglary - the starting point will rarely be less than 12 years’ imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias Dawson, a 29-year-old offender, violently attacked his pregnant, estranged wife in a hospital car park. He knocked her to the ground and repeatedly kicked her to the head. The Attorney General, presented this case to the Court of Appeal on 9 December 2010 and the defendant saw his original sentence of 12 months imprisonment suspended for 2 years with a 2-year supervision order, quashed and replaced with one of 4 years’ imprisonment&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;49-year-old Maureen Cunniam visited the home of her near neighbours, an elderly couple, and carried out a sustained and violent attack on them with a baseball bat. She had her 3 and a half year sentence quashed and replaced with one of 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Offender “X” received a 7-year sentence for 6 counts of raping his wife which the Court of Appeal overturned and replaced with one of 11 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Charnley was jailed for 5 years for downloading and retaining 11,000 indecent images and 356 films containing indecent images of children aged between 2 and 17, over a period of 18 months. They included images of rape and sadism. In addition, on 35 occasions, over a period of 2 and a half months between June 09 and the date of his arrest, the offender had contacted adults in the Far East via the internet who, for payment, provided children aged from 2 to 12 years for the offender to view and record as he caused or incited the children to engage in sexual activity. Lord Justice Moses said that this court has a duty to pass appropriate sentences to deter others committing these types of offences; he then quashed the original sentence and replaced it with one of 12 years imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vasile Oaches and Vasile Maris received 30 and 24 months’ imprisonment respectively for trafficking into the UK for sexual exploitation and controlling prostitution for gain. The men met the 19-year-old victim in Romania and lured her and her friend to the UK with the prospect of a decent job. A third young woman was collected en route to the UK. Once there the women were required to work as street prostitutes and the offenders took their earnings. The victim was slapped and threatened by Oaches. She was also required to have sex with friends of Oaches, in lieu of payment for rent. The victim managed to escape with the help of another man she knew from Romania. The ULS hearing took place in September 2010 and the men saw their sentences increased to 4 and 3 years respectively. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7939</id>
    <published>2011-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/juror-and-defendant-sentenced-for-contempt-of-court-over-facebook"/>
    <title>Juror and defendant sentenced for contempt of court over Facebook </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a case brought by the Attorney General and presented by the Solicitor General, a juror and an acquitted defendant in a drugs conspiracy trial in Manchester Crown Court have been given custodial sentences (1 suspended) at the High Court in London for contempt of court over online discussions the 2 had engaged in during the trial. They were found guilty by the High Court on Tuesday 14 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joanne Fraill, the juror, and Jamie Sewart, the defendant, discussed the trial on the social networking site Facebook. Their activities led to the trial in Manchester Crown Court in 2010 being abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Ouseley and Mr Justice Holroyde, sitting at the High Court, heard how the pair discussed the deliberations of the jury of which Fraill was a member and which had acquitted Sewart but had yet to return verdicts on 3 other defendants. The trial, which had been running for 10 weeks, ended when the judge discharged the jury after learning of Fraill’s actions. Fraill was sentenced today to 8 months in custody and Sewart, to 2 months’ custody, suspended for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC MP, who presented the case in person, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Lord Chief Justice could not have been clearer. Joanne Fraill and Jamie Sewart’s conduct was a clear contempt of court. Jurors should take careful note and know that the Law Officers will prosecute those who commit contempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both of these women were well aware that they should not have been engaging in this discussion. The jury system is a cornerstone of our society and confidence in this vital part of our criminal justice system will crumble if jurors do not take their responsibilities seriously. Long before social networks, the courts have been in no doubt that discussions inside the jury room must stay there. The internet doesn’t make judges’ warnings not to talk about a case or research it any less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application to prosecute was made by the Attorney General, Dominic Grieve QC MP, for contempt of court at common law and under section 8 of the Contempt of Court Act 1981. The Attorney and Solicitor General are able to bring proceedings in their public interest capacity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
