<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Increasing the number of available homes"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-22T12:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16798</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T12:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T12:41:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-visits-hidden-homes-in-wandsworth"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles visits ‘Hidden Homes’ in Wandsworth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles visited the Rollo housing estate in the London Borough of Wandsworth today (22 July 2012) to see how £3.6 million of government funding is helping the council provide more affordable homes for local families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the final 38 affordable new homes of the Hidden Homes initiative that celebrates its 10th anniversary this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles with Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1168/Rollo2-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wandsworth Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis welcome Eric Pickles to the borough to officially unveil the new Hidden Homes&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Offering excellent value-for-money, the cutting-edge programme converts vacant and disused spaces on housing estates - from boiler rooms to storage areas - into modern and attractive affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme has delivered 238 homes in Wandsworth over the past decade. These have been allocated to local families and first time buyers, often on a shared ownership basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hidden Homes approach has provided more affordable homes, and at the same time prevented these redundant spaces from becoming eyesores or potential havens for anti-social behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles praised the borough for boosting housing delivery that, in the 12 month period to March 2012, was the highest in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Wandsworth scheme was a lesson to other councils for delivering more affordable housing, despite the tough economic circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects like Hidden Homes also provide valuable economic regeneration, creating jobs and boosting the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is committed to delivering more affordable homes that families need. Our £19.5 billion investment is delivering 170,000 affordable homes, and our FirstBuy and NewBuy schemes are helping families take the next step on the property ladder with just a fraction of the normal deposit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we also want more councils to do more, and adopt innovative solutions like those being pioneered in Wandsworth. Using government and council funding, these Hidden Homes are making a fantastic contribution to the affordable housing landscape and giving families and first time buyers the chance to have their own home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabinet Member for Housing at Wandsworth Council, Councillor Paul Ellis said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Hidden Homes scheme has played a really major role in increasing the supply of affordable housing over the past decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well as proving incredibly cost effective, it has also helped create jobs in the construction sector and been the key to regenerating redundant land on housing estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the secretary of state will today unveil its biggest single scheme, and that as a result, 3 dozen families in housing need will be able to move into brand new high quality homes”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding for Hidden Homes builds on the options available for aspiring homeowners who want to get onto and up the housing ladder. This includes the NewBuy Guarantee and the reinvigorated Right to Buy, which will give thousands of council tenants the opportunity to buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632071654509/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16331</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-housing-starts-and-completions-funded-by-the-hca-and-the-gla-april-to-september-2012-13"/>
    <title>Affordable housing starts and completions funded by the HCA and the GLA - April to September 2012-13</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics on affordable housing starts and completions funded by the Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) and the Greater London Authority (GLA) were released on Friday 16 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures show the supply of homes delivered under the accelerated land disposal programme, the 2011-15 affordable homes programme (including the affordable homes programme, empty homes, homelessness change, mortgage rescue and traveller pitch funding), the economic assets programme, firstbuy, the get Britain building programme, the kickstart housing delivery programme, the national affordable housing programme and the property and regeneration programme. Details about these programmes can be found in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/housing-statistics"&gt;HCA Housing statistics release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 1 April and 30 September 2012, there were 3,735 affordable housing starts on site delivered in England through programmes managed by the HCA and the GLA. This represents an increase of 678 per cent compared to the 480 (revised) started in the same period of the previous year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Between 1 April and 30 September 2012, there were 11,432 affordable housing completions delivered through programmes through programmes managed by the HCA and the GLA. This represents a decrease of 11 per cent compared to the 12,778 completed in the same period in the previous year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on the number of affordable homes delivered under the HCA affordable housing programmes is published twice a year. From April 2012, the Mayor of London has had strategic oversight of housing, regeneration and economic development in London. This means that the HCA no longer publish affordable housing starts and completions for London and this responsibility has been taken over by the GLA. DCLG combines data from the HCA and the GLA to publish six monthly affordable housing starts and completions delivered nationally under the affordable housing programmes of the HCA and GLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the HCA affordable housing statistics, see their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/housing-statistics"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the GLA affordable housing statistics, see their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.london.gov.uk/datastore/package/gla-affordable-housing-programme-outturn"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15967</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/house-building-in-england-july-to-september-2012"/>
    <title>House building in England: July to September 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on house building in England were released on 15 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics in this release present figures on new build housing starts and completions in England. Figures for the UK and constituent countries are also available in the accompanying tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics report on the period July to September 2012 and update those previously released on 16 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the latest release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted house building starts in England increased by 18% and stood at 25,760 in the September quarter 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted completions fell, down 7% to 27,060 in the September quarter 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Private enterprise housing starts (seasonally adjusted) were 15% higher in the September quarter 2012 than the previous quarter, whilst starts by housing associations were 23% higher.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted private enterprise completions fell by 6% and housing association completions fell by 14% from the previous quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted starts are now 52% above the trough in the March quarter 2009 but 45% below the December quarter 2005 peak. Completions are 44% below their March quarter 2007 peak.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annual housing starts totalled 98,020 in the 12 months to September 2012, down by 9% compared with the year before. Annual housing completions in England reached 117,190 in the 12 months to September 2012, an increase of 6% compared with the previous 12 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16273</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16267</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T09:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-housing-supply-in-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Affordable housing supply in England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics on gross affordable housing supply in England were released on Thursday 1 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A total of 57,950 gross additional affordable homes were supplied in England in 2011-12. This is a decrease of 4% on the 60,430 (revised) affordable homes supplied in 2010-11.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;37,540 new affordable homes were provided for social rent in 2011-12, a decrease of 3% on 2010-11. A further 930 new affordable homes were provided for affordable rent in 2011-12, the first year for which this scheme has run.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;19,490 homes were provided through intermediate housing schemes, including shared ownership and shared equity, down by 10% on 2010-11.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were 52,880 new build affordable homes provided in 2011-12, representing 91% of all affordable homes provided in 2011-12 compared to 88% of total supply in 2010-11. This was the highest percentage reported since before 1991-92.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2011-12, 88% of affordable homes were in receipt of funding through the Homes and Communities Agency (excluding homes delivered under Section 106 without grant), a reduction from 92% in 2010-11. Around 92% of these were new build homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note: These statistics were assessed by the United Kingdom Statistics Authority in June 2011 (Report 117). We have addressed the requirements relating to these statistics to the satisfaction of the UK Statistics Authority and they are now accredited as National Statistics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14743</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/independent-panel-to-help-government-cut-housebuilding-red-tape-and-boost-growth"/>
    <title>Independent panel to help government cut housebuilding red tape and boost growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today launched a new independent group of building industry experts, tasked with simplifying the mass of rules imposed on developers and housebuilders, to make them easier to understand and follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Government’s Red Tape Challenge Ministers have made clear they want to do everything possible to remove unnecessary burdens and bureaucracy imposed on developers to get much needed new homes built, and support economic growth.  The current, complex system of building regulations and housing standards will be targeted by a new Independent Challenge Panel, which will consider how these requirements work together and what potential there is to free up the system and make it work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel will for the first time bring independent experts together with government and it will report to ministers in spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mr Foster also made clear that essential safety and accessibility protections will remain untouched and that homes will always need to be built to high sustainability and quality standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="housing-standards-review"&gt;Housing standards review&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the hundreds of standards that can be applied to new-build homes, some of which duplicate each other, a separate group will work alongside the new Challenge Panel to consider the specific issue of standards applied to housebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some of these standards are applied nationally across certain types of homes such as affordable housing, others are made mandatory by individual councils for building in their area and some are entirely voluntary - resulting in confusion for local people and developers. Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The requirement for two phone lines in home offices, irrespective of need and in addition to broadband connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rules on window sizes that include a ‘dirty window factor’ - imposing bigger windows to allow for dirt on them, rather than assuming people will simply clean their windows&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A requirement that ‘drying space’ is designed and assessed when often this is nothing more complicated than a washing line over a bath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflicting guidance on how to construct safe and accessible stairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards being assessed repeatedly by different people - such as planners, code assessors, building control officers - often looking at the same issues  but coming up with different answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This new review, led by DCLG and to be conducted by a group of industry representatives, will look to avoid overlap and duplication in the system, helping ensure builders meet the high standards that aspiring homeowners rightly expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The current array of different housing standards used in different parts the country is complex and counter-productive: confusing local residents, councillors and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is why an urgent review has now started, bringing the government together with housebuilders, planners, councils and architects to establish what the unnecessary measures are that we can cut out of the system, whilst ensuring buildings are still made to exacting standards.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I want to see a simpler set of housing standards that people can easily understand and that free up developers and councils to get on with the job of building the high quality new homes we so badly to get more first time buyers and families onto the housing ladder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review was part of the government’s housing and growth strategy announced on 6 September.  It will result in a clear plan of action by next spring that will be put out to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Independent Challenge Panel members are:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy Von Bradsky (architect)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Clements (building control)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Watson (planner)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kirk Archibald (developer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DCLG is chairing and leading the housing standards review and has convened a group of members from representative industry bodies, comprising:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;House Builders Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National House Builders Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habinteg Housing Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planning Officers Society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction Products Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Control Alliance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Association of Chief Police Officers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UKGBC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Research Establishment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Institute for British Architects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater London Authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the housing standards that the review will consider include the Code for Sustainable Homes, Secured by Design, Lifetime Homes, Standards and Quality in Development and the Homes and Communities Agency’s Housing Quality Indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The review is taking place alongside the review of planning practice guidance which was announced on 16 October 2012, and both groups will be working closely together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/planningandbuilding/pdf/2247429-1.pdf"&gt;Terms of reference for the Housing Standards Review&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 53kb)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comments and enquiries on the review should be emailed to &lt;a href="mailto:housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge was launched by the Prime Minister in April 2011 and is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/housing-and-construction/"&gt;Housing and Construction Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; was open for comment from the 12 January until 17 Febuary 2012. More information can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 10 September the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills announced that through the Red Tape Challenge at least 3,000 of the cross-government regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. By ‘scrapped’, we mean that regulation is completely removed from the statute book. By ‘reduced’, we mean that regulations are reduced in number (e.g. a consolidation, making the rules simpler to find and follow); and/or in terms of the burden they impose (for example: reducing who is caught by the regulation; removing domestic gold-plating of EU law; active renegotiation of EU law; simplifying requirements set by the regulation or in related guidance; or reducing the burden of inspection and enforcement arising from the regulation). Around 1,500 of the 3,000 changes will have a measurable financial benefit for business: this does not include consolidations of regulations without any changes to the content of those regulations. The Red Tape Challenge comprises regulation of UK origin and regulation that transposes EU laws. It does not include legislation or regulations falling within the responsibilities of the devolved administrations, tax and fees legislation or national security matters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9099</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/farmers-should-be-able-to-offer-affordable-homes-on-the-farm"/>
    <title> Farmers should be able to offer affordable homes on the farm</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils should look to amend their existing planning policies to make it easier for disused farm buildings to be converted into affordable homes said Communities Minister Andrew Stunell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average house price in rural England has more than doubled over the past decade to over £250,000, but the average salary is still £21,000. The numbers of people on social housing waiting lists in rural areas has risen to 750,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Mr Stunell has called on farmers to identify disused farm buildings that could be converted into new affordable homes for local people, and for councils to look favourably on their planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fulfils a key Coalition Agreement commitment to enable the building of Homes on the Farm, by encouraging the redevelopment of disused agricultural buildings as new and affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Farmers are the custodians of our countryside, managing thousands of acres of rural land across England. But when they want to make disused buildings available for new homes, they can often face an uphill battle to get planning permission in the face of their council’s development plans.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“As more young people are unable to afford to live in rural areas and village schools, shops and pubs struggle to survive, farmers are ideally placed to help bring the community together to help reverse this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“That’s why I want to make it easier for farmers to offer Homes on the Farm for local people. One small step for councils will offer a significant opportunity for communities to get the new and affordable homes their villages need. I want farmers to take their place at the forefront of this rural revolution alongside their local councils, to make farm buildings available, and to work with their local communities to shape the sustainable development of their countryside so it can remain a vibrant place to live for generations to come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National Farmers Union planning adviser Ivan Moss said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Home on the Farm scheme is an excellent opportunity for farmers who want to use their outbuildings for a constructive purpose. It should also sustain the rural economy by providing homes for those working in it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The NFU will watch with interest the outcomes of the first applications from farmers to their local councils to convert disused buildings into affordable homes and hope that councils will be equally eager to be pioneers in the scheme.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14725</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-self-build-projects-to-benefit-from-multi-million-fund"/>
    <title>First self-build projects to benefit from multi-million fund</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk today said he was delighted that the first applications for a slice of a new £30million self-build investment fund have been earmarked for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a special self-build workshop for local authority Leaders in London, Mr Prisk said that the first projects would benefit from over £1.1million to start work on up to 20 self-build plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following final checks and approvals, the applications in North East Derbyshire and Peterborough will be the first to receive the funding, which provides short-term finance to help unlock projects where groups of self-build homes are built at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister, along with self-build industry champion, architecture specialist and presenter of Channel 4’s Grand Designs Kevin McCloud, hosted the workshop for local authority Leaders in association with the Local Government Association, to discuss how they could support prospective self builders in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specialist team from Almere in the Netherlands also attended to share their expertise. Almere, near Amsterdam, is the largest low-cost self-build experiment in Europe, which has grown rapidly in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year the former Housing Minister travelled to Almere with a delegation from the UK self-build industry, and hosted an event with Dutch Government officials and business leaders at the British Embassy to boost trade and links between Dutch and British businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that there had been a great surge of interest in recent years for self-build, and it was now important that local authorities learnt from abroad and local projects to identify opportunities for self-build development in their plans, and to give people in their area the opportunity to build their own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Across the country, more people than ever want control over the design and build of their home. But these types of projects have often been held back because of limited land availability, reluctance by lenders to provide finance and red tape. So I’m delighted that the first self-build projects in Derbyshire and Peterborough have been earmarked for Government cash.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This money will be repaid as plots are sold, and I hope it will demonstrate to lenders, investors and the development industry that these types of projects are worth backing. But it’s not just about money, self builders and developers need the support of local authorities to get these projects off the ground. So I’m pleased we have the team from Almere to share their expertise, and I urge local authorities to learn from their example and help more self builders achieve their dreams.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin McCloud said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m delighted to attend this event today with the new Housing Minister and welcome the first approvals for cash from the Government’s £30million investment fund which will help drive activity in the sector and give more people the opportunity to build their own home. But it is not just about cash, we need to see more support from local authorities if we’re serious about making self build a mainstream housing option. And I hope we can draw inspiration from the projects like Almere, and many others across Europe, about what is achievable with strong local leadership and vision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval for the first custom build homes funding application with a value of £450,000 has been given to a developer in North East Derbyshire on a site at Morton for nine self-build plots. A second application for 11 self-build plots with a loan value of approximately £725,000 for a site in Peterborough has also been approved. Both approvals are subject to final due diligence and contract.  Details will be available once final due diligence checks have been finalised and contracts agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A further application for funding has been received for a multi-unit self build development on a site in Derbyshire and the Homes and Communities Agency is in discussion with several other project promoters who are seeking to apply for funding with more applications expected before the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the funding Custom Build Homes fund can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/custom-build"&gt;www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/custom-build&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £30million fund will be available over the next three years (2012 to 2015). Funding is available to cover the cost of building, land acquisition or other costs associated with a proposed development of five or more custom build homes with planning permission. The funding is available to eligible applicants bringing forward projects in England with the exception of London.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Separate funding arrangements are available for London. Further details fund can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing/homes-and-communities/build-your-own-home"&gt;www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing/homes-and-communities/build-your-own-home&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laying the Foundations: A Housing Strategy for England&lt;/em&gt; sets out the Government’s plans to support social mobility and get the housing market - and in particular new house building - moving again, including a Custom Build Homes programme to support and encourage more individuals and communities to build their own homes. The Housing Strategy can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/housingstrategy2011"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/housingstrategy2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13418</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/newbuy-guarantee-scheme-statistics-january-to-june-2012"/>
    <title>NewBuy guarantee scheme statistics: January to June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first release of official statistics concerning the NewBuy Guarantee scheme was released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority’s code of practice on 27 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics on the NewBuy Guarantee scheme cover quarterly and cumulative data for England up to 30 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release sets out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total Completions&lt;/strong&gt; (number of properties purchased under the scheme);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Government’s Contingent Liability&lt;/strong&gt; (the maximum possible cost to government as a result of government’s provision of a guarantee corresponding to these completions); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Government’s Total Costs&lt;/strong&gt; (the amount spent by government to date in payment of claims made by mortgage lenders against this guarantee).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
