<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Increasing the number of available homes"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15967</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/house-building-in-england-july-to-september-2012"/>
    <title>House building in England: July to September 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on house building in England were released on 15 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics in this release present figures on new build housing starts and completions in England. Figures for the UK and constituent countries are also available in the accompanying tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics report on the period July to September 2012 and update those previously released on 16 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the latest release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted house building starts in England increased by 18% and stood at 25,760 in the September quarter 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted completions fell, down 7% to 27,060 in the September quarter 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Private enterprise housing starts (seasonally adjusted) were 15% higher in the September quarter 2012 than the previous quarter, whilst starts by housing associations were 23% higher.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted private enterprise completions fell by 6% and housing association completions fell by 14% from the previous quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonally adjusted starts are now 52% above the trough in the March quarter 2009 but 45% below the December quarter 2005 peak. Completions are 44% below their March quarter 2007 peak.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annual housing starts totalled 98,020 in the 12 months to September 2012, down by 9% compared with the year before. Annual housing completions in England reached 117,190 in the 12 months to September 2012, an increase of 6% compared with the previous 12 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14476</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14743</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/independent-panel-to-help-government-cut-housebuilding-red-tape-and-boost-growth"/>
    <title>Independent panel to help government cut housebuilding red tape and boost growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today launched a new independent group of building industry experts, tasked with simplifying the mass of rules imposed on developers and housebuilders, to make them easier to understand and follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Government’s Red Tape Challenge Ministers have made clear they want to do everything possible to remove unnecessary burdens and bureaucracy imposed on developers to get much needed new homes built, and support economic growth.  The current, complex system of building regulations and housing standards will be targeted by a new Independent Challenge Panel, which will consider how these requirements work together and what potential there is to free up the system and make it work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel will for the first time bring independent experts together with government and it will report to ministers in spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mr Foster also made clear that essential safety and accessibility protections will remain untouched and that homes will always need to be built to high sustainability and quality standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="housing-standards-review"&gt;Housing standards review&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the hundreds of standards that can be applied to new-build homes, some of which duplicate each other, a separate group will work alongside the new Challenge Panel to consider the specific issue of standards applied to housebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some of these standards are applied nationally across certain types of homes such as affordable housing, others are made mandatory by individual councils for building in their area and some are entirely voluntary - resulting in confusion for local people and developers. Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The requirement for two phone lines in home offices, irrespective of need and in addition to broadband connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rules on window sizes that include a ‘dirty window factor’ - imposing bigger windows to allow for dirt on them, rather than assuming people will simply clean their windows&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A requirement that ‘drying space’ is designed and assessed when often this is nothing more complicated than a washing line over a bath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflicting guidance on how to construct safe and accessible stairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards being assessed repeatedly by different people - such as planners, code assessors, building control officers - often looking at the same issues  but coming up with different answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This new review, led by DCLG and to be conducted by a group of industry representatives, will look to avoid overlap and duplication in the system, helping ensure builders meet the high standards that aspiring homeowners rightly expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The current array of different housing standards used in different parts the country is complex and counter-productive: confusing local residents, councillors and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is why an urgent review has now started, bringing the government together with housebuilders, planners, councils and architects to establish what the unnecessary measures are that we can cut out of the system, whilst ensuring buildings are still made to exacting standards.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I want to see a simpler set of housing standards that people can easily understand and that free up developers and councils to get on with the job of building the high quality new homes we so badly to get more first time buyers and families onto the housing ladder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review was part of the government’s housing and growth strategy announced on 6 September.  It will result in a clear plan of action by next spring that will be put out to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Independent Challenge Panel members are:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy Von Bradsky (architect)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Clements (building control)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Watson (planner)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kirk Archibald (developer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DCLG is chairing and leading the housing standards review and has convened a group of members from representative industry bodies, comprising:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;House Builders Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National House Builders Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habinteg Housing Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planning Officers Society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction Products Association&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Control Alliance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Association of Chief Police Officers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UKGBC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Research Establishment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Institute for British Architects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater London Authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the housing standards that the review will consider include the Code for Sustainable Homes, Secured by Design, Lifetime Homes, Standards and Quality in Development and the Homes and Communities Agency’s Housing Quality Indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The review is taking place alongside the review of planning practice guidance which was announced on 16 October 2012, and both groups will be working closely together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/planningandbuilding/pdf/2247429-1.pdf"&gt;Terms of reference for the Housing Standards Review&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 53kb)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comments and enquiries on the review should be emailed to &lt;a href="mailto:housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge was launched by the Prime Minister in April 2011 and is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/housing-and-construction/"&gt;Housing and Construction Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; was open for comment from the 12 January until 17 Febuary 2012. More information can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 10 September the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills announced that through the Red Tape Challenge at least 3,000 of the cross-government regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. By ‘scrapped’, we mean that regulation is completely removed from the statute book. By ‘reduced’, we mean that regulations are reduced in number (e.g. a consolidation, making the rules simpler to find and follow); and/or in terms of the burden they impose (for example: reducing who is caught by the regulation; removing domestic gold-plating of EU law; active renegotiation of EU law; simplifying requirements set by the regulation or in related guidance; or reducing the burden of inspection and enforcement arising from the regulation). Around 1,500 of the 3,000 changes will have a measurable financial benefit for business: this does not include consolidations of regulations without any changes to the content of those regulations. The Red Tape Challenge comprises regulation of UK origin and regulation that transposes EU laws. It does not include legislation or regulations falling within the responsibilities of the devolved administrations, tax and fees legislation or national security matters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9099</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/farmers-should-be-able-to-offer-affordable-homes-on-the-farm"/>
    <title> Farmers should be able to offer affordable homes on the farm</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils should look to amend their existing planning policies to make it easier for disused farm buildings to be converted into affordable homes said Communities Minister Andrew Stunell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average house price in rural England has more than doubled over the past decade to over £250,000, but the average salary is still £21,000. The numbers of people on social housing waiting lists in rural areas has risen to 750,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Mr Stunell has called on farmers to identify disused farm buildings that could be converted into new affordable homes for local people, and for councils to look favourably on their planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fulfils a key Coalition Agreement commitment to enable the building of Homes on the Farm, by encouraging the redevelopment of disused agricultural buildings as new and affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Farmers are the custodians of our countryside, managing thousands of acres of rural land across England. But when they want to make disused buildings available for new homes, they can often face an uphill battle to get planning permission in the face of their council’s development plans.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“As more young people are unable to afford to live in rural areas and village schools, shops and pubs struggle to survive, farmers are ideally placed to help bring the community together to help reverse this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“That’s why I want to make it easier for farmers to offer Homes on the Farm for local people. One small step for councils will offer a significant opportunity for communities to get the new and affordable homes their villages need. I want farmers to take their place at the forefront of this rural revolution alongside their local councils, to make farm buildings available, and to work with their local communities to shape the sustainable development of their countryside so it can remain a vibrant place to live for generations to come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National Farmers Union planning adviser Ivan Moss said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Home on the Farm scheme is an excellent opportunity for farmers who want to use their outbuildings for a constructive purpose. It should also sustain the rural economy by providing homes for those working in it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The NFU will watch with interest the outcomes of the first applications from farmers to their local councils to convert disused buildings into affordable homes and hope that councils will be equally eager to be pioneers in the scheme.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14725</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-self-build-projects-to-benefit-from-multi-million-fund"/>
    <title>First self-build projects to benefit from multi-million fund</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk today said he was delighted that the first applications for a slice of a new £30million self-build investment fund have been earmarked for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a special self-build workshop for local authority Leaders in London, Mr Prisk said that the first projects would benefit from over £1.1million to start work on up to 20 self-build plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following final checks and approvals, the applications in North East Derbyshire and Peterborough will be the first to receive the funding, which provides short-term finance to help unlock projects where groups of self-build homes are built at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister, along with self-build industry champion, architecture specialist and presenter of Channel 4’s Grand Designs Kevin McCloud, hosted the workshop for local authority Leaders in association with the Local Government Association, to discuss how they could support prospective self builders in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specialist team from Almere in the Netherlands also attended to share their expertise. Almere, near Amsterdam, is the largest low-cost self-build experiment in Europe, which has grown rapidly in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year the former Housing Minister travelled to Almere with a delegation from the UK self-build industry, and hosted an event with Dutch Government officials and business leaders at the British Embassy to boost trade and links between Dutch and British businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that there had been a great surge of interest in recent years for self-build, and it was now important that local authorities learnt from abroad and local projects to identify opportunities for self-build development in their plans, and to give people in their area the opportunity to build their own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Across the country, more people than ever want control over the design and build of their home. But these types of projects have often been held back because of limited land availability, reluctance by lenders to provide finance and red tape. So I’m delighted that the first self-build projects in Derbyshire and Peterborough have been earmarked for Government cash.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This money will be repaid as plots are sold, and I hope it will demonstrate to lenders, investors and the development industry that these types of projects are worth backing. But it’s not just about money, self builders and developers need the support of local authorities to get these projects off the ground. So I’m pleased we have the team from Almere to share their expertise, and I urge local authorities to learn from their example and help more self builders achieve their dreams.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin McCloud said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m delighted to attend this event today with the new Housing Minister and welcome the first approvals for cash from the Government’s £30million investment fund which will help drive activity in the sector and give more people the opportunity to build their own home. But it is not just about cash, we need to see more support from local authorities if we’re serious about making self build a mainstream housing option. And I hope we can draw inspiration from the projects like Almere, and many others across Europe, about what is achievable with strong local leadership and vision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval for the first custom build homes funding application with a value of £450,000 has been given to a developer in North East Derbyshire on a site at Morton for nine self-build plots. A second application for 11 self-build plots with a loan value of approximately £725,000 for a site in Peterborough has also been approved. Both approvals are subject to final due diligence and contract.  Details will be available once final due diligence checks have been finalised and contracts agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A further application for funding has been received for a multi-unit self build development on a site in Derbyshire and the Homes and Communities Agency is in discussion with several other project promoters who are seeking to apply for funding with more applications expected before the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the funding Custom Build Homes fund can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/custom-build"&gt;www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/custom-build&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £30million fund will be available over the next three years (2012 to 2015). Funding is available to cover the cost of building, land acquisition or other costs associated with a proposed development of five or more custom build homes with planning permission. The funding is available to eligible applicants bringing forward projects in England with the exception of London.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Separate funding arrangements are available for London. Further details fund can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing/homes-and-communities/build-your-own-home"&gt;www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing/homes-and-communities/build-your-own-home&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laying the Foundations: A Housing Strategy for England&lt;/em&gt; sets out the Government’s plans to support social mobility and get the housing market - and in particular new house building - moving again, including a Custom Build Homes programme to support and encourage more individuals and communities to build their own homes. The Housing Strategy can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/housingstrategy2011"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/housingstrategy2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13418</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/newbuy-guarantee-scheme-statistics-january-to-june-2012"/>
    <title>NewBuy guarantee scheme statistics: January to June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first release of official statistics concerning the NewBuy Guarantee scheme was released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority’s code of practice on 27 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics on the NewBuy Guarantee scheme cover quarterly and cumulative data for England up to 30 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release sets out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total Completions&lt;/strong&gt; (number of properties purchased under the scheme);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Government’s Contingent Liability&lt;/strong&gt; (the maximum possible cost to government as a result of government’s provision of a guarantee corresponding to these completions); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Government’s Total Costs&lt;/strong&gt; (the amount spent by government to date in payment of claims made by mortgage lenders against this guarantee).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14710</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/councils-seeing-benefits-of-reducing-numbers-of-empty-homes"/>
    <title>Councils seeing benefits of reducing numbers of empty homes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bringing thousands of empty homes back into use has unlocked over £63million additional funding that is directly benefiting local communities through the successful New Homes Bonus scheme, Communities Minister Don Foster revealed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a further move towards greater Government transparency, the figures showed which councils have made the biggest reduction in empty homes and the New Homes Bonus that they will have received for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, local authorities have brought nearly 38,000 long-term empty homes back into use over the past two years - helping to tackle the housing shortage and providing a roof over the heads of hard working families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top five local authorities that have seen the biggest reduction in empty homes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Birmingham, which has brought 2,151 empty homes back into use, along with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manchester, 2,118 homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bradford, 1,944 homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liverpool, 1,855 homes, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salford, 1,582 homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the release of the figures, Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This information, shown in this way for the first time, lets people see how their councils are embracing the New Homes Bonus by examining their empty housing stock and turning it back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I’m delighted we’ve had such a positive start and encourage all councils to work hard in transforming empty properties, which drag down neighbourhoods, and instead turn them into homes fit for families.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“By making councils accountable to their residents, not to Whitehall, we are ensuring local tax-payers have the ability to check that money is being spent efficiently and decisions taken for the benefit of the communities they serve.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s powerful and innovative New Homes Bonus scheme rewards councils who increase their housing stock, either by building new homes or converting empty properties back into use, by match funding the additional council tax raised, with an additional amount for affordable homes, for the following six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has meant that communities are seeing the benefits of growth for the first time - in stark contrast to the previous, top-down system of regional housing targets which Ministers argue pitted neighbourhoods against developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information on New Homes Bonus can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/housing/housingsupply/newhomesbonus/"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/housing/housingsupply/newhomesbonus/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The statistics showing the reduction in the number of empty properties and subsequent New Homes Bonus for each local authority can be found in the table here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/housing/xls/2226017.xls"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/housing/xls/2226017.xls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13385</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:35:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/housing-and-growth--5"/>
    <title>Housing and growth</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission, Mr Speaker, I would like to make a statement on housing and planning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the coalition government inherited a legacy where house building had fallen to its lowest rates since the 1920s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a top-down planning system that built nothing but resentment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a regime of regional planning quangos that created paralysis and confrontation -  after 6 years of preparation, by the general election, less than 60 councils had completed local plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result was no development. No regeneration. No community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government wants to get the economy growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remove unnecessary red tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support locally led sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November, the government published a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; to support a thriving, active and stable housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, we published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to condense 1,000 pages of central planning guidance to just 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housebuilding is up: 29% higher in 2011 than in 2009. But there is more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, my department is announcing a further series of common sense measures to promote house building and support locally-led economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technical details are laid out in a written statement which has been laid before the House. I will summarise the key points for Hon Members:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;following on from &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/11300/2204242.pdf" title="Review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes"&gt;Sir Adrian Montague’s independent report (PDF 272 KB)&lt;/a&gt; on supporting the private rented sector, we are providing £200 million of new funding to support institutional investment in high-quality rented homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thanks to the action we have taken to tackle the last government’s deficit, we are passing on the lower costs of borrowing. We will be issuing a debt guarantee for up to £10 billion to support private investment in the private rented sector and in new affordable housing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will support up to an additional 15,000 affordable homes through the use of loan guarantees, flexibilities and capital funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we also intend to extend our successful refurbishment programme to bring an additional 5,000 existing empty homes back into use. The last government wanted to demolish Victorian terraces with John Prescott’s Pathfinder programme. By contrast, we are getting homes back into productive use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in total we will invest another £300 million in these measures to support new affordable homes and bring empty homes into use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we actively want to support home ownership, which fell under the last Parliament despite a Labour pledge to increase it by a million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are extending our successful FirstBuy scheme for first time buyers, with an additional £280 million of funding, helping up to 16,500 additional first-time buyers to purchase a home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to free up more brownfield land for development and regeneration, we will accelerate the release of surplus public sector land and empty offices through a targeted programme of transfers from other government bodies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will work with local authorities and developers to unlock locally supported large sites. Just last week, we were back to unblock the Eastern Quarry in the Ebbsfleet Valley - a major ex-industrial site that had stalled for a decade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are working with local communities and councils. But some councils need to raise their game, by failing to make planning decisions in a timely way. Planning delays create uncertainty both for local residents and local firms. So we will introduce a series of practical measures to help speed up planning decisions and appeals, and major infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some complex developments take time to assemble. So we are allowing for developers to extend the duration of existing planning permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are making it easier for developers to change unrealistic Section 106 agreements. A development which isn’t built means no Section 106 payments. Common sense reforms will result in more regeneration, more housing and more community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable development should go hand in hand with environmental safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can confirm that we have protected the Green Belt, in line with our commitment in the coalition agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always the case that councils can amend local Green Belt boundaries should they wish - and we will support councils which choose to. This can include introducing new Green Belt protection around new large developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is considerable previously developed land in many Green Belt areas. We encourage councils to make best use of this land, whilst protecting the openness of the Green Belt in line with the requirements of the National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to protect our countryside, we need to focus more growth in our town centres. So we are introducing measures to make it easier to turn empty commercial buildings into housing. Our high streets will benefit from a greater resident population, increasing footfall and supporting local shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nation, we have great pride in our homes. We want to make it easier for families to undertake home improvements - such as building a new conservatory. So we will be seeking to simplify and increase permitted development rights for householders. Cutting back municipal red tape in this way could provide a particular boost for small traders and small builders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, these practical measures build on the housing, local government finance and planning reforms already in play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving more power to individuals, to communities, to councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing new incentives to support local shops, local firms and local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering sustainable development and getting Britain building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14695</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"/>
    <title>Plan to boost British housebuilding, jobs and the economy</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister, alongside the Communities Secretary Eric Pickles, set out a major housing and planning package that will help deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to 70,000 new homes, including affordable housing and opportunities for first-time buyers to get onto the housing ladder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;140,000 jobs and a boost to the construction sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£40 billion guarantee for major infrastructure projects and £10 billion for new homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This includes a series of measures aimed at supporting businesses, developers and first-time buyers, while slashing unnecessary red tape across the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removing restrictions on house builders to help unlock 75,000 homes currently stalled due to sites being commercially unviable. Developers who can prove that council’s costly affordable housing requirements make the project unviable will see them removed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New legislation for Government guarantees of up to £40 billion worth of major infrastructure projects and up to £10 billion of new homes. The Infrastructure (Financial Assistance) Bill will include guaranteeing the debt of Housing Associations and private sector developers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up to 15,000 affordable homes and bring 5,000 empty homes back into use using new capital funding of £300m and the infrastructure guarantee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An additional 5,000 homes built for rent at market rates in line with proposals outlined in Sir Adrian Montague’s report to Government on boosting the private rented sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thousands of big commercial and residential applications to be directed to a major infrastructure fast track and where councils are poor at processing decisions developers can opt to have their decision taken by the Planning Inspectorate. More applications also will go into a fast track appeal process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16,500 first-time buyers helped with a £280m extension of the successful ‘FirstBuy’ scheme, which offers aspiring homeowners a much-needed deposit and a crucial first step on the housing ladder.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For a time limited period, slashing planning red tape, including sweeping away the rules and bureaucracy that prevent families and businesses from making improvements to their properties, helping tens of thousands of home owners and companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The measures announced today show this Government is serious about rolling its sleeves up and doing it all it can to kick-start the economy. Some of the proposals are controversial; others have been a long time in coming. But along with our Housing Strategy, they provide a comprehensive plan to unleash one of the biggest homebuilding programmes this country has seen in a generation. That means more investment around the county; more jobs for our people; and more young families able to realise their dreams and get on the housing ladder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is a Coalition Government, determined to get on with the job of delivering a healthier economy.Today’s major boost to housing and planning will make it easier to build a home, easier to buy a first home and easier to extend a home. A boost that will get Britain building again. Building thousands of affordable homes and generating thousands of new jobs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This Government wants to get the economy growing. To remove unnecessary red tape. To support locally-led sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Today we are announcing a further series of common sense measures to promote house building, speed up planning decisions and appeals, and major infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“These practical measures build on the housing, local government finance and planning reforms already in play. Delivering sustainable development and getting Britain building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14693</id>
    <published>2012-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/common-sense-planning-reform-to-create-more-homes-and-boost-the-high-street"/>
    <title>Common sense planning reform to create more homes and boost the high street</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has approved a new measure that will increase the number of homes in town centres and help increase footfall on high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New planning rights will allow more flats to be created above shops without the need for planning permission. Two flats will be allowed to be created in office or storage space under new permitted development rights coming into force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change further streamlines the planning system, making it easier, quicker and cheaper for people to create new homes in existing underused space. It has the potential to help increase the amount of affordable housing and ensures better use is made of existing developed land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relaxing planning restrictions on creating flats above shops can also help increase the vitality of town centres by increasing footfall and providing a boost to high street regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These are common sense planning reforms that will deliver more affordable homes in areas where there are good transport links whilst ensuring better use of existing developed land.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Cutting this red tape should be a shot in the arm for the high street increasing footfall and providing a boost to regeneration.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Greg Clark Mr Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Government is determined to make the very best use of existing buildings to provide more homes as quickly and simply as possible. This change offers real potential to provide more affordable housing and give a much needed boost to our high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Ensuring unused space above shops can be used in a better way is one of the many changes the Government has introduced to streamline the planning system and to cut unnecessary bureaucracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already taken steps to improve the planning system through the National Planning Policy Framework and the Localism Act, which are already delivering results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also announced proposed measures to simplify the planning system further by making it easier to temporarily re-use some buildings without needing planning permission, streamlining the paper work needed for planning applications and speeding up planning appeal decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has also outlined a package of measures to help high streets reclaim their role at the heart of our communities. These include encouraging town centres to become Town Team partners to benefit from the support and advice available from the Government and leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The change in permitted development rights applies to A1 (retail units) and A2 (financial/professional services units) commercial properties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current legislation only allows for one flat to be created above a shop without the need for a planning application.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new permitted development rights will come into force on 1 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
