<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/34108</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T12:36:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-reduction-scheme-taking-account-of-universal-credit-income"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax reduction scheme - taking account of universal credit income</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In October 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government published a document setting out how the default scheme will take account of claimants receiving universal credit, and how these measures will help to support positive work incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to feedback from interested parties, this document now provides some worked examples of how default scheme universal credit provisions operate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:55:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T16:10:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17739</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T18:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets--2"/>
    <title>Community Budgets</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I don’t want to talk about the ins and outs of community budgets, or the finer points of cost benefit analysis. I want to talk about their impact on people’s lives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why it’s a scandal that agencies in Doncaster, faced with more than 100 events involving children, failed to co-ordinate any realistic attempt to prevent what happened in the Edlington case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why so few children are getting their teeth checked in parts of Newcastle, that more and more are ending up having emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why in West Cheshire 1 woman faced 30 incidents of domestic abuse before feeling able to turn to an agency that might help her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to talk about my own area, Essex, and why some people still feel able to let a young father from that neck of the woods get caught up in a Kafkaesque nightmare - “Meeting upon meeting with different organisations” - just to get a bit of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that these are the types of service failure that the pilots themselves are addressing. Because if these initiatives were just about money, we’d rightly be accused of a lack of ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, we’re all having to live with less. And, given the waste, given the inefficiency, given the duplication that went on before, the purpose of this is to use less to deliver a better service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t just looking for these pilots to just patch things up. To mend and make do. To think about ‘service improvement’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people-at-the-centre-of-the-system"&gt;People at the centre of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems. Even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m glad to see that is what has been happening. The tri-borough initiative - part of the Whole-Place pilots - is proposing to reduce unplanned admissions to hospital. Putting the donkey work into helping older people with longer term conditions before they get to an acute stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got the greater Manchester pilot working with parents of children at risk so they don’t pass on the bad habits likely to hold kids back for the rest of their lives. The idea to ensure kids get a fresh start and can stand at the school gates on their first day ready with great excitement to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve got pioneers in West Cheshire making sure families with complex needs now have an advocate who’s going to stick with them through thick and thin. Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family at a staggering cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets. But we’ve worked out, if you get people together in a room - if you focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the re-offenders, the long-term unemployed and all those with dependencies - you can usually start taking dependence out the system. You can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth so they can lead independent lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re going to keep working with these 4 areas to make sure our plans really are do-able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we’re going to help other areas to learn from their experience. We know our colleagues across government are up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the way we’ve managed to bridge the old Whitehall, local government, voluntary sector fault lines has been one of the great success stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier on today we heard Norman Lamb speak about the pilot’s positive approach to health and social care integration. And we’re working with the Treasury, Work and Pensions, Education, Home Office and the Ministry of Justice to ensure we’re all on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="neighbourhoods-on-track"&gt;Neighbourhoods on track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know, as we’ve heard today, that our neighbourhood community budgets are on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ilfracombe to Haverhill they’re making sure their communities are involved in making the most of their resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critically, local folk are backing them. 89% of people surveyed in Poplar felt citizens should ‘do their bit’. While more than half wanted to be involved in turning their neighbourhood around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we’re seeing community budgets turning their irrepressible energy, their boundless enthusiasm, to that eternal question of reducing waste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilfracombe, for example, knows that nationally an estimated £300 million per year of NHS money is wasted through over prescription of medication. Imagine all those pills and potions sitting in the cupboard never being taken away. So Ilfracombe is tracking down that waste with the help of its local people to stop the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because what’s driving Ilfracombe, what’s driving us all is the priceless prize for getting this right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just savings of millions of pounds, but hearing from the young girl of the father in Essex I mentioned earlier talking about how she’s been; “changed… around”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing from the man who’d fallen on hard times describe how, by becoming a mentor, he now has; “something to get up for to make him feel better about himself that he is helping others”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is more than money. It is the prize. And the prize relates to people. There’s a real opportunity here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said it was brave, fool hardly, silly even, to try this. They said it was bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve been really impressed with how all the different organisations have risen to the challenge. We’ve always known these problems existed. Now we have the chance to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what fires you up and me up and Bob up is not the cost benefit analysis. It is the fact we can make a difference to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a noble cause. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just a case of government knows best. People must understand they too have a sense of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t lose that fire in your belly. Be innovative, be bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and I can make a difference. And together you and I will set us on course to make a difference for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17266</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:36:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-guidance-note-on-administrative-matters"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: guidance note on administrative matters </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The administrative elements will in future operate under existing Council Tax provisions in the Local Government Finance Act and related regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This note will provide clarity for local authorities on how some administrative elements will be dealt with under these provisions, where these are not covered in the Default Scheme and Prescribed Requirements Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16974</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-funding-arrangements"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: funding arrangements</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions for local council tax support schemes in England. This document sets out how the Government intends to distribute funding to support local schemes and seeks views on possible adjustments to allocations to avoid potential budgetary pressures in a few authorities. It is published alongside statements of intent for the key sets of regulations which will provide the legal framework for local schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16882</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:46:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/housing-capital-receipts-exemptions-from-regulations"/>
    <title>Housing capital receipts: exemptions from regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of receipts arising from the disposal of housing assets (ie assets held under part 2 of the Housing Act 1985 and for which account is made in the Housing Revenue Account) is governed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/1324/made"&gt;Local Authorities (Capital Finance and Accounting) (England) Regulations 2003 (as amended.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations require that, in short: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receipts arising from Right to Buy (and similar sales may be retained to cover the cost of transacting the sales and to cover the debt on the properties sold, but a proportion of the remainder must be surrendered to central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receipts arising from all other disposals may be retained in full provided they are spent on affordable housing, regeneration or the paying down of housing debt (each of which is defined in the regulations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, section 11(6) of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents"&gt;Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; (as inserted by section 174 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;) permits the secretary of state to enter into agreements with local authorities with the effect that any requirement imposed by these regulations does not apply, or is modified in its application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enter into such an agreement it is necessary for any interested authority to make an application to the secretary of state. This guidance sets out the Department for Communities and Local Government’s policy on such exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16664</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:24:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-rewards-for-local-growth-under-new-scheme"/>
    <title>Greater rewards for local growth under new scheme</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; creates a new model for funding local authorities from April 2013, linking their financial revenue to the decisions they take to support local firms and local jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government will retain a 50% local share of business rates and then keep a 50% share of any growth they generate, subject to a levy, providing a strong incentive to go for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new system could deliver around an extra £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020, and generate more business rate income for councils to help pay off the deficit and support frontline services that protect vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following consultation responses, the government has changed the approach to the levy to increase the rewards for growth. The maximum levy will now be 50p in the pound. This translates into very real benefits for authorities: after the central share and levy payments, at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document also confirms the safety net for when councils experience unexpected drops in revenue will guarantee a real terms income from business rates of 92.5%. This means council income will never fall below 7.5% of its baseline funding level ensuring no area gets left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document confirms that the government will implement the majority of the technical proposals for the operation of the scheme set out in the summer consultation, together with changes to a number of detailed aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, after listening to councils, we are setting the central principles for how the new rate retention scheme will work next year. Ahead of the formal funding settlement next month this will give councils the certainty and security to begin planning their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The old flawed system of government handouts to local authorities encouraged a begging bowl mentality, with each council vying to be more deprived than its neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These reforms allow councils to stand tall, and rewards them for supporting local jobs and local firms. All councils, including the least prosperous, have the opportunity to gain from this system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation originally proposed a levy set at higher ratio. This would have meant that a district council with a business rates baseline of £100 million and a baseline funding level of £5 million would have been subject to a levy rate of 95p in the pound. So if the authority realised business rates growth of £2 million, £1 million of this would have been paid to the central share, £200,000 would have been paid to the county council, and £760,000 would have been paid in a levy, leaving the authority with £40,000 of growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s document confirms that levy rate will in fact be limited to 50p in the pound creating a much greater growth reward. This would leave that same authority with £400,000, ie 10 times more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;Business rates retention: policy statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/a-plain-english-guide-to-business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention: plain English guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"&gt;Written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
