<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-13T13:43:56+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15179</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T13:43:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:43:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships--2"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on how to remove the barriers preventing local government pension scheme funds from investing in infrastructure projects and proposes two clear options for change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15610</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:23:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates--2"/>
    <title>Business rates</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 October, the government announced our intention to postpone the next business rates revaluation in England from 2015 to 2017. Clause 22 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; currently before the House of Commons will deliver upon this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recent Westminster Hall debate on business rates and during the second reading debate on the Bill, ministers committed to provide more information on the analysis which has informed the government’s position to assist parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full assessment would require a revaluation, which in itself would cost £43 million and take a significant amount of time. However, the Valuation Office Agency have today published their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/corporate/News/2012/newsRelease_November_2012.html"&gt;high level estimates of non-domestic rental and rating assessment movements for England&lt;/a&gt; as at January 2012; it provides an illustration of the potential impact those rateable values would have had on business rate bills. The Agency’s analysis is based on professional judgements informed by limited rental market evidence up to January 2012. The analysis has been prepared independently of ministers and published in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last revaluation was based on April 2008 valuations and rents set at the height of an unsustainable property boom. Since then, the economy and property market have faced exceptional changes. Rents have fallen since that property boom. Some groups have assumed that falling business rents would entail falling business rates. However, this is not the case. While aggregate rateable values have fallen, this would automatically be offset at the revaluation by a higher rating multiplier. Firms would just be required to pay a higher proportion of their rateable value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency’s estimates are based on an increase in the multiplier of 16%. My department has actually forecast an increase of 20%, as a consequence of inflation and the adjustment required to the multiplier for appeals; in this context, in practice, the losers would be likely to be even greater than those presented in the Agency’s paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Agency’s analysis suggests that 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates at a 2015 revaluation. This compares to 300,000 seeing reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectors would have faced big hikes including petrol stations (+28% tax paid), the self-catering industry such as caravan parks (+29% paid), hotels (+6% tax paid), theatres (+25% tax paid), and pubs (+11% tax paid). The retail sector overall would have seen a tax rise of 1% above inflation, and food retail and convenience stores in particular would have faced significant tax increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given business rates are the third biggest outgoing for local firms after staff and rent, such changes would invariably feed through to more expensive prices for family’s weekly shop, more expensive pints in pubs and a significant hit on Britain’s tourism trade. Indeed, as Community Pubs Minister, I am very aware of the concern expressed by honourable members on the pressures being faced by local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revaluations should be revenue-neutral, and equally, postponing the revaluation will be revenue-neutral. Overall the revaluation would not change the total business rates paid in England, so some sectors and locations would have seen reductions at 2015. During recent parliamentary exchanges, it was unfairly suggested that that this change was being done to assist southern parts of England at the expense of other parts of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that offices in central London would have seen by far the greatest reductions in tax paid if the 2015 revaluation had gone ahead (a fall in aggregate rateable value that is one of the reasons why the multiplier has to be increased by so much to make up for the lost revenue). There are complex variations by both locality and by sector in different parts of the country, but what is clear is that there would be far more losers than winners across the country as a whole. In making this decision, ministers are seeking to support the national interest and the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that as a very direct form of taxation, business rates are not popular. Local government finance is too often opaque and confusing. However, we are acting in an open and transparent manner. This independent evidence shows that by postponing the 2015 revaluation, we will protect local firms and local shops from sharp changes in business rates bills at a time when we want to ensure the economy is growing. It will provide business with a stable economic environment in which to invest and support jobs for the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the document will be placed in the Library together with a copy of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"&gt;Impact Assessment for the Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12868</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T10:27:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T10:27:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on how to remove the barriers preventing local government pension scheme funds from investing in infrastructure projects and proposes two clear options for change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12425</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T10:23:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/town-hall-pension-changes-could-unlock-up-to-22-billion-for-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Town hall pension changes could unlock up to £22 billion for infrastructure</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be free to pump as much as £22 billon more of pension fund investments into infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supporting the government’s ambitions to build more homes, roads or high speed railway under proposals announced by local government secretary Eric Pickles today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships" title="local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships - consultation"&gt;proposals&lt;/a&gt; would potentially allow councils to double the amount they can legally invest from their pension funds directly into key infrastructure projects in a new and more efficient way that ensures long-term value for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment in infrastructure is a vital part of the government’s economic growth strategy. Innovative approaches that increase the amount of finance available for projects are needed to back ambitions for the economy and to help manage the inherited deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local government pension scheme for England and Wales is administered by 89 separate local funds that hold combined investment assets worth £150 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pension fund rules are there to make sure investment risks are spread across different types of investments to give taxpayers long-term protection. Fund managers are currently limited in the amount they can invest via partnership arrangements, which includes many types of infrastructure investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals published for consultation today include an option to increase the current limit of 15% to 30%. This would clear the barriers standing in the way of better council investment giving them the scope to inject up to £45 billion in such arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Unlocking town hall pension pots so they can be used to invest in vital infrastructure projects is a common sense decision that will help this country complete on a global scale and get Britain building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By lifting the restrictions controlling local pension investments councils could pump a further £22 billion directly into job-creating infrastructure projects that will boost our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is potentially a huge development and investment opportunity we simply cannot afford to ignore that also allows us to maintain long-term value for money for the taxpayer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report by the Future Homes Commission said council pension funds could be used to build key infrastructure projects like new homes in the UK without increasing the government deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment decisions remain for individual local pension funds, which have a duty to protect the local council taxpayers, and local services and to ensure that there are no conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14747</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Minister praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a visit to Wiltshire Council Baroness Hanham saw first-hand the significant achievements made by the council whose trailblazing assets management strategies are protecting frontline services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and state of the art library which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medalist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medalists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torch bearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will save Wilstshire’s council tax payers at least £85 million. As two thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images from Baroness Hanham’s visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631902676938/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15726</id>
    <published>2011-10-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:27:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-capital-expenditure-and-receipts-in-england-2010-to-2011-final-outturn"/>
    <title>Local authority capital expenditure and receipts in England: 2010 to 2011 final outturn</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The national statistics on the final outturn figures of local authority capital expenditure and receipts in the financial year April 2010 to March 2011. These were released on 21 October 2011 under arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistical release includes data from 2006 to 2007 up to 2010 to 2011 and incorporates minor changes to the aggregate figures. It provides additional annexes which were not in the second provisional outturn published on 8 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;capital expenditure by local authorities in England rose to £23.1 billion in 2010 to 2011, a year-on-year increase of 8%, due mainly to the &lt;abbr title="Greater London Authority"&gt;GLA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s expenditure via Transport for London (TfL)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the &lt;abbr title="Greater London Authority"&gt;GLA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s expenditure was excluded from the England totals, then capital expenditure was unchanged from 2009 to 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capital expenditure has risen by nearly 42% in the last four years, nearly 28% in real terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capital receipts were unchanged in 2010 to 2011, at £1.5 billion, from 2009 to 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15899</id>
    <published>2010-10-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:29:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-capital-expenditure-and-receipts-in-england-2009-to-2010-final-outturn-revised"/>
    <title>Local authority capital expenditure and receipts in England: 2009 to 2010 final outturn (revised)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;National statistics on final outturn local authority capital expenditure and receipts in the financial year April 2009 to March 2010 were originally released on 28 October 2010 under arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. A revised version has been released under arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority, incorporating amendments made by four local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total capital expenditure has increased by 0.07 per cent. Capital receipts remain the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main points from the latest release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the underlying trend in capital expenditure shows an increase of 8% from 2008-09 to 2009-10, to £21.4 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capital expenditure has risen by 28% in the last four years, nearly 16% in real terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capital receipts remain well below the 2007-08 level, at £1.4 billion - this reflects a drop in the sale of assets by local authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the in-year capital receipts of £1.4 billion were more than offset by the use of £1.6 billion of capital receipts to finance expenditure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Greater London Authority (GLA) accounts for £3.2 billion (nearly 15%) of total capital expenditure in 2009-10; £2.7 billion of this is the expenditure of Transport for London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15863</id>
    <published>2010-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:18:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-capital-expenditure-and-financing-in-england-2007-to-2008-individual-local-authority-data"/>
    <title>Local authority capital expenditure and financing in England: 2007 to 2008 individual local authority data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data in these spreadsheets have been used to compile the final outturn estimates of local authority capital expenditure and financing for the financial year April 2007 to March 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of the original final outturn statistical release in 20 November 2008, the data in these spreadsheets have been revised (on 31 December 2008).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
