<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60020</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:33:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-finance-settlement-oral-statement"/>
    <title>Local government finance settlement oral statement</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission Mr Speaker, I should like to make a statement on finance for English local authorities for 2013 to 2014 and 2014 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement sets out how the coalition government is putting our public finances back on track [political content removed].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has shown great skill in reducing its budgets. Committed local authorities have protected front line services. Little wonder then that at a time of retrenchment satisfaction in council services has gone up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s settlement will see council expenditure fall in a controlled way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English local government accounts for £1 of every £4 spent on public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It spends £114 billion - that’s twice the defence budget and more than the NHS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this settlement recognises the responsibility of local government to find sensible savings and make better use of its resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It marks a new settlement for local government based on self determination and financial independence. A move from the begging bowl to pride in locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begins the biggest shake up of local finance in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are shifting power from Whitehall direct to the town hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April, authorities will directly retain nearly £11 billion of business rates instead of returning them to the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Striving councils will benefit by doing the right thing by their communities. If they bring in jobs and business they will be rewarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, New Homes Bonus remunerates councils for building more homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year the Bonus will be worth more than £650 million and even more in 2014 to 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our reforms an estimated 70% of local authority income will be raised locally compared to a little over half under the current formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A giant step for localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start-up funding assessment, which gives each council a share of the funding - confirmed in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement - will see £26 billion shared between councils across the country - with the smallest reductions for councils most reliant on government funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted local authorities on our proposals over the summer. And we’ve listened to what they told us. They told us that there should be less money held back from the settlement. So we’ve reduced the amounts that we are setting aside for New Homes Bonus, for the safety net and for academies funding. In total that means an additional £1.9 billion for local authorities upfront in 2013 to 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities also told us that they wanted a stronger growth incentive. We were happy to respond. So we’ve made the scheme more generous, ensuring that at least 25 pence in every pound of business rate growth will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement leaves councils with considerable total spending power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall reduction in spending power next year is just 1.7%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small number of authorities will require larger savings to be made but no councils face a loss of more than 8.8% in their spending power thanks to a new efficiency support grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, to qualify councils will have to improve services to qualify. It is unfair on the rest of local government to expect them to subsidise other councils’ failure to embrace modernity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is not about what councils can take. It’s about what they can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the settlement continues protecting fire and rescue as a blue light emergency service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we have announced £140 million of capital grant money to fire authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictably the doom mongers have been consulting their Mayan calendars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issuing dire warnings of the end of the world as we know it on Friday. A billion pound black hole in the local budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have shamefully predicted riots on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nostradamus needn’t worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because all those Malthusian predictions have come to naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns that the poorest councils or those in the north would suffer disproportionately are well wide of the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spending power for places is in the north compares well to those in the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also maintained the system of ‘damping’ - where government sets a ‘floor’ below which council funding will not fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s average grant reduction for the most dependent upper tier authorities will be less than 3%, compared to 8.7% for the wealthiest. That’s more support and protection than last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also confirm today that local authorities will be able to use the receipts from assets sales raised from 2012 to 2013 onwards to fund outstanding equal pay claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of what I’ve announced today, the Secretary of State for Health will in due course be confirming public health funding for local councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his Autumn Statement the Chancellor recognised the sector has risen to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, unlike most of central government, local government was exempted from the 1% top slice next year - worth approximately £240 million to councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as it looks to 2014 and beyond, local government needs to continue finding better, more efficient, ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There remains scope for sensible savings. With the exception of a handful of authorities, nobody has got to grips with procurement. More can also be done to share offices, share services, cut fraud and provide more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also asked the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, to pinpoint practical ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money and protect the quality and breadth of frontline fire services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is disappointing that the Shadow Fire Minister has signalled his opposition. It has been noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, and today, true to my Yorkshire roots, I’ve published 50 ways to save, setting out practical ways for councils to save money, big and small. But it all adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if councils merged their back offices like the Tri-Borough initiative in London, they could save £2 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement fraud costs taxpayers almost a billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils are sitting on £16 billion of reserves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils aren’t collecting over £2 billion of council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better property management could save £7 billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have also announced today that further savings will be made by the abolition of pensions for councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors should be champions of the people, not the salaried staff of the town hall state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s guide gives more power to the elbow and the public to challenge crude cuts and champion sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year’s exemption will give local authorities time to put their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s remind ourselves what this is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;safeguarding vital public services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protecting families and pensioners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ending the something for nothing culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is why, despite financial pressures, we will continue supporting for the third year running, those who insulate residents from further council tax hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have set aside an extra £550 million for local authorities to support council tax: £450 million over the next 2 years for the freeze and an additional £100 million for council tax support will be available in new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All councils have a moral duty to freeze council tax.
It doubled under Labour. It became unsustainable. 
We’ve cut it in real terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear this years freeze grant goes into base for the spending review period and has the same status as every other item in base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who would prefer to carry on with increases and see residents miss out should be ready to answer to their local taxpayers and not dodge them by setting the increase just below the threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For next year we have set the referendum threshold at 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also introduce a flexibility to support small district, police and fire authorities that have kept council tax low for years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Rt Hon friend the Local Government Minister has set out the details in a Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is democracy in action: if you want to hike taxes, put it to the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would contrast the action we have taken to freeze council tax with the new housing tax being introduced in the Republic of Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the deficit helps keep taxes down.
If you deny the deficit, taxes on everyday families will rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, to those who want to play the politics of division - let me say this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fair settlement - fair to north and south, rural and urban, shire and metropolitan England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is also a watershed moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in a generation, striving councils now have licence to go full steam ahead and grab a share of the wealth for their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stand tall, and seize the opportunities of enterprise, growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60026</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:07:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-pension-scheme"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 September 2001, the then Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions announced plans to give taxpayer-funded pensions to councillors, through access to the local government pension scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals came into force in 2003. The Councillors’ Commission report of the last administration noted that 912 councillors in England had joined that pension scheme by 2004. A Taxpayers’ Alliance survey in February 2009, across the whole United Kingdom, found that 3,527 councillors had pensions as of 2007 to 2008; a further survey in January 2012 found that figure had increased to 4,548 councillors by 2010 to 2011. The trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="abolition-of-taxpayer-funded-pensions"&gt;Abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in this government take a fundamentally different view to the last administration. We do not believe that taxpayer-funded pensions are justified. Councillors are volunteers undertaking public service; they are not and should not be employees of the council dependent on the municipal payroll. They are not professional, full-time politicians, nor should they be encouraged to become so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors do not receive a salary; rather, they receive allowances to compensate for their out-of-pocket expenses. Yet following changes made by the last administration, allowances have slowly become a form of salary, a situation worsened by the state-funded pensions. This is a corrosive influence on local democracy and independent thought, blurring the distinction between council staff and councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bit of the public sector needs to do its bit to help pay off the deficit inherited from the last administration. Local government grants are being reduced. Ministers have cut and then frozen their salaries. Public sector pensions, including parliamentary pensions, are being reformed to reduce the burden on taxpayers. It is only right that councillors do their bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that an occupational pension scheme intended for employees, and paid for by taxpayers, is an appropriate vehicle for councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="existing-pension-rights"&gt;Existing pension rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to consultation, we propose that there will be no access for councillors to the local government pension scheme in England from April 2014. In the interests of fairness, those councillors already in the scheme would have their accrued rights up to April 2014 fully protected, but would not be able to accrue any further benefits after that date in the existing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not prevent councillors contributing to a personal pension: if they put aside part of their (taxable) allowances into such a pension, then that is a matter for them; they will continue to receive income tax relief like any ordinary member of the population, subject to the prevailing tax rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although central records on councillors’ participation in the scheme are not held by my department, initial rough estimates suggest that this could save £7 million a year in taxpayers’ money. There is absolutely no case for increasing councillor allowances to compensate. Instead, councils may want to consider earlier, voluntary closure of the scheme to their councillors as a sensible saving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="civic-duty"&gt;Civic duty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility regulations for the local government pension scheme are overseen by my department. Although this is a centrally mandated change (as was its original introduction), we believe these reforms will assist localism and local democracy by encouraging a greater separation between councillors and officers. Robust local scrutiny of council spending requires councillors to be substantively independent of means and of thought from the body they are overseeing. Civic duty should not be bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe it will have any detrimental effect on people choosing to become councillors. The best thing we can do to encourage more people to take part in municipal public life is to decentralise power to local communities so being a councillor is a meaningful and rewarding role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="elected-mayors"&gt;Elected mayors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there is a greater expectation that an elected mayor is a full-time position. We therefore propose to consult on allowing elected mayors to remain in the scheme as a voluntary option (but not as an expectation), subject to local scrutiny, challenge and determination. The salaries of the mayor of London, members of the Greater London Assembly and police and crime commissioners will remain pensionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="timing"&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory consultation is required and will commence in due course, as part of the planned consultation on the wider reform of the local government pension scheme. We will consult with the Welsh Assembly government in respect of access to the local government pension scheme for councillors in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I would like to pay tribute to their often unsung and ongoing work in standing up for their local residents. We hope these reforms will further strengthen the integrity and independence of councillors and increase the respect within their communities for the voluntary work they undertake as champions of the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60073</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-finance-settlement-2013-to-2014-and-related-matters"/>
    <title>Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014 and related matters</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is about the local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014 and related matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information relating to this consultation and the local government finance settlement, view the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles" title='Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles'&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; from 19 December 2012 and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm" title="Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014"&gt;Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60081</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T19:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-practitioners-guide"/>
    <title>Business rates retention and the local government finance settlement: a practitioners guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide provides an overview of the calculations set out in the local government finance settlement report 2013 to 2014 and the draft local government finance settlement report 2014 to 2015. It sets out how the business rates retention scheme has been set up and how it will operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide is aimed at local authority practitioners and is intended to be read alongside both local government finance reports and supporting documents which can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm" title="Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014"&gt;local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt; website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glossary explaining the terminology used in the reports and in this document can be found at annex A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60082</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T19:30:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-plain-english-guide"/>
    <title>Business rates retention and the local government finance settlement: a plain English guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A guide explaining the changes to business rates and what the proposals mean for councils, local residents, businesses, charities, developers, and the police and fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57070</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:25:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-taking-work-incentives-into-account-guidance"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: taking work incentives into account: guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system. Councils will design local Council Tax reduction schemes for working-age applicants that will also support the wider objectives of welfare reform. This guidance sets out the key considerations for councils when designing their local scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54827</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-draft-council-tax-reduction-schemes-prescribed-requirements-and-default-scheme-england-amendment-regulations-2012"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Draft Council Tax reduction schemes (prescribed requirements and default scheme) (England) (amendment) regulations 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 7 September 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) confirmed its intention to update and align the premia/ applicable amounts in regulations for the default and pensioner schemes with current rates/ Department for Work and Pensions’ (&lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt;) autumn uprating. This would be done using Housing Benefit amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; said it would be working with &lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt; (again, in relation to the pension credit age and default schemes) to model the way in which non-dependent deductions would have been uprated had council tax benefit continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This draft statutory instrument effects these upratings and is being published ahead of the regulations being made, to give authorities early notice of the changes required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56701</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T12:36:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-reduction-scheme-taking-account-of-universal-credit-income"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax reduction scheme - taking account of universal credit income</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In October 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government published a document setting out how the default scheme will take account of claimants receiving universal credit, and how these measures will help to support positive work incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to feedback from interested parties, this document now provides some worked examples of how default scheme universal credit provisions operate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:55:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
