<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:55:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T16:10:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17266</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:36:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-guidance-note-on-administrative-matters"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: guidance note on administrative matters </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The administrative elements will in future operate under existing Council Tax provisions in the Local Government Finance Act and related regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This note will provide clarity for local authorities on how some administrative elements will be dealt with under these provisions, where these are not covered in the Default Scheme and Prescribed Requirements Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16974</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-funding-arrangements"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: funding arrangements</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions for local council tax support schemes in England. This document sets out how the Government intends to distribute funding to support local schemes and seeks views on possible adjustments to allocations to avoid potential budgetary pressures in a few authorities. It is published alongside statements of intent for the key sets of regulations which will provide the legal framework for local schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16882</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:46:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/housing-capital-receipts-exemptions-from-regulations"/>
    <title>Housing capital receipts: exemptions from regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of receipts arising from the disposal of housing assets (ie assets held under part 2 of the Housing Act 1985 and for which account is made in the Housing Revenue Account) is governed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/1324/made"&gt;Local Authorities (Capital Finance and Accounting) (England) Regulations 2003 (as amended.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations require that, in short: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receipts arising from Right to Buy (and similar sales may be retained to cover the cost of transacting the sales and to cover the debt on the properties sold, but a proportion of the remainder must be surrendered to central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receipts arising from all other disposals may be retained in full provided they are spent on affordable housing, regeneration or the paying down of housing debt (each of which is defined in the regulations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, section 11(6) of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents"&gt;Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; (as inserted by section 174 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;) permits the secretary of state to enter into agreements with local authorities with the effect that any requirement imposed by these regulations does not apply, or is modified in its application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enter into such an agreement it is necessary for any interested authority to make an application to the secretary of state. This guidance sets out the Department for Communities and Local Government’s policy on such exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16664</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:24:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-rewards-for-local-growth-under-new-scheme"/>
    <title>Greater rewards for local growth under new scheme</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; creates a new model for funding local authorities from April 2013, linking their financial revenue to the decisions they take to support local firms and local jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government will retain a 50% local share of business rates and then keep a 50% share of any growth they generate, subject to a levy, providing a strong incentive to go for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new system could deliver around an extra £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020, and generate more business rate income for councils to help pay off the deficit and support frontline services that protect vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following consultation responses, the government has changed the approach to the levy to increase the rewards for growth. The maximum levy will now be 50p in the pound. This translates into very real benefits for authorities: after the central share and levy payments, at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document also confirms the safety net for when councils experience unexpected drops in revenue will guarantee a real terms income from business rates of 92.5%. This means council income will never fall below 7.5% of its baseline funding level ensuring no area gets left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document confirms that the government will implement the majority of the technical proposals for the operation of the scheme set out in the summer consultation, together with changes to a number of detailed aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, after listening to councils, we are setting the central principles for how the new rate retention scheme will work next year. Ahead of the formal funding settlement next month this will give councils the certainty and security to begin planning their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The old flawed system of government handouts to local authorities encouraged a begging bowl mentality, with each council vying to be more deprived than its neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These reforms allow councils to stand tall, and rewards them for supporting local jobs and local firms. All councils, including the least prosperous, have the opportunity to gain from this system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation originally proposed a levy set at higher ratio. This would have meant that a district council with a business rates baseline of £100 million and a baseline funding level of £5 million would have been subject to a levy rate of 95p in the pound. So if the authority realised business rates growth of £2 million, £1 million of this would have been paid to the central share, £200,000 would have been paid to the county council, and £760,000 would have been paid in a levy, leaving the authority with £40,000 of growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s document confirms that levy rate will in fact be limited to 50p in the pound creating a much greater growth reward. This would leave that same authority with £400,000, ie 10 times more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;Business rates retention: policy statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/a-plain-english-guide-to-business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention: plain English guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"&gt;Written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16651</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:08:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"/>
    <title>Business rates retention: policy statement</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This policy statement provides early confirmation of the government’s policy decisions on the business rates retention scheme following the technical consultation that took place in the summer, and ahead of the provisional local government finance settlement which will constitute the government’s formal response to consultation. This policy statement, which includes an updated step-by-step guide to the scheme’s workings, will support local authorities in their preparations for smooth implementation of the business rates retention scheme from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16660</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:23:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"/>
    <title>Business rates retention</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am today publishing a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;policy statement&lt;/a&gt; that provides early confirmation of the government’s policy decisions in a number of key areas following this summer’s technical consultation on the new business rate retention scheme. This policy statement will support local authorities, ahead of the provisional local government finance settlement, in their preparations for smooth implementation of the business rates retention scheme from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business rates retention scheme will enable local authorities to retain a large proportion of locally collected business rates to help fund the services they provide, thereby creating a direct link between business rates collected and local authority income, and reducing local authorities’ dependency on central government grants. The scheme will give all councils a strong incentive to go for growth and could add approximately £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy statement confirms government’s intention to proceed with the implementation of a range of proposals that were set out in the technical consultation. It also sets out a number of changes to those proposals, in response to comments received to the consultation, including the government’s intention to maintain the 1:1 proportionate levy but with a limit of 50p in the pound. This will translate into very real benefits for authorities, allowing at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally to be retained locally. In addition, the policy statement sets out the government’s intention to fix the safety net at 7.5% - the most generous level within the range consulted upon. This guarantee will be maintained in real terms, since baseline funding levels will be uprated by &lt;abbr title="Retail Prices Index"&gt;RPI&lt;/abbr&gt; for the purpose of calculating eligibility for the safety net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, government considers that these policy decisions will result in a system that provides a strong growth incentive for authorities, while being underpinned by robust protections to help councils maintain effective services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have placed a copy of the policy statement in the library of the House. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2"&gt;policy statement and a revised plain English guide to business rate retention&lt;/a&gt; are also available on the GOV.UK website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="data-consultation"&gt;Data consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also today publishing the data consultation on the 2013-14 local government finance settlement. The consultation sets out the majority of data that may be used in calculating the provisional baseline funding levels and revenue support grant allocations from 2013-14. This release will enable local authorities to begin checking the indicator data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; can be found on the local government finance website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-council-tax-support"&gt;Local Council Tax support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for the introduction of local Council Tax support schemes in April 2013, the government consulted on aspects of the funding arrangements to support authorities to offer Council Tax support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I will publish an update on these arrangements, including on the government’s approach to addressing budget pressures to ensure all authorities have a fair starting point. Final funding allocations will be included in the provisional local government finance settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be publishing the Council Tax base regulations and the government response to the consultation on providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the final versions of 2 key Council Tax support regulations (first published in July) have been made and are soon to be published and laid before Parliament - the prescribed requirements scheme and the default scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the regulations will be available on the GOV.UK website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15610</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:23:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates--2"/>
    <title>Business rates</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 October, the government announced our intention to postpone the next business rates revaluation in England from 2015 to 2017. Clause 22 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; currently before the House of Commons will deliver upon this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recent Westminster Hall debate on business rates and during the second reading debate on the Bill, ministers committed to provide more information on the analysis which has informed the government’s position to assist parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full assessment would require a revaluation, which in itself would cost £43 million and take a significant amount of time. However, the Valuation Office Agency have today published their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/corporate/News/2012/newsRelease_November_2012.html"&gt;high level estimates of non-domestic rental and rating assessment movements for England&lt;/a&gt; as at January 2012; it provides an illustration of the potential impact those rateable values would have had on business rate bills. The Agency’s analysis is based on professional judgements informed by limited rental market evidence up to January 2012. The analysis has been prepared independently of ministers and published in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last revaluation was based on April 2008 valuations and rents set at the height of an unsustainable property boom. Since then, the economy and property market have faced exceptional changes. Rents have fallen since that property boom. Some groups have assumed that falling business rents would entail falling business rates. However, this is not the case. While aggregate rateable values have fallen, this would automatically be offset at the revaluation by a higher rating multiplier. Firms would just be required to pay a higher proportion of their rateable value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency’s estimates are based on an increase in the multiplier of 16%. My department has actually forecast an increase of 20%, as a consequence of inflation and the adjustment required to the multiplier for appeals; in this context, in practice, the losers would be likely to be even greater than those presented in the Agency’s paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Agency’s analysis suggests that 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates at a 2015 revaluation. This compares to 300,000 seeing reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectors would have faced big hikes including petrol stations (+28% tax paid), the self-catering industry such as caravan parks (+29% paid), hotels (+6% tax paid), theatres (+25% tax paid), and pubs (+11% tax paid). The retail sector overall would have seen a tax rise of 1% above inflation, and food retail and convenience stores in particular would have faced significant tax increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given business rates are the third biggest outgoing for local firms after staff and rent, such changes would invariably feed through to more expensive prices for family’s weekly shop, more expensive pints in pubs and a significant hit on Britain’s tourism trade. Indeed, as Community Pubs Minister, I am very aware of the concern expressed by honourable members on the pressures being faced by local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revaluations should be revenue-neutral, and equally, postponing the revaluation will be revenue-neutral. Overall the revaluation would not change the total business rates paid in England, so some sectors and locations would have seen reductions at 2015. During recent parliamentary exchanges, it was unfairly suggested that that this change was being done to assist southern parts of England at the expense of other parts of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that offices in central London would have seen by far the greatest reductions in tax paid if the 2015 revaluation had gone ahead (a fall in aggregate rateable value that is one of the reasons why the multiplier has to be increased by so much to make up for the lost revenue). There are complex variations by both locality and by sector in different parts of the country, but what is clear is that there would be far more losers than winners across the country as a whole. In making this decision, ministers are seeking to support the national interest and the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that as a very direct form of taxation, business rates are not popular. Local government finance is too often opaque and confusing. However, we are acting in an open and transparent manner. This independent evidence shows that by postponing the 2015 revaluation, we will protect local firms and local shops from sharp changes in business rates bills at a time when we want to ensure the economy is growing. It will provide business with a stable economic environment in which to invest and support jobs for the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the document will be placed in the Library together with a copy of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"&gt;Impact Assessment for the Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
