<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15610</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:23:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates--2"/>
    <title>Business rates</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 October, the government announced our intention to postpone the next business rates revaluation in England from 2015 to 2017. Clause 22 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; currently before the House of Commons will deliver upon this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recent Westminster Hall debate on business rates and during the second reading debate on the Bill, ministers committed to provide more information on the analysis which has informed the government’s position to assist parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full assessment would require a revaluation, which in itself would cost £43 million and take a significant amount of time. However, the Valuation Office Agency have today published their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/corporate/News/2012/newsRelease_November_2012.html"&gt;high level estimates of non-domestic rental and rating assessment movements for England&lt;/a&gt; as at January 2012; it provides an illustration of the potential impact those rateable values would have had on business rate bills. The Agency’s analysis is based on professional judgements informed by limited rental market evidence up to January 2012. The analysis has been prepared independently of ministers and published in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last revaluation was based on April 2008 valuations and rents set at the height of an unsustainable property boom. Since then, the economy and property market have faced exceptional changes. Rents have fallen since that property boom. Some groups have assumed that falling business rents would entail falling business rates. However, this is not the case. While aggregate rateable values have fallen, this would automatically be offset at the revaluation by a higher rating multiplier. Firms would just be required to pay a higher proportion of their rateable value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency’s estimates are based on an increase in the multiplier of 16%. My department has actually forecast an increase of 20%, as a consequence of inflation and the adjustment required to the multiplier for appeals; in this context, in practice, the losers would be likely to be even greater than those presented in the Agency’s paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Agency’s analysis suggests that 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates at a 2015 revaluation. This compares to 300,000 seeing reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectors would have faced big hikes including petrol stations (+28% tax paid), the self-catering industry such as caravan parks (+29% paid), hotels (+6% tax paid), theatres (+25% tax paid), and pubs (+11% tax paid). The retail sector overall would have seen a tax rise of 1% above inflation, and food retail and convenience stores in particular would have faced significant tax increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given business rates are the third biggest outgoing for local firms after staff and rent, such changes would invariably feed through to more expensive prices for family’s weekly shop, more expensive pints in pubs and a significant hit on Britain’s tourism trade. Indeed, as Community Pubs Minister, I am very aware of the concern expressed by honourable members on the pressures being faced by local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revaluations should be revenue-neutral, and equally, postponing the revaluation will be revenue-neutral. Overall the revaluation would not change the total business rates paid in England, so some sectors and locations would have seen reductions at 2015. During recent parliamentary exchanges, it was unfairly suggested that that this change was being done to assist southern parts of England at the expense of other parts of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that offices in central London would have seen by far the greatest reductions in tax paid if the 2015 revaluation had gone ahead (a fall in aggregate rateable value that is one of the reasons why the multiplier has to be increased by so much to make up for the lost revenue). There are complex variations by both locality and by sector in different parts of the country, but what is clear is that there would be far more losers than winners across the country as a whole. In making this decision, ministers are seeking to support the national interest and the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that as a very direct form of taxation, business rates are not popular. Local government finance is too often opaque and confusing. However, we are acting in an open and transparent manner. This independent evidence shows that by postponing the 2015 revaluation, we will protect local firms and local shops from sharp changes in business rates bills at a time when we want to ensure the economy is growing. It will provide business with a stable economic environment in which to invest and support jobs for the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the document will be placed in the Library together with a copy of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"&gt;Impact Assessment for the Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12425</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T10:23:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/town-hall-pension-changes-could-unlock-up-to-22-billion-for-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Town hall pension changes could unlock up to £22 billion for infrastructure</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be free to pump as much as £22 billon more of pension fund investments into infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supporting the government’s ambitions to build more homes, roads or high speed railway under proposals announced by local government secretary Eric Pickles today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships" title="local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships - consultation"&gt;proposals&lt;/a&gt; would potentially allow councils to double the amount they can legally invest from their pension funds directly into key infrastructure projects in a new and more efficient way that ensures long-term value for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment in infrastructure is a vital part of the government’s economic growth strategy. Innovative approaches that increase the amount of finance available for projects are needed to back ambitions for the economy and to help manage the inherited deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local government pension scheme for England and Wales is administered by 89 separate local funds that hold combined investment assets worth £150 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pension fund rules are there to make sure investment risks are spread across different types of investments to give taxpayers long-term protection. Fund managers are currently limited in the amount they can invest via partnership arrangements, which includes many types of infrastructure investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals published for consultation today include an option to increase the current limit of 15% to 30%. This would clear the barriers standing in the way of better council investment giving them the scope to inject up to £45 billion in such arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Unlocking town hall pension pots so they can be used to invest in vital infrastructure projects is a common sense decision that will help this country complete on a global scale and get Britain building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By lifting the restrictions controlling local pension investments councils could pump a further £22 billion directly into job-creating infrastructure projects that will boost our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is potentially a huge development and investment opportunity we simply cannot afford to ignore that also allows us to maintain long-term value for money for the taxpayer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report by the Future Homes Commission said council pension funds could be used to build key infrastructure projects like new homes in the UK without increasing the government deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment decisions remain for individual local pension funds, which have a duty to protect the local council taxpayers, and local services and to ensure that there are no conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12868</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on how to remove the barriers preventing local government pension scheme funds from investing in infrastructure projects and proposes two clear options for change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15179</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-investment-in-partnerships--2"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme: investment in partnerships</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on how to remove the barriers preventing local government pension scheme funds from investing in infrastructure projects and proposes two clear options for change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14747</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Minister praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a visit to Wiltshire Council Baroness Hanham saw first-hand the significant achievements made by the council whose trailblazing assets management strategies are protecting frontline services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and state of the art library which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medalist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medalists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torch bearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will save Wilstshire’s council tax payers at least £85 million. As two thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images from Baroness Hanham’s visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631902676938/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16268</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-transitional-grant-scheme"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: transitional grant scheme</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is making available an additional £100 million for 1 year to support those local authorities in developing well-designed council tax support schemes and maintain positive incentives to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant will be payable in March 2013 to those authorities who adopt schemes that must comply with criteria set by Government to ensure that low income households do not face an extensive increase in their council tax liability in 2013-14. This funding will enable councils to explore more sustainable approaches to managing the funding reduction that minimise the impact on vulnerable taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13397</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T16:52:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/localising-council-tax-support"/>
    <title>Localising Council Tax support</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 2010 Spending Review, the Government announced plans to localise council tax benefit and this is being taken forward through the Local Government Finance Bill currently before Parliament. From April 2013, these reforms will localise council tax support and give councils stronger incentives to support local firms, cut fraud, promote local enterprise and get people back into work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms contribute to the Government’s deficit reduction programme, delivering savings of 470million a year of taxpayers’ money in Great Britain from 2013-14. Welfare reform is vital to tackle the budget deficit, as council tax benefit expenditure in England increased from 2.0billion to 4.3billion from 1997-98 by 2010-11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Localisation will give local authorities the flexibility to design council tax support schemes for working age claimants in their area. We have been clear that councils have the scope to help manage the impact of the reduction in council tax support funding through securing sensible savings. To help the transition to these changes, my Department has already provided 30million of funding to help councils draw up local support schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a real incentive for councils to make savings in the new localised system from cutting fraud and error, where an estimated 200 million was paid out unnecessarily in 2011-12. However, we appreciate that these savings may not be delivered immediately in the first year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, to further assist the transition process, my Department is today announcing an additional 100million of funding for councils to help support them in developing well-designed council tax support schemes and maintain positive incentives to work. This is new and additional funding for local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As councils draw up their local schemes, it is clear that many are delivering savings using their local flexibilities and discretion, without unfairly increasing the burden on those who are currently on benefits. Equally, there are some councils which are asking for very large additional contributions from those on benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new 100million transition grant will seek to encourage best practice. The voluntary grant will be available to councils (billing and major precepting authorities) who choose to design their local schemes so that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;those who would be on 100 per cent support under current council tax benefit arrangements pay between zero and no more than 8.5 per cent of their council tax liability;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the taper rate does not increase above 25 per cent;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no sharp reduction in support for those entering work - for claimants currently entitled to less than 100 per cent support, the taper will be applied to an amount at least equal to their maximum eligible award.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In allowing flexibility over aspects of the scheme, we would not expect local authorities to impose large additional increases in non-dependant deductions. Councils will rightly want to avoid collecting small payments, and it may consequently be better value for money for councils to avoid designing schemes which seek to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of funding for which councils will be eligible to apply and the timescales and process for making an application will be published shortly. We anticipate that councils will make applications after 31 January 2013, and that funding will be paid in March 2013. The grant will be a simple one, easy to apply for and swiftly paid out, to help those councils who choose to do the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has a clear goal in tackling the deficit, and reducing spending on benefits. This measured, transitional approach will help deliver an important programme of welfare reform, whilst still protecting taxpayers’ broader interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16203</id>
    <published>2012-09-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-draft-council-tax-reduction-schemes-changes"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: draft Council Tax reduction schemes changes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system. This sets out the changes to the July 16 version of the Default Scheme regulations in list form. More significant changes responding to customer feedback are at the top of the list. Minor changes follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16206</id>
    <published>2012-09-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-default-and-prescribed-requirements-schemes"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: default and prescribed requirements schemes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This note explains changes introduced by the 7 September update of the Prescribed Requirements and Default Schemes and sets out plans for the autumn. This version makes minor ‘tidying up’ amendments to the initial drafts published on 16 July, and some (more noteworthy) responses to stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16371</id>
    <published>2012-09-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:32:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-prescribed-requirements-draft-regulations"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: prescribed requirements draft regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising council tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system. These draft regulations relate to the prescribed requirements of Council Tax reduction schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Schedules 1 to 6&lt;/strong&gt; of the prescribed requirements scheme are for pensioners only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Schedules 7 to 8&lt;/strong&gt; of the presribed requirements scheme applies for all applicants to local schemes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
