<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving local transport"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55970</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-for-everyone"/>
    <title>Transport for everyone </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker is calling on operators and local authorities to work with government to put accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help them to do this, the Department for Transport has published 2 action plans which set out priorities, as well as highlighting areas where action is in the pipeline or already underway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Transport for everyone’ outlines how operators, local councils and the Department can help to make it easier for people using public transport – particularly those with disabilities - to get to where they need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action plan builds on the success achieved in improving accessibility on public transport during the Olympics and Paralympics. At the heart of the plan is the importance of improving door-to-door journeys rather than addressing issues in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s equality action plan looks at how we can encourage a more inclusive transport network and underlines the importance of ensuring that policy makers at all levels are alive to the particular needs and concerns of different groups in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include affordability issues for young people and pensioners and the ability for all people to travel in safety and free from harassment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good transport system allows people to access jobs, opportunities and vital services - it needs to work for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the concerns that specific groups of people have about public transport and so we have pulled together ideas from across the transport sector on how these concerns can be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The action plans will help policy makers, as well as transport operators, to tackle problems head on and - more importantly - to level the playing field for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Sayce OBE, Disability Rights UK Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An accessible transport infrastructure is essential for what Disability Rights UK wants to achieve – disabled people playing a full and equal part in society. Over the past 20 years we have come a long way as our practical guide ‘Doing transport differently’ shows but there are still too many attitudinal, communication and physical barriers facing disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Action plan’ is a step change towards making further progress. We welcome the commitment that the Department for Transport will continue to work in partnership with disabled people and our organisations to ensure the most effective steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Accessibility action plan’ builds on the transport successes of the Olympic and Paralympic Games and aims to create a long lasting legacy of improved access and information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Olympic and Paralympic Games, public transport operators carried thousands of spectators with disabilities and work was done to ensure that the travelling public had easy access to information. One of the aims of the ‘Accessibility action plan’ will be to build on the Games Spectator Journey Planner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new planner would cover a wider geographical area and more types of transport as well as being made accessible to people with visual impairments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other measures outlined in the plan include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considering where £100 million of extra funding might be best spent in the long term to improve accessibility of railway stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible further amendments to the Blue Badge scheme to tackle abuse and fraud in this area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building on guidance for mobility scooters and powered wheelchairs to encourage training for those using this equipment &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Equality action plan’ sets out in one place what the department is doing to ensure people from all parts of society have the option to use public transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points addressed in the plan include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessibility to public transport for young people, older people and those living in rural areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety and personal security for women travellers, particularly at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling hate crime and bullying on buses and other public transport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promoting employment of under-represented groups within the transport industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both documents include lists of issues and the actions that have been, or will be, taken to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Accessibility action plan’&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;‘Equality action plan’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the interests of transparency and to enable as many people as possible to have their say, the ‘Equality action plan’ will be open for comment until 15 February. These will feed in to a final version of the document which will be published in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55824</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:34:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:34:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-13-december-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 13 December 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) has published the following transport statistics: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/transport-statistics-great-britain-2012"&gt;transport statistics Great Britain: 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/quarterly-bus-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;quarterly bus statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/vehicle-licensing-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;vehicle licensing statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/national-travel-survey-2011"&gt;national travel survey: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agencys-motorway-and-a-road-network-october-2012"&gt;reliability of journeys on the Highways Agencys motorway and ‘A’ road network: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See statistics at &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; for details on all &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55866</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/accessibility-action-plan-and-equality-action-plan"/>
    <title>Accessibility action plan and equality action plan</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today pleased to be publishing the department’s accessibility action plan &lt;a href="/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Transport for Everyone: an action plan to improve accessibility for all’&lt;/a&gt;, and, for comment, a draft &lt;a href="/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;equality action plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has already been achieved in making transport more accessible, and the accessibility action plan seeks to address the challenges that remain. In doing so, we also want to draw on the success of the Olympic and Paralympic Games which demonstrated what can be done to provide those using our public transport system with a positive experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility action plan focuses not only on improving physical accessibility, but also on providing better information for the traveller, and on improving attitudes and behaviour, especially towards disabled passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying our priorities in the action plan, we have worked with a large number of representative organisations, individuals, transport operators and local authorities. I am grateful for the support and input that they have provided.  We want transport to be accessible by all and the plan moves us further towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equality action plan presents some of the activities we are undertaking to meet our duties under the equalities legislation, and provides an initial set of priorities for promoting equality and well-being, based on the evidence we have gathered and the engagement we have already had with transport organisations and other interested parties. We are seeking comments on this initial draft and will publish a final version following further engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56454</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-03T22:04:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/proportion-of-urban-trips-under-5-miles-taken-by-i-walking-or-cycling-ii-public-transport"/>
    <title>Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles taken by (i) walking or cycling (ii) public transport</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="type-of-indicator-impact-indicator"&gt;Type of indicator: Impact indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-england-data-are-also-available-for-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: England (data are also available for Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-region-and-country"&gt;Information broken down by: Region and country&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2011, 39% of urban trips under 5 miles in England were taken by walking or cycling and 9% were taken by public transport.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles taken by (i) walking or cycling; (ii) public transport: England, 2010 and 2011 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Walking or cycling&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Public transport&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;All modes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;37%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;For urban trips under 5 miles in England:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;39% were taken by walking or cycling in 2011 compared with 37% in 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9% were taken by public transport in 2011, compared with 10% in 2010. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London was the region with the highest proportion of walking or cycling and public transport trips, 43% and 22% respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The region with the lowest proportion of walking or cycling trips was the West Midlands (32%). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The South West had the lowest proportion of public transport trips (4%).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/nts99-triips-and-distance-travelled-per-person-per-year"&gt;Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles by main mode: England, 2007 to 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proportions of walking or cycling and public transport trips are calculated using the number of trips under 5 miles as reported in the National Travel Survey by residents living in urban areas (settlements of over 3,000 population). Data are available by region and county.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: annual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: 13 December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: July 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Travel Survey (NTS) collects data on personal travel in Great Britain. The NTS reports on trends in personal travel including key questions on how, why and when people travel for all age groups. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/national-travel-survey-statistics"&gt;Further information and statistics from the NTS.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: email &lt;a href="mailto:national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; or telephone 020 7944 3097&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56534</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-monitoring-and-evaluation-framework"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund monitoring and evaluation framework</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework sets out the department’s requirements from the monitoring and evaluation activity of Local Sustainable Transport Fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) projects and the roles of the department and project teams in delivering these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework articulates which &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects are expected to fulfil which elements of monitoring and evaluation and provides project teams with the flexibility to collect evidence in a way that reflects the local variation of projects and data availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17618</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T09:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/green-bus-fund-round-4"/>
    <title>Green Bus Fund round 4</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Bus Fund supports bus companies and local authorities in England to help them buy new low carbon buses. Its main purpose is to support and speed up the introduction of hundreds of low carbon buses across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bidding guidance and documents are intended for bus operators and local authorities who want to submit bids for grant under the 4th round of the government’s Green Bus Fund. The bidding guidance explains the eligibility terms, the bidding process and how bids should be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17108</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:08:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"/>
    <title>Cash boost to get England cycling</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cities, towns and villages across England are set to benefit from an extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure.  The new funding was announced today by Transport Minister Norman Baker, at a conference in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new funding will help people take to two wheels.  Projects could include better cycle facilities at railway stations, improved cycle links, or projects to improve the layout of road junctions to make them more cycle-friendly. Previous investment has seen some great projects making a real difference in communities, including better cycle routes from residential areas to schools to encourage the next generation of cyclists to cycle more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference in Leicester, attended by Public Health Minister Anna Soubry and Norman Baker, explores how councils’ health and transport officials can work better together to deliver better options for cycling and walking in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is great for your health, the economy, and for the environment so we are determined to make it easier for people to cycle whether for leisure, getting to the shops or as part of their commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the success of the Olympics, there is a huge appetite for more cycling provision from the travelling public and we need to capitalise on this enthusiasm at local and national level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are investing £20 million in cycling infrastructure and getting councils to bring an end to silo working in their offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public Health Minister Anna Soubry said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being active helps us stay healthy and protects against life threatening conditions such as heart disease, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a great way for adults to get their recommended 150 minutes of physical activity each week and this funding will help encourage more people to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million announced today is in addition to £30 million already announced for similar projects this year which drew in an additional £15 million in matched funding from local sources.  The projects to be funded will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"&gt;written statement&lt;/a&gt; was laid in Parliament this morning &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence today also published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nice.org.uk/"&gt;guidance on public health for local authorities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17109</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T09:50:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Additional funding for cycling infrastructure</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has today made available an additional £20m for our existing infrastructure projects to support cycling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will increase the total available for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Community Linking Places Fund (in addition to the £15m announced on 7 February 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving cycle safety at junctions (in addition to the £15m announced on 26 June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Community Linking Places Fund is primarily for improvements to cycling and walking infrastructure, facilities and links. This includes improving access to the rail network by bicycle. In addition the fund aims to support jobs, enhance access to employment and encourage greater use of more environmentally friendly transport.   Projects currently being supported were announced on 6 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment in junctions - for use by English local authorities outside London - will help to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured, or are deemed to be at greater risk.  Local authorities are currently submitting bids for funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand from local authorities, Sustrans and train operating companies, who are delivering the infrastructure, has been high.  An increase of £20m to the total funding available will allow the Government to support more high quality proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the projects to be supported under the additional funding will be published early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"&gt;Cash boost to get England cycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16957</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-weston-transport-improvements"/>
    <title>Green light for Weston transport improvements</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will support economic growth in Weston-super-Mare and reduce congestion in the town centre. The work will also improve links between local roads and the M5 motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to increase capacity of the M5 Junction 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new link road for buses to access Worle railway station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bus priority measures at junctions and bus only sections to improve bus access to the south of Worle Station, linking it with regeneration areas at Weston Airfield and Locking Parklands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new 320 space car park with a bus interchange, drop-off and cycle facilities together with improvements to the north-side car park at Worle Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased capacity between the town centre and the regeneration areas through road widening and new routes for pedestrians and cyclists as well as bus priority measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great scheme that will support employment, reduce congestion and make it easier for people using public transport in and around Weston-super-Mare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £10.4 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country and the region needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Weston package scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work is currently planned to start in March 2013 with the package scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Weston package scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The package of measures, promoted by North Somerset Council, is scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
