<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-local-transport/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving local transport"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15105</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T12:52:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"/>
    <title>Low carbon bus calculator</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the benefits of purchasing a low carbon bus will be different for each operator and will depend on the way in which the bus in service is used. So, Department for Transport economists have produced a transparent, user-friendly toolkit to be used by bus operators and local authorities to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (&lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;). Your assessment should always compare the &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; to an equivalent diesel bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit allows you flexibility in changing the input assumptions to those most relevant to you. You will be able to assess the financial implications of purchasing a &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;, based on the fuel savings on offer (as advised by &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturers or experienced in trials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet tool is intended to provide indicative estimates only and &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; does not vouch for the accuracy of such estimates. Please note that the Department for Transport does not accept any liability for any decisions that may be taken on the basis of such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit will be routinely updated and refined. Details of any updates or changes that are made will be outlined in the ‘Intro’ worksheet of the toolkit. We therefore encourage you to visit this website regularly and download the toolkit to ensure you are using the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14394</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T16:55:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:55:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-bus-subsidy-reform"/>
    <title>Consultation on bus subsidy reform</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the government published ‘Green light for better buses’ in which it set out a series of reforms to improve local bus subsidy arrangements and regulations in England outside London. The proposals have been carefully formulated to attract more people onto buses, to ensure better value for the taxpayer and to give local transport authorities more influence over their bus networks. This consultation paper seeks views on how the subsidy proposals set out in ‘Green light for better buses’ are to be implemented. In particular the consultation covers how changes to the payment of Bus Service Operators Grant (&lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt;) are to be implemented. &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; is the main form of bus subsidy funded by the government and is paid at present to the companies which operate bus services. The reforms to &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; set out in ‘Green light for better buses’ include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;devolution of &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; to local authorities where the funding relates to services they support - i.e. tendered services - to allow decisions to be taken locally on how it should be spent;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a new local government fund - Better Bus Areas - to encourage local transport authorities and bus companies to work closely together to improve services and boost passenger numbers;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;devolution to Transport for London or the Greater London Authority of the &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; paid to London bus operators who operate services under contract to TfL; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tightening the existing rules defining which bus services can claim &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt;, so that the funding is put to the best possible use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/green-bus-fund-round-1/"&gt;Green bus fund publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14385</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T13:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T13:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/double-boost-for-carbon-cutting-buses"/>
    <title>Double boost for carbon cutting buses</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An extra £20 million is being made available for the government’s Green Bus Fund Transport Minister Norman Baker has announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in a second boost for low carbon buses Mr Baker has today launched an easy-to-use toolkit to allow local authorities and bus operators to make informed decisions on investing in carbon cutting buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million funding will be the fourth round of the Green Bus Fund, bringing the total support for this initiative to £95 million since its launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional funding has been found from an underspend in the Department for Transport’s budget and those wishing to buy green buses will be able to apply for the round four support this financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cutting carbon emissions from transport is not a choice, it is a necessity and that is why I am prioritising green buses and giving operators and local authorities an extra £20 million to deliver on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our new toolkit will be indispensible in allowing those considering investment in low carbon buses to see the advantages for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new online low carbon bus calculator will make it easier to quickly work out the savings that can be made over time through cheaper running costs and fuel efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details on the bidding process and eligibility will be published soon on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new low carbon bus toolkit will help operators and local authorities work out how the finances might stack up, with or without support from the Green Bus Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those wanting to work out how long it will take for a low carbon bus to pay for itself can now go online and use the new calculator which will allow them to quickly work this out using assumptions around capital costs and fuel efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While buses using low carbon technologies tend to be more expensive than conventional buses many are eligible for government support and running costs are usually lower so that, over time, they are actually the more economical choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toolkit launched today will allow councils and operators to see at a glance how quickly they can expect a return on investment in low carbon buses using a variety of carbon saving technologies such as hybrid or electric buses. It also shows operators and local authorities the savings on offer through reduced running costs from low carbon buses compared with running a bus using conventional fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toolkit also allows the user to tailor the calculation of costs to their specific circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"&gt;toolkit is available&lt;/a&gt; on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Round 4 of the Green Bus Fund was launched on the 6 November 2012. Bidding and eligibility guidance for the 4th round will be issued shortly on the Department for Transport website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland is holding a separate £3 million competition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The budget for round 4 of the Fund is £20 million with the funding coming from an underspend in the department’s budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the fourth round of the government’s grant. Round one was launched in 2009 and paid up to 100 per cent of the difference, with round two paying up to 90 per cent and round three up to 80 per cent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/background-to-the-green-bus-fund"&gt;fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buses funded through the Green Bus Fund are eligible for the Bus Service Operators Grant (BSOG) Low Carbon Bus incentive of 6p for every kilometre operated in service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous rounds of the Green Bus Fund have part funded diesel hybrid buses, which run on a combination of diesel and a battery, fully electric buses and biomethane-fuelled gas buses. Eligibility for the 4th round will be published shortly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each year, every low carbon bus in London saves around 26 tonnes of CO2 compared with its diesel equivalent, with buses outside London estimated to save around 22 tonnes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/investment-in-green-buses"&gt;Investment in Green Buses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/12467</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T13:09:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/investment-in-green-buses"/>
    <title>Investment in green buses</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce today that the department is making a further £20 million available to help bus operators and local authorities in England buy low carbon emission buses through a fourth round of the Green Bus Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operators and authorities will be able to bid for a share of this funding to meet the additional up-front cost of purchasing these buses, and we calculate that this will allow for around 300 new low carbon buses to be bought. This investment will aid the department’s overarching objectives of helping to create growth and cut carbon, as well as help to support UK manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guidance document will be published later this month giving more details of how bus operators and local authorities can bid for a share of this fund. Copies of this will be placed at the same time in the libraries of the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"&gt;toolkit has also been published today&lt;/a&gt; advising bus operators and local authorities on how quickly they can expect a return from investing in low carbon emission buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121106a"&gt;Double boost for carbon cutting buses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13288</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:41:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-standard-for-cycle-training-outcomes"/>
    <title>National standard for cycle training outcomes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Standard Outcomes cycle information for instructors, instructor trainers and levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14141</id>
    <published>2012-10-28T13:27:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-28T13:27:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/taxi-and-private-hire-services-consultation"/>
    <title>Taxi and private hire services consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Law Commission published a consultation paper with provisional proposals for reform of the legal framework relating to taxis and private hire vehicles on 10 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These proposals retain the important distinction between taxis - which can ‘ply for hire’ on the street or a cab rank - and private hire vehicles which can only be pre-booked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all vehicles would be subject to national minimum safety standards and, for private hire vehicles, these would replace more than 340 sets of local regulations. This will reduce the burden on business because, once appropriately licensed, a private hire firm could work freely across the country, without geographical restrictions. This would contribute to widening consumer choice and to making services cheaper and more competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Law Commission also make suggestions covering a wide range of issues, including improving provision for persons with disabilities, quantity restrictions and enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation-documents"&gt;Consultation documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://lawcommission.justice.gov.uk/consultations/1804.htm"&gt;Taxi and private hire services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14845</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T14:58:37+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T14:58:37+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/public-consultation-on-the-future-design-of-the-national-travel-survey"/>
    <title>Public consultation on the future design of the National Travel Survey</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation covers 4 areas of proposals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving to a global positioning system (&lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt;) methodology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing the length of the questionnaire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;geographic coverage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;amending the methodology of the survey to make cost savings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respondents are asked to provide feedback on the consultation questions, complete two simple tables identifying what National Travel Survey data they use and to provide suggestions on how the methodology of the survey could be amended to make cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14484</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T10:44:13+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T10:44:13+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/devolving-local-major-transport-schemes-consultation"/>
    <title>Devolving local major transport schemes consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government produced this document to develop a discussion and accepted views on a new system of prioritising and funding for local major transport schemes. A new system, once in place, will enable construction to begin after the end of the current Spending Review period - 2014 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact-assessment"&gt;Impact assessment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//publications/ia-devolving-local-major-transport-schemes/"&gt;Annex B: impact assessment of devolving local major transport schemes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/baker-20120918a"&gt;Devolving Local Major Transport Schemes: Next Step, written statement by Norman Baker, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-04/"&gt;More local decisions for transport schemes, press release, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/grenning-20120131/"&gt;Consultation on devolving local major transport schemes for the next Spending Review period - written ministerial statement by the Secretary of State for Transport,&lt;/a&gt; 31 January 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120131a/"&gt;Press release: Devolution of local transport&lt;/a&gt;, 31 January 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14249</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T19:22:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Transport White Paper Creating Growth, Cutting Carbon, published in January 2011, placed localism at the heart of the transport agenda in order to cut carbon emissions and create local growth. A total of £560 million was originally made available through the Local Sustainable Transport Fund to enable the Department to fund a number of high quality bids. Funding was topped up with a further £40 million to £600 million in 2012 to accommodate approval for a greater number of bids (with match funding being provided by local authority partners). In total, DfT awarded funding to 96 packages to 77 authorities to deliver their schemes between 2011 and 2015. Along with local contributions provided by all funded project teams, over £1 billion is now being invested in local sustainable travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding announcements made were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11 September 2012, Ministers approved just under £5 million to Tyne and Wear ITA for a small project, based on the strongest elements of their Large Project proposal (which was turned down for funding in June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;27 June 2012, Ministers awarded £225 million to 12 large projects (above £5 million), plus £41 million to 14 tranche 2 projects (small projects up to £5 million)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;24 May 2012, Ministers awarded £113 million to 30 tranche 2 projects (small projects up to £5 million)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 July 2011, Ministers awarded £155 million to 39 tranche 1 projects (small projects up to £5 million)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Sustainable Transport Fund bidding rounds are now closed and the fund is fully committed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="lstf-workshops"&gt;LSTF workshops&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Materials from the department’s programme of workshops with local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tranche-2---october-2011"&gt;Tranche 2 - October 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/lstf-tranche2-workshops/"&gt;Video presentation by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/BISCore/economic-development/docs/S/supporting-local-growth-tom-smyth-bis"&gt;Workshop presentation: ‘Supporting Local Growth’ by Tom Smyth - BIS (PPT - 186 KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="tranche-1---february-2011"&gt;Tranche 1 - February 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/lstf"&gt;Video presentation by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15695</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T15:17:31+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T15:17:31+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/alternatives-to-travel-a-call-for-evidence-guidance-document-and-questionnaire"/>
    <title>Alternatives to travel: a call for evidence - guidance document and questionnaire</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The alternatives to travel: call for evidence ‘Guidance document’ and ‘Questionnaire’ are being published to assist with the development of longer term alternatives to travel strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Document setting out the government’s next steps on alternatives to travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/alternatives-to-travel-next-steps"&gt;Alternatives to travel: next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/baker-20110119/"&gt;Local transport white paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nbtn.org.uk/ways2work/"&gt;National Business Travel Network Ways2work toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-10/"&gt;Alternatives to travel: a call for evidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/sustainable/alternatives-to-travel"&gt;Alternatives to travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/sustainable/"&gt;Sustainable travel and environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
