<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/50185</id>
    <published>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:36:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/investigation-into-overheating-in-homes-literature-review"/>
    <title>Investigation into overheating in homes: literature review</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This literature review focuses on 3 main areas: whether overheating is occurring in new dwellings, in existing dwellings and whether or not retrofitting/refurbishing existing dwellings is likely to increase the risk of overheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has been carried out on behalf of government by a consortium led by AECOM, and supported by the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and University College London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second output from this work is an analysis of gaps and recommendations report identifying the main gaps in the literature, and areas where further work might be of most value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/50186</id>
    <published>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/investigation-into-overheating-in-homes"/>
    <title>Investigation into overheating in homes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report identifies the main gaps in the literature on overheating in homes, and recommends areas where further work might be of most value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis has been carried out on behalf of Government by a consortium led by AECOM, and supported by the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and University College London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the second project output, the first being a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/investigation-into-overheating-in-homes-literature-review"&gt;literature review&lt;/a&gt; covering whether overheating is occurring in new dwellings, in existing dwellings and whether or not retrofitting/refurbishing existing dwellings is likely to increase the risk of overheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50178</id>
    <published>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tighter-checks-to-keep-cowboy-builders-out"/>
    <title>Tighter checks to keep cowboy builders out</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tradesmen who operate under self-check schemes, which allow them to check their own work, will be required to meet higher standards and prove they meet the right levels of quality, giving householders the peace of mind that work on their homes is up to scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures will also ensure that householders have a financial safety net in place such as a guarantee or insurance, to catch them if self-check installers fail to finish work properly or if they can’t be chased through the courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 85,000 complaints are made about building work in homes each year according to the Office of Fair Trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current self-check schemes have conditions in place to keep the cowboys out. Today’s proposals will further protect people from shoddy work and raise the bar for self-check tradesmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations running self-check schemes will now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;need to be accredited to an international quality standard in order to operate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have to assess that their members’ competence levels and actual work are up to national standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be required to promote the membership and use of their schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cowboy builders that leave behind a trail of shoddy work costing householders thousands to put right, give the rest of the industry a bad name. We are determined to keep the cowboys from infecting self-check schemes, which let hardworking competent tradesman get on with providing high quality work, quickly and at fair prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m determined to ensure that consumers are properly protected. By raising the bar even higher for self-check tradesman, we are sorting the rogues from the professionals, making it easier for people to identify competent installers and giving them the confidence that they will receive a high quality of work - or be protected if they don’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the year to March 2011, Consumer Direct received 70,000 complaints from consumers about general home improvements, maintenance and repairs, and an additional 15,000 specifically about the (window and conservatory) glazing sector. (Source: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/markets-work/othermarketswork/home-repairs/"&gt;Home Repairs and Improvements: A Research Report by TNS-BMRB for the Office of Fair Trading,&lt;/a&gt; June 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/34846/2156713_1_.pdf"&gt;conditions of authorisation (PDF 60KB)&lt;/a&gt; for competent person scheme operators are published today, together with an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/8405/2157372.pdf"&gt;impact assessment (PDF 325KB&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-competent-person-self-certification-schemes"&gt;summary of responses to consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also published today is an invitation for applications to be made to the Department for Communities and Local Government for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-competent-person-schemes/how-schemes-are-authorised"&gt;new or extended schemes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Installers of windows and boilers and other tradesmen can be part of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-competent-person-schemes"&gt;competent person schemes&lt;/a&gt; which allow them to self-check (self-certify) the compliance of their work with &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient"&gt;building regulations&lt;/a&gt;. The self-check system cuts out the need for checking by the local authority or other third parties, allowing quality work to be done quickly and saving the customer money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11597</id>
    <published>2012-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-impact-of-european-fire-test-and-classification-standards-on-wallpaper-and-similar-decorative-linings"/>
    <title>The impact of European fire test and classification standards on wallpaper and similar decorative linings</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The overall aim of this project was to understand the impact of European fire test and classification standards on building regulations and UK industry, in particular, on wallpapers and similar decorative linings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome from the project would seek to establish the realistic performance of these types of products and determine whether the classifications that they achieved were appropriate to the actual hazard to life that they posed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report details the test methodology, results and observations from the fire tests undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11187</id>
    <published>2012-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2012-circular-01-2012"/>
    <title>The Building Act 1984, Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012: circular 01/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this Circular is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw attention to the fact that the amendments apply in England and to excepted energy buildings in Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;amend the name of  the registration body Building Engineering Services Competence Accreditation Limited to Building Engineering Services Competence Assessment Limited wherever it appears in Schedule 3 to the Building Regulations 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remove the name of Benchmark Certification Limited in respect of a number of types of work in Schedule 3 to the Building Regulations 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012 make minor amendments to the Building Regulations 2010 (SI 2010/2214), and should be read in conjunction with the Building Regulations 2010 (see links, top right, under ‘On other sites’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a priced publication available from TSO (The Stationery Office), PO Box 29, Norwich NR3 1GN. Order through the Parliamentary Hotline (Lo-call): 08457 023 474, fax: 0870 600 5533, textphone 0870 240 3701, email: book.orders@tso.co.uk or visit www.tsoshop.co.uk to buy online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17532</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"/>
    <title>Building regulations: access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilet and regulation 7, and is section 1 of 4, relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 1 provides an overview of the consultation package as a whole as well as proposals on a number of areas including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replacing the currently referenced standards in part A (structure) with the new British Standards based on Eurocodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligning the existing guidance in Approved Document C (site preparation and resistance to contaminants and moisture) with the most up-to-date radon maps to ensure the safety provisions are targeted appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarifying the guidance on access statements in Approved Document M (access to and use of buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalising the guidance supporting parts M, K and N (access, protection from falling, collision and impact and glazing respectively) to remove unnecessary costs on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making minor changes to the technical guidance in Approved Document B (fire safety) to resolve practical problems in the application of requirement B2 (internal fire spread (linings))&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the intention to take forward the repeal of the fire protection provisions in the Local Acts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the non-regulatory approach proposed in relation to domestic security and changing places toilets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="draft-approved-documents"&gt;Draft Approved Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published alongside this section of the consultation is a draft version of a new Approved Document K (protection from falling, collision and impact). Not only does this reflect the proposed changes resulting from the rationalisation of parts K, M and N, it also seeks consultees’ views on the proposed new style of Approved Documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new style has also been applied to a draft revised Approved Document regulation 7 which can be found in the main consultation document as annex I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-consultation-sections"&gt;Other consultation sections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17533</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"/>
    <title>Building regulations: electrical safety</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out detailed proposals on part P, and is section 3 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise. It includes proposals to reduce the cost associated with the provisions governing electrical safety in the home whilst not undermining safety benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17539</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"/>
    <title>Building regulations: the building control system</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on the building control system, and is section 4 of 4 relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 4 includes proposals on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving local authority building control processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving private sector approved inspector arrangements, including removing the warranty link rule&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extending the competent person self-certification schemes framework and introducing specialist third-party certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing ‘appointed persons’ to act as compliance co-ordinators on construction sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17544</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"/>
    <title>Building regulations: conservation of fuel and power</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on part L of the building regulations. It is section 2 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes proposals for tighter carbon dioxide emission standards for new homes and non-domestic buildings, to take the next step towards zero carbon standards, plus tighter performance standards for works to existing buildings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper also contains proposals to introduce, on a phased basis, requirements for additional energy efficiency improvements to be carried out when other specified works (eg extensions) are planned and Green Deal finance is available as an option to meet the up-front costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11183</id>
    <published>2011-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/information-update-for-domestic-energy-assessors"/>
    <title>Information update for domestic energy assessors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document describes the major changes that are being made to the content and format of the Energy Performance Certificate (EPC) for domestic buildings. It also notes the additional training requirements that will be introduced shortly for Domestic Energy Assessors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
