<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14602</id>
    <published>2012-06-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tighter-checks-to-keep-cowboy-builders-out"/>
    <title>Tighter checks to keep cowboy builders out</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New measures have been put in place to help protect people from cowboy builders Communities Minister Andrew Stunell announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tradesmen who operate under self check schemes, which allow them to check their own work, will be required to meet higher standards and prove they meet the right levels of quality, giving householders the peace of mind that work on their homes is up to scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures will also ensure that householders have a financial safety net in place such as a guarantee or insurance, to catch them if self-check installers fail to finish work properly or if they can’t be chased through the courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 85,000 complaints are made about building work in homes each year according to the Office of Fair Trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current self-check schemes have conditions in place to keep the cowboys out. Today’s proposals will further protect people from shoddy work and raise the bar for self-check tradesmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations running self-check schemes will now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;need to be accredited to an international quality standard in order to operate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have to assess that their members’ competence levels and actual work are up to national standards; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be required to promote the membership and use of their schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Cowboys builders that leave behind a trail of shoddy work costing householders thousands to put right, give the rest of the industry a bad name. We are determined to keep the cowboys from infecting self-check schemes, which let hardworking competent tradesman get on with providing high quality work, quickly and at fair prices.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I’m determined to ensure that consumers are properly protected. By raising the bar even higher for self-check tradesman, we are sorting the rogues from the professionals, making it easier for people to identify competent installers and giving them the confidence that they will receive a high quality of work - or be protected if they don’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the year to March 2011, Consumer Direct received 70,000 complaints from consumers about general home improvements, maintenance and repairs, and an additional 15,000 specifically about the (window and conservatory) glazing sector. (Source: Home Repairs and Improvements: A Research Report by TNS-BMRB for the Office of Fair Trading, June 2011 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/markets-work/othermarketswork/home-repairs/"&gt;www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/markets-work/othermarketswork/home-repairs/&lt;/a&gt; (external link)).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new conditions of authorisation for Competent Person scheme operators are published today, together with an impact assessment and the summary of responses to consultation: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/competentpersonsschemes/"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/competentpersonsschemes/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also published today is an invitation for applications to be made to the Department for new or extended schemes. Details can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/competentpersonsschemes/howapply/"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/competentpersonsschemes/howapply/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Installers of windows and boilers and other tradesmen can be part of Competent Person schemes which allow them to self-check (i.e. self-certify) the compliance of their work with Building Regulations. The self-check system cuts out the need for checking by the local authority or other third parties, allowing quality work to be done quickly and saving the customer money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11597</id>
    <published>2012-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-impact-of-european-fire-test-and-classification-standards-on-wallpaper-and-similar-decorative-linings"/>
    <title>The impact of European fire test and classification standards on wallpaper and similar decorative linings</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The overall aim of this project was to understand the impact of European fire test and classification standards on building regulations and UK industry, in particular, on wallpapers and similar decorative linings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome from the project would seek to establish the realistic performance of these types of products and determine whether the classifications that they achieved were appropriate to the actual hazard to life that they posed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report details the test methodology, results and observations from the fire tests undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11187</id>
    <published>2012-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2012-circular-01-2012"/>
    <title>The Building Act 1984, Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012: circular 01/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this Circular is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw attention to the fact that the amendments apply in England and to excepted energy buildings in Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;amend the name of  the registration body Building Engineering Services Competence Accreditation Limited to Building Engineering Services Competence Assessment Limited wherever it appears in Schedule 3 to the Building Regulations 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remove the name of Benchmark Certification Limited in respect of a number of types of work in Schedule 3 to the Building Regulations 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012 make minor amendments to the Building Regulations 2010 (SI 2010/2214), and should be read in conjunction with the Building Regulations 2010 (see links, top right, under ‘On other sites’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a priced publication available from TSO (The Stationery Office), PO Box 29, Norwich NR3 1GN. Order through the Parliamentary Hotline (Lo-call): 08457 023 474, fax: 0870 600 5533, textphone 0870 240 3701, email: book.orders@tso.co.uk or visit www.tsoshop.co.uk to buy online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12725</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"/>
    <title>Building regulations: the building control system</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on the building control system, and is section 4 of 4 relating to the 2012 Building Regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 4 includes proposals on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving local authority building control processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving private sector Approved Inspector arrangements, including removing the Warranty Link Rule&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extending the competent person self-certification schemes framework and introducing specialist third party certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing ‘Appointed Persons’ to act as compliance co-ordinators on construction sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Section 1 - Introduction to the consultation package and proposals on Parts A, B, C, K, M and N, Access Statements, security, Changing Places toilets and Regulation 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 2 - Part L (Conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 3 - Part P (Electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12726</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"/>
    <title>Building regulations: electrical safety</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out detailed proposals on Part P, and is Section 3 of 4 relating to the 2012 Building Regulations consultation exercise. It includes proposals to reduce the cost associated with the provisions governing electrical safety in the home whilst not undermining safety benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Section 1 - Introduction to the consultation package and proposals on Parts A, B, C, K, M and N, Access Statements, security, Changing Places toilets and Regulation 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 2 - Part L (Conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 4 - the building control system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12727</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"/>
    <title>Building regulations: conservation of fuel and power</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on Parts L, and is Section 2 of 4, relating to the 2012 Building Regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes proposals for tighter carbon dioxide emission standards for new homes and non-domestic buildings, to take the next step towards ‘zero carbon’ standards, plus tighter performance standards for works to existing buildings. The paper also contains proposals to introduce, on a phased basis requirements for additional energy efficiency improvements to be carried out when other specified works (eg extensions) are planned, and Green Deal finance is available as an option to meet the up-front costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Section 1 - Introduction to the consultation package and proposals on Parts A, B, C, K, M and N, Access Statements, security, Changing Places toilets and Regulation 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 3 - Part P (Electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 4 - the building control system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12728</id>
    <published>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"/>
    <title>Building regulations: access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on Parts A, B, C, K, M and N, Access Statements, security, Changing Places toilet and Regulation 7, and is Section 1 of 4, relating to the 2012 Building Regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 1 provides an overview of the consultation package as a whole as well as proposals on a number of areas including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replacing the currently-referenced standards in Part A (Structure) with the new British Standards based on Eurocodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligning the existing guidance in Approved Document C (Site preparation and resistance to contaminants and moisture) with the most up-to-date radon maps to ensure the safety provisions are targeted appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarifying the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M (Access to and use of buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalising the guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to remove unnecessary costs on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making minor changes to the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety) to resolve practical problems in the application of Requirement B2 (Internal fire spread (linings))&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the intention to take forward the repeal of the fire protection provisions in the Local Acts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the non-regulatory approach proposed in relation to domestic security and Changing Places toilets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="draft-approved-documents"&gt;Draft Approved Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published alongside this section of the consultation is a draft version of a new Approved Document K (Protection from falling,collision and impact)(see under Download). Not only does this reflect the proposed changes resulting from the rationalisation of Parts K, M and N, it also seeks consultees’ views on the proposed “new style” of Approved Documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new style has also been applied to a draft revised Approved Document Regulation 7 which can be found in the main consultation document as Annex I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-consultation-sections"&gt;Other consultation sections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Section 2 - Part L (Conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 3 - Part P (Electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Section 4 - the building control system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11183</id>
    <published>2011-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/information-update-for-domestic-energy-assessors"/>
    <title>Information update for domestic energy assessors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document describes the major changes that are being made to the content and format of the Energy Performance Certificate (EPC) for domestic buildings. It also notes the additional training requirements that will be introduced shortly for Domestic Energy Assessors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11572</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:33:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/structural-robustness-and-disproportionate-collapse-of-buildings-international-research"/>
    <title>Structural robustness and disproportionate collapse of buildings: international research</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This research report concludes an extensive international literature review into robustness and disproportionate collapse in structures undertaken on behalf of the Department for Communities and Local Government (DCLG) and the Centre for the Protection of National Infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report aims to ascertain the state of knowledge in the subject and identify the gaps in that state of knowledge against which future research initiatives can be targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings and recommendations in this report are those of the consultant authors and do not necessarily represent the views or proposed policies of DCLG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9094</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/andrew-stunell-welcomes-key-appointments-to-building-regulations-committee"/>
    <title>Andrew Stunell welcomes key appointments to Building Regulations Committee</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell today announced a new chairman of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee (BRAC). BRAC is the consultative body which provides strategic and technical guidance to the Government on standards for the design, sustainability and construction of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Cooper is to be appointed as chairman of the Committee, replacing Michael Finn after 10 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Caplehorn, Alan Crane and Stephen Wielebski have also been re-appointed to serve a further three-year term as members of the committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I would like to thank Michael Finn for his outstanding contribution in his 20 years as both member and Chair of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee. Under Michael’s leadership the committee has been instrumental in helping to deliver safe, healthy, accessible and sustainable buildings across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“But I am sure that under Neil Cooper’s chairmanship, the Committee will continue to play a key role, particularly given the increasing focus on sustainability and energy efficiency of buildings. I very much look forward to working with him.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I would also like to thank Peter Caplehorn, Alan Crane and Stephen Wielebski who have all agreed to serve a further term as members of the Committee. They bring experience and expertise in their respective fields and have been re-appointed to ensure the high quality of advice provided by the Committee is maintained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Cooper said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I am delighted and privileged to be appointed to the position. The Committee has made a positive and vital contribution to effective regulation under Michael’s leadership and I intend to ensure this continues. We face many challenges in respect of delivering sustainable buildings, as well as ensuring appropriate and achievable standards are in place to provide healthy and safe environments. I look forward to working with my colleagues to help the Minister achieve this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. The Building Regulations Advisory Committee is a statutory advisory body that exists to advise Ministers on the making of Building Regulations and works closely with Government officials in the development of both regulations and wider policies on building related matters. There are currently 15 Building Regulations Advisory Committee members. The work of the Committee is concerned with regulations applicable in England and Wales. Comparable regulations apply in Northern Ireland and Scotland, which have their own advisory committees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Appointments to the Building Regulations Advisory Committee are made jointly by the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government and the Secretary of State for Wales in open competition, in accordance with the Commissioner for Public Appointments’ Code of Practice for Ministerial Appointments to Public Bodies. Following the transfer of functions under the 1984 Building Act, Welsh Ministers will appoint a new separate committee for Wales and BRAC will cover England only from 31 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Terms of appointment are made on merit and are usually between two to three years; there is no minimum or maximum level of membership. All re-appointments are made following performance assessments by the Chair in liaison with Department for Communities and Local Government officials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. The Chair and members are appointed on an independent basis to represent particular areas/fields of expertise and experience, relevant to the Building Regulations, rather than as delegates of particular organisations or interest groups. They are unpaid for their work both on the main Building Regulations Advisory Committee and associated working parties, but can claim travel and other expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Full details of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee membership and further information about the Committee can be found on the Department for Communities and Local Government’s website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/buildingregulationsadvisory/"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/buildingregulations/buildingregulationsadvisory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Neil Cooper Dip Surv, MRICS, FBEng, MIoD is a chartered surveyor and currently Managing Director of MLM Building Control Ltd. Neil is also a founding member and former Chair of the Association of Consultant Approved Inspectors. Neil was appointed as a member of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee in October 2006 and has been Deputy Chair of the Committee since February 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
