<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Increasing the UK’s exports and attracting inward investment"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T12:21:57+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65618</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T12:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T12:21:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretary-william-hague-met-the-ethiopian-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary William Hague meets the Ethiopian Foreign Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary discusses human rights with the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary met the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros on 10 January. Dr Tedros also met the Minister of Africa, Mark Simmonds, and the Secretary of State for International Development, Justine Greening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary discussed a range of issues including the UK’s bilateral relationship with Ethiopia, regional security, commercial relations and counter-terrorism. The Foreign Secretary also underlined the importance the UK attaches to human rights and raised concerns over the sentences handed down under Ethiopia’s anti-terrorism laws.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office officials also attended a business roundtable chaired by Dr Tedros in the Ethiopian Embassy for existing and potential investors.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/54856</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:57:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/championing-britain-through-commercial-and-economic-diplomacy"/>
    <title>Championing Britain through commercial and economic diplomacy </title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague tells British diplomats they must intensify work to champion the UK as a destination for foreign investment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, more than at any moment in modern history, British diplomacy must play a central role in supporting jobs and growth in our economy. We need commercial diplomacy and economic expertise to run through the bloodstream of the Foreign Office, and it really is starting to do so. Western economies are facing significant economic and fiscal challenges. There is simply no option to generate growth through increased government expenditure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that as well as using diplomacy to tackle threats in the world and to advance human rights and freedom, all the things the Foreign Office does so well, we also need to build up our influence where it counts, in new trading hubs and high-growth economies of the 21st century as well as our vitally important markets in Europe and the United States. You are on the front line helping us to do this, making the contacts, speaking to business leaders and building the influence that will enable British companies to remain competitive in a global market. We need your local knowledge and understanding to spot both opportunities and barriers to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were important changes to make and I want to thank you personally for responding so readily and energetically in making them happen, which is something that I can see and feel wherever I go. British business also appreciates it, as the results of a recent survey clearly show. But that survey also highlighted that we must sustain this effort over the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to build on these successes, increase our ambition, and reach even further; because if we don’t then others will in our place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is you who is making clear that Britain is open for business and has an abundance to offer. I have been immensely impressed by your efforts so far. The skills that you display in getting under the skins of your local cultures, building relationships with business, lobbying officials, and reporting economic and political developments, are the skills that will allow us to give British business the competitive edge that it needs. Whether it be championing the UK’s contribution to the green economy, or influencing trade negotiations in Brussels, it is you, our network, which is connecting opportunities abroad to jobs at home. I want you to know that the work you are doing is vitally important. It is important to us in the FCO. It is important to the Prime Minister. And it is important to the whole country. So, I will champion you and the work you do and I want you to champion Britain. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/50172</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:14:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-philippines-partners-for-prosperity"/>
    <title>Britain and the Philippines: Partners for Prosperity</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has given a speech about the growing trade partnership between the UK and the Philippines. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here today, and especially pleased that we are in the company of Foreign Secretary del Rosario. I would like to thank the Makati Business Club, the Management Association of the Philippines and the British Chamber of Commerce for inviting me to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real thrill to be in the Philippines, on my first official visit to this beautiful country. It is almost 30 years since I was last here, in a personal capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a busy two days ahead and have just come from a very productive meeting with President Aquino, during which we discussed how Britain and the Philippines can work together to tackle today’s global challenges and support each other’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on the latter that I will focus today. I will talk first about the United Kingdom’s role in today’s changing world, before setting out why I think Britain and the Philippines can be powerful partners for prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom, like the Philippines, is an island nation – a characteristic which, unsurprisingly, has shaped how we view ourselves and the world around us. Britain is a relatively small place. We had enough but not bountiful natural resources. Combine that with a predisposition towards adventure and discovery, and it led us to build truly global networks and trade links. One thinks of names like Drake, Raleigh and Shackleton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No market was too far or too difficult; no peak too high. Indeed, the globalisation that people tend to view today as a very modern phenomenon has roots that go much deeper. The world in which the Victorians lived was far more integrated in some ways, with Britain sitting at the heart of a global economic system, including a de facto single currency – the Gold Standard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this brought us to South-East Asia. Our ties to countries like Malaysia and Singapore are perhaps best known and are still extremely strong. However, Britain’s links to the Philippines stretch back just as far. The first British Consul arrived as early as 1844. And I am reminded of one of your most famous national heroes, José Rizal, who lived in London’s Primrose Hill in the 1880s. Visitors today will find a blue plaque on the house in which he lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, and particularly in the last couple of decades, I have heard some say that Britain lost sight of the importance of South-East Asia; that our attention was diverted elsewhere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that relationships changed. But while it may have felt to some as if Britain had lost focus, we never went away. The commercial figures alone bear this out. UK trade and investment with South-East Asia today is still far higher than it is with China, despite the exceptional levels of growth and development that China has seen over the past 15 years. That said, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office has under the current Government significantly strengthened this focus, placing an even greater emphasis on our engagement with South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have rebalanced our foreign policy and diplomatic network. On a practical level, that means opening new missions, sending more diplomats to places like the Philippines. We are creating around 50 new jobs across the region. And I am sure many of you will have taken note of last month’s visit to Laos by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, to reopen the British Embassy there. The UK is now represented in all ten ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking this new approach because we see the emergence and re-emergence of economies across the world – not least the growth and development in Asia – as an opportunity. I believe there is much that we can achieve if we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is a key element of my Government’s efforts to deliver sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from an unbalanced growth model, reliant on government spending, to one based on expanding trade, encouraging inward investment, increasing the share of our economy that comes from exports, and manufacturing the goods that today’s consumers want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to meet our ambitious target to double exports to £1 trillion a year by 2020, we need to grow our exports by eight percent a year. Some of these will go to traditional markets like the European Union, but we are looking increasingly to fast-growing economies in places like South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Europe, the UK is leading the efforts to open up the EU market to trade with other nations. Growth may be slow in Europe – the forecasts suggest we can expect only 0.4 per cent next year – but it is still the biggest marketplace in the world, doing £11 trillion of business every year and encompassing 500 million consumers and 21 million companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our prosperity agenda forward won’t be easy – the global economic environment clearly remains a challenge. But it is a challenge I am confident Britain can respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we are doing within the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to embed commercial thinking should help. We are now training our diplomats in commercial as well as foreign affairs, and deploying new commercial staff across our diplomatic network. Our Ambassadors increasingly undertake secondments to companies before taking up their postings to gain firsthand commercial experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the often bleak commentary from elements of the media, the British economy has real strengths. Just think of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games held earlier this year. The Games followed hot on the heels of Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, and showcased to the world Britain’s diversity, openness, creativity and dynamism – politically, culturally and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is renowned for its excellence in financial services, the creative industries and, of course, in education. But as anyone who visited the British Business Embassy at Lancaster House in London during the Olympics would have noticed, we also remain one of the world’s most important manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s car industry, currently undergoing a renaissance, is one such example. We are home to seven global car manufacturers.  Ford, General Motors, Jaguar Land Rover and Mini you will know, but we also have big investments from Honda, Toyota and Nissan too, who produced over 480,000 vehicles in Britain last year. In total, more than one million vehicles and two million engines are produced in the UK each year, and over three-quarters of the vehicles we manufacture are exported. And enthusiasts of faster cars will know that eight Formula One teams have their headquarters in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the UK’s expertise across this and many other sectors makes us a highly compatible partner for the Philippines. I would point, for instance, to finance, where our ICT specialists are helping the Philippine Stock Exchange expand their optic fibre network across the ASEAN region; and to healthcare, where our extensive experience in Public-Private Partnerships is helping the Philippines in their plans to develop a centre of excellence in orthopaedic medicine, modelled on the Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our sectoral expertise is certainly not the only reason. What makes Britain a particularly attractive partner is, I think, the openness of our economy, our transparency and adherence to the rule of law and our firm belief in the rules-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of economic uncertainty, some are inevitably tempted to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. But protectionism is a short-term measure with long-term consequences, and in Britain we are taking the opposite approach. History has taught us that more trade, more competitiveness and making the UK open for business and open for investment are what will steer us towards sustainable economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines is heading down the same path, and I would highlight four areas that point towards this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is corruption, which remains a scourge on the global economy. It adds as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries. Those who are hardest hit are often the poorest and most vulnerable in society. That is why we are proud to have introduced the Bribery Act in the UK to address this all-too-common problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Aquino’s anti-corruption efforts and business-friendly policies such as the Integrity Initiative and the decision to join the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative are exactly the right thing to be doing – particularly now, during this period of global economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area is building the infrastructure needed to provide the foundations for long-term prosperity. Modern economies need roads, digital and cellular communications, public transport, schools and hospitals. Without them, we cannot deliver the skilled and trained workforce required to compete in the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third area is ensuring peace and stability. This is perhaps the most crucial platform for prosperity. I am proud that the UK played a small but important role in the framework agreement in Mindanao as a member of the international contact group.  And I would like to take this opportunity to repeat our deepest condolences for the terrible devastation caused there by Typhoon Pablo. Successful implementation of the framework agreement will unlock the economic potential of that area. We are also working closely with Secretary del Rosario and his team to bring about a peaceful resolution of the claims in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connected to international peace and stability is the fourth area: shunning protectionism and embracing free trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ future will not be shaped by growth in the archipelago alone. Whether it is through its overseas workers, the foreign investment that can create jobs, or its export markets abroad, it is clear that future prosperity here will be based on partnerships. This agenda is moving in the right direction.  But I think we can go further and faster. Agreeing a free trade agreement between the EU and the Philippines would be a valuable step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this policy prescription is good for your economy. But it is also vital for your broader development. International trade and investment is not just the best route to development; history tells us it is the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am speaking to you here today because I think – in fact I am certain – that the relationship between Britain and the Philippines can play an important part in promoting our mutual prosperity. We have much in common, and economies that rely on a strong and open global economy. We are democracies, with a strong attachment to human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today Secretary del Rosario marked this growth by signing a joint plan of action that will take our relationship to a new level. This is a genuinely exciting proposition. Our partnership will help to shape the business environment – working together on issues like anti-corruption, competitiveness, economic reform, a low-carbon economy and building awareness about the opportunities for trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade between our countries currently stands at around £1.1 billion. That is impressive, but is I think a fraction of what it can be, particularly when you consider just how fast your country is growing. In this year’s third quarter, growth in the Philippines reached 7.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joint action plan should help us to realise this potential. But we as governments can only do so much. Ultimately, it is businesses that will drive growth. We need your help to generate interest, build awareness and deliver projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore pleased that we have with us today some excellent examples of successful companies operating here –like Standard Chartered Bank, Marks and Spencer and Debenhams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On visas – not always an easy subject – I know that we have a fast, fair and efficient service here, and that we are opening new services to facilitate quick and easy travel for business via Saturday openings, a premium service and a new visa application centre in Cebu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sign that we are indeed open to business is the large number of Filipino overseas workers that are employed in the UK, who are making a valuable contribution to our economy but also sending back remittances to family in the Philippines. Their contribution cuts across many sectors, but is particularly evident in health and care work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that our new visa services will lead to many more visitors travelling between our countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help bring this about, I will sign a new air services agreement later today with Secretary Abaya, and meet Ramon Ang and Philippines Airlines, who hope to start direct flights to London soon. And, incidentally, their passengers will probably be arriving on new aircraft made partly in Britain, following the announcement by Philippines Airlines in August of a $7 billion order from Airbus for over 50 new aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to share our policy experience in infrastructure development, energy and Public-Private Partnerships so you can learn from our experiences, our successes and, occasionally, our mistakes. When President Aquino visited London in the summer, he went to St Pancras Station, a successful example of how well Public-Private Partnerships can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope what you have heard today is a clear indication of the UK’s role in today’s global economy, of what is happening here in the Philippines and, most importantly, a compelling vision for how Britain and the Philippines can be partners for prosperity, looking to the future with confidence and optimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit is just one of what I am confident will be many high-level visits in the coming months. I know that my colleague, the Foreign Secretary William Hague, is keen to visit in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the rest of my programme, and – with your agreement – I will not leave it another 30 years before I return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer, George Osborne, has delivered his 2012 Autumn Statement to Parliament.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17810</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T12:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:39:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-kuwait-joint-steering-group-communique"/>
    <title>UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group Communiqué</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The steering group aim to strengthen ties between the UK and Kuwait, they discussed issues including trade and investment and defence and security.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inaugural meeting of the UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group took place at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office in London on 28 November 2012, and formed part of the State Visit to the UK of His Highness Sheikh Sabah Al Ahmad Al Jaber, the Amir of Kuwait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Steering Group was launched by The Rt Hon William Hague, British Foreign Secretary, and His Excellency Sheikh Sabah Al Khalid Al Sabah, the Kuwaiti Minister of Foreign Affairs and Deputy Prime Minister, with the aim of further strengthening the ties between the two countries, across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group agreed to meet every six months under the leadership of Alistair Burt MP, Minister for the Middle East and South Asia, and His Excellency Khaled Sulaiman al Jarallah, Undersecretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting the breadth of the bilateral relationship, the group discussed a range of issues, including trade and investment; migration; defence and foreign policy; and international development:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On trade and investment, Ministers committed to seek out opportunities to strengthen commercial links between the UK and Kuwait and stressed the importance of encouraging the growth of business between the two countries. The Ministers welcomed the appointment of Baroness Morris as UK Trade Envoy to Kuwait, applauded Kuwait’s ambitious National Development Plan and agreed that UK companies had a vital role to play in supporting it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On defence and security, Ministers pointed to the close cooperation between the two countries, enshrined in a shared military history and a strong tradition of military officer exchanges, and committed to strengthening this partnership further in support of shared regional objectives. They agreed to build a strategic dialogue going forward, discuss cooperation on defence equipment and to increase training in the military field. It has been agreed that the UK will refurbish Kuwait’s Hawk trainer aircraft.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On regional issues, Ministers discussed Israel/Palestine and the need for both sides to return to negotiations. Ministers agreed to work together to improve stability in the region, urging reconciliation in Syria and committing to coordinate closely to support political progress in Yemen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On international development, Alan Duncan MP, UK Minister for Development, held a separate bilateral meeting with the Kuwaiti Minister for Foreign Affairs. Recognising the role both countries already play, and committing to learn from each other’s experiences, they agreed to work together as partners on this globally important area.
Ministers also discussed prospective cooperation on migration, education and healthcare, and agreed to follow up progress across the board at their next meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18382</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:40:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-mongolia-round-table-discussions-held-in-london"/>
    <title>UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions held in London</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire met the Mongolian Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs for discussions on defence reform and trade links</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 28 November, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire hosted Damba Gankhuyag, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Mongolia for the tenth UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks focused on commercial relations, foreign policy issues and defence cooperation, with the UK and Mongolia ultimately signing a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to increase defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU is aimed at supporting Mongolian defence reform, in light of its peacekeeping activities in UN operations and its recently joining the OSCE. Through modernising equipment, Mongolia hopes to become even more efficient in supporting international operations in less stable regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global partner, Mongolia is becoming ever closer to the UK, with increasing trade and cultural links. The Minister discussed how best to share the UK’s experience of cultivating and managing investment in both directions to improve bilateral trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks saw the UK and Mongolia strengthen their relationship, on the eve of celebrating the fiftieth Anniversary of diplomatic relations next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI hosted a business session in the afternoon, which was attended by a large number of business representatives discussing Mongolia’s extractive industries, mutually beneficial opportunities and Stock Exchange collaboration. The talks were concluded by a session on education cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the tenth UK-Mongolia Round Table. Held every two years, the talks form a key part of the UK – Mongolia relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17277</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T12:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:38:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-meets-kuwaiti-minister-of-foreign-affairs"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary meets Kuwaiti Minister of Foreign Affairs </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague and the Kuwaiti Foreign Minister chaired the inaugural meeting of the UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was delighted to welcome His Excellency Sheikh Sabah Khaled Al-Hamad Al-Sabah, Kuwait’s Minister of Foreign Affairs and Deputy Prime Minister, to the Foreign Office today. The United Kingdom and Kuwait enjoy a historic relationship whose foundations date back to the eighteenth century. As long-standing friends we have been through much together, including the liberation of Kuwait from Saddam Hussein’s forces in 1991.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kuwait is a key ally in a region with significant implications for the security and prosperity of the United Kingdom On coming to office I was clear that we needed to do more to enhance our relationship and today I am pleased to announce the inauguration of a new UK-Kuwait Joint Steering Group. This will meet regularly to deepen the strong ties between our countries and provide a forum to develop our partnership on trade, foreign and security policy – including the UK’s decision to help Kuwait with its security infrastructure to help counter the threat from terrorism - and development where Kuwait has a strong record as a generous donor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today we discussed our bilateral relations and reiterated our commitment to build on progress and increase trade to £4 billion by 2015. We also spoke about the political situation in Kuwait and I made clear the UK’s continued support for Kuwait’s deep-seated democratic tradition and its fully elected Parliament and vibrant media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally we discussed the current situation in Middle East, including the Palestinian resolution at the UN General Assembly, Iraq, Syria and Iran. In particular I made clear that I believe it is time for a huge effort on the Middle East peace process and that we continue to urge the United States to give a decisive lead in the coming months before a two state solution slips away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/media/item/411801.html" title="UK business partnership with Kuwait"&gt;UKTI statement: UK business partnership with Kuwait&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinkuwait.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Kuwait"&gt;UK in Kuwait website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/ukinkuwait" title="@ukinkuwait"&gt;Follow @ukinkuwait&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35615</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-meets-julian-castro-mayor-of-san-antonio"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary meets Julian Castro, Mayor of San Antonio</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary: "Mayor Castro’s visit to London showcases the best of the transatlantic relationship. It has strengthened our ties with San Antonio, the US’s seventh largest city, and helped promote our mutual prosperity."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 20 November, the Foreign Secretary met Julian Castro, Mayor of San Antonio.  During his two day visit to London, Mayor Castro visited Tech City with an accompanying trade delegation and also gave a speech at the London School of Economics on US leadership in the 21st Century.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After their meeting, the Foreign Secretary said, “Mayor Castro’s visit to London showcases the best of the transatlantic relationship.  It has strengthened our ties with San Antonio, the US’s seventh largest city, and helped promote our mutual prosperity.  Three hundred British companies are already located in Texas and, by increasing our cooperation on energy and high-tech in particular, our ambition is to enhance our cooperation on economic development even further over the coming years.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
