<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-piracy-off-the-coast-of-somalia/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-piracy-off-the-coast-of-somalia/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-piracy-off-the-coast-of-somalia/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Preventing and reducing piracy off the coast of Somalia  "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56873</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:23:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/private-security-companies"/>
    <title>Private Security Companies</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the development of a regulatory system for private security companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aims to raise the global standards of private security companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) working in complex and high risk environments overseas. To this end, we have been working closely with interested partners, including industry and civil society, to establish a voluntary, independently audited and internationally recognised regulatory system that is practicable, effective and affordable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification to professional standards is the next step towards effective voluntary regulation. First the Government endorsed the Montreux Document in 2008, in which States commit to observe existing international legal obligations relevant to the operations of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in areas of armed conflict. Secondly, in 2010, an International Code of Conduct for Private Security Providers (&lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt;) was created. This provides a set of principles to guide companies. The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been signed by over 500 &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;, around a third of them British. We have reviewed options on setting new professional standards to make the Code effective. We now intend to issue an HMG publication specifying that ASIS PSC 1-2012 is the applicable standard for UK-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments on land overseas. I will place a copy of the publication in the libraries of both Houses. Companies, independent auditors and the UK Accreditation Service (&lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) will then take the further steps to enable auditing against these standards to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; mandated the development of auditable standards to ensure that signatory companies are implementing their commitments under the code. In response to this requirement, the international security trade association, ASIS, was funded by the Department of Defense to develop the standard – ‘PSC1’ – for the regulation of private security companies operating on land in complex environments overseas. This standard was drafted in a multinational and multi-stakeholder forum in which UK Government, UK industry and UK civil society fully participated.  It was published in March 2012 as an approved American National Standard and is the only standard currently available for companies operating in this field. &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; seeking certification in the UK to this new standard will have to be audited by independent third party auditors accredited by &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our trade association partners, the Security in Complex Environments Group, will, in consultation with Government, develop guidance to help British &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; meet the requirements of the new standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ambition is to have a single, internationally agreed standard and we therefore welcome the fact that PSC1 was recently submitted to the International Standards Organisation (ISO) to be considered for adoption as an international standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments. This process may take some time. We will review the need for a separate HMG publication of this standard once the ISO process has been completed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working with other States, industry and civil society internationally to ensure that there should be globally recognised standards and that UK companies are not unfairly disadvantaged by raising their standards. We expect that the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; governing board, when established, will advise that certification to the PSC 1 standard by suitably accredited independent auditors will meet the Code’s requirements for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to have auditable professional standards. We are still consulting with industry and civil society partners on what additional steps &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; might need to take to obtain full certification by the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; that they are meeting the Code’s principles but I can confirm that there will be no need for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to go through duplicate auditing procedures to become certified.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; was drafted with land-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in mind. However, since 2010 there has been a rapid rise in the number of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on anti-piracy operations at sea. Although many of the principles relating to &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on land and at sea are similar, there are important legal and practical differences. The Government is therefore also contributing to an international drafting process under the ISO for an equivalent professional standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in the maritime sector. A draft maritime standard was introduced at the International Maritime Organisation in late November. If and when this standard is adopted, &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will start the process of accrediting suitably qualified independent third party auditors to certify UK-based maritime &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity on the standards against which &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; should be audited is an important step forward in the drive to raise standards in this industry through voluntary action, but independently audited. It is also a practical illustration of the Government’s commitment to human rights and to working with business and civil society to find effective ways to implement our commitments even in the most challenging environments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50198</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:45:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/piracy-ransoms-task-force-publishes-recommendations"/>
    <title>Piracy Ransoms Task Force publishes recommendations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Today the Piracy Ransoms Task Force presented its conclusions on how to work together to reduce the threat of piracy and ultimately ransom payments to pirates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force was established by the Prime Minister, David Cameron, after the London Conference on Somalia in February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14-nation Task Force, brought together policy makers from some of the world’s largest Flag States (countries where vessels are registered), nations whose seafarers are most commonly at risk, and those countries at the forefront of the military response to piracy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Task Force made four recommendations in its final report to the Contact Group on Piracy off the Coast of Somalia in New York:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a new strategic partnership between Flag States, the private sector and law enforcement agencies that brings together those tackling piracy and those subjected to it in a united effort to break the piracy business model;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a more co-ordinated approach to information-sharing to provide evidence to pursue and prosecute all involved in piracy;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen co-ordination between Flag States, the private sector and military responders to prepare for potential hostage situations; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage implementation of anti-piracy measures, including greater compliance with Best Management Practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s conclusions from the Piracy Ransoms Task Force are a welcome step in the right direction. International action, led by the UK, is starting to beat back in the global fight against piracy. The dramatic reduction in pirate activity in the past year shows how important collective action is, and the recommendations of the Task Force should make it harder for pirates to receive, and to profit from, ransom payments. But seafarers of all nations remain at risk, and we must continue to work to break the piracy business model, with the ultimate ambition of bringing an end to ransom payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Government firmly supports and endorses the conclusions of the Piracy Ransoms Task Force. Only through the international community working together to break the pirates’ business model will we reach a position whereby pirates are no longer able to receive or profit from ransom payments. The Government will continue to work as a leading member of the Contact Group and with industry in taking forward the implementation of the task force’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35286</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-09T20:31:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-sharpens-skills-for-the-gulf"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth sharpens skills for the Gulf</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The ship's company of Royal Navy warship HMS Monmouth have been keeping themselves in shape and ready for operations in the Gulf while transiting the Mediterranean.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate and crew of 215 left Plymouth last month and will be policing busy shipping lanes in the Gulf crucial to maritime trade in order to disrupt and deter piracy and other illegal activities at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep the ship at a high level of readiness takes a lot of training and hard work, so, during the ship’s transit to the region, the crew have been taking part in a wide variety of physical and military exercises to keep themselves ready for operational duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A period in the eastern Mediterranean allowed the weapon engineering department to take advantage of a NATO training exercise in Crete and prove the accuracy of all sensors and weapon systems on board. This also allowed the ship’s Royal Navy and Royal Marines boarding teams to participate in multiple boarding exercises with Greek forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One dramatic element of the training was ‘fast roping’ down to the ship from a Lynx helicopter operated and maintained by members of the ship’s flight from 815 Naval Air Squadron, who are embarked for the deployment. The warfare department also provided gun shoots and small-arms firings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Marine White takes part in a continuation shoot on board HMS Monmouth whilst transiting the Mediterranean en route to the Gulf " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1587/HMS_Monmouth_sharpens_skills_for_the_Gulf2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Marine White takes part in a continuation shoot on board HMS Monmouth whilst transiting the Mediterranean en route to the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Ben Shread, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While shooting, fast roping and simulated boarding of small boats took place above deck, the chefs were busy cooking meals for the ship’s company but still found the time to make a replica chocolate version of Nelson’s flagship Victory for the wardroom’s Trafalgar Night dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sailors themselves are also being put through their paces by Leading Physical Trainer Danny Card who has been running boxing circuits and early morning workouts each day to keep them fighting fit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Almost 100 per cent of the ship’s company are in date for their standard fitness test and the majority are highly motivated to get fitter during the deployment,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a high demand for lots of different types of fitness training, with every range of fitness represented taking part in physical exercise on board each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This busy period for the ship’s company supplements the months of operational training they had before leaving the UK - the crew of HMS Monmouth is ready in all respects if called into action in the patrol area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35220</id>
    <published>2012-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-sutherlands-top-gunners-fend-off-french-top-guns"/>
    <title>HMS Sutherland's top gunners fend off French top guns</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Sutherland came under attack from supersonic French fighters based in Djibouti as the frigate swapped counter-piracy duties for a brief return to traditional war-fighting training.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Devonport-based frigate came under ‘attack’ from a pair of French Mirage jets of 3/11 Course Squadron based in Djibouti during air defence training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At high altitude the Mirages can notch up speeds in excess of 1,500mph (2,400km/h) - more than twice the speed of sound. At low level, they’re limited to a little under 690mph (1,110km/h), whereas Sutherland can get up to 39.5mph flat-out (34 knots or 64km/h) - achieved during speed trials back in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its top low-altitude speed, a Mirage will eat up 1,012 feet (308m) every second - which gives gunners like Able Seaman Herring three seconds to react; the range of the minigun - a Gatling gun which spews out up to 6,000 rounds a minute - is a little over 3,000 feet (914m).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training, known in military parlance as an ADEX (Air Defence Exercise), came about thanks to the personal touch; a couple of French pilots came aboard the frigate when she took a break from her patrols to take on supplies, and thus the seeds were sown for a ‘workout’ which tested airmen and sailors alike:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was fantastic training for the entire ship’s company - we practised our core war-fighting skills in the operations room, ship handling from the bridge, and there was battle damage overlaid to test the entire ship’s company,” said Sutherland’s Operations Officer Lieutenant Commander Tom Westwood.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Mirages carried out simulated missile raids and bombing attacks for an hour. Sutherland defeated each incoming raid and manoeuvred aggressively to ensure all her weapons and sensors could engage the targets.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Mirage pilots commented on the difficulty they faced attacking the ship due to her manoeuvres and the skill of the ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will though be back to give it another go; Sutherland intends to repeat the exercise with the French when she’s next in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not merely the gunners aboard the ship who’ve been tested recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short visit to the Omani capital of Muscat, the frigate headed out into the Gulf of Oman to join US forces for a three-day submarine hunt as Sutherland and the Arleigh Burke Class destroyer USS Nitze tried to find an American hunter-killer boat lurking somewhere below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the Devonport-based frigate could call upon the ship’s Merlin, call-sign ‘Warlock’, to track down the ‘foe’; the helicopter is widely acknowledged in naval circles as the best there is at sub-hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Merlin crew, who’ve devoted most of the deployment to maritime security and board and search operations with Sutherland’s Royal Marines Commando detachment, a spot of ‘pinging’ was a welcome return to the helicopter’s raison d’etre:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The anti-submarine exercise allowed us to refresh and refine our core and advanced anti-submarine warfare skills in challenging environmental conditions,” said Merlin Flight Commander Lieutenant Earl Kingston.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It was the perfect opportunity for my team to adjust our traditional tactics - normally employed in more temperate climes - to the unique oceanography of this region.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And it allowed us to work closely with our American cousins and make use of their submarine, so we gained an insight into the different tactics they employ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the exercise Sutherland and Nitze conducted a simultaneous fuel replenishment at sea with the aptly-named USNS Supply, an American fast combat support ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sutherland will continue her wide-ranging mission - a combination of keeping the sea lanes open for lawful usage by mariners and working with friendly nations and navies in the region - until the year’s end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/43381</id>
    <published>2012-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T22:54:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-helps-reduce-somali-pirate-activity"/>
    <title>Royal Navy helps reduce Somali pirate activity</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Following his posting as Commander of the UK Counter-Piracy Task Group, Captain Gerry Northwood, Royal Navy, has written in The Times newspaper about how concerted efforts are helping reduce attacks on merchant vessels.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Northwood writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Eleven pirates on board with automatic weapons and rocket-propelled grenades. All comms on ship are down. Crew safe in engine room and have control of engine and steering. Please help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message was contained in a plastic water bottle thrown into the Indian Ocean by a member of the security team on board the Italian Merchant Vessel Montecristo, which the previous day had been boarded by Somali pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate times require desperate measures and, in this age of satellites, radar and computers, calling for help via a message in a bottle certainly qualifies as an act of desperation. The security team had attached a strobe light to the bottle, which, fortunately for the 23 Montecristo crew members, was picked up by a US frigate, De Wert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not far from her was our ship, the Royal Fleet Auxiliary Fort Victoria, equipped with a Royal Navy helicopter and Royal Marine boarding teams. We were able to answer the master of Montecristo’s plea for help, recapture his ship from the pirates, and return it to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The gunner on HMS Somerset's Merlin helicopter fires shots across the bow of a pirated dhow " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1964/Royal_Navy_helps_reduce_Somali_pirate_activity2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The gunner on HMS Somerset's Merlin helicopter fires shots across the bow of a pirated dhow pi[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Kyle Heller and LA (Phot) Dave Jenkins, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 15 Somalis we detained are now in Italian custody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montecristo was lucky; lucky that Fort Victoria could cross 550 miles [885km] of Indian Ocean, the distance from Portsmouth to Edinburgh, before the pirates broke into the crew safe area or ‘citadel’. But she also made her own luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was well prepared for her transit of the Indian Ocean with razor wire defences of her upper decks and superstructure. These at least slowed the pirates down as they boarded the vessel and gave the crew and their unarmed security team time to retreat and barricade themselves into the engine room, and wait for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Montecristo incident is the Somali piracy problem and some of its solutions in microcosm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago Somali pirates were a regular feature in the news. The number of attacks on merchant vessels was in double figures each month and the number of vessels held by the Somalis for ransom had increased to more than 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advent of Somali piracy in 2008 caught people by surprise, and there was a strong sense that nothing could be done to defeat the pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no obvious solution to the problems of Somalia ashore, the huge distances involved made it difficult for military forces to protect merchant vessels effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give some idea of scale, in the four months that Fort Victoria was at sea she operated in an area the size of western Europe, patrolling a front 2,300 miles [3,700km] long - the distance from Berlin to Moscow - and steaming a total of 27,000 miles [43,500km].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something has been done and the past few months have seen a significant reversal of fortunes. Attacks on merchant vessels are down by 80 per cent and today there are only a handful of vessels held captive off the Somali coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most merchant vessels in the Indian Ocean and the Gulf of Aden are now employing armed and unarmed security teams, along with other protection measures. Collectively this description of merchant ship self-protection goes by the mundane name of ‘industry best management practice’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet these measures work. In most cases they prevent the pirates successfully boarding vessels. This enables the patrolling naval forces to locate the attacking pirate vessels and detain the Somalis for prosecution. All this has served to set back Somali piracy activity to 2007 levels and to reduce their cashflow significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are tactical successes that must be viewed in the context of a much bigger strategic picture. They depend on a far wider network of operations involving politicians, commercial shipping and other agencies. When Fort Victoria recently captured 14 Somali pirates we were able to take them to the Seychelles for prosecution. Thanks to the support of the British High Commissioner to the Seychelles and his strong relations with members of its government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is an even bigger strategic picture. The pressure put on pirates by military success has created headroom for those tackling the more intractable issues of governance ashore in Somalia. This week’s Somalia Conference in London marks the next stage in restoring calm to the Indian Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/43383</id>
    <published>2012-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T23:01:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-returns-pirated-dhow-to-owner"/>
    <title>Royal Navy returns pirated dhow to owner</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy and Royal Marines personnel embarked on Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) vessel Fort Victoria have successfully rescued a dhow from the clutches of 14 suspected Somali pirates and returned it to its rightful Yemeni owner.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni fishing dhow, which was recovered from the suspected Somali pirates on Friday 13 January 2012, had been hijacked and held in a known pirate camp ashore. Awadh Barasheed, the owner of the dhow, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am happy to receive my dhow back after being pirated since 18 May 2011. I would like to thank the coalition forces and specifically the British Navy for retrieving my dhow from the hands of the criminal pirates. This dhow is the only source of income for me, my brothers and our families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy and Royal Marines personnel embarked on RFA Fort Victoria were able to hand back the dhow in international waters in the Gulf of Aden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Gerry Northwood, Royal Navy, Commander of the UK Counter-Piracy Task Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The dhow was handed to the captain of Yemeni Navy ship 1031 and the agent acting on behalf of the dhow’s owner. This was an excellent example of the Royal Navy and the Yemeni Navy working together for the common good of the local maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Gerry Northwood presents a plaque to the captain of Yemeni Navy ship 1031 " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1967/Royal_Navy_returns_pirated_dhow_to_owner2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Gerry Northwood presents a plaque to the captain of Yemeni Navy ship 1031 [Picture: LA(Phot) Kyle Heller, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Saleh Bayumain, Chairman of the Dhow Owners Association of Mukalla, passed a message back to the Yemeni Liaison Officer based at Combined Maritime Forces headquarters to express his own appreciation of the Royal Navy, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are happy to see a member of our association is getting back to business. On behalf of all dhow owners of Mukalla I would like to express my gratitude to the commander of the British naval ship and his dedicated and noble crew members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My thanks also extend to all the maritime forces who patrol the area and fight piracy; they have helped us on many occasions and provided help in terms of food, water, fuel and mechanical support. Thanks also to our Navy and Coast Guard who followed up with this issue from the beginning and co-ordinated the delivery of the dhow to its owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2008 the Royal Navy has been actively assisting the local maritime community in the Horn of Africa and the Indian Ocean through international counter-piracy efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO-led counter-piracy task force conducts routine visits to local ships, merchant vessels and fishing dhows going about their lawful business in international waters to confirm that they are safe and to reassure them that the international maritime forces are in the area as a force for good, to protect them from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Northwood added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased that we were able to return the dhow to its rightful owner. It is important that through our co-operation with the Yemeni Navy we reassure the local maritime community that we are able to protect their interests. They are as much the victims of Somali piracy as the larger international ships navigating through the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFA Fort Victoria has been acting as part of a NATO task group in support of Operation OCEAN SHIELD. In the past ten days, five pirate groups have been successfully disrupted in the Gulf of Aden and over fifty pirates are potentially facing the prospect of prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55934</id>
    <published>2012-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-fac-report-on-piracy"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes FAC report on piracy</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague has welcomed the Foreign Affairs Committee (FAC) report "Piracy off the Coast of Somalia".</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement today, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the Foreign Affairs Committeepira report into Piracy off the coast of Somalia. Somali piracy has grown into a major international problem, exacerbating the wider challenges we face in helping Somalia recover from conflict and drought. We will use the London Conference on Somalia to chart a way forward on the future political direction of Somalia, the vital humanitarian effort and the international community’s approach to tackling piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I particularly welcome the FAC’s clear support for our military engagement in the Gulf of Aden and in the wider Indian Ocean, for our position on establishing an extra-territorial Somali court, and policy of prosecuting pirates in local courts and our prisoner transfer agreements. Britain will continue to work with the UN, African Union, regional partners and the Somali people to build a stable Somalia and through our work with DFID to build sustainable alternative livelihoods for coastal communities in Somalia.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/41672</id>
    <published>2011-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T13:49:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-cumberland-continues-to-support-carrier-charles-de-gaulle"/>
    <title>HMS Cumberland continues to support carrier Charles de Gaulle</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Cumberland has continued her operations over the Christmas and New Year period in support of the French aircraft carrier Charles de Gaulle by escorting her through the Strait of Hormuz early Boxing Day morning (26 December 2010).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While most people in Britain were sleeping off the Christmas Day excess, HMS Cumberland led the French carrier group through the vital Strait of Hormuz and into the Gulf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British frigate had been acting in support of Charles de Gaulle in the Indian Ocean while she conducted air operations into Afghanistan over the Christmas period. Cumberland’s duties with the French will continue in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cumberland’s Christmas tasking afforded her crew little opportunity to relax and enjoy the festivities, although, in traditional fashion, roast turkey and all the trimmings was served to the sailors by Cumberland’s Captain and officers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Steve Dainton, Captain of HMS Cumberland, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cumberland’s tasking in support of Charles de Gaulle over Christmas has demonstrated the longstanding and close working relationship between the French Navy and us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Strait of Hormuz is a vital sea lane and Cumberland has been tasked to assist in the provision of security for the French carrier. This is a task we have already provided for other high value shipping since we’ve been on task in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Cumberland (background) and French carrier Charles de Gaulle (foreground) " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1749/HMS_Cumberland_continues_to_support_carrier_Charles_de_Gaulle2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Cumberland (background) and French carrier Charles de Gaulle (foreground) [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cumberland is a versatile multi-role frigate, and is as much at home providing support to the carrier as she has been providing a reassuring presence to peaceful maritime use of the Gulf since the beginning of November 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She assumed responsibility as the on-watch Gulf frigate from HMS Somerset on 31 October 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, she has been employed conducting energy security patrols in the Gulf, ensuring the safety of critical energy supply routes for the UK and her allies. She has also been tasked with the protection of the Al Basra oil platform in Iraqi territorial waters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 80 per cent of Iraq’s GDP is pumped through the terminal and into waiting oil tankers which then pass through the strategically critical Strait of Hormuz. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Cumberland will remain on task in the Gulf until well into the New Year. She is due to return home to Devonport in March prior to decommissioning in the summer as part of savings following the Strategic Defence and Security Review. She sailed from the UK on 30 September 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/43374</id>
    <published>2010-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T22:34:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-destroy-pirate-vessel"/>
    <title>Royal Marines destroy pirate vessel</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Marines based onboard a Royal Navy warship destroyed a boat yesterday that was being used by pirates off the coast of Somalia to attack merchant ships.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Marines, from Plymouth-based frigate HMS Montrose, fired their machine guns at the pirate vessel as they hovered above it in the warship’s Lynx helicopter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incident took place during a routine patrol off the Somali coast yesterday, Tuesday 23 November 2010, when the helicopter identified the suspect boat as the whaler from MV Aly Zoulfecar, which had been acting as a pirate ‘mother ship’ since it was hijacked on 3 November 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whaler was anchored off a known pirate camp and, once permission had been given to take it out, the Royal Marines marksmen fired their M3M .50-calibre machine guns and destroyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Montrose’s Commanding Officer, Commander Jonathan Lett, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Montrose has been patrolling off the Somali coast for some time and we know how the pirates operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our destruction of the whaler close to a known pirate camp has sent a message to the Somali pirates that NATO and other coalition forces are willing to take the fight to them in order to prevent them from attacking merchant ships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Montrose is operating off the Somali coast as part of NATO’s counter-piracy operation, OCEAN SHIELD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
