<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/maintaining-an-effective-independent-nuclear-deterrent/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-an-effective-independent-nuclear-deterrent/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-an-effective-independent-nuclear-deterrent/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Maintaining an effective, independent nuclear deterrent"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T10:04:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59911</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:04:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-united-kingdom-s-future-nuclear-deterrent-2012-update-to-parliament"/>
    <title>The United Kingdom’s future nuclear deterrent: 2012 update to Parliament</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This report explains the progress the MOD has made on this programme and set out what is expected to be achieved over the coming year.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 May 2011, the Ministry of Defence (MOD) announced that the first milestone (known as Initial Gate) for the Successor deterrent submarine programme had been passed and that a five year-long, £3 billion Assessment Phase had been approved. The main purpose of the Assessment Phase is to refine the design of the successor submarine prior to the main investment decision (known as Main Gate), which will be taken in 2016. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of annual reports that will explain the progress the MOD has made on this programme and set out what is expected to be achieved over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/43707</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T16:18:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-2-billion-contract-awarded-for-new-attack-submarine"/>
    <title>£1.2 billion contract awarded for new attack submarine</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MOD has awarded a £1.2 billion contract for Audacious, the latest Astute Class attack submarine to be built for the Royal Navy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Audacious" title="Audacious"&gt;Audacious&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth of 7 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class" title="Astute Class"&gt;Astute Class&lt;/a&gt;  submarines being built for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt;. They are the most technologically-advanced the Royal Navy has ever sent to sea and offer a step-change in capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.www.baesystems.com/" title="BAE Systems"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; will safeguard 3,000 skilled jobs at Barrow-in-Furness in Cumbria and represents a significant step forward in the Astute submarine programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 2 boats, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/HMS-Astute" title="HMS Astute"&gt;Astute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Ambush" title="Ambush"&gt;Ambush&lt;/a&gt;, are currently undergoing sea trials to rigorously test their systems. Astute has conducted deep dive trials and successfully fired Tomahawk land attack missiles and Spearfish torpedoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambush’s ability to dive and surface has been successfully tested, as has her propulsion system, and the third boat, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Artful" title="Artful"&gt;Artful&lt;/a&gt;, is reaching the final stages of her construction at Barrow shipyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD can also confirm today that a further £1.5 billion has been committed to the remaining 3 submarines in the class. This has enabled early build work to start on the next boat (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Anson" title="Anson"&gt;Anson&lt;/a&gt;) and long lead items to be ordered and bought for the as yet unnamed boats six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This £1.2 billion contract marks an important step forward in the progress of the Astute programme and moves the Royal Navy closer to adding more of these highly advanced and powerful attack submarines to its fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce today that the MOD is committing more than £1.5 billion for boats five, six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Astute " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1735/45150807.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Astute sails up the Clyde estuary (library image) [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) J J Massey, Crown Copyright/MOD 2009]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding demonstrates our commitment not only to a key Royal Navy capability but also to the submarine industry in Barrow which will play a vital role in Astute for decades to come. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD’s Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Astute Class will become the jewel in the crown of the Royal Navy’s Submarine Service and boasts much greater firepower and more advanced sonar and communications than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These submarines represent a huge leap forward in technology and will operate all over the world with the Royal Navy. These boats provide the optimum capability a submarine can offer in land strike, strategic intelligence-gathering, anti-submarine and surface ship warfare, and protection of the strategic deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Featuring the latest nuclear-powered technology, the Astute Class never need to be refuelled and can circumnavigate the world submerged, manufacturing the crew’s oxygen from seawater as they go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 7,400-tonne Astute Class are quieter than older submarines, and can operate covertly and remain undetected despite being 50% bigger than the Royal Navy’s current &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class" title="Trafalgar Class"&gt;Trafalgar Class&lt;/a&gt; submarines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55164</id>
    <published>2012-07-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-signs-trident-support-contract"/>
    <title>MOD signs Trident support contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Ministry of Defence has today signed a 15-year contract with ABL Alliance to provide support of the Trident Strategic Weapon System at the Royal Naval Armament Depot (RNAD) Coulport and the Strategic Weapon Support Building (SWSB) Faslane, both of which are part of Her Majesty's (HM) Naval Base Clyde.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNAD Coulport has provided support to the UK’s nuclear deterrent for over 40 years, delivering safe and secure support to both the Polaris and Trident Strategic Weapon Systems. In 2008 the MOD started looking at a range of options to ensure that the work of Coulport, and associated work at the SWSB, can continue to be carried out effectively in the long term, and in May 2011 we decided that the most effective way to sustain the workforce in the future was to use an experienced supplier within the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the conclusion of our commercial negotiations, we have signed a 15-year contract to outsource elements of support at Coulport and the SWSB. The contract is with an industrial alliance of contractors: AWE plc, Babcock and Lockheed Martin UK Strategic Systems (LMUKSS), known collectively as the ABL Alliance, under a prime and strategic sub-contractor arrangement, with AWE plc in the role of prime contractor. This will ensure that the highly skilled workforce at Coulport and in the SWSB can be maintained in the long term, delivering vital support to the Trident system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three contractors have extensive experience of supporting the UK’s independent nuclear deterrent, gained over many years: AWE plc has successfully run the Atomic Weapons Establishment under Government Owned Contractor Operated (GOCO) arrangements since 2000, so this new arrangement is a natural extension of their current role in supporting the nuclear warhead carried by our Trident missiles. In addition, Babcock carries out all our major submarine maintenance at Devonport Dockyard, and already plays a major role in submarine support at HM Naval Base Clyde; and LMUKSS is part of the consortium that owns AWE plc, and has an existing role in providing Strategic Weapon System support in the SWSB and at Coulport. With their impressive track records, I am confident that these companies have the knowledge and experience to operate Coulport and the SWSB to the high standards we expect, and will build on the skills of the existing workforce. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under these arrangements 149 MOD civilian posts will transfer to ABL Alliance under the Transfer of Undertakings Protection of Employment (TUPE) Regulations (2006). The staff transferring are specialist SWS industrial and technical grades, warehousing operatives, logistic support services, supervisors and managers. In addition, 39 Royal Navy posts will be seconded to the alliance. The Department has already engaged extensively with the relevant Trade Unions, and this will continue as the formal TUPE consultation process now takes place. Subject to the successful completion of this further consultation, and on conclusion of a six-month transition phase, Vesting Day will take place, which will mark the formal start of the new arrangement. This is currently scheduled for January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Naval Base Clyde has an excellent safety record and we are determined to maintain the highest standards of safety. The MOD will continue to own the Naval Base sites, including Coulport, and Naval Base Commander Clyde will retain overall responsibility for security and for the activities carried out at Coulport and the SWSB. The site will also continue to be a MOD Nuclear Authorised site, so will be subject to regulation by the Defence Nuclear Safety Regulator, the Office of Nuclear Regulation and other regulatory bodies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/34803</id>
    <published>2012-06-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/080-2012-hammond-announces-1billion-contract-to-power-future-submarines"/>
    <title>080/2012 - Hammond announces £1billion contract to power future submarines</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MoD has awarded Rolls Royce a £1.1 billion contract to produce new reactor cores for the Royal Navy’s nuclear submarines and upgrade the plant where they will be built.
The nuclear reactor cores will be used to power the seventh and final Astute Class submarine and the first of the Royal Navy’s next generation of nuclear deterrent submarines, known as the Successor Class.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investment – which secures 300 jobs at Rolls Royce - will also fund an eleven-year refurbishment of Rolls Royce’s plant at Raynesway in Derby, extending its operating lifetime by more than 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract will see construction of new buildings that will replace existing facilities that have reached the end of their useful life.
Replacing the existing infrastructure with state of the art nuclear reactor core production facilities will cost around £500m. A further £600m will be spent on producing new reactor cores for the Astute and Successor Class submarines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announcing the contract, Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having balanced the MoD’s books we can now invest in vital strategic capabilities to meet the present and future defence needs of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This contract will secure hundreds of highly-skilled jobs for UK industry, while retaining our sovereign nuclear capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Raynesway site has played a key part in the production and maintenance of our nuclear deterrent for more than 50 years. This regeneration will make sure it continues to do so for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoD’s Director of Submarines, Rear Admiral Simon Lister, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very pleased that this contract has been signed as it will ensure that our future submarines are powered with the very best reactor cores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raynesway is a centre of excellence for nuclear reactor core production and the site works to stringent health and safety practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The site has an excellent safety record and this investment will make sure that the very highest standards of nuclear and conventional safety continue to be maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rolls-Royce in Derby is contracted by the MoD to support the UK’s submarine programme through the provision of a plant design, support and manufacturing capability. They are not involved in nuclear weapons related work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Astute Class are the largest, most advanced and most powerful attack submarines ever operated by the Royal Navy. They are nuclear-powered but not nuclear-armed. The Strategic Defence and Security Review, published in October 2010, confirmed that the MoD plans to purchase seven Astute-class submarines, which are in various stages of build and development, with the First of Class, HMS Astute, commissioned into the Royal Navy in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with almost all large-scale complex programmes it is necessary to procure some Long Lead Items in advance to ensure their availability for when the submarine build is commenced; this will also ensure that the boats can be delivered to schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information, please contact Lex Oliver in the MoD Press Office, on 0207 218 3256.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photographs of HMS Astute are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dni.mod.uk"&gt;www.dni.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Username: GuestUser
Password: WhiteBoard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/18754</id>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:20:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-02-09-royal-navy-club-founders-day-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/02/09 - Royal Navy Club Founder's Day Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for the Armed Forces at Trinity House, London on Thursday 9 February 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chairman, First Sea Lord, Gentlemen, it is an honour to be invited to address this year’s Founders’ Day dinner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the Admiralty Board, may I thank you Mr Chairman for your hospitality - and the Elder Brethren of Trinity House for allowing us to celebrate here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a busy year for the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the First Sea Lord intends to speak about operations, so let me express my appreciation, and that of the Government, for the incredible work that has been done by the Royal Navy since the last Founder’s Day Dinner: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On standing operations around the globe; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining our nuclear deterrent; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Royal Marines and others in Afghanistan; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the very substantial Naval contribution to Operation Ellamy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-state-of-the-nation"&gt;The State of the Nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by acknowledging, that as well as being a busy time for the Navy, it has been a great stretch, and this last 18 months has been particularly difficult as the reality of what the SDSR means settles in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing ships like Cumberland decommissioned - or Ark Royal - or aircraft like Harrier - all having given such good service to the Navy and the nation over many years;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy seeing gaps appear in naval capabilities like carrier strike;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not easy saying goodbye to colleagues you’ve served with for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redundancy programme, in particular, is a matter of great regret to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m sure everyone here recognises that the Government had to act to tackle the huge bow wave of unfunded liabilities that had built up in the Defence programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in itself, would have been a daunting effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not only this, I think, that has been so sobering over the last 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also been the realisation by many, particularly those of us concerned with the defence of the nation, of just how threatening the UK’s financial situation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The national debt has now topped a trillion pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are spending £50bn a year on the interest alone - the equivalent of a dozen Queen Elizabeth Aircraft Carriers or 33 Astute Class submarines - the scale of what we, as a nation, are facing becomes clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years ago, it was institutions like Northern Rock and the Royal Bank of Scotland that were being bailed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last year it’s been whole countries - Ireland, Greece, Italy, Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the United States has had its credit rating down-graded - and is cutting its defence budget by a staggering $500bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eurozone crisis has thrown a spotlight on just how exposed Britain’s economy is - and it has shown us just how isolated Britain could quickly become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nietzsche said - if you gaze for long into an abyss, the abyss gazes also into you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced, that in this era of great volatility, in this era of interconnectedness, in this era of economic exposure, Britain will continue to need all the benefits, all the influence and all the security that accrue from being a maritime power of significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is: how do we sustain that power in an age of austerity and competing demands - austerity and competing demands that are shared by our most dependable allies too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I try to answer that question, let me set out why Britain needs to remain a maritime power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-utility-of-maritime-power"&gt;The Utility of Maritime Power&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am of course preaching to the converted here so I will keep it brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an operational point of view, maritime power is essential in a world where we have to project power to protect our national security;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we have to gain access to, and operate in, other domains in far flung parts of the world;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the littoral remains the focus of so much human activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea-basing provides choice and flexibility in deploying and sustaining force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides mobility, range and endurance and can help overcome a whole host of challenges associated with having a footprint on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are not abandoning carrier-strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we will maintain our amphibiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a vital part of the balanced capabilities that we have defined as Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maritime power, for Britain in particular, has never been solely about the application of military force in time of hot war - it is about a continuous national presence in other parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating slices of sovereign territory from which to operate and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea is a one of the most important global super-highways that Britain, as an island nation, depends upon for our prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on imports of goods and energy - the vast, vast majority coming by sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that dependence on the sea, especially for energy, is only going to increase in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only what comes and goes by sea - the trade which sustains our way of life - it is also about the resources the sea provides which need protecting - oil, minerals, fish, increasingly off-shore wind power too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe seas enable strong economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy has always played a part - sometimes alone, sometimes alongside our allies and friends - in making sure the vital sea arteries in the global commons are protected and that international law is observed - providing deterrence, reassurance, and influence - contributing to the nation’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="austerity-and-the-royal-navy"&gt;Austerity and the Royal Navy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, why more than any other institution in the country, you of the Royal Navy understand the inextricable link between economic power and the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is woven into much of your history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said an Army marches on its stomach - well it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Cicero said, finances are the sinews of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole of the Armed Forces march on the public purse - on the back of the taxes we all pay - and the size of the public purse depends ultimately on the health of the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, in my view, the coalition Government is right to focus its priority attention on getting the deficit under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right not only for the economy - but in the long-term it is right for national security too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only with healthy public coffers can we hope to sustain, in the long-term, the investment required for the high-tech, well equipped military forces we know we will need in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have had to act to both balance the Defence budget and bring the Defence Programme in line with the financial reality the country faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Budget took a hit - not nearly as much as some other departments - but a reduction in resources none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach the next General Election, and in preparation for the next Defence Review in 2015, the approach the political parties take to the Defence budget will be a measure of how committed they are to realising Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, thanks to cross-Government agreement, we now have the ability to plan on the budget allocated to defence equipment and support increasing by 1% a year in real terms between 2015 and 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been difficult but we are now close to achieving a sustainable budget for the first time in decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly confident that the end is in sight to the period of retrenchment and the period of growth will in time begin again with funds released for projects outside the core programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget that we are still spending considerable sums on Defence - over £150 billion over the next decade on defence equipment and support alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Royal Navy - we are already beginning to see the shape of Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Daring, Dauntless and Diamond now part of the fleet, Dragon expected in the Spring, and Defender and Duncan coming on line - in the Type 45, Britain can boast one of the most advanced warships in the world - and the envy of our allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Astute is nearing the end of her sea trials to be followed over the next few years by Ambush, Artful, Audacious, Anson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2020, the Queen Elizabeth Class Carriers - the largest ships the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime thereafter, the Type 26 Global Combat Ship will begin to come on stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these will be leaders in their field and represent the most capable, high-technology platforms the Royal Navy has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ship for ship this will be one of the most powerful fleets in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be smaller - yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fleet be able to do everything, everywhere, every time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No - of course not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are entering an era in which all of Britain’s security requirements - and those of our dependent territories - can only be guaranteed through our alliances and through our partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in reality, it has always been thus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to turn a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need now to begin the hard work of putting the Fleet of 2020 together, bringing these platforms on line, making sure we retain the right skills, developing new recruits, maintaining the profile of the Navy in the public mind - all the while delivering on operations - keeping our citizens safe - protecting our interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me pay tribute to the way the First Sea Lord has set out his vision of a powerful, adaptable and vibrant Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you here are in attendance through your qualification for command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the moral component of leadership is one of the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are currently serving we need you to be focussed, positive, full of ideas, prepared to change yourself, willing to drive change in others, inspiring those around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are no longer serving we need your continued energy and experience, advocating in public for maritime power - even if it means - every now and then - holding people like me to account for the decisions we are taking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this Founder’s Day, together we celebrate the long and illustrious history of the Royal Navy - but let us today also look forward with confidence in the future too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55408</id>
    <published>2011-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:05:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/navy-sub-fires-first-tomahawk-missile"/>
    <title>Navy sub fires first Tomahawk missile</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The first of the Royal Navy's new attack submarines, HMS Astute, has blasted Tomahawk missiles far across the North American skies as part of her first test firing mission.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 5.5-metre-long cruise missile weighs 1,300kg and has a range of more than 1,000 miles (1,600km). In the firing tests this month the Tomahawk weapons rocketed from HMS Astute at up to 550 miles per hour (885km/h) across the Gulf of Mexico. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Astute’s Commanding Officer, Commander Iain Breckenridge, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This first-of-class firing proves that Astute is a truly capable submarine. It means that the UK Submarine Service will be able to provide the UK’s strike capability for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Astute is in the Gulf of Mexico for the first test run of her system. She has the largest weapon-carrying capacity of all the Royal Navy’s attack submarines and can hold a combination of up to 38 Tomahawk missiles and Spearfish torpedoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See Related Links to watch video footage of the first launch of a Tomahawk missile from HMS Astute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is the only country supplied with the Tomahawk technology by the USA, and has been in operation since 1999. Missiles have been launched from various submarines to support operations in Afghanistan, Iraq and, most recently, Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Astute Class of nuclear-powered attack submarines are the most technologically-advanced submarines to serve with the Royal Navy and will progressively replace the Trafalgar Class currently in service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been designed with modern operations in mind and are vastly different in shape, size, capacity and capability to their predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Breckenridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The most noticeable difference for the ship’s company is that for the first time everyone has their own bunk. Design changes that will make an operational difference include the fact that we have a reactor that will never need to be refuelled in the boat’s 25-year life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have optronic masts instead of traditional periscopes, which means we have saved lots of space in the control room as well as having the benefit of digital cameras instead of traditional optical periscopes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Astute Class is designed to perform a number of roles including anti-submarine and surface ship warfare, and gathering intelligence to protect the UK’s strategic deterrent and surface shipping. It can also attack targets on land with Tomahawk guided missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The First of Class, HMS Astute was commissioned into the Royal Navy on 27 August 2010 and is currently undertaking a period of extensive sea trials before she is handed over for operational service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She will continue her trials in the USA until the early spring and will return to the UK for training before her first operational deployment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/18733</id>
    <published>2011-10-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:36:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-10-13-hms-anson-keel-laying-ceremony"/>
    <title>2011/10/13 - HMS ANSON Keel Laying Ceremony</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at Barrow-in-Furness, Cumbria on Thursday 13 October 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, it is a great pleasure to be here today to lay the keel of the fifth Astute Class submarine - ANSON. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submarine is the seventh British warship and the first submarine to bear this title, and is being named after the Admiral of the Fleet George Anson, who was one of our greatest First Lords of the Admiralty and noted for his circumnavigation of the globe, as well as his role overseeing the Royal Navy during the Seven Years War.  During Anson’s time in the Admiralty, his reforms reached into every aspect of the Navy, from shipbuilding and technological developments, to training and discipline, and command and control.  His work transformed our naval power into a global asset, and it laid the foundations for the naval victories of his era and the generation that followed.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that we lay the keel for Boat 5 of our new attack submarine flotilla as we ourselves continue through a planned course of Defence Reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last October, we confirmed our commitment to build a class of seven Astute Submarines.  ANSON will now join her sister boats, AMBUSH, ARTFUL and AUDACIOUS in construction here at Barrow.  Indeed, behind me you can see the great progress being made with ARTFUL and AUDACIOUS as they are welded together, fitted out and tested, and in essence ‘brought to life’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, many of you here today will recall the rather wet and blustery November day in 2009 when the first of class, HMS ASTUTE, sailed from Barrow to begin a programme of extensive and rigorous sea trials and training, which are demonstrating the boat’s capability.  I am pleased to report that ASTUTE is on track to begin her operational service around the end of 2012.  I was also delighted to learn that, the second of the Astute Class, AMBUSH, has successfully completed her first dive in the shipyard’s basin.  This is a critical milestone ahead of the boat’s planned exit from Barrow early next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are clear that the Royal Navy has a requirement for nuclear powered submarines.  Royal Navy submarines have made, and will continue to make, a vital contribution to the defence of the UK and interests overseas.  What many people do not appreciate is that they are perform a wide range of unique and essential military tasks, including global reach and endurance, and conduct unsupported operations in hostile environments whether operating close to the coast or deep in the oceans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I don’t need to tell you that the Astute Class provides a step change in anti-submarine and anti-surface warfare, protecting our Nuclear Deterrent, land attack, and intelligence gathering.  They have an improved capability for world-wide operations, much greater firepower, better communications, and crew accommodation than in-service submarines.  With advanced stealth technology, the Astute Class has been designed to be quieter than any of her predecessors and thus very hard to detect.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructing nuclear submarines is one of the most complex projects that our maritime industry - indeed any industry - undertakes.  The Royal Navy often say that the Astute Class is more sophisticated than the space shuttle and, for this reason alone, I pay tribute to the thousands of skilled people at BAE Systems Submarine Solutions and in the supply chain, as well as in the Royal Navy and the Ministry of Defence, who will be involved not just in ANSON’s construction journey but who have been and will be involved in the production of the Astute Class of submarines as a whole.  Being here today, in the very heart of the UK’s centre for excellence for submarine design and building, I can clearly see why each and every one of you are rightly proud of the contribution you are making in building the most powerful and advanced attack submarines ever delivered to the Royal Navy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government has provided assurances for the Astute Programme and also confirmed the long-term future of the Submarine Programme with a commitment to Continuous At Sea Deterrence and the Successor SSBN Programme.  However, given the challenges faced in balancing the Defence budget, such a commitment is predicated on the delivery of significant future efficiencies - in fact £900 million worth of efficiencies over the next 10 years.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work strand is known as the Submarine Enterprise Performance Programme (or SEPP), and we are engaged with the British submarine industry to improve efficiency and optimise to expected demand its capacity to build and support submarines &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since last year, the Ministry of Defence has been working collaboratively with BAE Systems Submarine Solutions, Babcock Marine, and Rolls Royce to transform the way the submarine programme is delivered and managed.  We want a Submarine Enterprise that is efficient and effective, and that offers sustainability in terms of skills, facilities and infrastructure.  I believe that we can deliver the SEPP objective of: “Performance Up, Cost Out, and Sustainability In” by developing a value for money submarine enterprise - built on long-term commercial arrangements - that recognises the contribution of each of the key industrial participants and provides the necessary programme stability for benefits of long-term partnering to be realised.  Through SEPP, the Ministry of Defence has established new collaborative ways of working in which joint MOD-Industry project teams have been pooling skills and expertise to ensure that the submarine programme is managed effectively; this unprecedented level of collaboration can only be good for all of us committed to the delivery of these fine boats.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEPP is the key to transformation in the Submarine Enterprise and I have every confidence in the joint team to deliver what we expect.  As you heard John Hudson say a few minutes ago, BAE Systems Submarine Solutions believe they will deliver ANSON in twenty percent less time than ASTUTE.  With SEPP at the helm of the Astute Submarine Programme - and indeed the Defence Submarine Programme as a whole - this is a transformation promise of which Admiral Anson himself would be proud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, let me say again how pleased I am to be here today.  Together we are witnessing the next step in this important programme that will deliver Defence capability and help ensure security for us all for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/34171</id>
    <published>2011-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:00:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/nuclear-liabilities-management-strategy"/>
    <title>Nuclear Liabilities Management Strategy</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy sets out the MOD’s high level approaches for managing the nuclear materials, fuel, sites, facilities, submarines and radioactive waste resulting from the Defence Nuclear Programme.  It provides the basis for a coherent approach to decommissioning and disposal activities relating to the UK’s nuclear weapon and nuclear submarine programmes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56706</id>
    <published>2011-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:06:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plans-for-successor-nuclear-deterrent-submarine-announced"/>
    <title>Plans for successor nuclear deterrent submarine announced</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox has today announced that approval has been given for the early phase of design of the submarine that will deliver the UK's nuclear deterrent well into the 2060s.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The submarines that will replace the existing Vanguard Class will be powered by a new nuclear propulsion system known as the Pressurised Water Reactor 3. This will deliver a longer lasting and more cost effective capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The continuous at sea deterrent is the ultimate guarantee of our national security and for the past 42 years the Royal Navy has operated continuous patrols to ensure just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not know how the international environment will change over the next 50 years and we cannot dismiss the possibility that a direct nuclear threat to the UK might emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is simply not the right time to unilaterally give this capability up. This programme of great national importance will also secure the future of one of Britain’s major manufacturing sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approval of this early phase of design - known as Initial Gate - ensures that while the main build decision for the submarines will not be taken until 2016, more detailed design work will be undertaken and long-lead items ordered so that the first submarine is delivered in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD’s Director Submarines, Rear Admiral Simon Lister, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While the Pressurised Water Reactor used in our existing submarines is a robust, highly controlled system that meets our stringent safety standards, the new Pressurised Water Reactor 3 will deliver further improvements such as ease of operation and lower costs over its extended life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of jobs will be secured across the country as a result of successor nuclear deterrent contracts being placed. Under this next phase, contracts are likely to cost in the region of £3bn. Overall, it is estimated that the submarines will be within the £11-14bn estimate set out in the 2006 White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Value for Money Study conducted alongside the Strategic Defence and Security Review, it was concluded that the MOD could demonstrate its commitment to disarmament by reducing the number of warheads and missiles carried on our submarines and this work is already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government is committed to maintaining a minimum credible nuclear deterrent and policy remains that a minimum nuclear deterrent based on the Trident missile delivery system and continuous at sea deterrence is right for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement reflected the desire of the Liberal Democrats to continue to make the case for alternatives. That is why the Defence Secretary has also announced the initiation of a study to be undertaken by the Cabinet Office and overseen by the Minister of State for the Armed Forces to review the costs, feasibility and credibility of alternative systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/34178</id>
    <published>2011-05-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:00:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-united-kingdom-s-future-nuclear-deterrent-the-submarine-initial-gate-parliamentary-report"/>
    <title>The United Kingdom’s Future Nuclear Deterrent: The Submarine Initial Gate Parliamentary Report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of this report is to outline the work that has taken place since the Parliamentary vote of March 2007; the decisions taken at Initial Gate; and the next steps that will be taken in the coming months and years to ensure the successful delivery of a successor nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
