<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/meeting-nato-and-eu-treaty-defence-commitments/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/meeting-nato-and-eu-treaty-defence-commitments/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/meeting-nato-and-eu-treaty-defence-commitments/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Meeting NATO and EU Treaty defence commitments"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T01:09:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55755</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T01:09:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T01:09:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-contribution-to-libya-campaign"/>
    <title>UK forces' contribution to Libya campaign</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a media briefing held earlier today, 27 October, in the Ministry of Defence Main Building, Air Marshal Peach began with a brief narrative of the operation recalling that, in February, as a result of the deterioration of the situation in Libya, there was quite a lot of work for Permanent Joint Headquarters (PJHQ) to do in terms of getting entitled persons out of the country:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The first thing I want to say about that is to say thank you to the government and the people of Malta for letting us form a base there. In terms of geography, that gave us a special advantage to deal with the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PJHQ, under the Air Marshal’s command, is a high-readiness group of people, ready to deploy rapidly around the world when something happens. In this case, they formed a non-combatant evacuation coordination cell, and by doing this avoided the situation where potentially three different countries could have sent three different aircraft in a disorganised way to pick up the same group of people: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a very soft attempt to coordinate across a group of nations who were all trying to do the same thing,” said the Air Marshal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was very successful. It was quite a tough call. We took a risk on the Sunday in particular, when we went deep with a C-130 into the desert. It was uncertain because of the number and nationality of the people there kept fluctuating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the same objective, Type 22 frigate HMS Cumberland was then moved into Benghazi harbour, which the Air Marshal also described as very uncertain at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think it was a very successful part of the story, we evacuated 1,400 people out of a total of 4,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An added advantage gained from this operation, known as Op DEFERENCE, was that it built up knowledge of the country and provoked some thinking about what might happen next:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were a bit surprised at how quickly things moved on,” said the Air Marshal. “We had the USCR 97 at the end of February, the National Transition Council established 5 March and then the no-fly zone was established. In quick time, some very successful operations were developed leading up to the hand over to NATO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost a maritime embargo was established in which the Royal Navy played a key role with a number of ships and people who understood very well command and control in these situations and how to do boarding and embargo operations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The influence of UK officers and men and women in command and control throughout this operation is something we should pay tribute to,” said Air Marshal Peach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A no-fly zone was quickly established. Having been personally involved in four of these in previous times, the Air Marshal said that, “we know how to do that.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO then took over, naming the operation ‘UNIFIED PROTECTOR’, and set up its HQ in Naples, a traditional NATO control centre:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the important features of this operation is the harmony and the importance of the role of Italy,” said Air Marshal Peach, “harmony because the Italian military authorities have been extremely good hosts for the UK, and the importance of the geography is pretty obvious. The amount of support they gave us, bases, fuel, logistics, command and control was and is extremely important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In supporting civilians who were being “quite aggressively killed by the Libyan forces,” Air Marshal Peach said that what he wanted to highlight above all was the importance of the precise application of force:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We judged, and I continue to judge, that unnecessary damage, or worse, the causing of civilian casualties would be a strategic liability for the campaign. The discipline of the ship, aircraft and helicopter crews are something I want to record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with NATO partners, Apache attack helicopters were introduced, mounted from HMS Ocean, to provide a useful tactical capability and, at the request of the NTC special advisers, “not Special Forces,” were introduced and who played a useful role in supporting the NTC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key military objective at this point in addition to protecting civilians from pro-Gaddafi forces was reducing the command and control of the regime to stop the attack on their own people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what was going on inside Libya was a key task throughout, not just along the coastal strip but deep inside the country as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also had some unusual tasks,” said Air Marshal Peach, “which I would not have predicted - for example, guarding Libyan dinars contained in a RAF C17 flown into Benghazi to get the money flowing; done, for obvious reasons, in complete secrecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Army Air Corps Apache and United States Air Force HH60 helicopters on board HMS Ocean, supporting Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR in the Mediterranean " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5335/UK_forces__contribution_to_Libya_campaign-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Army Air Corps Apache and United States Air Force HH60 helicopters on board HMS Ocean, supporting Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR in the Mediterranean  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Gaddafi regime fell back on traditional homeland areas the fighting in and around Sirte was very difficult as the need for the disciplined application of force was more important than ever:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At this point after all this investment of effort, we were not going to spoil it by being wanton in the application of force. So a number of times we held back, we held off, we made sure that the rules of engagement were strictly followed,” said Peach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have now reached the point where we are continuing to support operations awaiting direction from the North Atlantic Council, which we expect in the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The themes and lessons that have been identified by PJHQ include precision in the use of weapons which has been, the Air Marshal felt, world class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The accuracy, the consistency, and the predictions of the serviceability of our weapons has been confounded. The British weapons in particular have been world class. The low collateral damage of Brimstone is at the top end of anybody’s inventory in the world,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this precision, the Air Marshal argued, was not just because the bombs were good, but because of the ways in which the ships crews and the air crews are using and interpreting the rules of engagement, using their weapons in a disciplined way, guided by the AWACS aircrews operating 24-hours-a-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helicopters that deployed provided the ability to go as deep as 50 miles (80km) inland against a series of military targets. Video footage shows a crew taking out a target with two hellfire missiles; the second being fired and destroying the vehicle after those on the ground had been given time to flee. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At no point,” said the Air Marshal, “have British servicemen targeted individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tornados carried British-designed and British-built Brimstone missiles, which proved to be a world class weapon system. The Tornado, although undeniably an old platform, is bang up to date in terms of what’s going on inside the cockpit as far as control software, intelligence and reconnaissance is concerned, the Air Marshal said, and he also praised the ground crews who worked round the clock to make sure the aircraft kept flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a new aircraft is the Typhoon, and the Air Marshal said the aircraft had been adapted to carry weapons such as laser-guided bombs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained that the complimentary way Typhoons worked alongside the Tornados, using their targeting pods to create additional intelligence and reconnaissance, was very important: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Typhoon has been a great success on this operation,” he said. “We have also been very pleased with the way that the Army Air Corps adapted to life on the ocean wave aboard HMS Ocean; a first for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshall Peach closed by saying that the UK did not do all this alone, and that the success of the operation had depended on the input of 19 partner countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55749</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:48:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:48:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-commits-more-troops-to-balkans-peacekeeping-mission"/>
    <title>UK commits more troops to Balkans peacekeeping mission</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company of soldiers will be based in the UK, ready to deploy at short notice to the region if required as part of EUFOR (European Union Force) Operation ALTHEA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operation ALTHEA has the backing of a UN mandate and provides a military presence in Bosnia and Herzegovina to help maintain a safe and secure environment in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Minister for International Security Strategy, Gerald Howarth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This contribution reflects the UK’s strong political support for EUFOR Operation ALTHEA and our determination to help maintain a safe and secure environment in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While the security situation in the region remains calm and stable, it is essential that we provide EUFOR with the necessary resources to perform the mission’s mandate in full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;EUFOR provides an important safeguard underpinning stability and ensuring that Bosnia and Herzegovina can continue to make progress on its path towards EU and NATO accession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pledge of more troops in support of Operation ALTHEA will not take place until December in order not to impact on the Armed Forces’ commitment to the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EUFOR Operation ALTHEA became the legal successor in December 2004 to NATO’s SFOR (Stabilisation Force) mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EUFOR has the backing of a UN Chapter VII Mandate and its aim is to ensure continued compliance with the Dayton Peace Agreement and the continuance of a safe and secure environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55744</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:35:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:35:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-vietnam-sign-defence-co-operation-memorandum-of-understanding"/>
    <title>UK and Vietnam sign Defence Co-operation Memorandum of Understanding</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Astor of Hever, Parliamentary under Secretary of State for Defence, signed the MOU with Lieutenant General Nguyen Chi Vinh, Vietnam’s Deputy Minister of National Defence, at Lancaster House today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signing of this MOU follows on from the Strategic Partnership Declaration signed on 8 September 2010 by Vietnam’s Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister, Pham Gia Khiem, and the UK Foreign Secretary, William Hague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreement with Vietnam demonstrates the UK’s commitment to pursuing an active foreign policy with emerging powers around the world. The UK aims to make the Strategic Partnership a springboard to take our growing bilateral trade relationship to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Partnership Declaration demonstrates the breadth and the depth of our co-operation, including defence and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is looking to engage more closely with countries in South East Asia and the Defence Co-operation MOU signed today between Lord Astor and Lieutenant General Vinh is another example of this regional engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected that today’s MOU signing will further enhance the bilateral relationship and will aid the exchange of information in areas such as training and peace support operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Astor said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the opportunity to meet with Lieutenant General Nguyen Chi Vinh today and to sign the Defence Co-operation MOU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We had fruitful discussions on a number of topics and hope that the MOU will help to facilitate a deeper level of co-operation between our two nations, enhancing the bilateral relationship envisaged in the Strategic Partnership Declaration signed in London last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55730</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:53:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:53:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-french-ships-rendezvous-off-libyan-coast"/>
    <title>UK and French ships rendezvous off Libyan coast</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy’s helicopter carrier, and her French counterpart, Mistral, a Marine nationale (French Navy) projection and command ship, are both operating attack helicopters as part of the NATO-led Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR, enforcing UN Security Council Resolution (UNSCR) 1973 to protect Libyan citizens. Mistral recently took over operations from her sister ship Le Tonnerre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When British Prime Minister David Cameron and French President Nicolas Sarkozy signed the Defence Co-operation Treaty in November 2010, it was not expected that the opportunity would present itself quite so quickly to be able to practically demonstrate the two nations’ armed forces working more closely together, as a way of improving collective defence capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy and Marine nationale ships have been involved in operations off Libya since the start of the operation earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, there has been close coordination on attack helicopter maritime strike missions, and both HMS Ocean and Mistral have each embedded a liaison officer onboard the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have also been a number of visits between the Command teams in order to further understand how the other operates, further contributing to the aim of having, by the early 2020s, the ability to deploy an integrated British-French carrier strike group, incorporating assets from both countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since having been allocated to the mission in late June 2011, HMS Ocean has had several intensive periods at sea, launching embarked Apache Attack Helicopters from 656 Squadron Army Air Corps into Libya in support of the NATO-led operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Apaches have been ably assisted by other helicopters embarked on HMS Ocean, namely Sea King Mk 7s of 857 Naval Air Squadron, providing maritime surveillance, and Lynx Mk 7s of 847 Naval Air Squadron, providing force protection and logistic support. Together, the Apaches and Sea King Mk7s have flown a significant number of operational sorties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since leaving the UK in late April 2011, HMS Ocean has conducted over 2,000 deck landings by both embarked and visiting aircraft. This has included French Pumas flying from the aircraft carrier Charles de Gaulle, as well as both the amphibious ships Le Tonnerre and Mistral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean left the UK in April 2011 as part of the UK’s Response Force Task Group to conduct a series of pre-planned amphibious exercises in the Mediterranean, known as Cougar 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the escalating events in Libya, the UK Government took the opportunity in May 2011 to re-task one of the most flexible ships in the Royal Navy’s inventory, and ordered HMS Ocean to support the enforcement of UNSCR 1973.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to HMS Ocean, the other Royal Navy and Royal Fleet Auxiliary ships taking part in this operation currently comprise destroyer HMS Liverpool, mine countermeasures vessel HMS Bangor, and support ship RFA Fort Rosalie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Co-operation Treaty between the UK and France was drawn up to build upon commitments made in last year’s Strategic Defence and Security Review to create stronger strategic defence relationships with our main allies whose security interests and military capabilities are closest to our own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55715</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:10:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:10:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/action-in-libya-has-prevented-humanitarian-catastrophe"/>
    <title>Action in Libya has prevented 'humanitarian catastrophe'</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Updating Parliament on the situation in Libya, the Foreign Secretary said that 34 nations are now providing a range of assistance and that, since Thursday, a total of 701 sorties and 276 strike sorties have been conducted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, the Ministry of Defence announced that yesterday, 5 April 2011, RAF Tornado GR4s again deployed from Gioia del Colle in Italy to conduct armed air reconnaissance and overwatch patrols over Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course of this action, a number of Paveway IV and Brimstone missiles were launched at military targets in the areas of Misurata and Sirte. A total of 12 targets were hit - six armoured fighting vehicles and six battle tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two Typhoon aircraft also flew from Gioia del Colle to police the no-fly zone, and two RAF VC10 tanker aircraft supported these operations, providing air-to-air refuelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A United States Harrier jet, assigned to the 26th Marine Expeditionary Unit, returns to the amphibious assault ship USS Kearsarge in the Mediterranean for fuel and ammunition resupply following a strike mission over Libya " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5272/Action_in_Libya_has_prevented__humanitarian_catastrophe_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A United States Harrier jet, assigned to the 26th Marine Expeditionary Unit, returns to the amphibious assault ship USS Kearsarge in the Mediterranean for fuel and ammunition resupply following a strike mission over Libya [Picture: Lance Corporal Michael S Lockett, US Marine Corps]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in agreement with NATO, the UK is to move four RAF Typhoons from an air defence role, policing the no-fly zone, to a ground attack role - further bolstering the coalition’s ability to strike targets on the ground. This follows yesterday’s deployment of an additional four RAF Tornados to Gioia del Colle in support of the ongoing operation. The UK currently has 16 ground attack aircraft under NATO command. This meets present operational requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total number of UK fast jets deployed in southern Italy, including those under UK command on standby to support operations, currently stands at 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy continues to play a vital role in the NATO maritime element of Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR. HMS Brocklesby and HMS Cumberland are both enforcing the arms embargo on Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said that the coalition has ‘all but eliminated’ the Gaddafi regime’s air defence capability and stopped it from bombarding Libyan cities from the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also said that the coalition is destroying key regime military assets, including main battle tanks and mobile artillery, and that the arms embargo is being enforced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Mr Hague warned that the regime is still able to inflict considerable damage on Libya’s civilian population using ground forces, and indeed is deliberately inflicting such harm, particularly in the towns of Brega, Misurata and Zintan, where the heaviest fighting is taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So long as the regime continues to attack areas of civilian population, the coalition will continue military action to implement the UN Security Council Resolution,” Mr Hague said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said that the UK is also one of over thirty nations contributing to the humanitarian effort in Libya. Food distribution is taking place at six locations in opposition-held areas in the east of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The World Food Programme has over ten thousand tonnes of food positioned inside Libya and neighbouring countries, and hopes to reach 85,000 people. DFID [Department for International Development] is flying tents for over 10,000 displaced people from its stocks in Dubai to be distributed by the Red Crescent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Several consignments of medical supplies have been successfully delivered to Misurata, and yesterday a Turkish hospital ship was able to evacuate 230 wounded people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said that a further British diplomatic mission has travelled to Benghazi, led by Christopher Prentice, and, while Britain is not engaged in arming the opposition forces, it is prepared to supply non-lethal equipment to help protect civilian lives and facilitate the delivery of humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55711</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:00:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:00:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/additional-raf-tornado-jets-arrive-in-italy"/>
    <title>Additional RAF Tornado jets arrive in Italy</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aircraft, flown by crews from RAF Lossiemouth, mark a significant increase in the RAF’s reconnaissance capabilities as part of Operation ELLAMY over Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the jets arrived fitted with a RAPTOR (Reconnaissance Airborne Pod for Tornado) device which enables the aircraft to provide detailed reconnaissance imagery over large areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a secondary function, the Tornado GR4 jets will also be available to boost the strike capability of NATO operations over Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="One of the four additional RAF Tornado GR4 jets touches down at Gioia del Colle air base in southern Italy " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5266/Additional_RAF_Tornado_jets_arrive_in_Italy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;One of the four additional RAF Tornado GR4 jets touches down at Gioia del Colle air base in southern Italy [Picture: Corporal Pete Devine, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Gioia del Colle, Officer Commanding 2 (Army Cooperation) Squadron, Wing Commander Nick Tucker-Lowe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The arrival of the additional GR4s will be a considerable boost to the already potent combat intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance capability that the Tornado GR Force already brings to Operation ELLAMY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To date, 2 (AC) Squadron have had huge success with the precise engagement of hundreds of targets and the collection of thousands of images which have provided valuable intelligence for NATO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These additional aircraft will allow us to further increase our presence over the skies of Libya and ensure that we continue to protect Libyan civilians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crews from 2 (AC) Squadron, based at RAF Marham in Norfolk, have been operating the 12 Tornado GR4 aircraft already based at Gioia del Colle since May 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also six Typhoon jets deployed alongside the Tornado GR4s, currently operated by personnel from 3 (Fighter) Squadron, RAF Coningsby. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few days the aircraft will be prepped for operations by the personnel of 906 Expeditionary Air Wing and take to the skies over Libya as part of Operation ELLAMY.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55710</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T22:57:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T22:57:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/additional-raf-tornados-for-operations-over-libya"/>
    <title>Additional RAF Tornados for operations over Libya</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aircraft are in addition to 12 RAF Tornados already deployed at Gioia del Colle. This latest deployment is intended to bolster NATO’s reconnaissance capability. Equipped with RAPTOR (Reconnaissance Airborne Pod for Tornado) pods, RAF Tornados can provide extremely detailed reconnaissance imagery over large areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment will have no effect on operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an update on Libya operations, Major General Nick Pope, the Chief of the Defence Staff’s Communications Officer, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;British forces have again been in action over Libya, protecting civilians from the depredations of Colonel Gaddafi’s regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yesterday morning [Thursday 14 July 2011], a Royal Air Force patrol located a BMP armoured personnel carrier near Zlitan, to the west of Misurata. A precision attack by a Typhoon multi-role fighter, using a Paveway guided bomb, successfully destroyed the vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The precision, accuracy and weight of NATO’s air strikes have caused significant damage to Gaddafi’s regime forces attacking Libyan people - the RAF alone has to date damaged or destroyed more than 500 military targets including command and control sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, as the campaign has progressed, the regime is increasingly attempting to conceal troops, equipment and headquarters, often in populated areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gathering the intelligence needed to precisely target these forces remains a key part of NATO’s efforts in prosecuting this campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why in the coming days the UK will deploy an additional four RAF Tornado GR4s to Gioia del Colle, primarily in the reconnaissance role to further support this effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a formidable attack aircraft this deployment will also provide a useful secondary increase to NATO’s overall strike capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NATO already benefits from the twelve RAF Tornados already deployed at Gioia del Colle. This latest deployment will bolster NATO’s reconnaissance capability. The deployment will have no effect on operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55621</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:57:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:57:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/kings-troop-rha-moves-into-state-of-the-art-facilities-in-woolwich"/>
    <title>King's Troop RHA moves into state-of-the-art facilities in Woolwich</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new facilities were delivered by the Defence Infrastructure Organisation (DIO), working with industry partner Morgan Sindall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoolchildren and veterans organisations lined the route as the entire Troop - comprising six gun teams with officers and mounted detachments in full ceremonial regalia - rode through Woolwich town centre and gave a salute to councillors and other dignitaries outside Woolwich Town Hall before formally riding into their new home at Napier Lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the six First-World-War-era thirteen-pounder field guns was pulled by six magnificent horses to the delight of the crowds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for Woolwich, with its long history of military links, the event had additional poignancy, as these guns were returning to the home of the Royal Arsenal, where they were built, and of the Royal Artillery, for whom they were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On arrival at Napier Lines, the King’s Troop Royal Horse Artillery hosted members of the Royal Borough of Greenwich and gave them a guided tour of the new facilities and stables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Hundreds of excited schoolchildren, waving flags, lined the streets of Woolwich to watch the parade " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5229/King_s_Troop_RHA_moves_into_state-of-the-art_facilities_in_Woolwich_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hundreds of excited schoolchildren, waving flags, lined the streets of Woolwich to watch the parade [Picture: Sergeant Steven Hughes RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major construction project, delivered as a stand-alone prime contract, the work included demolition of existing buildings as well as converting one of them into an indoor riding school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other work included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Troop headquarters, stores and workshops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pharmacy and forge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gun park for housing the regimental cannons and limbers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stabling and exercise facilities for 140 horses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all-weather and grassed training areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The project was accepted for MOD use last month (January 2012), with an agreement for a groundbreaking biomass plant to be delivered at a later date. This will use renewable energy derived from horse manure collected on-site to provide heat for the new facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All told, the project has resulted in the formation of 31,000 square metres of external exercise and parade areas together with a total floor area in excess of 10,500 square metres for offices and workshops, excluding hard and soft landscaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIO Head of Projects, Bill Yardley, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to have worked so successfully with our industry partner Morgan Sindall to deliver these state-of-the-art facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have put a lot of hard work into providing a new home for King’s Troop which will be fit to help them to successfully prepare for the ceremonial duties which they will carry out in the months and years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of King’s Troop Royal Horse Artillery, Major Mark Edward, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have inherited a fabulous new facility at Woolwich, the birthplace of the Royal Artillery. It’s bespoke to our requirements and will be a real enhancement for us and for our horses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrival of the King’s Troop in Woolwich builds on links between the military and the borough of Greenwich dating back almost three centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Artillery was founded in 1716, the first barracks for the Artillery were built in 1720 on the Royal Arsenal site, and the construction of the current barracks on Woolwich Common took place between 1781 and 1802.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the unit carried out a 41-gun Royal Salute in Hyde Park to mark the 60th anniversary of the accession of Her Majesty The Queen to the throne and the formal start of her Diamond Jubilee year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to moving to Woolwich, the unit was stationed in St John’s Wood and had been since its formation by King George VI in 1947.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The King’s Troop Royal Horse Artillery is a British Army mounted, ceremonial unit that fires Royal Salutes on royal anniversaries and state occasions, and they provide a gun carriage and a team of black horses for state and military funerals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit’s soldiers also mount the Queen’s Life Guard at Horse Guards each summer when the Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment embark on military training outside London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;King’s Troop also has a vital operational role. Their soldiers are trained as fighting soldiers, with six of them currently deployed in Afghanistan. When the Army mobilises, the unit provides heavy goods vehicle drivers who deliver ammunition to artillery units around the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55598</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:39:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:39:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rafs-sentinel-relocates-to-gioia-del-colle"/>
    <title>RAF's Sentinel relocates to Gioia del Colle</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move signifies the UK’s continuing support to the operation and the National Transitional Council, bringing peace and stability to the troubled region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since operations began in March 2011 the Sentinel aircraft has been operating over the skies of Libya every day, helping to build a better picture of what’s going on on the ground. This has been especially important because of the lack of human intelligence-gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the pace of operations, the Sentinel Force Element Commander, Squadron Leader Hector Hillman, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;During the period of operations the aircrews have been flying sorties of ten plus hours; this tempo and flying rate has been challenging for both air and ground crews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a huge amount of raw data for the Ground Imagery Analysts to review and the engineers have been working around the clock to ensure the aircraft are serviceable, allowing them to carry out their missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sentinel system is operated by 5 (Army Cooperation) Squadron, the largest flying squadron in the RAF. It is a joint squadron, always commanded by an RAF Wing Commander, and its home base is RAF Waddington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aircraft are manned by two RAF pilots, a mission commander and two onboard imagery analysts (IAs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intelligence gathered is analysed by the airborne IAs who transmit key information directly to other NATO assets during the sortie, as well as developing a ‘first look’ product for immediate dissemination upon landing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="5 (Army Cooperation) Squadron's Sentinel aircraft arrives at Gioia del Colle air base " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5194/RAF_s_Sentinel_relocates_to_Gioia_del_Colle_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;5 (Army Cooperation) Squadron's Sentinel aircraft arrives at Gioia del Colle air base
[Picture: Senior Aircraftwoman Tracey Dobson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Officer Commanding 5 (Army Cooperation) Squadron, Wing Commander Al Marshall, explained how the move to Gioia del Colle will enhance the Sentinel’s mission effectiveness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relocation of Sentinel to Gioia del Colle air base reduces our transit distance to and from Libya, increasing the time that the aircraft is able to remain on task for each sortie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This increased task time will permit additional data to be collected and, when combined with the ability to interact face-to-face with the colocated Tornado GR4 crews and Tactical Imagery Wing analysts, will significantly enhance the contribution that Sentinel is able to make to the Libya operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By having air and ground crews working closely alongside each other, there is an opportunity for improved fusion of Tornado’s reconnaissance product and the Sentinel’s enhanced reconnaissance and surveillance systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a package of air power, their effect is ever-enduring and their contribution has been crucial to the success of the RAF’s mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanding Officer of 906 Expeditionary Air Wing, Group Captain Squires, welcomed the move and emphasised the benefits of this integration to Op ELLAMY, the UK’s contribution to Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The colocation of Sentinel and Tornado will provide an excellent opportunity to fuse the two platforms’ differing ISR [intelligence, surveillance amd reconnaissance] capabilities and provide a better understanding of a complex battlespace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month the Typhoons left theatre to focus on their main effort, defence of the UK mainland, leaving the Tornado GR4 as the sole fast jet, multi-role capability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55515</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:05:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:05:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-typhoons-fly-7-000-miles-for-ex-bersama-lima"/>
    <title>RAF Typhoons fly 7,000 miles for Ex Bersama Lima</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Typhoon multi-role aircraft deployed from 6 Squadron’s base, RAF Leuchars in Fife, to take the 7,000-mile (11,265km) trip to Royal Malaysian Air Force (RMAF) Base Butterworth in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The squadron’s pilots made the journey over four days, with stops in Jordan, Oman and Sri Lanka, supported throughout by engineers and ground crews as well as a VC10 aircraft of 101 Squadron, based at RAF Brize Norton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This detachment is also the first time that Tranche 2 Typhoon aircraft have deployed on an overseas exercise of this type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the aircraft arrived in Malaysia fully serviceable, a considerable achievement given the length of the journey. Exercise Bersama Lima 11 realises a long-held aspiration to deploy Typhoon as part of the FPDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participating in the exercise will provide squadron personnel with valuable expeditionary training in a tropical environment as well as experience operating in complex packages with multinational participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 Squadron will continue to maintain its primary Quick Reaction Alert mission at RAF Leuchars during this deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond arrived in Singapore yesterday morning for the 40th anniversary of the FPDA and met with his defence counterparts from Singapore, Malaysia, New Zealand and Australia before laying a wreath at the Kranji War Memorial Cross alongside Vice Admiral George Zambellas. Mr Hammond then flew to Malaysia where he visited RMAF Butterworth and emphasised the importance of the partnership for security in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Two RAF Typhoons in flight (stock image)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5122/RAF_Typhoons_fly_7_000_miles_for_Ex_Bersama_Lima_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Two RAF Typhoons in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Taz Hetherington, Crown Copyright/MOD 2004]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that we were able to deploy Typhoon for the duration of this FPDA exercise. It underscores the UK’s continued commitment to the FPDA and to our defence engagement in South East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Typhoon has proven itself on operations over Libya in both air-to-air and ground attack roles and its versatility, endurance and reliability will provide a valuable contribution to the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The FPDA has an enduring value in ensuring security in the region and it is reassuring to see the same level of commitment from our partners. Singapore and Malaysia have been pivotal members of this pact and I am honoured to be in the region to mark this historic milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Commanding 6 Squadron, Wing Commander Roddy Dennis, who is leading the detachment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have made a tremendous start to Exercise Bersama Lima and I am incredibly proud of all of 6 Squadron’s personnel, both on the ground and in the air, who have accomplished this long-range deployment, halfway around the world, within an extremely tight lead-up time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looking towards the rest of the exercise, we are very much looking forward to the training opportunities that Exercise Bersama Lima 11 will offer us, particularly the opportunity to test and improve our air defence and air combat skills against other aircraft types such as the RAAF [Royal Australian Air Force] F/A-18, RMAF MiG-29 and F/A-18, RSAF [Republic of Singapore Air Force] F-15SG and F-16, whilst operating with the new RAAF Wedgetail Airborne Early Warning and Control aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also very much looking forward to testing ourselves in the hot and humid conditions found here in Malaysia, and to interacting with our FPDA partner nations in the air and on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely pleased that we have achieved all of this in such short order, especially in light of the recent support the squadron gave to the Typhoon Force on Op ELLAMY and whilst maintaining our primary responsibility - Quick Reaction Alert for the northern UK from RAF Leuchars; it is a true credit to everyone on 6 Squadron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
