<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/attorney-generals-office</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/attorney-generals-office.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Attorney General's Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T16:08:25+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60286</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:08:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/law-officers-departments-digital-strategy"/>
    <title>Law Officers' Departments - Digital Strategy</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This strategy sets out how the Law Officers’ Departments will become digital by default</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy sets out how the Law Officers’ Departments will become digital by default. It fulfils the commitment made in the Civil Service Reform Plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56596</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:15:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ago-civil-service-people-survey-results-2012"/>
    <title>AGO civil service people survey results 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General’s Office (AGO) results for the civil service people survey 2012 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/54845</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T12:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-new-home-on-the-web-for-fco-mod-bis-and-ago"/>
    <title>The new home on the web for FCO, MOD, BIS and AGO</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>GOV.UK is the new place for corporate and policy information from the Foreign Office, Ministry of Defence, Department for Business and the Attorney General's Office. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four central government departments and several of their public bodies have today (13 December, 2012) become the latest central government organisations to move their corporate and policy content onto the new GOV.UK website - the new single home for all government services and information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign and Commonwealth Office (&lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt;), Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;), Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Attorney General’s Office (&lt;abbr title="Attorney General's Office"&gt;AGO&lt;/abbr&gt;) have moved their content to the new website, joining the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) whose content moved to GOV.UK last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section on GOV.UK makes it simpler, clearer and faster to find out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how government works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the government is doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you can get involved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="new-web-addresses"&gt;New web addresses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All web addresses have been redirected, so you don’t need to update your bookmarks, but you might want to make a note of the new addresses: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/fco" title="FCO"&gt;www.gov.uk/fco&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/mod" title="MOD"&gt;www.gov.uk/mod&lt;/a&gt; - Ministry of Defence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/bis" title="BIS"&gt;www.gov.uk/bis&lt;/a&gt; - Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ago" title="AGO"&gt;www.gov.uk/ago&lt;/a&gt; - Attorney General’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section of GOV.UK has been designed to make government information easier to find and more transparent for the user. For the first time, you can begin to find out what’s happening inside government all in one place, and in a clear, consistent and transparent format. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that the new website looks very different from the ones it has replaced. The look is one obvious difference but many of the other significant changes are less visible.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topics"&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see information from multiple government departments grouped by topics. For example, you can see how policies from &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; are contributing to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"&gt;national security&lt;/a&gt; or combating &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="clear-policies"&gt;Clear policies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those departments and agencies who have moved to GOV.UK are publishing their policies according to the outcome the government is trying to achieve. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6" title="making it easier to set up and grow a business"&gt;making it easier to set up and grow a business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally" title="promoting human rights internationally"&gt;promoting human rights internationally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament" title="working towards nuclear disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each policy, you can see a list of all the related announcements, consultations and publications in one list, called ‘activity’. The activity tab makes it easy for you to track what is happening on the policies that interest you, for example all government activity that relates to &lt;a href="/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity" title="establishing stability in Afghanistan: activity"&gt;establishing stability in Afghanistan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="more-about-inside-government-and-govuk"&gt;More about Inside Government and GOV.UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Government is still a work in progress, with only some organisations live. Work will continue as other departments and organisations, many hundreds in total, move their information to GOV.UK. This will happen in batches and will be completed by March 2014.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more here: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/tour#inside-government"&gt;Inside Government tour and introductory video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://digital.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/2012/11/05/what-is-inside-government/"&gt;Blog post: What is Inside Government?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17487</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/proceeds-of-crime-act-2002-code-of-practice-under-section-377a"/>
    <title>Proceeds of Crime Act 2002: code of practice under Section 377A</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Investigation powers under Proceeds of Crime Act: search and seizure warrants, disclosure, account monitoring and other orders.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the code of practice governing investigation powers by prosecutors in England, Wales and Northern Ireland including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;production orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and seizure warrants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disclosure orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;customer information orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;account monitoring orders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_27890"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27890-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/thumbnail_Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27890-accessibility-help"&gt;Code of practice issued under Section 377A of the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;216 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;52 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-27890-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Code%20of%20practice%20issued%20under%20Section%20377A%20of%20the%20Proceeds%20of%20Crime%20Act%202002%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Code%20of%20practice%20issued%20under%20Section%20377A%20of%20the%20Proceeds%20of%20Crime%20Act%202002%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Code of practice issued under Section 377A of the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56766</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:23:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/types-of-contempt-of-court-dealt-with-by-the-attorney-generals-office"/>
    <title>Types of contempt of court dealt with by the Attorney General's Office</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>The Attorney General and Solicitor General (the Law Officers) can be asked to look at some types of contempt of court.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contempt of court is where someone does not respect a court or disrupts its work by words or actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General can take legal action in the public interest if contempt of court has been committed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main types of contempt are publication contempt, juror contempt and contempt in civil cases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="publication-contempt"&gt;Publication contempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes material is published which risks damaging a trial. This could be in a newspaper, television, radio or on the internet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material could have broken the laws concerning contempt of court if it could affect the way a jury thinks about a case, or prejudice it so much that a trial cannot take place or has to be stopped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material could be in contempt of court and the Law Officers can prosecute whoever published the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="juror-contempt"&gt;Juror contempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A juror may commit contempt if he or she disobeys an order of the Judge or tells someone who is not on the jury details of the jury’s thoughts and decisions on the case they are considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a judge will deal with contempt by a juror straight away - for example, a juror who disrupts the trial or is not on time. When a more detailed investigation is needed, a judge will often ask the Attorney General for advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contempt-in-civil-cases"&gt;Contempt in civil cases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a civil case where the punishment is financial, somebody connected to the case can be in contempt by making a false written statement. The Attorney’s role is limited to deciding if there has been a contempt of court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17681</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:56:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:56:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/attorney-general-s-guidelines-for-prosecutors-section-18-of-the-regulation-of-investigatory-powers-act-2000-england-and-wales"/>
    <title>Attorney General’s Guidelines for Prosecutors: Section 18 of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000 (England and Wales)</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Guidelines for prosecutors in applying section 18 of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act (RIPA) in England and Wales.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These guidelines concern the approach to be taken by prosecutors in applying section 18 of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act (&lt;abbr title="Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act"&gt;RIPA&lt;/abbr&gt;) in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/28510</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:52:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:52:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-prosecutors-convention-2009-updated-2012"/>
    <title>The Prosecutors’ Convention 2009 (updated 2012)</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>The responsibilities of prosecutors where a suspect’s conduct could be dealt with in different ways and by different organisations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-purpose-of-the-prosecutors-convention"&gt;The purpose of the Prosecutors’ Convention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.1
The Prosecutors’ Convention sets out the responsibilities of prosecutors where a suspect’s conduct could be dealt with by criminal or civil/regulatory sanctions and/or where more than one prosecuting authority and investigating body share the power to take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.2	
In such cases, depending on the extent to which more than one authority is pursuing or wishes to pursue an investigation, decisions will have to be taken about whether and how investigations should proceed and as to the choice of criminal charges or civil or regulatory sanction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3
The aim is to ensure that cases are conducted in a way that is just and which best serves the overall public interest, so that the public can have confidence in the outcome. Through the Convention, prosecuting authorities commit themselves to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actively managing the interface with other prosecutors and investigators from the earliest possible stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working together in a co-ordinated manner to ensure that decisions in individual cases are taken promptly and that they serve the overall public interest, having regard to the nature and seriousness of the harm and offences alleged, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enforcing the law in a fair and effective way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="the-prosecutors-responsibilities-are-to"&gt;The prosecutor’s responsibilities are to:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1
Consider the nature of the conduct being investigated and to identify as early as possible any interests shared with another investigative authority, prosecutor or regulatory body. Prosecutors are likely to be advising from an early stage in an investigation and are in a good position to identify any links that have not already been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.2	
Establish the nature or scope of any overlapping interest in the case and any relevant criteria for decisions. The aim is to make an informed decision about the most appropriate means of proceeding in the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.3
Establish effective lines of communication from an early stage as the best way to secure co-ordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.4
Work together to develop an agreed case management strategy, and to co-ordinate decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check whether there is an existing operational &lt;abbr title="Memorandum of Understanding"&gt;MOU&lt;/abbr&gt; or case plan between the relevant agencies. Consider drawing up such an &lt;abbr title="Memorandum of Understanding"&gt;MOU&lt;/abbr&gt; for the individual case once the case strategy is agreed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where investigations are proceeding at different rates, prosecutors should advise on the modification of investigation plans to improve the prospects of co-ordinated decisions and efficiency; and to ensure that significant decisions are taken with due regard to the potential impact on any other investigation or prosecution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where prosecution is or may be needed in the public interest, to ensure that the right charges are brought and that the right prosecuting authority or prosecuting authorities proceed in a way that best reflects the nature and seriousness of the offences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where action falling short of prosecution by one or more authorities may be considered more appropriate, applying established policies and principles, prosecutors will encourage agreement about which civil or regulatory orders or sanctions are warranted and who is best placed to pursue them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prosecutors will ensure that jointly conducted or related criminal proceedings are pursued fairly, complying with disclosure (including third party disclosure) obligations and ensuring that specialist advice is obtained where this could improve the conduct or presentation of the case; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prosecutors will work with colleagues to co-ordinate the announcement of decisions to individuals and to the public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="factors-for-early-consideration"&gt;Factors for early consideration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.1.	
Subject to the application of more detailed case management protocols (such as those referred to in section 4) preliminary discussions should focus on the following as a minimum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the nature and focus of any parallel interest in the conduct under investigation; the powers and sanctions that may be applicable and any decision making criteria&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the stage that any investigation or investigations have reached&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether any investigation or prosecution could or should be jointly conducted. If a joint investigation is not possible, the question will be how best to co-ordinate related investigations and prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;which agency is best placed to take lead responsibility for any prosecution? This may depend on a variety of factors including the nature of the most serious offences and where the most relevant expertise lies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the timing of any proceedings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mechanisms for preserving and sharing evidence and information; and any relevant gateways or legal provisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for specialist or expert prosecutors’ advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;arrangements for the service of evidence and the retention and disclosure of unused material to ensure that disclosure obligations are fulfilled, subject to any legal constraints; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any other aspect of case management that is relevant in the particular case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;3.2.	
In circumstances where prosecution by more than one authority cannot be avoided or where an investigation results in a joint or related prosecution, the agencies involved should co-ordinate the communication of their 	decisions to individual suspects and any victims; as well as co-ordinating any public announcements about 	prosecution decisions, preferably by way of a joint press statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="effective-operation-of-the-convention"&gt;Effective operation of the convention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.1	
The Head of each Prosecuting Authority or Team will be, or will name, the Prosecutors’ Convention Senior Responsible Officer for that authority (&lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt;). The Prosecutors’ Convention &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; will be responsible for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing the initial point of contact for inter agency co-ordination purposes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that there is an identified and accountable line of effective communication between each agency, to include regular structured contacts and oversight of the case management strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;monitoring the way in which the Convention is given effect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking prompt action to resolve any difficulties or disagreements that arise as to how the case should be best be approached. The expectation is that problems will be resolved by the prosecuting authorities, where necessary at the level of the Head of the relevant authorities. The Attorney General’s Office is available to assist by giving guidance where this would be helpful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;4.2	
The Prosecutors’ Convention &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; will ensure that prosecutors are aware of the Convention; that they have easy access to it; and will give any advice and guidance they may need from the &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; in individual cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.3	
The SROs will be responsible for ensuring that their authorities and prosecutors as a whole learn from experience in conducting individual cases and use it to inform and improve future case handling, whether a case illustrates the benefits of good practice or whether problems have been faced and overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.4
Where they consider it advantageous or desirable, prosecuting authorities (including investigators and others) may develop separate protocols to deal with specific areas of overlap in working practice, outlining in more detail how the aims, objectives and principles of the Convention are to be fulfilled in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.5	
Existing supplementary protocols include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work-Related Deaths Protocol (Crown Prosecution Service, Office of Rail Regulation, British Transport Police, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Health and Safety Executive, Local Government Association)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guidelines on the Investigation of Cases of Interest or Concern to the Financial Services Authority or other Prosecuting Authorities and Investigating Agencies (&lt;abbr title="Financial Services Authority"&gt;FSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, Serious Fraud Office, Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform, CPS, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Crown Office, &lt;abbr title="Director of Public Prosecutions"&gt;DPP&lt;/abbr&gt; (NI), &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; Scotland)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third party disclosure protocol (CPS, Revenue and Customs Prosecutions Office, SFO, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arrangements between civilian and military prosecuting and investigating authorities governing how they will work together, decide issues of jurisdiction and where necessary decide how an allegation will be investigated. Some of these protocols are currently being revised in the light of legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;4.6
Signatories will encourage associated prosecuting authorities and investigators to abide by the spirit of this Convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="parties"&gt;Parties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.1	
The parties to this Convention are those prosecuting authorities who have adopted it by signing the attached schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="schedule-to-the-prosecutors-convention"&gt;Schedule to the Prosecutors’ Convention&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attorney General’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Civil Aviation Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crown Prosecution Service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for Work and Pensions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environment Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Services Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food Standards Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gambling Commission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health and Safety Executive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information Commissioner’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maritime and Coastguard Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office of Rail Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revenue and Customs Prosecutions Office (incorporated into CPS in 2010)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serious Fraud Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Service Prosecuting Authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56042</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:11:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:11:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/attorney-general-s-guidelines-on-disclosure-2005-and-2011"/>
    <title>Attorney General’s guidelines on disclosure 2005 and 2011</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disclosure in criminal cases is the process to make sure that investigators and prosecutors provide defendants with information obtained during the investigation which may help them to prepare their defence. It is an essential part of all criminal investigations and prosecutions. The Attorney General has issued guidelines for prosecutors, investigators and defence lawyers on the conduct of disclosure in investigations and prosecutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first edition was published in 2005 and updated in 2011 with supplementary guidelines on digitally stored material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51747"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51747-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/thumbnail_Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51747-accessibility-help"&gt;Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;49.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51747-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202005%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202005%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2005").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51748"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51748-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/thumbnail_Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51748-accessibility-help"&gt;Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;53.8 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51748-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202011%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202011%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2011").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/48345</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:17:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/attorney-general-applies-for-fresh-inquests-for-victims-of-hillsborough-disaster"/>
    <title>Attorney General applies for fresh inquests for victims of Hillsborough disaster</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An application has been made to the High Court for new inquests into the deaths of the 96 victims.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General, Dominic Grieve &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Member of Parliament"&gt;MP&lt;/abbr&gt;, today (10 December 2012) made an application to the High Court for new inquests into the deaths of the 96 victims of the Hillsborough tragedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the case for the High Court to quash the original inquests is a good one. My application has now been lodged with the Court. It is my intention to appear to argue the case at the hearing that will take place in the High Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application aims to meet tests set out in Section 13 of the Coroners Act, the most relevant of which are the discovery of new facts or evidence and that it is necessary or desirable in the interests of justice that new inquests should be held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal ground for the application is the new medical evidence. The alteration to police and emergency services evidence is a supporting factor, as is stadium safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The views of the families were sought before filing this application. All support the quashing of the inquests and the ordering of new ones. The coroners for South Yorkshire and West Yorkshire (in the case of Anthony Bland) were also contacted and support the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The court will now fix a date for hearing. The timing of this is a matter for the court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional analysis for this application was provided by Dr Bill Kirkup CBE, a member of the Hillsborough Panel, and Professor Jack Crane, a forensic pathologist and State Pathologist for Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intention to apply for fresh inquests was announced on 16 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Attorney General takes decisions on whether to apply to the High Court for an inquest as part of his public interest function, independently of government and strictly on the basis of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He has no power to order a new coronial inquest. A new inquest can only be ordered by the High Court on an application made either by the Attorney General or by a third party with the consent of the Attorney General. But before any such application can be made, the Attorney General has to be satisfied that he has sufficient evidence in an admissible form, to persuade the Court that the test set out in section 13 of the Coroners Act 1988 is met.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the Court quashes the original inquests and orders fresh inquests to be heard, its powers under section 13 application are limited to referring the cases back to administrative district in which they were originally heard. In 95 of the cases this means that in the first instance the cases must be sent back to Sheffield or Doncaster (Doncaster being the other coroner in that administrative district). In the light of the concerns of the families, the Attorney will suggest that the Court should return the cases to Doncaster. Where the inquests are in fact heard will then be a matter for the coronial process.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56028</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T12:07:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T12:07:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/juror-jailed-for-discussing-trial-with-defendants"/>
    <title>Juror jailed for discussing trial with defendants</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A juror who discussed the trial he was involved in with 2 of the defendants has been jailed for 4 months</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Judges at the High Court today jailed a juror for 4 months for contempt of court, after he admitted discussing an ongoing trial with 2 of the defendants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Pardon was a juror on a 13-week trial of 6 men at Wolverhampton Crown Court in December 2011. He admitted that before the jury had finished deciding all of its verdicts he approached one of the defendants and discussed the jury’s deliberations with him. At that stage 3 defendants had been convicted on one count, and one acquitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial judge, &lt;abbr title="His Honour Justice"&gt;HHJ&lt;/abbr&gt; Walsh, was informed and took no action as he wished to see if the jury was able to reach a verdict on the remaining count.  It became apparent that they could not and he discharged them. After this, Pardon attempted to approach a second defendant who declined to speak with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judge referred the contempt to the Attorney General and the 3 convicted defendants lodged appeals. Today’s hearing was before the Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Mitting and Mr Justice Griffith Williams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attorney General Dominic Grieve QC MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a compelling public interest in addressing any contempt of the judicial process. Mr Pardon’s conduct had serious consequences. The trial was disrupted and as a result the 3 convicted defendants appealed against their convictions, convictions won after a lengthy police investigation and trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 8(1) of the Contempt of Court Act 1981 provides, so far as relevant, that: ‘it is a contempt of Court to obtain, disclose or solicit any particulars of statements made, opinions expressed, arguments advanced or votes cast by members of a jury in the course of their deliberations in any legal proceedings’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under section 8(3), the Attorney General has responsibility for bringing proceedings to address such contempt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
