<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/attorney-generals-office</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/attorney-generals-office.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Attorney General's Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/54845</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-new-home-on-the-web-for-fco-mod-bis-and-ago"/>
    <title>The new home on the web for FCO, MOD, BIS and AGO</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four central government departments and several of their public bodies have today (13 December, 2012) become the latest central government organisations to move their corporate and policy content onto the new GOV.UK website - the new single home for all government services and information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign and Commonwealth Office (&lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt;), Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;), Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Attorney General’s Office (&lt;abbr title="Attorney General's Office"&gt;AGO&lt;/abbr&gt;) have moved their content to the new website, joining the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) whose content moved to GOV.UK last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section on GOV.UK makes it simpler, clearer and faster to find out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how government works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the government is doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you can get involved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="new-web-addresses"&gt;New web addresses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All web addresses have been redirected, so you don’t need to update your bookmarks, but you might want to make a note of the new addresses: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/fco" title="FCO"&gt;www.gov.uk/fco&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/mod" title="MOD"&gt;www.gov.uk/mod&lt;/a&gt; - Ministry of Defence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/bis" title="BIS"&gt;www.gov.uk/bis&lt;/a&gt; - Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ago" title="AGO"&gt;www.gov.uk/ago&lt;/a&gt; - Attorney General’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section of GOV.UK has been designed to make government information easier to find and more transparent for the user. For the first time, you can begin to find out what’s happening inside government all in one place, and in a clear, consistent and transparent format. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that the new website looks very different from the ones it has replaced. The look is one obvious difference but many of the other significant changes are less visible.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topics"&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see information from multiple government departments grouped by topics. For example, you can see how policies from &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; are contributing to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"&gt;national security&lt;/a&gt; or combating &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="clear-policies"&gt;Clear policies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those departments and agencies who have moved to GOV.UK are publishing their policies according to the outcome the government is trying to achieve. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6" title="making it easier to set up and grow a business"&gt;making it easier to set up and grow a business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally" title="promoting human rights internationally"&gt;promoting human rights internationally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament" title="working towards nuclear disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each policy, you can see a list of all the related announcements, consultations and publications in one list, called ‘activity’. The activity tab makes it easy for you to track what is happening on the policies that interest you, for example all government activity that relates to &lt;a href="/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity" title="establishing stability in Afghanistan: activity"&gt;establishing stability in Afghanistan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="more-about-inside-government-and-govuk"&gt;More about Inside Government and GOV.UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Government is still a work in progress, with only some organisations live. Work will continue as other departments and organisations, many hundreds in total, move their information to GOV.UK. This will happen in batches and will be completed by March 2014.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more here: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/tour#inside-government"&gt;Inside Government tour and introductory video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://digital.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/2012/11/05/what-is-inside-government/"&gt;Blog post: What is Inside Government?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17487</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T14:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T14:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/proceeds-of-crime-act-2002-code-of-practice-under-section-377a"/>
    <title>Proceeds of Crime Act 2002: code of practice under Section 377A</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the code of practice governing investigation powers by prosecutors in England, Wales and Northern Ireland including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;production orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and seizure warrants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disclosure orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;customer information orders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;account monitoring orders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_27890"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27890-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/thumbnail_Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15330/Code_of_Practice_Issued_Under_Section_377A_of_the_Proceeds_of_Crime_Act_2002.doc.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27890-accessibility-help"&gt;Code of practice issued under Section 377A of the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;216 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;52 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-27890-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Code%20of%20practice%20issued%20under%20Section%20377A%20of%20the%20Proceeds%20of%20Crime%20Act%202002%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Code%20of%20practice%20issued%20under%20Section%20377A%20of%20the%20Proceeds%20of%20Crime%20Act%202002%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Code of practice issued under Section 377A of the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17803</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T16:09:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T16:09:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/types-of-contempt-of-court-dealt-with-by-the-attorney-generals-office"/>
    <title>Types of contempt of court dealt with by the Attorney General's Office</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contempt of court is where someone does not respect a court or disrupts its work by words or actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General can take legal action in the public interest if contempt of court has been committed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main types of contempt are publication contempt, juror contempt and contempt in civil cases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="publication-contempt"&gt;Publication contempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes material is published which risks damaging a trial. This could be in a newspaper, television, radio or on the internet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material could have broken the laws concerning contempt of court if it could affect the way a jury thinks about a case, or prejudice it so much that a trial cannot take place or has to be stopped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material could be in contempt of court and the Law Officers can prosecute whoever published the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="juror-contempt"&gt;Juror contempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A juror may commit contempt if he or she disobeys an order of the Judge or tells someone who is not on the jury details of the jury’s thoughts and decisions on the case they are considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a judge will with contempt by a juror straight away - for example, a juror who disrupts the trial or is not on time. When a more detailed investigation is needed, a judge will often ask the Attorney General for advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contempt-in-civil-cases"&gt;Contempt in civil cases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a civil case where the punishment is financial, somebody connected to the case can be in contempt by making a false written statement. The Attorney’s role is limited to deciding if there has been a contempt of court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17681</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:56:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:56:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/attorney-general-s-guidelines-for-prosecutors-section-18-of-the-regulation-of-investigatory-powers-act-2000-england-and-wales"/>
    <title>Attorney General’s Guidelines for Prosecutors: Section 18 of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000 (England and Wales)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These guidelines concern the approach to be taken by prosecutors in applying section 18 of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act (&lt;abbr title="Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act"&gt;RIPA&lt;/abbr&gt;) in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/28510</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:52:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:52:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-prosecutors-convention-2009-updated-2012"/>
    <title>The Prosecutors’ Convention 2009 (updated 2012)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-purpose-of-the-prosecutors-convention"&gt;The purpose of the Prosecutors’ Convention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.1
The Prosecutors’ Convention sets out the responsibilities of prosecutors where a suspect’s conduct could be dealt with by criminal or civil/regulatory sanctions and/or where more than one prosecuting authority and investigating body share the power to take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.2	
In such cases, depending on the extent to which more than one authority is pursuing or wishes to pursue an investigation, decisions will have to be taken about whether and how investigations should proceed and as to the choice of criminal charges or civil or regulatory sanction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3
The aim is to ensure that cases are conducted in a way that is just and which best serves the overall public interest, so that the public can have confidence in the outcome. Through the Convention, prosecuting authorities commit themselves to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actively managing the interface with other prosecutors and investigators from the earliest possible stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working together in a co-ordinated manner to ensure that decisions in individual cases are taken promptly and that they serve the overall public interest, having regard to the nature and seriousness of the harm and offences alleged, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enforcing the law in a fair and effective way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="the-prosecutors-responsibilities-are-to"&gt;The prosecutor’s responsibilities are to:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1
Consider the nature of the conduct being investigated and to identify as early as possible any interests shared with another investigative authority, prosecutor or regulatory body. Prosecutors are likely to be advising from an early stage in an investigation and are in a good position to identify any links that have not already been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.2	
Establish the nature or scope of any overlapping interest in the case and any relevant criteria for decisions. The aim is to make an informed decision about the most appropriate means of proceeding in the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.3
Establish effective lines of communication from an early stage as the best way to secure co-ordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.4
Work together to develop an agreed case management strategy, and to co-ordinate decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check whether there is an existing operational &lt;abbr title="Memorandum of Understanding"&gt;MOU&lt;/abbr&gt; or case plan between the relevant agencies. Consider drawing up such an &lt;abbr title="Memorandum of Understanding"&gt;MOU&lt;/abbr&gt; for the individual case once the case strategy is agreed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where investigations are proceeding at different rates, prosecutors should advise on the modification of investigation plans to improve the prospects of co-ordinated decisions and efficiency; and to ensure that significant decisions are taken with due regard to the potential impact on any other investigation or prosecution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where prosecution is or may be needed in the public interest, to ensure that the right charges are brought and that the right prosecuting authority or prosecuting authorities proceed in a way that best reflects the nature and seriousness of the offences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where action falling short of prosecution by one or more authorities may be considered more appropriate, applying established policies and principles, prosecutors will encourage agreement about which civil or regulatory orders or sanctions are warranted and who is best placed to pursue them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prosecutors will ensure that jointly conducted or related criminal proceedings are pursued fairly, complying with disclosure (including third party disclosure) obligations and ensuring that specialist advice is obtained where this could improve the conduct or presentation of the case; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prosecutors will work with colleagues to co-ordinate the announcement of decisions to individuals and to the public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="factors-for-early-consideration"&gt;Factors for early consideration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.1.	
Subject to the application of more detailed case management protocols (such as those referred to in section 4) preliminary discussions should focus on the following as a minimum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the nature and focus of any parallel interest in the conduct under investigation; the powers and sanctions that may be applicable and any decision making criteria&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the stage that any investigation or investigations have reached&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether any investigation or prosecution could or should be jointly conducted. If a joint investigation is not possible, the question will be how best to co-ordinate related investigations and prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;which agency is best placed to take lead responsibility for any prosecution? This may depend on a variety of factors including the nature of the most serious offences and where the most relevant expertise lies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the timing of any proceedings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mechanisms for preserving and sharing evidence and information; and any relevant gateways or legal provisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for specialist or expert prosecutors’ advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;arrangements for the service of evidence and the retention and disclosure of unused material to ensure that disclosure obligations are fulfilled, subject to any legal constraints; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any other aspect of case management that is relevant in the particular case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;3.2.	
In circumstances where prosecution by more than one authority cannot be avoided or where an investigation results in a joint or related prosecution, the agencies involved should co-ordinate the communication of their 	decisions to individual suspects and any victims; as well as co-ordinating any public announcements about 	prosecution decisions, preferably by way of a joint press statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="effective-operation-of-the-convention"&gt;Effective operation of the convention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.1	
The Head of each Prosecuting Authority or Team will be, or will name, the Prosecutors’ Convention Senior Responsible Officer for that authority (&lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt;). The Prosecutors’ Convention &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; will be responsible for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing the initial point of contact for inter agency co-ordination purposes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that there is an identified and accountable line of effective communication between each agency, to include regular structured contacts and oversight of the case management strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;monitoring the way in which the Convention is given effect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking prompt action to resolve any difficulties or disagreements that arise as to how the case should be best be approached. The expectation is that problems will be resolved by the prosecuting authorities, where necessary at the level of the Head of the relevant authorities. The Attorney General’s Office is available to assist by giving guidance where this would be helpful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;4.2	
The Prosecutors’ Convention &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; will ensure that prosecutors are aware of the Convention; that they have easy access to it; and will give any advice and guidance they may need from the &lt;abbr title="Senior Responsible Officer"&gt;SRO&lt;/abbr&gt; in individual cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.3	
The SROs will be responsible for ensuring that their authorities and prosecutors as a whole learn from experience in conducting individual cases and use it to inform and improve future case handling, whether a case illustrates the benefits of good practice or whether problems have been faced and overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.4
Where they consider it advantageous or desirable, prosecuting authorities (including investigators and others) may develop separate protocols to deal with specific areas of overlap in working practice, outlining in more detail how the aims, objectives and principles of the Convention are to be fulfilled in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.5	
Existing supplementary protocols include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work-Related Deaths Protocol (Crown Prosecution Service, Office of Rail Regulation, British Transport Police, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Health and Safety Executive, Local Government Association)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guidelines on the Investigation of Cases of Interest or Concern to the Financial Services Authority or other Prosecuting Authorities and Investigating Agencies (&lt;abbr title="Financial Services Authority"&gt;FSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, Serious Fraud Office, Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform, CPS, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Crown Office, &lt;abbr title="Director of Public Prosecutions"&gt;DPP&lt;/abbr&gt; (NI), &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; Scotland)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third party disclosure protocol (CPS, Revenue and Customs Prosecutions Office, SFO, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arrangements between civilian and military prosecuting and investigating authorities governing how they will work together, decide issues of jurisdiction and where necessary decide how an allegation will be investigated. Some of these protocols are currently being revised in the light of legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;4.6
Signatories will encourage associated prosecuting authorities and investigators to abide by the spirit of this Convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="parties"&gt;Parties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.1	
The parties to this Convention are those prosecuting authorities who have adopted it by signing the attached schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="schedule-to-the-prosecutors-convention"&gt;Schedule to the Prosecutors’ Convention&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attorney General’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Civil Aviation Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crown Prosecution Service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for Work and Pensions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environment Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Services Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food Standards Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gambling Commission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health and Safety Executive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information Commissioner’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maritime and Coastguard Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office of Rail Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revenue and Customs Prosecutions Office (incorporated into CPS in 2010)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serious Fraud Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Service Prosecuting Authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56042</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:11:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:11:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/attorney-general-s-guidelines-on-disclosure-2005-and-2011"/>
    <title>Attorney General’s guidelines on disclosure 2005 and 2011</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disclosure in criminal cases is the process to make sure that investigators and prosecutors provide defendants with information obtained during the investigation which may help them to prepare their defence. It is an essential part of all criminal investigations and prosecutions. The Attorney General has issued guidelines for prosecutors, investigators and defence lawyers on the conduct of disclosure in investigations and prosecutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first edition was published in 2005 and updated in 2011 with supplementary guidelines on digitally stored material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51747"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51747-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/thumbnail_Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16237/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2005.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51747-accessibility-help"&gt;Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;49.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51747-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202005%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202005%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2005").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51748"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51748-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/thumbnail_Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16239/Attorney_General_s_guidelines_on_disclosure_2011.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51748-accessibility-help"&gt;Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;53.8 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51748-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202011%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Attorney%20General%27s%20guidelines%20on%20disclosure%2C%202011%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;correspondence@attorneygeneral.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Attorney General's guidelines on disclosure, 2011").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/48345</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T14:17:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:17:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/attorney-general-applies-for-fresh-inquests-for-victims-of-hillsborough-disaster"/>
    <title>Attorney General applies for fresh inquests for victims of Hillsborough disaster</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General, Dominic Grieve &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Member of Parliament"&gt;MP&lt;/abbr&gt;, today (10 December 2012) made an application to the High Court for new inquests into the deaths of the 96 victims of the Hillsborough tragedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the case for the High Court to quash the original inquests is a good one. My application has now been lodged with the Court. It is my intention to appear to argue the case at the hearing that will take place in the High Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application aims to meet tests set out in Section 13 of the Coroners Act, the most relevant of which are the discovery of new facts or evidence and that it is necessary or desirable in the interests of justice that new inquests should be held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal ground for the application is the new medical evidence. The alteration to police and emergency services evidence is a supporting factor, as is stadium safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The views of the families were sought before filing this application. All support the quashing of the inquests and the ordering of new ones. The coroners for South Yorkshire and West Yorkshire (in the case of Anthony Bland) were also contacted and support the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The court will now fix a date for hearing. The timing of this is a matter for the court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional analysis for this application was provided by Dr Bill Kirkup CBE, a member of the Hillsborough Panel, and Professor Jack Crane, a forensic pathologist and State Pathologist for Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intention to apply for fresh inquests was announced on 16 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Attorney General takes decisions on whether to apply to the High Court for an inquest as part of his public interest function, independently of government and strictly on the basis of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He has no power to order a new coronial inquest. A new inquest can only be ordered by the High Court on an application made either by the Attorney General or by a third party with the consent of the Attorney General. But before any such application can be made, the Attorney General has to be satisfied that he has sufficient evidence in an admissible form, to persuade the Court that the test set out in section 13 of the Coroners Act 1988 is met.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the Court quashes the original inquests and orders fresh inquests to be heard, its powers under section 13 application are limited to referring the cases back to administrative district in which they were originally heard. In 95 of the cases this means that in the first instance the cases must be sent back to Sheffield or Doncaster (Doncaster being the other coroner in that administrative district). In the light of the concerns of the families, the Attorney will suggest that the Court should return the cases to Doncaster. Where the inquests are in fact heard will then be a matter for the coronial process.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56028</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T12:07:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T12:07:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/juror-jailed-for-discussing-trial-with-defendants"/>
    <title>Juror jailed for discussing trial with defendants</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Judges at the High Court today jailed a juror for 4 months for contempt of court, after he admitted discussing an ongoing trial with 2 of the defendants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Pardon was a juror on a 13-week trial of 6 men at Wolverhampton Crown Court in December 2011. He admitted that before the jury had finished deciding all of its verdicts he approached one of the defendants and discussed the jury’s deliberations with him. At that stage 3 defendants had been convicted on one count, and one acquitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial judge, &lt;abbr title="His Honour Justice"&gt;HHJ&lt;/abbr&gt; Walsh, was informed and took no action as he wished to see if the jury was able to reach a verdict on the remaining count.  It became apparent that they could not and he discharged them. After this, Pardon attempted to approach a second defendant who declined to speak with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judge referred the contempt to the Attorney General and the 3 convicted defendants lodged appeals. Today’s hearing was before the Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Mitting and Mr Justice Griffith Williams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attorney General Dominic Grieve QC MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a compelling public interest in addressing any contempt of the judicial process. Mr Pardon’s conduct had serious consequences. The trial was disrupted and as a result the 3 convicted defendants appealed against their convictions, convictions won after a lengthy police investigation and trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 8(1) of the Contempt of Court Act 1981 provides, so far as relevant, that: ‘it is a contempt of Court to obtain, disclose or solicit any particulars of statements made, opinions expressed, arguments advanced or votes cast by members of a jury in the course of their deliberations in any legal proceedings’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under section 8(3), the Attorney General has responsibility for bringing proceedings to address such contempt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17492</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T15:22:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T15:22:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/jury-vetting-right-of-stand-by-guidelines--2"/>
    <title>Jury vetting: right of stand by guidelines</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-exercise-by-the-crown-of-its-right-of-stand-by-update-2012"&gt;The exercise by the Crown of its right of stand by (update 2012)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1988 the defence right to challenge jurors without cause was abolished, the prosecution right to do so was, however, retained.  This means that the prosecution can object to a potential juror without giving any reason. It is recognised that this is an exceptional power and so the Attorney General, therefore, issues guidance to prosecutors on its use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, the use of the right of stand by is limited to those cases which involve national security or terrorism. The guidelines outline the circumstances in which it is appropriate for the prosecution to exercise this power and the procedure which is to be followed. The guidelines make clear that the authority to use this power is limited to the Attorney General. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous versions of the guidelines included an annex prepared by the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) on the conduct of inquiries into a juror’s previous convictions. This is now done automatically by Her Majesty’s Courts Service and therefore the &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; guidance is no longer relevant and, in consequence, is not included in these 2012 guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guidelines"&gt;Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General has issued the following guidelines on the exercise by the Crown in England and Wales of its right to stand by. The guidelines update the previous guidelines issued in 1989 to coincide with the implementation of the Criminal Justice Act 1988 s.118, which abolished the right of peremptory challenge. These updated guidelines are to have effect from the 27th November 2012. The Attorney General has also issued amended guidelines on jury checks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 Although the law has long recognised the right of the Crown to exclude a member of a jury panel from sitting as a juror by the exercise in open court of the right to request a stand by or, if necessary, by challenge for cause, it has been customary for those instructed to prosecute on behalf of the Crown to assert that right only sparingly and in exceptional circumstances. It is generally accepted that the prosecution should not use its right in order to influence the overall composition of a jury or with a view to tactical advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 The approach outlined above is founded on the principles that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. the members of a jury should be selected at random from the panel subject to any rule of law as to right of challenge by the defence, and  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. the Juries Act 1974 identifies those classes of persons who alone are disqualified from or ineligible for service on a jury. No other class of person may be treated as disqualified or ineligible.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 The enactment by Parliament of s.118 of the Criminal Justice Act 1988 abolishing the right of defendants to remove jurors by means of peremptory challenge makes it appropriate that the Crown should assert its right to stand by only on the basis of clearly defined and restrictive criteria. Derogation from the principle that members of a jury should be selected at random should be permitted only where it is essential.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 Primary responsibility for ensuring that an individual does not serve on a jury if he is not competent to discharge properly the duties of a juror rests with the appropriate court officer and, ultimately the trial judge. Current legislation provides, in ss.9 to s.10 of the Juries Act 1974, fairly wide discretion to excuse, defer or discharge jurors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 The circumstances in which it would be proper for the Crown to exercise its right to stand by a member of a jury panel are:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. where a jury check authorised in accordance with the Attorney General’s Guidelines on Jury Checks reveals information justifying exercise of the right to stand by in accordance with para.11 of the guidelines below and the Attorney General personally authorises the exercise of the right to stand by; or  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. where a person is about to be sworn as a juror who is manifestly unsuitable and the defence agree that, accordingly, the exercise by the prosecution of the right to stand by would be appropriate. An example of the sort of exceptional circumstances which might justify stand by is where it becomes apparent that, despite the provisions mentioned in para.4 above, a juror selected for service to try a complex case is in fact illiterate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="jury-checks"&gt;Jury checks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 The principles which are generally to be observed are:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. that members of a jury should be selected at random from the panel,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. the Juries Act 1974 identifies those classes of persons who alone are either disqualified from or ineligible for service on a jury; no other class of person may be treated as disqualified or ineligible,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c. the correct way for the Crown to seek to exclude a member of the panel from sitting as a juror is by the exercise in open court of the right to request a stand by or, if necessary, to challenge for cause.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Parliament has provided safeguards against jurors who may be corrupt or biased. In addition to the provision for majority verdicts, there is the sanction of a criminal offence for a disqualified person to serve on a jury. The omission of a disqualified person from the panel is a matter for court officials - they will check criminal records for the purpose of ascertaining whether or not a potential juror is a disqualified person.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 There are, however, certain exceptional types of case of public importance for which the provisions as to majority verdicts and the disqualification of jurors may not be sufficient to ensure the proper administration of justice. In such cases it is in the interests of both justice and the public that there should be further safeguards against the possibility of bias and in such cases checks which go beyond the investigation of criminal records may be necessary.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 These classes of case my be defined broadly as (a) cases in which national security is involved and part of the evidence is likely to be heard in camera, and (b) security and terrorist cases in which a juror’s extreme beliefs could prevent a fair trial.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 The particular aspects of these cases which may make it desirable to seek extra precautions are:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. in security cases a danger that a juror, either voluntarily or under pressure, may make an improper use of evidence which, because of its sensitivity, has been given in camera,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. in both security and terrorist cases the danger that a juror’s personal beliefs are so biased as to go beyond normally reflecting the broad spectrum of views and interests in the community to reflect the extreme views of sectarian interest or pressure group to a degree which might interfere with his fair assessment of the facts of the case or lead him to exert improper pressure on his fellow jurors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 In order to ascertain whether in exceptional circumstances of the above nature either of these factors might seriously influence a potential juror’s impartial performance of his duties or his respecting the secrecy of evidence given in camera, it may be necessary to conduct a limited investigation of the panel. In general, such further investigation beyond one of criminal records made for disqualifications may only be made with the records of the police. However, a check may, additionally be made against the records of the Security Service. No checks other than on these sources and no general inquiries are to be made save to the limited extent that they may be needed to confirm the identity of a juror about whom the initial check has raised serious doubts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 No further investigation, as described in para.6 above, should be made save with the personal authority of the Attorney General on the application of the Director of Public Prosecutions and such checks are hereafter referred to as ‘authorised checks’. When a chief officer of police or the prosecutor has reason to believe that it is likely that an authorised check may be desirable and proper in accordance with these guidelines, he should refer the matter to the Director of Public Prosecutions. In those cases in which the Director of Public Prosecutions believes authorised checks are both proportionate and necessary, the Director will make an application to the Attorney General. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 The Director of Public Prosecutions will provide the Attorney General with all relevant information in support of the requested authorised checks.  The Attorney General will consider personally the request and, if appropriate, authorise the check. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 The result of any authorised check will be sent to the Director of Public Prosecutions. The Director will then decide, having regard to the matters set out in para.5 above, what information ought to be brought to the attention of prosecuting counsel.  The Director will also provide the Attorney General with the result of the authorised check.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 Although the right of stand by and the decision to authorise checks are wholly within the discretion of the Attorney General, when the Attorney General has agreed to an authorised check being conducted, the Director of Public Prosecutions will write to the Presiding Judge for the area to advise him that this is being done.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 No right of stand by should be exercised by counsel for the Crown on the basis of information obtained as a result of an authorised check save with the personal authority of the Attorney General and unless the information is such as, having regard to the facts of the case and the offences charged, to afford strong reason for believing that a particular juror might be a security risk, be susceptible to improper approaches or be influenced in arriving at a verdict for the reasons given above.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 Information revealed in the course of an authorised check must be considered in line with the normal rules on disclosure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 A record is to be kept by the Director of Public Prosecutions of the use made by counsel of the information passed to him and of the jurors stood by or challenged by the parties to the proceedings. A copy of this record is to be forwarded to the Attorney General for the sole purpose of enabling him to monitor the operation of these guidelines.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14 No use of the information obtained as a result of an authorised check is to be made except as may be necessary in direct relation to or arising out of the trial for which the check was authorised. The information may, however, be used for the prevention of crime or as evidence in a future criminal prosecution, save that material obtained from the Security Service may only be used in those circumstances with the authority of the Security Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier guidelines can be found at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk"&gt;National Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17478</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T15:20:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T15:20:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-acceptance-of-pleas-and-the-prosecutors-role-in-the-sentencing-exercise"/>
    <title>The acceptance of pleas and the prosecutor's role in the sentencing exercise</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="a-foreword"&gt;A: Foreword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A1. Prosecutors have an important role in protecting the victim’s interests in the criminal justice process, not least in the acceptance of pleas and the sentencing exercise. The basis of plea, particularly in a case that is not contested, is the vehicle through which the victim’s voice is heard. Factual inaccuracies in pleas in mitigation cause distress and offence to victims, the families of victims and witnesses. This can take many forms but may be most acutely felt when the victim is dead and the family hears inaccurate assertions about the victim’s character or lifestyle. Prosecution advocates are reminded that they are required to adhere to the standards set out in the Victim’s Charter, which places the needs of the victim at the heart of the criminal justice process, and that they are subject to a similar obligation in respect of the Code of Practice for Victims of Crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A2. The principle of fairness is central to the administration of justice. The implementation of Human Rights Act 1998 in October 2000 incorporated into domestic law the principle of fairness to the accused articulated in the European Convention on Human Rights. Accuracy and reasonableness of plea plays an important part in ensuring fairness both to the accused and to the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A3. The Attorney General’s guidelines on the acceptance of pleas issued on December 7, 2000 highlighted the importance of transparency in the conduct of justice. The basis of plea agreed by the parties in a criminal trial is central to the sentencing process. An illogical or unsupported basis of plea can lead to an unduly lenient sentence being passed, and has a consequential effect where consideration arises as to whether to refer the sentence to the Court of Appeal under section 36 of the Criminal Justice Act 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A4. These guidelines, which replace the guidelines issued in October 2005, give guidance on how prosecutors should meet these objectives of protection of victims’ interests and of securing fairness and transparency in the process. They take into account paragraphs IV.45.4 and following of the Consolidated Criminal Practice Direction, amended May 2009 and the guidance issued by the Court of Appeal (Criminal) Division in R v Beswick [1996] 1 Cr.App.R. 343, R v Tolera [1999] 1 Cr.App.R. 25 and R v Underwood [2005] 1 Cr.App.R 178. They complement the Bar Council guidance on written standards for the conduct of professional work issued with the 7th edition of the code of conduct for the Bar of England and Wales and the Law Society’s professional conduct rules. When considering the acceptance of a guilty plea prosecution advocates are also reminded of the need to apply ‘The Farquharson Guidelines on The Role and Responsibilities of the Prosecution Advocate’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A5. The guidelines should be followed by all prosecutors and those persons designated under section 7 of the Prosecution of Offences Act 1985 (designated caseworkers) and apply to prosecutions conducted in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="b-general-principles"&gt;B: General principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B1. Justice in this jurisdiction, save in the most exceptional circumstances, is conducted in public. This includes the acceptance of pleas by the prosecution and sentencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B2. The Code for Crown Prosecutors governs the prosecutor’s decision-making prior to the commencement of the trial hearing and sets out the circumstances in which pleas to a reduced number of charges, or less serious charges, can be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B3. When a case is listed for trial and the prosecution form the view that the appropriate course is to accept a plea before the proceedings commence or continue, or to offer no evidence on the indictment or any part of it, the prosecution should whenever practicable speak to the victim or the victim’s family, so that the position can be explained. The views of the victim or the family may assist in informing the prosecutor’s decision as to whether it is the public interest, as defined by the Code for Crown Prosecutors, to accept or reject the plea. The victim or victim’s family should then be kept informed and decisions explained once they are made at court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B4. The appropriate disposal of a criminal case after conviction is as much a part of the criminal justice process as the trial of guilt or innocence. The prosecution advocate represents the public interest, and should be ready to assist the court to reach its decision as to the appropriate sentence. This will include drawing the court’s attention to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any victim personal statement or other information available to the prosecution advocate as to the impact of the offence on the victim &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where appropriate, to any evidence of the impact of the offending on a community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any statutory provisions relevant to the offender and the offences under consideration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any relevant sentencing guidelines and guideline cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the aggravating and mitigating factors of the offence under consideration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;B5. The prosecution advocate may also offer assistance to the court by making submissions, in the light of all these factors, as to the appropriate sentencing range. In all cases, it is the prosecution advocate’s duty to apply for appropriate ancillary orders, such as anti-social behaviour orders and confiscation orders. When considering which ancillary orders to apply for, prosecution advocates must always have regard to the victim’s needs, including the question of his or her future protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="c-the-basis-of-plea"&gt;C: The basis of plea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C1. The basis of a guilty plea must not be agreed on a misleading or untrue set of facts and must take proper account of the victim’s interests. An illogical or insupportable basis of plea will inevitably result in the imposition of an inappropriate sentence and is capable of damaging public confidence in the criminal justice system. In cases involving multiple defendants the bases of plea for each defendant must be factually consistent with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C2. When the defendant indicates an acceptable plea, the defence advocate should reduce the basis of the plea to writing. This must be done in all cases save for those in which the defendant has indicated that the guilty plea has been or will be tendered on the basis of the prosecution case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C3. The written basis of plea must be considered with great care, taking account of the position of any other relevant defendant where appropriate. The prosecution should not lend itself to any agreement whereby a case is presented to the sentencing judge on a misleading or untrue set of facts or on a basis that is detrimental to the victim’s interests. There will be cases where a defendant seeks to mitigate on the basis of assertions of fact which are outside the scope of the prosecution’s knowledge. A typical example concerns the defendant’s state of mind. If a defendant wishes to be sentenced on this basis, the prosecution advocate should invite the judge not to accept the defendant’s version unless he or she gives evidence on oath to be tested in cross-examination. Paragraph IV.45.14 of the Consolidated Criminal Practice Direction states that in such circumstances the defence advocate should be prepared to call the defendant and, if the defendant is not willing to testify, subject to any explanation that may be given, the judge may draw such inferences as appear appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C4. The prosecution advocate should show the prosecuting authority any written record relating to the plea and agree with them the basis on which the case will be opened to the court. If, as may well be the case, the basis of plea differs in its implications for sentencing or the making of ancillary orders from the case originally outlined by the prosecution, the prosecution advocate must ensure that such differences are accurately reflected in the written record prior to showing it to the prosecuting authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C5. It is the responsibility of the prosecution advocate thereafter to ensure that the defence advocate is aware of the basis on which the plea is accepted by the prosecution and the way in which the prosecution case will be opened to the court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C6. In all cases where it is likely to assist the court where the sentencing issues are complex or unfamiliar the prosecution must add to the written outline of the case which is served upon the court a summary of the key considerations. This should take the form of very brief notes on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any relevant statutory limitations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the names of any relevant sentencing authorities or guidelines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scope for any ancillary orders (eg concerning anti-social behaviour, confiscation or deportation will need to be considered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the age of the defendant and information regarding any outstanding offences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;C7. It remains open to the prosecutor to provide further written information (for example to supplement and update the analysis at later stages of the case) where he or she thought that likely to assist the court, or if the judge requests it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C8. When the prosecution advocate has agreed the written basis of plea submitted by the defence advocate, he or she should endorse the document accordingly. If the prosecution advocate takes issue with all or part of the written basis of plea, the procedure set out in the Consolidated Criminal Practice Direction (and in Part 37.10(5) of the Criminal Procedure Rules) should be followed. The defendant’s basis of plea must be set out in writing identifying what is in dispute; the court may invite the parties to make representations about whether the dispute is material to sentence; and if the court decides that it is a material dispute, the court will invite further representations or evidence as it may require and decide the dispute in accordance with the principles set out in R v Newton, 77 Cr.App.R.13, CA. The signed original document setting out the disputed factual matters should be made available to the trial judge and thereafter lodged with the court papers, as it will form part of the record of the hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C9. Where the basis of plea cannot be agreed and the discrepancy between the two accounts is such as to have a potentially significant effect on the level of sentence, it is the duty of the defence advocate so to inform the court before the sentencing process begins. There remains an overriding duty on the prosecution advocate to ensure that the sentencing judge is made aware of the discrepancy and of the consideration which must be given to holding a Newton hearing to resolve the issue. The court should be told where a derogatory reference to a victim, witness or third party is not accepted, even though there may be no effect on sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C10. As emphasised in paragraph IV.45.10 of the Consolidated Criminal Practice Direction, whenever an agreement as to the basis of plea is made between the prosecution and defence, any such agreement will be subject to the approval of the trial judge, who may of his or her own motion disregard the agreement and direct that a Newton hearing should be held to determine the proper basis on which sentence should be passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C11. Where a defendant declines to admit an offence that he or she previously indicated should be taken into consideration, the prosecution advocate should indicate to the defence advocate and the court that, subject to further review, the offence may now form the basis of a new prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="d-sentence-indications"&gt;D: Sentence indications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D1. Only in the Crown Court may sentence indications be sought. Advocates there are reminded that indications as to sentence should not be sought from the trial judge unless issues between the prosecution and defence have been addressed and resolved. Therefore, in difficult or complicated cases, no less than seven days notice in writing of an intention to seek an indication should normally be given to the prosecution and the court. When deciding whether the circumstances of a case require such notice to be given, defence advocates are reminded that prosecutors should not agree a basis of plea unless and until the necessary consultation has taken place first with the victim and/or the victim’s family and second, in the case of an independent prosecution advocate, with the prosecuting authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D2. If there is no final agreement about the plea to the indictment, or the basis of plea, and the defence nevertheless proceeds to seek an indication of sentence, which the judge appears minded to give, the prosecution advocate should remind him or her of the guidance given in R v Goodyear (Karl) [2005] EWCA 888 that normally speaking an indication of sentence should not be given until the basis of the plea has been agreed or the judge has concluded that he or she can properly deal with the case without the need for a trial of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D3. If an indication is sought, the prosecution advocate should normally enquire whether the judge is in possession of or has access to all the evidence relied on by the prosecution, including any victim personal statement, as well as any information about relevant previous convictions recorded against the defendant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D4. Before the judge gives the indication, the prosecution advocate should draw the judge’s attention to any minimum or mandatory statutory sentencing requirements. Where the prosecution advocate would be expected to offer the judge assistance with relevant guideline cases or the views of the Sentencing Guidelines Council, he or she should invite the judge to allow them to do so. Where it applies, the prosecution advocate should remind the judge that the position of the Attorney General to refer any sentencing decision as unduly lenient is unaffected. In any event, the prosecution advocate should not say anything which may create the impression that the sentence indication has the support or approval of the Crown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="e-pleas-in-mitigation"&gt;E: Pleas in mitigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E1. The prosecution advocate must challenge any assertion by the defence in mitigation which is derogatory to a person’s character, (for instance, because it suggests that his or her conduct is or has been criminal, immoral or improper) and which is either false or irrelevant to proper sentencing considerations. If the defence advocate persists in that assertion, the prosecution advocate should invite the court to consider holding a Newton hearing to determine the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E2. The defence advocate must not submit in mitigation anything that is derogatory to a person’s character without giving advance notice in writing so as to afford the prosecution advocate the opportunity to consider their position under paragraph E1. When the prosecution advocate is so notified they must take all reasonable steps to establish whether the assertions are true. Reasonable steps will include seeking the views of the victim. This will involve seeking the views of the victim’s family if the victim is deceased, and the victim’s parents or legal guardian where the victim is a child. Reasonable steps may also include seeking the views of the police or other law enforcement authority, as appropriate. An assertion which is derogatory to a person’s character will rarely amount to mitigation unless it has a causal connection to the circumstances of the offence or is otherwise relevant to proper sentencing considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E3. Where notice has not been given in accordance with paragraph E2, the prosecution advocate must not acquiesce in permitting mitigation which is derogatory to a person’s character. In such circumstances, the prosecution advocate should draw the attention of the court to the failure to give advance notice and seek time, and if necessary, an adjournment to investigate the assertion in the same way as if proper notice had been given. Where, in the opinion of the prosecution advocate, there are substantial grounds for believing that such an assertion is false or irrelevant to sentence, he or she should inform the court of their opinion and invite the court to consider making an order under section 58(8) of the Criminal Procedure and Investigations Act 1996, preventing publication of the assertion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E4. Where the prosecution advocate considers that the assertion is, if true, relevant to sentence, or the court has so indicated, he or she should seek time, and if necessary an adjournment, to establish whether the assertion is true. If the matter cannot be resolved to the satisfaction of the parties, the prosecution advocate should invite the court to consider holding a Newton hearing to determine the issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
