<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/defence-equipment-and-support</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/defence-equipment-and-support.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Defence Equipment and Support</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/54845</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:38:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-new-home-on-the-web-for-fco-mod-bis-and-ago"/>
    <title>The new home on the web for FCO, MOD, BIS and AGO</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four central government departments and several of their public bodies have today (13 December, 2012) become the latest central government organisations to move their corporate and policy content onto the new GOV.UK website - the new single home for all government services and information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign and Commonwealth Office (&lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt;), Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;), Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Attorney General’s Office (&lt;abbr title="Attorney General's Office"&gt;AGO&lt;/abbr&gt;) have moved their content to the new website, joining the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) whose content moved to GOV.UK last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section on GOV.UK makes it simpler, clearer and faster to find out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how government works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the government is doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you can get involved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="new-web-addresses"&gt;New web addresses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All web addresses have been redirected, so you don’t need to update your bookmarks, but you might want to make a note of the new addresses: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/fco" title="FCO"&gt;www.gov.uk/fco&lt;/a&gt; - Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/mod" title="MOD"&gt;www.gov.uk/mod&lt;/a&gt; - Ministry of Defence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/bis" title="BIS"&gt;www.gov.uk/bis&lt;/a&gt; - Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ago" title="AGO"&gt;www.gov.uk/ago&lt;/a&gt; - Attorney General’s Office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Inside Government section of GOV.UK has been designed to make government information easier to find and more transparent for the user. For the first time, you can begin to find out what’s happening inside government all in one place, and in a clear, consistent and transparent format. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that the new website looks very different from the ones it has replaced. The look is one obvious difference but many of the other significant changes are less visible.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topics"&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see information from multiple government departments grouped by topics. For example, you can see how policies from &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; are contributing to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"&gt;national security&lt;/a&gt; or combating &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="clear-policies"&gt;Clear policies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those departments and agencies who have moved to GOV.UK are publishing their policies according to the outcome the government is trying to achieve. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6" title="making it easier to set up and grow a business"&gt;making it easier to set up and grow a business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally" title="promoting human rights internationally"&gt;promoting human rights internationally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament" title="working towards nuclear disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each policy, you can see a list of all the related announcements, consultations and publications in one list, called ‘activity’. The activity tab makes it easy for you to track what is happening on the policies that interest you, for example all government activity that relates to &lt;a href="/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity" title="establishing stability in Afghanistan: activity"&gt;establishing stability in Afghanistan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="more-about-inside-government-and-govuk"&gt;More about Inside Government and GOV.UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Government is still a work in progress, with only some organisations live. Work will continue as other departments and organisations, many hundreds in total, move their information to GOV.UK. This will happen in batches and will be completed by March 2014.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more here: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/tour#inside-government"&gt;Inside Government tour and introductory video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://digital.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/2012/11/05/what-is-inside-government/"&gt;Blog post: What is Inside Government?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45348</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-20-science-and-technology-in-optimising-security-defence-and-security"/>
    <title>2012/11/20 - Science and Technology in Optimising Security, Defence and Security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Professor Bernard Silverman and City Forum for that introduction and for inviting me to join you here to open today’s Round Table event with many of the country’s leading defence and security scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am quite sure that some of you, at events like this, are quite capable of standing up and explaining with convincing authority what the world is going to look like in ten, twenty or even thirty years time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be able to describe a compelling vision of future threats and future technologies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oil shortages and global famines; bioterrorism and space wars; Chinese hegemony and European superstates.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much may be foreseeable by commentators and academics, but the reality for those of us in the Ministry of Defence is that we cannot know with certainty what is going to happen in the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that we are helpless against unpredictable events.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot prevent the passage of time, but we can influence its course and prepare for its currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Security Strategy laid out potential threats and prioritised perceived risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It depicted a world in which the only certainty is uncertainty.  Where national events can very quickly escalate to global crises and where threats to the UK can come from diverse and unexpected sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can mitigate risk through international development, investment in multinational institutions, diplomacy and capacity building, but at some point we know that military intervention will be required to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Science and Technology Laboratory and our Development Concepts and Doctrine Centre do some excellent work looking at the types of scenarios in which our Armed Forces might be required to intervene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they would be the first to admit that they possess no crystal ball, which is why they look at many scenarios, not one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the key to responding to an unknown future is flexibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Ministry of Defence that is about developing Armed Forces and Defence capability that can deal with a broad range of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to use the language of this conference we cannot afford to prepare for just a single type of “game changer”, we must consider all possible game changers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blueprint for agile, adaptable Armed Forces is Future Force 2020.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-technology"&gt;Importance of Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be effective Future Force 2020 must have the best equipment available: class leading platforms, complex weapon systems and supporting ISTAR assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it not just about kit.  Our Armed Forces must be well trained and understand how best to use their equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profitable and high tech British Defence and Security sector is essential to achieving both those goals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to know what our next security challenge will look like, but I confidently predict that the private sector and our world class academic institutions will be central to helping us deal with it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cyber, to space, to nano technology, Britain has world leading companies underpinned by world leading scientific research, developing applications, some of which I have already seen helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging this technological innovation to flourish is vital to our national security and our prosperity, contributing to export led recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my new role I have responsibility for Defence exports as well as procurement, so encouraging responsible Defence exports is a particular priority for me.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is partly to stimulate this growth which is why the MOD has protected its annual investment in Science and Technology at 1.2% of the Defence Budget - over £400 million a year  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of guaranteeing a minimum level of S&amp;amp;T funding is in line with recommendations from Lord Heseltine’s recent thought provoking review.  He highlights the valuable role that government investment can have in catalysing private sector innovation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why more than 60% of our S&amp;amp;T budget is spent outside of government - including a new £32 million research contract which we recently signed with BAE Systems to explore the next generation of maritime capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of the contract is designed to maximise the reach of our S&amp;amp;T funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the project will be managed by a team from BAE, there will be numerous participants in the research, from large companies, to academia, to SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine also mentions the contribution that SMEs make to the economy and in particular to innovation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, like my predecessor Peter Luff, whom I know relished his role in supporting Science and Technology, am a champion of the SMEs doing innovative work in the Defence and Security sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that SMEs are not the only source of original thinking in our sector, but they often provide the niche expertise which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in supporting SMEs in this area, helping them to commercialise their high tech ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last four years the CDE has received nearly 4,000 proposals for funding, resulting in around 600 contracts valued at around £35 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be holding a marketplace on 3rd December where those SMEs who have successfully demonstrated innovative technology will have a chance to present their capabilities to our prime contractors - boosting their prospects of being introduced into the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are some amazing ideas and technologies which have been developed by the innovators we have funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example, on display at this CDE event will be Blue Bear Systems Research Ltd, which is developing a morphing wing for small UAVs based on the dynamics of a bird wing.  This project exploits the design work already done for us by Mother Nature to help ensure our next generation of UAVs will be faster and more agile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the heat sensing compact video camera developed by Dreampact Ltd, which can be handheld or rifle mounted for surveillance or gunsight use in conditions of total darkness, fog, smoke or dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the projects featured at the CDE Marketplace demonstrate the ingenuity and practical focus of the SMEs we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for you to understand how we are using CDE to leverage innovation I want to tell you the story of a company called Crib Gogh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crib Gogh was a one man company based in Stoke-on-Trent developing innovative load carrying systems for soldiers - mainly vests and rucksacks with ergonomic weight distribution and energy dissipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crib Gogh received an initial £56,000 from CDE, followed up by a second contract from Dstl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this funding the company is now able to submit proposals for production level equipment into DE&amp;amp;S, the part of the MOD that acquires and supports equipment and services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has developed a lightweight prototype stretcher that is now under assessment by Dstl. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has boosted Crib Gogh’s profile enabling it to develop relationships with specialists in lightweight materials and pursue export opportunities in Europe and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has increased its turnover allowing its expansion and the recruitment of an additional employee with two more posts being considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to SMEs, even to a business as small as a one-man band, is to support, not stifle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we fund SMEs to work on specific projects for us.  They keep the intellectual property rights for their work, and can develop them however they want, once they have completed their project with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the commercial potential for Defence related intellectual property can also be shown by the success of P2i.  This company was created to exploit the liquid repellant technology coming from a Dstl project, which developed clothing to protect Service personnel from chemical attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P2i’s revolutionary nano-coating process dramatically reduces the&lt;br&gt;
surface energy of a material, so that when liquids come into contact with it they form beads and simply roll off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is so successful that P2i has been able to position itself as a world leader in this field. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology has been successfully applied to a wide range of products, such as electronic devices, filtration products and clothing - including Kangol hats now being marketed by the US actor Samuel L. Jackson.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our S&amp;amp;T investment can stimulate commercial applications well beyond the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that the MOD does have an important role to play in dipping into a dynamic pool of innovation to drive defence applications forward which can lead to economic benefits for the nation far more valuable than just for the immediate Defence objective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we only get that by leaving companies free to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-operations"&gt;Current Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Minister for Defence Equipment Support and Technology I have two main challenges:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, to ensure that our Armed Forces have the equipment they need for today;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, to ensure that our Armed Forces have the equipment they need for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of our business means that a good proportion of the MOD’s endeavour and resources will always be focussed on current operations of the day.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our first priority remains Afghanistan.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the men and women of our Armed Forces are making the greatest sacrifices and this is where we must put our main effort.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But meeting current requirements is not distinct from developing future capabilities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War does not stand still, it evolves - measures and countermeasures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been in Afghanistan for more than ten years now.  And in that time the equipment used by our troops has changed, in some areas, beyond recognition.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing the equipment for current operations involves a never ending feedback loop - the needs of theatre, the development and testing of solutions, the deployment of novel capabilities and then returning to the new needs of theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is yesterday’s tomorrow: the equipment being used in Helmand now is the product of research and development effort from years in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the gears of counter-terrorism have forced us to shorten the time between identifying a need and deploying a solution - to save lives and to increase capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of the Foxhound patrol vehicle, partly funded by the MOD’s Science and Technology budget, is an outstanding example of this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound employs world leading technology to provide an unparalleled balance of protection, weight and agility for a vehicle of its class.  It can drive away with only three wheels and its engine can be replaced easily and quickly in challenging conditions.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound took just 40 months from concept to initial operating capability, an impressive timeline for such an advanced platform.  Forty months to design it, build it and deploy it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this urgency these vehicles are now being used by our troops in Afghanistan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these vehicles are not just of utility to our operations in Afghanistan.  They are so flexible and capable that they will form the backbone of Army 2020, the blueprint for our future Army.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flexibility was built into the design.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is Foxhound built to work in a wide variety of environments, but it has the potential to be modified easily in the future - for example, by replacing the current crew compartment with an alternative configuration to meet future requirements.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adaptability of Foxhound and the speed at which it was taken from concept to operational deployment were only possible because of a strong partnership between the MOD, the Defence scientific community and the Defence Industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good communications between the customer, the developers and the manufacturers were at the heart of the project’s success.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can rightly be proud of Foxhound, which was designed and built in Britain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it represents a model for how the MOD and Defence Industry can collaborate to deliver innovative operational capability: urgently, flexibly and above all intelligently.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the MOD to apply these principles to all of our procurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="intelligent-customer"&gt;Intelligent Customer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already made great progress towards this goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence budget has been balanced for the first time in a generation - eliminating the vast £38 billion black hole we inherited from the previous administration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many difficult decisions have been taken.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult, but necessary decisions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the MOD’s equipment and support spending within the £160bn budget envelope we have set for the next ten years is essential.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining the overheated, essentially aspirational, equipment programme of the last Government was not an option.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would have condemned us to face future conflicts hamstrung by a deficit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the budget now includes proper contingency funding, which will allow us to respond proactively to future events.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But procurement reform is not just about fiscal management, it is also about ensuring the best equipment for our future Armed Forces and the best value for money for the taxpayer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are looking at improving DE&amp;amp;S to allow an injection of private sector expertise, tools and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a great believer in the wisdom of one sector above another.  I believe that we can all learn from each other: Government, industry and academia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becoming a more intelligent customer requires dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-co-operation"&gt;International Co-operation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That dialogue must include international co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For in a world of new realities - with fiscal constraints and unpredictable threats - none of us, not even our friends here today from the US, can afford to maintain all possible capabilities to deal with all possible eventualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative research is not just nice-to-have, it is absolutely essential if we are to maintain a technological advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country can claim to have a monopoly on innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Defence research we are working with a number of countries bilaterally, or through organisations such as NATO: from traditional allies such as Australia, with whom we have recently signed a co-operative facilities arrangement, and France, where 60 projects are under consideration for collaboration, to emergent powers such as India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year our Chief Scientific Adviser signed a Letter of Arrangement with his Indian counterpart agreeing to pool science and engineering experience on areas such as advanced explosives and factors affecting human performance on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is really important that we work alongside a diverse range of partners, especially on issues of technological interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In circumstances where we don’t know what the next operation will be or who we will need to work alongside, building interoperability is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that technology remains an enabler, not an inhibitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion, I’m afraid I have been unable to give you a simple and definitive answer on how to deal with future uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to offer some vision of building flexibility into our Armed Forces so they can respond to the future, whatever shape it takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the MOD it is a case of hedging, not speculating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vibrant Science and Technology community in this country is at the heart of our strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you what our next major operation will be.  I can’t tell you what the next significant technological advance will be.  I can’t even tell you, with certainty, what the next threat to the UK will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can tell you that it will be the ingenuity and drive of our scientists and businesses, and the bravery and dedication of our Armed Forces that will allow us to respond in the way this country has always responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History has shown that Britain has in-built resilience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanks, radar, computing - necessity has always born us invention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never be complacent, but we should always be confident that we can and will deal with the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I trust that you will use today’s conference to help define where the defence and security industry can most benefit our Armed Forces of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45367</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-16-odgers-berndtson"/>
    <title>2012/10/16 - Odgers Berndtson</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Odgers Berndtson and Berwin Leighton Paisner for providing this opportunity to talk to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first formal speech to a defence industry forum since taking over my responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already briefly met some of you, or colleagues from the companies you represent, at one of our “industry days” last month at Abbey Wood, and some brave souls who attended the recent party conference in Birmingham recently, for which I am grateful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am delighted to be able to speak to you collectively in a little more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a steep learning curve, having not had the benefit of a background in the military.  So I am standing by to engage, initially with the Armed Forces to understand their needs and operational requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But developing a dialogue with you is also an important part of my path along this curve and will shape the way I approach this complex role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So tonight I will touch on Defence acquisition, but I also want to give you a sense of who the new Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology is and what my priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by telling you a little about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told you I am not a military man - although I did have some modest exposure to Salisbury plain as an army cadet at school and to the RAF as a member of the University Air Squadron at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came into politics after a career in business.  I was first elected in 2005 at the tender age of 46 - one of the eldest of my cohort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My constituents often tell me, and it is a view that I happen to share, that those elected to Parliament can contribute most to their communities if they have experience of the world beyond Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experience is twenty years in business advising major corporates - working across a range of sectors and companies - including retail - I hope some of you may at some stage have bought a book from an Ottakar’s bookshop, a company I co-founded in 1988 and sold to Waterstone’s, a year after I was elected, in 2006 - by luck as it happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am, by background, a businessman and an entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that this commercial experience will give me a useful and relevant perspective on some of the issues I will be dealing with at the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is already clear to me that being a Minister at the MOD will be unlike anything I have done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise that defence of the realm is the first duty of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is a great privilege to be working in the Ministry of Defence with some of the best, brightest - and bravest - people that our country has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in that context I would just like to pay tribute to my predecessors and good friends, Peter Luff and Sir Gerald Howarth, whom many of you have got to know well.  Both have been most gracious in offering me their full support in this new role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I come to the department not representing any vested interests - but with a clear focus on my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is to do my best for the men and women of our Armed Forces who rely, sometimes for their very lives, upon the equipment and support for which I am now responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also determined to do my best for British taxpayers, who are hard-pressed, especially at the moment, and deserve effective and efficient Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am determined to do my best for the British economy, to ensure where possible that the defence equipment sector plays its part in the growth agenda for Britain: to recruit British engineers; to encourage British technology; and to develop British exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing business in Britain to contribute to Britain’s defence: generating the equipment and support that our Armed Forces need to protect the country; and generating jobs and revenue for the UK that can help balance the cost of defence to the Treasury - and in the final analysis - the taxpayer, where the financial burden ultimately falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With shrinking Defence budgets in many developed countries, I understand how difficult it is out there for the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am under no illusion that the world of defence equipment, procurement and support is simple and straightforward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we face unique and difficult challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cannot be met by Government alone - or by business alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a clear need for us to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my first message for you tonight is that I am here not just as a customer, but also as a collaborator, to listen, to understand - and to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been given a clear mandate from the Prime Minister and the Secretary of State to encourage a strong and viable Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why I am pleased that I have been given the added responsibility for Defence Exports, as well as for procurement, within the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about that today, but let me start by outlining some of those challenges I referred to a moment ago.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are difficult times for our Armed Forces as they undertake a tough transformation while continuing to operate in dangerous circumstances in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations have to remain the No 1 priority - and it will be my No 1 priority to make sure that our Forces have all they need to get that job done as safely as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these are difficult times for the country as a whole and Defence must continue to play its part in putting the economy on the right track. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fortunate to arrive at the Ministry of Defence after many of the toughest decisions have already been taken.  Thanks to the courage of the Secretary of State Philip Hammond, and his predecessor Liam Fox, we now have a balanced budget for the first time in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme has been reined in and we have a deliverable path towards Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in contrast to the previous Government who operated an unfunded wish list.  Those years of over-programming created a climate of uncertainty and criticism that was beneficial neither to us nor to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I see my first task as ensuring that the MOD’s equipment and support spending is kept within the £160bn budget envelope we have set for the next ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be publishing our Equipment Plan in the coming months. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide you, our contractors, with greater granularity than ever before about how money will be spent across the breadth of capabilities, providing a year-by-year breakdown for equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that this will help you to build your planning on a firmer foundation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, the Defence Industrial Strategy that Jim Murphy seems to think existed under the last administration was built on the shifting sands of a fantasy programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing little certainty - and therefore no ability to plan properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a strategy at all - it was more of a mirage.  And I don’t mean the aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I will heed his advice accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By eliminating the black hole in the Defence budget, and putting the equipment programme on a sustainable basis, we are providing industry with the confidence that we can deliver the programme that will underpin Future Force 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been tough to achieve that balanced budget - sacrifices have had to be made that, I’m sure many of us would rather we hadn’t had to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has meant job losses - in the Armed Forces, in the civil service, and yes, in the Defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is why we can’t afford to lapse from our discipline now - because that would just mean bigger cuts in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward the MOD is determined to be a more intelligent customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone with whom the Defence sector can do business - effective and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This links to my second priority, which is to ensure that Defence Procurement plays its part in the transformation programme within the MOD, to make the procurement function as efficient as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this efficiency should be delivered through abandoning the annual efforts of the previous administration to fit the equipment programme, often at the last minute, within that year’s spending limit - pushing programmes into subsequent years, introducing inevitable cost and delay into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the noble Admiral Lord West recognised that this was a “ludicrous” way to procure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that both private sector and public sector understand what it is that we each seek to achieve from a programme - and make sure those objectives are in concert rather than in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which prompts me briefly to comment on last weekend’s revelations focused on certain former senior officers claims to influence the way military equipment is procured. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that such claims are exaggerated and equipment decisions are chosen by current not former MOD decision makers. The system we have is completely robust, but we are looking at whether any rules have been broken.  We are also considering the level of access we give retired officers to the MOD and ensuring we are informed of their commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These types of issues, though, should not dissuade us from pursuing legitimate and transparent consultation with industry.  It is essential that we continue to share skills and experience - bringing private sector discipline and productivity to public procurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are looking at restructuring DE&amp;amp;S to allow for the injection of new ideas and new experience from the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already stated its preference for an option which establishes a Government Owned, Contractor Operated -  or GOCO - entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are legitimate concerns about this process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most relate to propriety, accountability and measuring performance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have been engaging with industry in recent months to gain your input, as we explore further the options and begin to develop a commercial strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we have also begun earlier this month a Soft Market Testing exercise with potential providers to sound out their issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is undoubtedly an innovative approach to defence procurement and so it is all the more important to make sure incentives are aligned, but also to ensure that the interests of Defence and equipping our Armed Forces remain paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we decide and whatever we do, I would stress that we will continue the engagement we have started with our main contractors to ensure industry is well informed and any concerns can be taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been looking closely at plans within the department to reform the arrangements in place for single-source procurement through the Yellow Book with its Review Board. This has remained in effect in broadly similar form since first introduced in 1968.  I’ll repeat that: 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many of the companies represented here took part in the consultation around this reform earlier this year and I am grateful for the responsible way in which you recognised the merits of reform. I hope to be in a position to publish our conclusions in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of collaboration needs to be at the heart of everything we do, at every level: from Prime to SME, from local to international, bottom-up as well as top-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keen to champion SMEs, just as my predecessor did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make a vital contribution to the national economy, but also to local economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my appointment I have visited a company in my own constituency, Grainger &amp;amp; Worrall, which makes engine casings for high performance cars and Formula One, but also has some products used in defence. This was something I was previously ignorant of, despite this not being my first visit.  Perhaps the company did not believe this was something they could talk about to an outsider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company is a medium sized employer in a national context, but one of the largest employers within its community and its fortunes affect the wellbeing of hundreds of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs often provide the source of innovation and adaptation which can lead to breakthroughs in defence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Defence Enterprise has already done some excellent work in this area to open MOD’s science and technology investment to our high tech companies.  And it will be holding a marketplace of some of the best SME ideas for you, our Primes, on 3rd December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those SMEs who have successfully delivered innovative technology will have a chance to present their capabilities to our primes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be your chance to take advantage of the MOD’s investment in early stage technology, to improve the product you deliver to us, and have available for export. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you will agree that it will be in all our mutual interests to nurture the innovation that these companies can drive. So, I would urge you to make sure you are represented at this event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also ask you to consider how you can monitor better the contribution of SMEs to your own procurement for the MoD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has aspirations for the proportion of procurement provided by SMEs across Whitehall. As the MOD is the largest direct purchaser in Government this has particular relevance to me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am keen to encourage our Prime contractors to do a better job at informing my officials of the number of SMEs and the value of their contributions to contracts placed with larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the other end of the scale our new approach to industrial engagement encourages overseas based suppliers to invest in the UK’s defence and security sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working with overseas based suppliers through the Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy to promote the UK as a prime location for their supply chains and for research and development investment, and technology transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This policy initiative to encourage inward investment was launched this Spring and has already secured its first accredited member, with another about to sign and several other overseas based contractors showing considerable interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third priority, where I believe a fresh collaboration can take place, is working together to encourage your business growth through exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the previous Government, I am not embarrassed about responsible Defence Exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need responsible exports and we shall be clear about the licencing regime which governs what can be sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am clear that Britain’s Defence sector is a vital strategic asset to this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only for the vital role you play in helping to create military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also for the contribution you make to Britain’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jobs you sustain, the skills you maintain and the taxes you pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because we recognise the importance of that strategic asset that we worked so hard to ensure that the UK’s national security interests were properly protected in the BAE/EADS merger negotiations - something of a major, if completely unexpected, preoccupation in my first month as a Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong UK Defence sector - manufacturing, servicing, and crucially exporting - is a vital part of our strategy of rebalancing our economy so it can return to sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the MOD is committed to supporting the Defence Growth Partnership work led by BIS and announced by the Prime Minister at the Farnborough International Air Show in July. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It builds on the successful model of joint Government and Industry engagement already established for the Aerospace sector. The partnership will identify ways to remove barriers to growth and enhance the competitiveness of the UK defence sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will contribute to the overall approach set out earlier this year in our National Security Through Technology White Paper -working to enable UK-based industry to be competitive and provide the best value for money in meeting our defence and security needs, as well as helping you to export successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Defence exports are unlike other products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are more than simple sales of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are high value, highly regulated and play an important role in foreign policy as well as just contributing to balance of payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow governments are partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us in our pursuit of bilateral relationships - and in pursuit of national security and international stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, in terms of industrial and technological co-operation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can Government do better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - we can optimise your prospects for export success in the formulation of our own acquisition plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about acquisition processes that will take better account of the commercial landscape - building in exportability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This needs a new system for building robust business cases - setting out why more readily exportable capabilities are also in the interests of UK Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - We can help to make sure that UK products are the best and most advanced on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure the wider package on offer to our allies is as attractive as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Export success depends on more than just the hardware on offer and I will back you in meeting the wider requirements of our allies.  For instance, by providing the capacity, wherever possible, for training alongside UK Forces, or helping you to provide long term equipment support and the responsible transfer of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the first rate innovation the UK defence industry creates, the MOD cannot fulfil its mission of defending the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But innovation is also key to exports in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be impossible to sustain this innovation without sustaining the science and engineering skills on which it is built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our intention to sustain investment in defence science and technology, halting years of decline in this spending, to ensure our Armed Forces continue to use state of the art techniques and equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why in one of my first acts as a Minister, I signed a concordat for the MOD to support the exciting Bloodhound project which hopes to smash the land speed record in a cutting edge vehicle driven by an RAF pilot, with support from the Army’s Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers and using Typhoon test engines from the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This MOD support is specifically to inspire young people to study maths and science at school - becoming the engineers of the future that you and we, at the MOD, so urgently need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging engineers and scientists in Britain to make the most of their innovative talent is critical for our future export prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - we can intervene when necessary, banging the drum for British products whenever Ministers are overseas - from the Prime Minister down, to a degree that Labour completely neglected to do in their years in Government, with some notable exceptions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Hague told us last week, to the incredulity of the party conference audience, that he is already the first Foreign Secretary since we were last in Government to have made bilateral visits to Canada, New Zealand and Australia - three of the Five Eyes grouping, our closest defence partners.  None of his Labour predecessors did so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that this whole Government is energised to help you create opportunities to sell your world leading products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promotion activity in government is led by the Defence &amp;amp; Security Organisation within UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment, who you will all know well, and with whom I am already working closely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to combine responsibilities for defence procurement and for exports within MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My role will be to enable both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In concluding I want to re-emphasise my commitment to maintain a dialogue with you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to cutting bureaucracy and helping you on exports, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to developing science and engineering skills and supporting innovation, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, when it comes to developing the best way ahead for reform of acquisition and the future of DE&amp;amp;S, I am not just listening, but acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the MOD to be a world leader in defence acquisition, so that other nations look at the UK model as an exemplar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we are going to achieve this is with your support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45364</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-12-ssafa-fund-raising-dinner-ads-event-as-part-of-farnborough-2012"/>
    <title>2012/07/12 - SSAFA Fund Raising Dinner (ADS event as part of Farnborough 2012)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Sir Stephen [CAS].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you to the ADS team for hosting tonight’s dinner.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on a very successful Farnborough 2012, and to all the sponsors and donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you are laying plans for an equally successful Farnborough 2014, and a show within a show - the Unmanned Aerial Systems Expo. This is a really important area for us and the UK needs to demonstrate leadership. This initiative is therefore doubly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks to Robin for his remarks, and to you in the aerospace industries for recognising so  generously the support from ministers across government at this year’s show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of government representation is certainly a far cry from the days when you were lucky to be able to secure just one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we do value the aerospace sector - civil and defence - and we understand the role of government in supporting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting it with words and deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words with real intent. And tangible deeds that count. Such as the Chancellor highlighting the aerospace sector in his Budget speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the old cliche has it, “actions speak louder then words.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visit companies, not just defence companies, I always wait for that moment when they give me the well worn line about people being their greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It too is a cliche - but it happens to be true, as all good cliches are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret in business is to mean it, and to be able to demonstrate a genuine commitment to it. Not just to say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s not a company going through the motions and just paying lip service to this maxim which impresses me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really impresses me is a company proving that the men and women who work for them really are their greatest resource&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because people matter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s my theme tonight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know for a fact, for example, that SSAFA Forces Help does demonstrate that commitment and support in a very practical way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA knows that people are at the heart of defence and that what they do when they serve Queen and country demands a generous response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a week when the platforms have taken centre stage, it’s worth reminding ourselves that for Defence people really are our greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That stunning display from Typhoon was only possible because of the skills of the pilot - Scott,  the people in the engineering crew on the ground, the people in industry who support the plane, the people in four nations who make it and the brilliant people who designed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People, always people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know he’s not here so I can say nice things about him behind his back, that link is personified in the work of your chairman, General Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, who moved from platforms to people when he moved from CDM to SSAFA. MOD’s loss was SSAFA’s gain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have emotions, ambitions, skills, hopes and fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it turns out there are even those in the defence industry who have emotions too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - let me just say for the record that I’ve always found Robin Southwell to be a business like chap, a matter of fact kind of guy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His role as ADS President is to fight your corner, champion your interests and act as an advocate for industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his job in EADS is to sell me anything he can. And he does a good job in both roles, in a robust kind of way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he is a man who says what he thinks. I think “shooting from the lip” is the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was still rather taken aback when I opened the Financial Times  earlier this year - Friday 24 February to be precise - and saw a piece about the defence industry’s relationship with Government which read - and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love,” says Robin Southwell, head of the UK arm of EADS, the pan-European defence contractor and president of ADS, the industry’s biggest trade group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was - as you can imagine, because I do like to think of myself as emotionally aware and sensitive man - most concerned by this heartfelt plea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the next time that I met Robin I went out of my way to ensure that he did feel sufficiently cherished. That he got the love he craved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember engulfing him in a fond embrace in the street outside Portcullis House in the Palace of Westminster. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, Robin did seem rather taken aback.  I like to think he was probably just carried away by the sheer emotion of the moment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, though, he was reacting to my comment that this demonstration of love discharged all MoD’s financial obligations to EADS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, “We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tribute-to-industry"&gt;Tribute to industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do hope that everyone here this evening from industry appreciates that we do recognise the vital contribution you are making to our defence effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular your responsiveness in recent years when it has come to our operations in Libya and Afghanistan in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, thanks to your efforts, our forces today are better equipped than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that because of the universally positive feedback I get from one very discerning focus group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People whose lives very often depend on the way we deliver  acquisition and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking here of course about our servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meet them regularly on my visits to theatre and here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They speak in glowing terms about the quality and availability of their equipment.  The protection and cutting edge, battle winning capability of the equipment you produce and we provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your contribution is likely to grow as we develop the Total Support Force concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you will make that contribution with people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their talent and dedication will enable our Armed Forces to keep the nation safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one major obstacle - and I’ll be talking about this in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have heard what the Prime Minister said on Monday about the Aerospace Growth Partnership and the beginning of a similar dialogue with the defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the approach set out in the Aerospace Growth Partnership  and the National Security through Technology White Paper, we will now begin a dialogue with you to see what we can do to create an environment in which you are strong and can flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope it will put paid, once and for all, to some of the speculative debate about our real intent our the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper may be tough love Robin, but it is love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, though, we can also start looking forward and talking about the wider context. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be much to talk about. Challenges and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the top of the agenda I believe will be the obstacle I referred to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the whole issue of skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any business needs the right people to succeed. Your companies are no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - of course you need a healthy order book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But without skilled engineers in particular you simply won’t be able to develop and integrate the equipment, to write the software, to understand and interpret our requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these people we cannot safeguard our operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know you can’t find them. At all levels of engineering and in all disciplines there seems to be a shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met one engineering company a few months ago who’ve given up looking for engineers in the UK and are recruiting from Spain, Portugal and Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smaller defence companies I meet complain about all kinds of things, and understandably so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But top of their list is skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked about these issues endlessly as a nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers just aren’t valued sufficiently highly in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an urban myth that this country doesn’t make anything anymore. And that manufacturing is dead or dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So schools don’t encourage bright young people into science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And anyway they’re often too focussed on university and not enough on technical vocational options for their pupils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities offer too many general courses that don’t produce the technical, specialist skills you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely passionate about the need to do more about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not making specific suggestions here tonight to address it, but I certainly hope it will be a major theme of the dialogue the Prime Minister announced on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the only one, but perhaps the most important one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people are indeed our most important asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s show is of course a great chance to enthuse and inspire future generations of engineers and scientists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you’ll be doing that at tomorrow’s dedicated Futures Day when you should have 7,500 young people there from schools and universities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets hope their visit to Farnborough tomorrow will inspire some of these young people to pursue a career in science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of initiative I warmly commend - it’s definitely the way forward for our science and technology sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the Bloodhound world land speed record project which is doing excellent work to inspire school pupils with the massive excitement of technical innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus tonight has been on people and I have spoken about the needs of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also the case in Defence, that people in industry serve the people in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask a lot of these servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also ask a lot of their families.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We owe them all a huge debt of gratitude for the sacrifices they make on our behalf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the work of SSAFA is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the money you raise this evening will make a real difference to the lives of thousands of men, women and children. Serving personnel, families and veterans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA promises a lifetime of support - and it delivers just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our oldest service charities, it works tirelessly to provide a wealth of practical, hands on support and guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its people include many experts and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to health and social work, for example, and running the SSAFA Norton Homes which provide accommodation for families visiting injured personnel recovering at Birmingham and Headley Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a huge pool of committed volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of men and women who give up their time to work in communities, bases, units and garrisons up and down the country, as well as overseas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money you pledge tonight will ensure SSAFA Forces Help has the money it needs to continue this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Defence Minister I have the huge privilege of working with and for the United Kingdom’s Armed Forces - quite simply the  bravest, most committed people it is possible to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are our nation’s greatest asset, and tonight our generosity can demonstrate our understanding of that vital truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45370</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-02-motorsport-industry-association"/>
    <title>2012/07/02 - Motorsport Industry Association</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Alistair [Fergusson, Managing Director of Alcon Components] for that introduction. It is a pleasure to see you all here this evening and I am grateful to Chris [Aylett, Chief Executive Officer of the Motorsport Industry Association] for inviting me to say a few words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorsport is one of the few, perhaps the only, high tech industry where the UK is comprehensively world beating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technological advantage born in the UK continues to deliver race wins and championships around the world, season after season, under the flag of almost every nationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It supports tens of thousands of high value jobs here in the UK and puts billions of pounds into the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will forgive me for reminding you that, as a former chairman of the Business, Innovation and Skills Committee, I published a report that recognised your industry as one of national importance and a crown jewel of UK manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I think that was one of my own recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely stand by that conclusion. And from my office in the Ministry of Defence, I can see that you are in fact even more important than that report said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Armed Forces, technological advantage is - quite literally - a matter of life or death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be the case, that where the military led the civilian world followed. But more than ever this is a trend that is reversing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yours is a sector more responsible for this than most. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to say that Defence is harnessing the technological strides being made in your industry like never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One person more than any other is to thank for the blossoming of this relationship - and not just for being our host tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Drayson [Rt Hon Lord Drayson of Kensington], when he was sat in my place at the MOD, led the establishment of the first formal dialogue between your industry and the Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His other great gift to Defence was the Centre for Defence Enterprise - but that’s a subject of another occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He, of course, has quite a motor-racing pedigree himself - I’ve been following his Tweets from Goodwood over the weekend - so it is no surprise that he had the foresight to recognise the benefits that your industry could bring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, while success has many fathers, he should be justly proud of our biggest collaborative achievement so far, the delivery of the first Foxhound patrol vehicles to Afghanistan only last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound is a UK design and 90% of the companies involved in its production are UK based. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is only possible because British companies like you enable us to exploit state of the art technologies in areas such as machining and composites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound is an amazingly agile piece of kit, with an engine which can be removed and replaced in just 30 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been designed to withstand a direct strike from an Improvised Explosive Device and, not only keep those inside safe, but be able to drive away on just three wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Ricardo who was responsible for the original concept and has been instrumental in its design and manufacture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it was an ex-Formula One design engineer who was responsible for the vehicle pod, using materials more commonly found on the Grand Prix circuit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, Lifeline Fire &amp;amp; Safety Systems provide the innovative fire suppression systems to the engine and internal compartment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also had similar success with other MIA members on important projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, you have already heard from Alistair of Alcon Components, who have used their extensive motorsport experience to provide brakes for an upgraded Jackal armoured vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NAR group have drawn on their Paris-Dakar experience to design a new dust proof cooling system for the Panther, Mastiff and Ridgeback vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorsport has made many other contributions to Defence - in airframes and radars for example. You should be proud of these achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are making a very real difference to our personnel in Afghanistan today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may have already noted that the Army has a penchant for naming their vehicles after dogs. Foxhound, Mastiff, Husky, Jackal, Ridgeback, Wolfhound, Springer…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now we have adopted another canine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was at Millbrook driving Foxhound, I was asked by Richard Noble to be an engineering champion for the Bloodhound project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to propel the land speed record beyond a thousand miles per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you will know, the Royal Air Force and the Army are already deeply involved supporting the construction of the vehicle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be supporting the record attempts themselves in 2013 and 2014 in South Africa. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed the driver, Andy Green, is himself a serving officer in RAF, with the very ordinary job of Tornado pilot when he is not off breaking records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared access to leading edge, high performance engineering will, I have no doubt, bring direct benefit back into Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the project - just like the broader motorsport industry - is energising interest in science, technology, engineering and mathematics in our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sparking the imagination of the next generation of engineers and scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them will, in future, be responsible for winning championships, and boosting our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of them will be responsible for winning wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of winning, we come to the award…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Peter Luff MP then presented the award for Outstanding Contribution to the Motorsport Industry to John Surtees, OBE] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45368</id>
    <published>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-28-the-defence-industrial-base-a-critical-component-of-military-capability"/>
    <title>2012/06/28 - The Defence Industrial Base - A Critical Component of Military Capability</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It really is a pleasure to be at RUSI once again and to have the opportunity of discussing such an important issue and at such an appropriate moment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, to those from industry, I’m very glad that this event is focusing on you, and your businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the challenges - and opportunities - you will be encountering as Defence becomes more streamlined. More challenging. And more disciplined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an appropriate moment for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is published, the defence budget is balanced, defence transformation continues apace, we are near reaching conclusions on the future of DE&amp;amp;S and the National Audit Office is considering our equipment plan prior to its publication. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s clearly the right moment to clarify some of the issues affecting defence companies. I also say that because I was somewhat baffled by elements of the pre-conference papers for this event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There appear to be a number of misunderstandings - which I suspect may be more widely shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m aware that some of these misunderstandings could be down to us. Perhaps we in MOD have not been sufficiently clear when it comes to explaining the principles, rationale and implications of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months on we’re now busy taking the White Paper forward. Have we, though, successfully concluded the whole communication process with industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked hard - and continue to do so - to make sure that the logic and implications of our White Paper are fully understood within the MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing a mindset has taken time even within our own organisation, never mind across industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think I may need to bang the drum a bit louder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take SMEs - Small and Medium-sized enterprises.  I was more than a little surprised when I saw that there was no mention at all of SMEs in those pre-conference papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s because they are the life blood of any industry and are therefore something I highlight in every speech and meeting. Today will be no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, repeating new truths doesn’t necessarily mean we think all the old ones have all lost their validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if I talk up SMEs and don’t say so much about Primes, it’s not because I don’t value both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s because I think we all - the Armed Forces, MOD, DE&amp;amp;S and the Primes - need to value SMEs much more than we have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I welcome today as an opportunity to set the record straight on a number of fronts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on I’ll be exploring the whole ‘off the shelf’ principle, and our commitment to exports. As well as clarifying our stance on sovereign requirements.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, though, I want you from industry to be in no doubt whatsoever that you are a critical component of military capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your people, your products, your services equip, transport, protect, clothe, feed, support our Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Secretary of State has made clear, the defence of our nation is a team effort. Defence contractors, civilians and the Armed Forces themselves are the three essential pillars of the whole force concept which delivers modern defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are hundreds of you, of every size - primes, medium and small, even micro enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you have a global presence - others are smaller firms based just here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are involved in a range of activities and would not brand yourselves as defence-centric companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of you have been involved in the provision of UORs in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I speak there are around five thousand contractors out in theatre, supporting our Armed Forces in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the honour of presenting medals to a number of them whose work has been crucial to our effectiveness there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year industry also did a magnificent job in support of the Libya campaign, and - for the record - there’s a dedicated case study on their contribution to Operation Ellamy on page 24 of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact I also wrote letters of thanks and appreciation to some twenty companies of all sizes who played a crucial role in Op Ellamy. I could easily have written ten times that number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take just one example - Typhoon, and the way industry optimised its capability for that operation. Of course, the excellence of the aircraft played its part too, but it was private sector companies and their staff that kept it flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, thanks to your innovation - and strong partnership working with organisations like DSTL - our Forces have superb kit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it is the best they have ever had. And as good as can be found anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your part in that remarkable achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be a cliche, but it is true - necessity is the mother of invention. That has certainly been the case in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And significant parts of that defence innovation, as is so often the case, are being transferred across to the civilian world.&lt;br&gt;
I’m thinking here in particular of the advances in battlefield medicine which are also driving forward changes in the NHS. &lt;br&gt;
So - you are a vital part, all of you, of our defence effort. You make defence happen.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s this - I don’t actually agree with the title for this conference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not because you aren’t a critical component of military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, it’s the first three words of the conference theme that worry me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was Voltaire who wrote that the Holy Roman Empire was neither holy, nor Roman, nor an empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is with the “defence industrial base”, a term that makes my heart sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, it’s not just about defence, because of the increasing overlap with Security - a major theme of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about industry but technology. More about that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not about a narrowly defined base when so many of our key suppliers have supply chains that reach around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the phrase defence industrial base summons up visions of some giant monolith - shielded from the market forces that are always the driver of efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faceless, intransigent - and unaccountable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful symbol of the problems that have faced defence acquisition in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete antithesis of the way we intend to run our whole defence equipment and support programme.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look specifically at that third word; ‘base.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a problem with the very idea that we have - or indeed should have - a ‘defence industrial base’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly, it’s more complicated that that. In fact, I’m not sure it’s even factually correct these days to refer to a ‘defence industry’ as a collective concept. Your diversity is your strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality - as I said earlier - is that defence equipment and support covers a huge and diverse range of activity, and companies of just about every size, with varying degrees of dependence on the MOD budget.  And they are all important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From primes to start-ups. Providing everything from syringes to submarines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their services and products often cover a range of sectors. They certainly don’t want to get pigeon holed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is driving fundamental change in our supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those smaller companies are so often the ones who are proving to be innovative and agile - and sensitive to the customer’s needs in these times of austerity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are out there winning international business in today’s tough global environment - and not waiting for the MOD to make up its mind about what it will buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are looking for greater SME involvement in our procurement strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not for altruistic reasons - but because we are determined to drive in innovation and responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will also hard-wire this approach into the reformed DE&amp;amp;S and its harder-edged relationship with the MOD customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are defence industries. But as I said earlier, their supply chain spreads around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are industries which contribute to defence but which have their origins, or the majority of their business, in other sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are industries that may not yet be on our radar which should be - and which must be encouraged to make their contribution to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in Defence value you highly, but you are not a united industrial base as such.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also striving to increase the proportion of the equipment and support solutions that we buy in open competition. More of that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do understand the limits on competition in defence acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all on this issue, our security depends on us being able to protect our sovereign requirements for operational advantage and freedom of action. And we will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is where the misunderstandings between us -  between the MOD and industry - most urgently need to be addressed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These concepts were, after all, an important feature of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old phrase “sovereign capability” trips easily off the tongue. But it can lead to some pretty woolly thinking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Industrial Strategy of 2005 listed the capabilities industry had.  And then said what Government would do to protect them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed everybody and anybody to claim that their capability was essential and that, implicitly, the MOD would have to fund it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An approach that proved to be unaffordable - and downright illogical in an age of rapid change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the White Paper “National Security Through Technology” does what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets out an approach that starts with what the State needs for its security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it looks at the different ways of achieving it, establishing affordability, what it will acquire, and how it will acquire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now embedding this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper implementation team is looking now at exactly how best to embed these concepts - and that of exportability - in both Main Building and the Front Line Commands. And how to take account of the views of industry and DE&amp;amp;S.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process we will follow is much more subtle and nuanced than some commentators seem to have understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will buy equipment using the route most appropriate for that equipment bearing in mind its nature and our need for operational advantage and freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek exemptions from EU procurement rules to sustain our technological advantage where we need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important, however, that you recognise and understand that we’re not going back to producing a long list of specific sovereign capabilities - effectively owned by specific companies - that we will protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is changing too fast, and money is too tight - as indeed they both probably always were - to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future lies in open systems - as we see in the Land Open Systems Architecture approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise this means big change for many larger firms in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the gains for Defence as a whole are real. And I believe greater competitiveness will help the big companies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, be very clear, the skills and resources to deliver operational advantage and freedom of action will be safeguarded when we must do so to protect the nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the White Paper we set out the broad circumstances where this will apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real challenge we all face is not new acquisition processes but constrained acquisition budgets here and, indeed around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be skills the UK needs to safeguard and with development money for new projects constrained, some of them may be at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would have faced the challenge of how to deal with in any event, White Paper or no White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having operational advantage and freedom of action in the future depends investment in the future of the right technologies now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are constantly assessing what we believe are critical technologies - and why our decision to protect the Science and Technology budget from further cuts is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently announced a billion pound investment in the Rolls Royce core production capability at Derby. Here is a clear example of a technology and skill set we know we do need to sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the announcement at the end of last year of additional funding for research into next generation of highly capable air systems - a £40 million four-year research contract with BAE Systems to explore critical technologies and key systems integration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be other such examples and we will take careful note of the views of industry as we identify and address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will be for the Government to determine how best to sustain the technology - perhaps, for example, by collaboration with one of our most trusted allies rather than by maintaining a single UK source.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is a national business - but it is not an industry of the state. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state has its defence requirements, and they are being met by an increasingly diverse range of suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of you realise that Hewlett Packard is our fourth biggest supplier? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that SMEs now win over 42 per cent of all the contracts we let? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the overall value of those contracts is lower, at 13 per cent of our spending. But it is a very significant amount given that the sheer scale of many of our programmes mean they are outside the scope of SMEs, at least as prime contractors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, the beguiling argument that spending money on Defence will create more jobs for UK PLC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in essence, defence is in some way special in its capacity to generate employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does have an academic term: ‘Military Keynesianism’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, John Maynard Keynes himself didn’t approve of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Keynes wrote an open letter to President Franklin Roosevelt. In that letter he said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”… a war has always caused intense industrial activity. In the past orthodox finance has regarded a war as the only legitimate excuse for creating employment by governmental expenditure. You, Mr President, having cast off such fetters, are free to engage in the interests of peace and prosperity the technique which hitherto has only been allowed to serve the purposes of war and destruction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I agree with Keynes - up to a point. There are many ways to stimulate an economy other than by investing in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We buy defence equipment and support that equipment because we need it to secure our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the duty of the MOD to buy what we need to do that and to protect our sovereignty - no more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the consequences of the acquisition decisions we take in the MOD have implications for the responsibilities of other Government departments - or vice versa - the White Paper established a ministerial committee to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a sub-set of full-blown military Keynesianism that asserts we should always try to buy defence equipment in our own country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a “red in tooth and claw” capitalist to believe in capitalism’s principal tenets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that the greatest long-term good is served when competition is allowed to work. That means efficient markets and real wealth creation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it’s good when British-based companies win UK defence contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often our needs will mean buying British from single sources; 40 percent of our defence equipment and support budget is spent that way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And much of the remaining 60 per cent is also won by British companies too because you are so good at what you do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look through the announcements we have made recently - on Sea Ceptor, Sea Viper, the Core Production Capability, the refit of HMS Vengeance, maintaining Hercules, the Warrior Capability Sustainment Programme, Foxhound, Scout - the list goes on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of highly skilled jobs secured by our acquisition and support decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course buying defence equipment creates jobs. But so does investing in the arts, in hospitals, in schools, in roads, in housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to justify defence spending by its potential for job creation, others in Government would raise their eyebrows and offer a rather incredulous response along the lines of: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh really? More jobs than funding research in the civil aerospace technology? Or rolling out Broadband across the UK?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK defence companies do make an important contribution to our economy. I celebrate that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the only reasons for the MOD to go out of its way to protect their technologies are operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlie Blakemore of BAE Systems told it like it was when he announced last month the loss of jobs at their munitions factory in Monmouthshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said - and I’m quoting here from the BBC: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to adapt to very challenging market conditions, and further reduce our overheads to drive better value for our customers and increase our competitiveness in the export market.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words capture the kind of hard headed realism companies across the spectrum need to adopt if they are to succeed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are new opportunities for industry too. Not just in equipment acquisition, but also in support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means a new appreciation and understanding of what support means. And the number of services and capabilities it actually covers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly as we roll out the Total Support Force concept, which will include a sizeable number of contractors doing jobs we always thought were done by people in uniform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are real new commercial opportunities here for you. I appreciate the work being done by industry to help us drive this agenda forward to our mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake. We do want you to thrive and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the White Paper clearly spelt out earlier this year, it is in our interests to have successful - and competitive - defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you heard from Susanna Mason, this is a Government committed to promoting an environment conducive to responsible defence exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her appointment as MOD lead for exports is a tangible sign of our commitment to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our real challenges in implementing the White Paper is driving exportability into our requirement setting process from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realise that even a simple term like ‘exportability’ means different things to different people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, in this context it does not simply mean “capable of being exported within the constraints of the export licensing regime”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proud of our responsible and tough regime - although I know it could often work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, fundamentally it means, from the very beginning of a project, making defence equipment that the UK requires attractive to potential overseas customers. That brings benefits to us and to you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring this issue is fully addressed as we devolve responsibility to the front line commands is a major White Paper implementation task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, on the subject of international acquisition policies, I often hear it said that the White Paper does not address industrial participation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s simply not the case. I refer you to page 48, paragraph 154 of the White Paper for a clear summary of our new policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new approach towards engagement with overseas suppliers aims to encourage these companies to invest in the UK supply chain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance as a prime location to engage in research and development investment and technology transfer;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, these activities will also underpin the promotion of the UK’s defence and security exports, exploring what assistance can be provided to help UK exporters meet their global offset obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s precisely because we want you to succeed, and to deliver our operational advantage and freedom of action into the foreseeable future that I have - for the first time - put a floor under the science budget. To ensure that we as a nation we can remain at the forefront of cutting edge, battle-winning technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our national security depends on that. And that means a lot of opportunities for you.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of contractors have told me they consider the White Paper to be pragmatic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the policy it articulates is in fact a continuation of what had been the Department’s direction of travel for several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that the White Paper spells it out in black and white. And provides industry with the clarity - and honesty - you have been asking for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the commitments to science, to exports, and to SMEs are new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a change from the 2005 Defence Industrial Strategy which this year’s White Paper replaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also agree wholeheartedly with John Maynard Keynes when he said, or at least is believed to have said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When the facts change, I change my mind. What do you do, sir?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well here are some of the facts - the realities - which I believe have changed or become more prominent over the last seven years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A global network of alliances with whom we intend to cooperate more deeply:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The international distribution of manufacturing:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Massive civil sector investment in R&amp;amp;D that increasingly spins in to Defence: &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rapidly advancing, often disruptive technology (some increasingly expensive, other parts of which become ever lower-cost):&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And increasing financial challenge and austerity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what do these facts - these new realities - mean in practice? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they mean working more closely with our allies on acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On very large programmes like JSF with the US and a wide range of international partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On specific much smaller-scale programmes such as aspects of counter- IED technology with the Germans - as I saw at DVD last week when I met MineWolf Abacot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or across a wide portfolio of programmes in the framework of the wide-ranging Franco-British agreement. Here we are working on complex weapons, unmanned combat systems, support for A400M, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then again, there are occasions when addressing this new world means single source non-competitive contracts to build nuclear powered submarines, to develop unmanned combat air systems, to build complex warships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it means mutual commitment like the one in the complex weapon pipeline arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinction between the old approach and the new one is this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policy will, more often than in the past, lead the Government to open up our defence contracts to international competition -  just, indeed, as the last Government judged it right to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, don’t forget that, as the EU takes more steps to enforce the Defence Procurement Directive, more and more European opportunities will open to British companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are competitive here, you will succeed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recent history shows us that there is absolutely no reason why UK companies should not win MOD business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at Foxhound. An excellent example of an agile and versatile vehicle - a contract competed for and won by British companies, Force Protection Europe and Ricardo, sustaining around 750 highly-skilled jobs across the UK.  And with huge export potential too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the Warrior Capability and Sustainment Programme - a contract which will create and sustain around 600 British jobs -    was won by Lockheed Martin UK in a competitive process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also the case that big contracts awarded overseas will also help to open up those international markets to British companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MARS tankers are a case in point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of British companies took part in the international competition - which was quite rightly initiated by the previous Government because they recognised, as tankers, they were not “warlike stores”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, no British company submitted a final bid for the build contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - of course I would have preferred it if there had been a competitive British bid. But in the end there wasn’t any British bid at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build contract has been awarded to Daewoo Shipbuilding and Marine Engineering of South Korea, but the ships are designed by a British company, BMT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there will be up to £150 million of associated contracts for the MARS project, many of them offering opportunities for SMEs here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MARS means UK companies have the chance to show their potential to one of the world’s largest shipyards and for DSME to get first hand experience of the services and products that can be provided cost-effectively from UK companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Korea at DSME’s hugely impressive yard on Monday. I heard of the close working relationship developing between DSME and BMT. It looks very likely to lead to further ships, based on the successful MARS design, being developed and sold to third countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means additional opportunities for the British marine engineering industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of equal significance is the potential of opening up the Korean defence market for other UK companies as the strategic relationships created through MARS develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early and encouraging sign is the significant breakthrough into the Korean naval propulsion market made by Rolls Royce. I was delighted to hear that contract announced on Tuesday in Seoul alongside representatives of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came back from South Korea yesterday and at the airport I met a Royal Navy team going in to discuss naval cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many similar challenges and shared understandings, the potential for ever deeper collaboration and partnership is very real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do agree with the pre-conference papers that MOD is adopting the ‘tough love’ approach when it comes to our relationship with industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re being equally as tough on ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recognised that we’ve got to change - and drive forward a new culture across the MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means changes ahead at DE&amp;amp;S and in the way we do business. You will be aware of Bernard Gray’s Materiel Strategy and the Defence Transformation agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is still underway as decisions are being made and you will hear more about our thinking as soon as we are ready. However, we are determined that the MOD will be a better informed and more demanding customer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I draw all this to a conclusion, I would like, briefly, to reflect on the overarching theme of this conference, “Defence, Industries and Society”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’d all agree that today the nation - quite rightly - holds our Armed Forces in very high regard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Armed Forces Day on Saturday, we will see this high regard turned into practical support up and down the country. I’m looking forward to events in my own constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thousands of men, women and children who line the streets up and down the country for homecoming parades show that support and admiration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public also recognises - in very tangible ways - the sacrifices the Armed Forces and their families make. Just look at the success of a charity like Help for Heroes which has raised £100 million in its first four years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to recognise that defence spending is in competition with all the other things that taxpayers’ expect the  Government to spend their money on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, there appears to be a greater willingness in the UK to fund Defence than in most Western nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the British people have seen the news, they read the newspapers. They know that the MOD has been culpable of gross financial mismanagement and - let’s be frank here -  squandering their money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two years of the Coalition Government have been spent dealing with the horrendous national deficit. But MOD Ministers have had this challenge compounded by Defence’s own broken finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both were real security risks in their own right. A country cannot be strong unless its finances are strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a Government department cannot do its job unless it manages its finances well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case that is best summarised as “It’s only by looking after the bottom line that we can really look after the front line.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that balancing the MOD’s books has been a tough and time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - we’re there. We’ve balanced the budget. We will be announcing an audited 10-year equipment programme as soon as the National Audit Office completes its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result we will be spending a lot of taxpayers’ money on equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over ten years that will be £160 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - in contrast to the unfunded aspirations of the past, this is real money - including around £4 billion of contingency on the committed programme and £8 billion of headroom to fund additional projects from our Single Integrated Priority List.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, that all gives defence companies a lot more certainty than most businesses ever have about their customer’s requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this happy state is to endure it will take a lot of discipline from all of us - and especially from the MOD - officials, front line commands and politicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The balanced budget, the Yellow Book review (something there wasn’t time to talk about today incidentally), the Materiel Strategy, Defence Transformation and the White Paper are all essential building blocks of a new more confident, sustainable, effective Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the moment of maximum pain. But it’s also the moment when the light at the end of the tunnel may actually be precisely that, and not the light of another train bearing down upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the messages of the White Paper must be understood properly both within and outside the MOD and the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must think more about defence and security as a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must think more about technology, the way it is changing and what we need to protect the State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we must nurture the growing diversity of what once saw itself as a defence industrial base but is now a complex supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the habits of a lifetime is never easy, but that is what I am inviting those of you who have not already done so to do now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have to be competitive. Growth will be hard won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will only be able to export something if it is competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we get there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We build in exportability;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We support UK companies in export campaigns;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invest in the right technologies;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We allow SMEs the space to flourish;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We protect our operational advantage and freedom of action;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We focus on building and retaining competitive advantage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collaborate more with our closest partners;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And crucially, we always remember affordability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach may be driven by austerity but just happens to be intellectually right too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective should not be to protect a defence industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should rather be to create the right incentives to grow thriving, vibrant companies that can compete globally and supply Defence in the UK with what we need, when we need it, at a price that the taxpayer can afford.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45357</id>
    <published>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-21-defence-vehicles-dynamics-dvd"/>
    <title>2012/06/21 - Defence Vehicles Dynamics (DVD)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be back here at Millbrook. Having the chance to see world class land systems being put through their paces is fascinating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this event is also a reminder that equipping and supporting our forces is a wide-ranging effort. I’m delighted to see so many companies - primes and SMEs - here from a range of sectors who contribute to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a number of contractors are also represented. Your role in facilitating and supporting operations will become ever more prominent as the Total Support Force concept is driven though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the last DVD event back in 2010 very well. I have to say it was a somewhat less soggy occasion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had just taken up my post as Minister for Defence Equipment and Support, and this was one of my first engagements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-time-of-change"&gt;A time of change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge amount has happened in the intervening two years. I’d like to highlight just three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review - the SDSR - has provided the strategic direction which was so urgently required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Defence transformation - the vital reforms needed to ensure delivery of Future Force 2020 - is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - and these are words I wondered if I would ever be able to say - we’ve balanced the Defence budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the winds of change continue to blow across every area of defence, and I know that these are uncertain times for the Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will certainly be challenges ahead, for example, devolving control of the acquisition process down to the Front Line Commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pr12---bringing-certainty"&gt;PR12 - bringing certainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the announcement of PR12 means we can all now plan for the future with a certainty that we just couldn’t before as we continued to wrestle with a huge deficit and the legacy of financial over-commitment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army in particular paid a very high price for this overheated equipment programme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and again your projects were shelved simply because they had relatively shorter lead times and it was easy to cancel, postpone or reduce them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to say that our careful planning will put an end to this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the Army will be one of the primary beneficiaries of PR12.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="funding-in-place-for-the-armoured-vehicle-programme"&gt;Funding in place for the Armoured Vehicle Programme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the books has enabled us to move forward to plan and deliver an Armoured Vehicle Programme over the next decade which will deliver a fleet of state of the art, high tech and easily deployable fighting vehicles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£5.5 billion pipeline, funding has been secured for Armoured Fighting Vehicles. This sum guarantees funding for:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An Upgrade for Warrior and the Challenger Life Extension&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new fleet of Utility vehicles to come on stream from the mid 2020s as a replacement for Bulldog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support costs for Foxhound beyond operations in Afghanistan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And, of course, the Scout programme - a new family of reconnaissance vehicles. The programme is now well into its demonstration phase and is on display here today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Scout, we will first need to reset the programme in order to remain within the pipeline profile. We will then drive hard to a Main Gate 2, at which point production numbers will be finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these fleets are now all lined up and accounted for in the Armoured Vehicle Pipeline - a highly disciplined approach which will enable us to keep firm control every step of the way when it comes to costs, numbers, performance and sequencing.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And across the board this approach exemplifies a new financial rigour which will run through the equipment programme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot, and will not, allow Defence acquisition and support to lapse back into chaos, mismanagement and fiscal incompetence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="land-open-systems-architecture"&gt;Land Open Systems Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of this Armoured Vehicle Programme will be the development of a Land Open Systems Architecture - or LOSA -  which I’m delighted to see is the central theme of this year’s conference.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open systems - and the flexibility they provide - are a central principle of the White Paper we published earlier this year.  It means that from day one modularity, interoperability and the ability to upgrade are key factors of the design process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foxhound"&gt;Foxhound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound - which, as we announced at the weekend, has already begun to arrive in Afghanistan - is a great example of this new generic architecture structure.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s extraordinarily agile, exploits state of the art technology from the UK’s world-leading motorsport industry, and has an engine which can be removed and replaced in half an hour.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And its UK designed and built - with 90% of the companies involved in its production UK based. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound’s arrival in theatre has been highly anticipated and I’m not in the least bit surprised. I  have driven it. I know just how good it is. And just how easy it is to drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress is also being made on Terrier. Initial production vehicles are undertaking acceptance trials and training at a bespoke facility has commenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Terrier is likely to be the last in a long and illustrious line of armoured vehicles built in Newcastle, where a great workforce has made a fine contribution to Defence over many a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that must be a matter for regret, I am encouraged that this contribution is now being made around the UK - in South Wales, on the South Coast, in Coventry and elsewhere, by primes, SMEs and newcomers to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uors---driving-forward-innovation"&gt;UORS - driving forward innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Land equipment has been transformed in recent years. I think its fair to say that we have learnt more in this domain than any other sector.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to thank those of you here from industry for your responsiveness on the UOR front - you really have done a magnificent job in recent years in getting essential kit our to our troops in theatre.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UOR process in particular has been a driver of innovation. Great strides have been made when it comes to high tech adaptation and integration.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs have a particular role to play in this. Companies like Formaplex which has a background in luxury cars and Formula One vehicles, and which are currently producing the Foxhound vehicle pods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re a good example of a company with no previous track record of working in defence who are bringing their expertise to a defence UOR.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are exactly the kind of projects which will help to develop and sustain our skills base here in this country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exports"&gt;Exports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will of course be challenges for the Land sector as our requirements change with our return to contingency operations after Afghanistan and the bringing of some UOR vehicles into core.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are also opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just reiterate what I said back here at DVD 2010 about our commitment to reinvigorating our agenda for responsible British defence exports. And how keen I was to ensure this was taken forward.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years on, and the more I see of our defence industries the more convinced I am by just how much they have to offer the global market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m delighted that there’s real impetus behind supporting exports.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI is energised. We have appointed Susanna Mason as MOD Director for exports. And promoting defence exports is now a central effort of our defence diplomacy drive, and the way we engage with international partners.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence industries are - and I am confident will remain -  vibrant and successful here in the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are changes ahead.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our core mission will remain - to deliver military success on operations. And to ensure that we have the ability to project power and protect our national security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of this effort is the essential requirement - that together we are meeting so well - to ensure our troops have the equipment they need, when they need it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You here today have made a very important contribution to that requirement in the past, are doing so as we speak, and will - I know - do so in the months and years ahead.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/45351</id>
    <published>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-24-qinetiq-70th-anniversary-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/05/24 - Qinetiq 70th Anniversary Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good evening &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Headmaster. [Headmaster of Malvern - Antony Clark]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a privilege to be here in the peaceful and glorious surroundings of Malvern College. In the middle of what I call God’s own country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although of course as a local Member of Parliament - like Harriet Baldwin - with the privilege of representing this county I’m aware that I say that with a certain partiality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headmaster - thank you for your hospitality this evening. And I am delighted to see that we are also joined by Malvern staff, pupils and brilliant physicists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Adam (Adam Palser - QinetiQ Group Plc) if you’re the custodian of Malvern then I suppose that I am the paymaster - so together we make a great team.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tre---the-move-to-malvern"&gt;TRE - the move to Malvern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we gather here this evening we look back 70 years ago to a very different time and place.  To the dark and terrible days of a nation -indeed a world - at War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was also a war that shaped the present day - and a lot of the changes we now take for granted. The move of aircraft manufacturers to the North West of England from London, for example, to take them  beyond the range of German bombers. Now the North-West is the centre of advanced aerospace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And May 1942 saw the Headmaster of this College, all his staff and pupils, pack their bags and de-camp to Harrow School at the express instruction of the Prime Minister himself, Winston Churchill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Malvern is a centre of scientific excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One wonders, looking back, exactly why Harrow - a London school was chosen. I wonder if the fact that Churchill himself was an old boy had something to do with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently it was quite ok to evict Malvern pupils at just one week’s notice to the risky environs of North London as long as scientists had somewhere safe to carry on their important work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if today’s Malvern parents would be quite so understanding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was of course a fact that German air attacks posed a very real threat to the essential work of the Training Research Establishment - or TRE as it was known - based on the cliffs of Worth Matravers in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Churchill was absolutely adamant that TRE - and the RAF Radar Research and Development Establishment -  be immediately relocated to Malvern. The fact that we had just raided the equivalent German facility also had a lot to do with it, as Adam (Palser) has just explained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes said that the War was won on the playing fields of Malvern. I am sure that there is a great deal of truth in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of radar is complex and like so many personal endeavours - particularly in the field of human achievement - is the cumulative work of inventors, scientists and engineers from a number of countries over many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there can be no doubt that the work on the magnetron taken forward by the men and women working at Malvern - some of the great brains of their generation, and known affectionately by the RAF as ‘the boffins’ - was ground breaking and changed the direction of the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That scientific legacy was carried forward across the generations.  And so Malvern developed that reputation as a hub of scientific endeavour which - thanks to Qinetiq - continues to this day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dera---qinetiq-and-dstl"&gt;DERA - Qinetiq and DSTL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years the research facility here at Malvern  evolved over time to become the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency. The process of invention continued along the way, and a number of vital technologies were developed. Liquid Crystal Display - how many local people know that came from here? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a number of you here this evening worked for the Agency, and that today has been a great opportunity for some happy reminiscing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency then went on to be split into two separate organisations back in 2001. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was Qinetiq. The other, the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory. Still part of MOD and more commonly known as DSTL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qinetiq is now a global brand, and your scientists and engineers help some of the world’s top manufacturers push the boundaries of technology in aviation, energy, IT and space exploration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - 70 years on you are still here in Malvern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your strong and enduring links with Defence do of course continue.  Take just one, radar, as an  example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The establishment of Radar at Malvern was in part to protect the development of the ground imaging radar called H2S. And to be clear, that’s quite different to the high speed rail link HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, airborne radar imaging is performed daily in Afghanistan using Synthetic Aperture Radar from Sentinel R1 surveillance aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The performance of that vital capability Sentinel is due to world leading focussing algorithms developed at Malvern by scientists now working for Qinetiq.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Watson-Watt - a great pioneer of radar technology - was very clear about the importance of effective collaboration between the military and the scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back many years later he said, and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that our success in radar depended fundamentally on…the intimacy and complete confidence between the operational user and the scientific and technical researcher and developer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a unique relationship which continues to this day. Today our servicemen and women look to British scientists  for this special expertise and support.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the operational tempo of recent years in Iraq, Afghanistan and Libya have seen more scientists and operational analysts on the front line than at any time since the Second World War. Defence scientists today are certainly no back room boffins. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanders look to them for expert scientific advice and rapid technical solutions to very specific threats and issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our scientists have a 24 hour reach back to colleagues  here in the UK and to our intellectual network in industry and universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure our people are well equipped and supported with the battle winning capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="innovation-and-the-uor-process"&gt;Innovation and the UOR process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was already very clear back in May 1942 was that technology was going to play a deciding role in the conflict and that electronic supremacy - what Churchill called ‘The Wizard War’ - would be a deciding factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in today’s fast moving operational environment the imperative to be able to exploit new and emerging technologies is just as pressing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is precisely what we did when it came to developing Foxhound - the next generation of light protected patrol vehicle for our forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re looking for the ability to remove and replace an engine in  just 30 minutes, and for that vehicle to be able to drive away from an ambush on only three wheels necessary - then you go to the very best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why Foxhound was devised by engineers from, among other areas,  the World Rally Championship, McLaren F1 and BMW and incorporates Formula One racing technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="technology-at-heart-of-defence"&gt;Technology at heart of Defence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology has an absolutely fundamental role in providing Defence and security to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="help-for-heroes"&gt;Help for Heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Defence is really about people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ‘well done’ to that hardy bunch from Qinetiq who have just recreated the journey taken by all those scientists from Worth Matravers in Dorset here to Malvern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That journey today was on two wheels in aid of Help for Heroes -well done on the £3,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of Help For Heroes is clear evidence of the tremendous respect and affection of the British people have for  our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="my-role-as-minister-for-defence-equipment-support-and-technology"&gt;My role as Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology it’s my job - my duty - to ensure that these courageous and committed men and women have what they need to do their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best battle winning capability and the best support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a mission the importance of which I am reminded whenever I meet our Armed Forces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visit Afghanistan and meet the amazing men and women who work on the MERT - or Medical Emergency Response Teams. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And have the opportunity to see for myself at first hand the ground breaking technologies saving lives today on today’s front line. Technologies which owe so much to British scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I go to see our equipment in action and talk to the service personnel who use it - and whose lives depend on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days our forces are giving an unequivocal ‘thumbs up’ to the excellent range of kit and equipment now at their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Patrick Sanders, for example, who last year commanded 20th Armoured Brigade in Afghanistan has described the equipment his troops had - and I quote: “second to none” and “the best that I’ve experienced in 27 years.” And a lot of that is down to science. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="courage-and-sacrifice-of-our-service-personnel"&gt;Courage and sacrifice of our service personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course I’m also reminded of the importance of what we all do to support our Armed Forces when I meet our serving personnel back here at home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I was talking to personnel from the Navy and RAF who took part in last year’s Libya campaign, and were attending a reception at the House of Commons held in their honour to celebrate their courage and heroism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a junior rating who talked about what it was like to be working in the Ops Room of HMS Liverpool when it came under missile attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the deck hands of HMS Ocean who got the Apache helicopters off and safely home. They spoke of black helicopters on a black night on a black sea.  Not an easy job with whirling blades, weapons loaded and adrenalin pumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also spoke to the Typhoon and Tornado pilots who flew 16 hour missions,  and struck again and again with such deadly precision against the Qadhafi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own county regiment - The 2nd Mercians, who I still think of by the way as the Worcestershire and Sherwood Foresters -   have of course served with tremendous valour in recent times. Some have tragically lost their lives, and some have been very seriously injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RSM of the Second Mercians said something very perceptive about the young men and women he recently commanded in Helmand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you here may have seen an article last month in the Worcester News in which RSM Martyn Chatterley described them as “absolutely exceptional”, and wrote the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“People talk about the ‘Play Station’ generation, and how the youth of today are not up to anything , but this is just not the case.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of soldiering, Afghanistan brings together everything you are trained for and learn - every single aspect of what makes the modern professional soldier.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these guys have proven they have what it takes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbling words. And a reminder that today’s Armed Forces are just as brave, and just as resourceful, as those sailors, soldiers and airmen of 1942.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A readiness to explore new boundaries and exploit technology was critical then - and is just as critical today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I note that the Malvern College motto is: ‘Sapiens Qui Prospicit’ or ‘Wise is the person who looks ahead’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually - perhaps we should adopt it as a motto for the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do hope, Headmaster, that you heed this clarion call - I know this is a school with an excellent reputation for promoting and recognising scientific achievement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you and your teaching staff encourage pupils to look ahead, to realise their potential  and pursue careers in these fields. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This country needs our scientists and engineers. And a lot more of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry is crying out for them. Our national security demands them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, as I look ahead, I can say with absolute confidence that this country’s independence - and our contribution to a better and safer world - will continue to depend on our scientific wizards. Many of whom are here with us tonight.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wizards of the present, and I hope, of the future too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, Qinetiq, on your first 70 years at Malvern. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your work is carrying forward the legacy of those early pioneers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprising men and women who worked so tirelessly to push forward the boundaries of scientific endeavour. And to whom we owe so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/18706</id>
    <published>2011-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-03-15-rusi-cranfield-university-acquisition-reform-conference"/>
    <title>2011/03/15 - RUSI/Cranfield University Acquisition Reform Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to add my own appreciation to that of others, and say that it is a great privilege and a pleasure to work with you on the vital task of acquisition reform.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You approach this difficult issue with insight, courtesy and determination: a great combination when change is needed. Your support for the MoD, for DE&amp;amp;S, for our industry, and in support of our exports has been remarked on by many, and is admired by all.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I last spoke at a Shrivenham acquisition conference almost two years ago, when my report had yet to be published. Then, I shared with the audience some of my key conclusions. I am sad to say that these conclusions were subsequently leaked to the media.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was sad that the information itself was leaked, but mostly I was sad that the poor quality PowerPoint slides that someone had made to try to explain my conclusions to others were passed off to the BBC as being my work. I’d never be seen dead producing that kind of low quality graphics.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whether in tawdry black and white or glorious Technicolour, the conclusions of that report are now, of course, a matter of record. In some senses, it is a matter of history.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That “bow wave” of impending costs that I demonstrated was about to descend on the MoD has now crashed down upon us. And it has done so at precisely at the worst possible time, when the government has to retrench more generally, when money is so tight.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the impact of this perfect storm is all too clear. Key capabilities have had to be cut, important programmes cancelled. Many good and capable crown servants are in the process of being laid off. It is a grim picture for all of us who care about the robust health of the UK’s Armed Forces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No part of this reduction is welcome, and indeed the Government has made clear its distaste of the action it has had to take to balance the budget. But the worst example of what has had to happen is in my mind the fate of the Nimrod MRA4 programme.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not because I have a particular view about the importance or otherwise of this capability, I leave that well-worn fight to others. It is because the MoD will have spent £4bn on this capability over the past 15 years and ended up with, nothing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the worst indictment of the defence programme I can imagine. Just think of what capabilities we could have had for that money: imagine the number of aspects of defence that could have been improved. Or perhaps, don’t. To do so may be too disheartening.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the programme had to be abandoned, I have no doubt. The MoD simply could not afford to carry on with that capability, alongside all of the other priorities in the defence budget, and with the limited cash available.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I am not cross because the programme was stopped. My ire is raised because the situation that gave rise to the expenditure of £4bn on a programme we could not afford was predictable. This disaster could have been avoided if action had been taken earlier.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the exemplar par excellence of what happens if the department lives beyond its means. Put simply, if you start more things than you can afford to finish, then sooner or later you are going to waste money by having to cancel some of those projects.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is worse, you will probably waste money on all of your projects along the way because you will slow everything down in a brave attempt to stave off the inevitable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My report made a number of points, some say too many. The MoD helpfully, and accurately I think, boiled this down into two key principles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the MoD must balance its budget over the short, and even more importantly, the long term. We are in a long-term business, and we must plan for the long term. We have to be realistic and clear-eyed about what our programme will cost, and we have to balance what we are planning to buy against the cash we are likely to have.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we must make sure that DE&amp;amp;S is well set up to acquire and support the equipment within the plan. We have to be able to deliver.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two tasks are, I believe, the principle focus that Min(DEST) and I will have in driving forward acquisition reform in the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how is the MoD doing so far? Well, I am pleased to say that the department has made considerable progress on both fronts since I gathered the data for my report two years ago.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the programme is more realistically costed now than it was then, and painful actions were taken in the SDSR to address the bow wave in the programme. This process is not yet complete, as both the Secretary of State and Min(DEST) have made clear on a number of occasions, but a decisive start has been made.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parenthesis at this point, I should like to say that I personally have little or no time for those who have criticised the SDSR for making cuts in the defence programme. I believe that ministers and officials have been brave in tackling the problem left to them, and that they have shouldered their responsibilities admirably in acting as they have.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When confronting the financial picture faced by the MoD, the new government faced three choices: to find more money, almost impossible with a budget deficit in excess of 10 per cent of national income; to pretend, and so to visit further “Nimrods” on a badly-served MoD; or to act courageously to take on the issue.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad to say that the government chose this last course. It is, and was, the only responsible way. Unfortunately, as ministers have made clear, we are not yet at the end of this difficult and undesirable process. The current budget round, and probably the next few, are going to be extremely difficult for the MoD, as it seeks to get its budget fully back under control. It is not quite “blood, sweat, tears and toil,” but it is certainly going to be “hard pounding gentlemen”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this regard, the task of defence reform, and indeed the test of its success, must be to see whether the defence budget cannot just be balanced, but that institutional mechanisms must be put in place to ensure that it remains balanced into the future. As I know only too well, it is one thing to take weight off, it is quite another thing to keep it off.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My report recommended a number of actions which I felt would achieve this effect: from placing responsibilities on the Permanent Secretary, through to an Executive Committee of the board, to 10 year fixed MoD budgets and mandatory quinquennial defence reviews.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is with some disappointment that I have to observe that many of these measures have not been enacted. And while this is an art, not a science, and there may be many ways to resolve these problems, I do not abandon my views of the way forward until I meet a better model.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genuinely balancing this programme, and keeping it balanced so that the organisation has a fighting chance to deliver what is asked of it, must be the overriding test of this aspect of defence reform. I look forward with eager anticipation to what Lord Levene will bring forward. But if the team struggles for a model, I can always point them at my report….  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balanced and well-costed programme has to be the cornerstone of success for the MoD. I make no apology for repeating the point, because without achieving this outcome, little else is possible.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can try to improve skills and processes within DE&amp;amp;S as much as we like, we can splint and tourniquet the system as much as we wish, but in the end, cost growth and time delays will burst out like damp through a repainted wall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us assume, therefore, that this difficult work of bringing the defence budget into balance has been achieved fully. No mean feat, as I have said, but let us make it so, at least in our mind’s eye. What then? What next? What more do we need to do to improve the performance of the MoD?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I move on to the second point in the department’s summary of my report. We have to equip Defence Equipment and Support to enable it to be able to deliver.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this arena, as in others, I made recommendations for change. Much attention was focused on the Go-Co proposal, which I am pleased to say, gathered almost universal approval, falling just short of any actual support.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are reasons I made this recommendation, which we could discuss if you wish. Even though it seems to me extremely unlikely that this idea will be pursued, given the lack of support it received, there is, nonetheless, a need to realise the objectives it sought to achieve.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the point in my report that key disciplines have been downgraded over recent years in the name of saving money, and that the erosions of these functional skills harms the ability of DE&amp;amp;S to deliver. Most saliently, and ironically, our cost-estimating teams have been run down over the past decade, removing our ability to complete that most crucial of tasks, estimating the size of programme we can afford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also observed how finance, engineering and project management skills had not had the prominence they deserve.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, as with the point about the size of the programme, I am pleased to be able to report back that good progress has been made in the course of the last two years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cost Assurance and Analysis Service within DE&amp;amp;S is in the process of being rebuilt and reskilled, to allow us to cost our projects fully. It is absolutely vital that these people have the freedom to advocate their “should cost” views without fear or favour. I intend to back this effort to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment has also been made in the finance function of DE&amp;amp;S, to bring greater financial modeling skill into the organisation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to build on this success. I will give greater prominence and control to the Finance, Commercial, Engineering and Project Management functions. I intend to build skills in risk management and project control.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line management of individual projects will remain strong, but the functional skills that are needed to actually deliver the outcomes need to be built up if we are to succeed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right that an orchestra needs a conductor, but it also needs the disciplines of strings, woodwind, brass and percussion if the symphony is to be played. And each of those disciplines needs leadership, skill and development if it is to shine.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is in hand to look at this and other issues within DE&amp;amp;S. Over the next few months a team under the leadership of General Chris Deverell will be re-evaluating all aspects of DE&amp;amp;S’s work. This is part of a commitment I made to the workforce when I first arrived, that I would work with them and seek their views about the way forward, before making major changes within DE&amp;amp;S.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also asked the team to look at the relationships between DE&amp;amp;S and MoD Centre, the Front Line Commands, and Industry. I have invited them to look at other large scale procurement and support organisations. I will be encouraging them to explore the skills and secrets of other project management organisations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, this will be to re-walk a path I trod in my own studies of two years ago. But again, I make no apology for this. In part, because this team may discover many things I missed. In part, because even if they do not, it is only right that the staff of DE&amp;amp;S have the opportunity to explore the ground I have covered, and come to their own views about the best way forward.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way there will be a synthesis of the independence that outside views bring, along with the expertise that in-house experience offers. I know that everyone is working diligently and co-operatively towards the best possible outcome for the organisation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two main thrusts, therefore in acquisition reform. A deep commitment and drive to balance the budget, and to find ways to keep it balanced, and a thorough and collaborative approach to bringing best practice into DE&amp;amp;S so that it can confound its critics and be justifiably proud of what it delivers to our Armed Forces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I close, let me touch on two other issues. First, the proposed reduction in numbers within the Ministry of Defence as a whole, and DE&amp;amp;S in particular. This will certainly make it harder to deliver a better output, not least because some of our brightest and best may be tempted by severance packages and a career in the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will have to strive to avoid losing our talented people in these difficult days. And it may be that this whole process forces us to a fundamental re-evaluation of those services the organisation provides.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I would also say this: less does not always mean worse. Sometimes involving too many people complicates decision making and slows down progress. Placing power and responsibility in fewer hands can be motivating and liberating, if we have the confidence to do it. Ironically, we might actually be able to deliver more satisfying and productive careers to those who stay with us, than we have been able to in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a linked point: a great deal has been made by the Defence Reform Unit about accountability. I’m fine with that. Indeed, sometimes people accuse me of taking responsibility for things that are not mine to run!   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet to be properly accountable, one also needs the power to act. Too often in government we seek to find someone to blame, only to find out that so many people had a finger in the pie that it is impossible to hold anyone to account.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a real desire to change this, then I think this would be for the good. But I would urge those involved to understand the full implication of their statements. Accountability has to be matched with decision-making power or it is nothing more than show.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But accountability with power is a fantastically energising force. It could transform the way that business is done within the whole of government, not just the MoD. If it came to pass, it would make the lives of those given the power to act far more rewarding. Making such a profound cultural shift within government will take huge effort and courage. If it were done, though, it would unleash great spirits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this will be hard work, but success would be so self-evidently worthwhile that it has to be worth all of the striving. There is real excitement beyond the difficulties of today, much to look forward to. We have much to be proud of already. Let us make the future something to shout about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
