<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T14:49:59+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/6620</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:49:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:49:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"/>
    <title>National Measurement Office</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) - previously known as the National Weights and Measures Laboratory (NWML) - regulates the development and use of weighing and measuring equipment to ensure that weights and measures are accurate, fair and legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain and enforce weights and measures regulations, the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with local authorities’ trading standards departments and inspectors, local weights and measures authorities and approved verifiers of weights and measures equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s consulting services help small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) to develop specific measuring products, processes or services. It also helps SMEs to understand the regulations covering their weighing and measuring instruments and how to comply with the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; still provides services under the name of NWML including product certification, quality management systems certification and calibration services to several sectors of industry and local government, all or most of which have some element of weighing or measuring either in their manufacturing processes or in their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with WELMEC (the European co-operation in legal metrology) and OIML (the International Organisation of Legal Metrology) to maintain UK consumer and business confidence in legal measurement abroad. It also takes part in preparing OIML recommendations and represents the UK at the OIML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide also outlines the work of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority, the part of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; responsible for enforcement work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-work-of-the-national-measurement-office"&gt;The work of the National Measurement Office&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) - previously known as the National Weights and Measures Laboratory (NWML) - is an executive agency of the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is responsible for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;policy on measuring instruments that are used in trade - eg preparing legislation under the Weights and Measures Act 1985 and European Communities Act 1972, and proposals for reforming Weights and Measures Act&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that the UK implements European directives on measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legal metrology - ie requirements for legal verification of measuring instruments - in the UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal metrology makes it possible to buy and sell accurate quantities of goods. Without accurate measurements, there would be no possibility of a fair marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; helps ensure the accuracy of the majority of measuring instruments used for trade and pre-packaged goods in the UK - including pre-packaged goods in supermarkets, check-out scales, petrol pumps and beer glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; provides guidance to industry and the public, and enforces UK and European Union weights and measures legislation. Key regulations include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Weights and Measures Act 1985 and secondary legislation, including the Weights and Measures (Packaged Goods) Regulations 2006&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Deregulation (Weights and Measures) Order 1999&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Measuring Instruments Directive 2004/22/EC and the Non-Automatic Weighing Instruments Regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;, the National Measurement System (NMS) unit is responsible for scientific and industrial metrology. Scientific metrology deals with the organisation, development and maintenance of measurement standards. Industrial metrology ensures the adequate functioning of measurement instruments used in industry, production and testing processes. The NMS carries out its tasks in a UK network of measurement laboratories, which include the National Physical Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=484"&gt;Read information on the National Measurement system on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nwml-services"&gt;NWML Services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NWML Calibration Team, approved under the UK Accreditation Service maintains standards for mass, volume and length measurement. In addition to calibration, NWML provides testing, product and QMS certification services for industry and local authorities - eg local authority Trading Standards. For more information, see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;product certification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also provides a consultancy service to manufacturers that are developing new weighing and measuring equipment. For more information, you can also see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;consultancy and consulting services&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses should be aware that NWML Certification Services is changing its name to &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services as of 1 April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Access the industry service forms offered from the NWML&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nmo-enforcement-authority"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the role of the National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) has expanded to include the enforcement of regulations aimed at protecting the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority, part of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;, is responsible for enforcing environmental legislation under the Restriction of the Use of Certain Hazardous Substances in Electrical and Electronic Equipment Regulations 2008 (RoHS Regulations) which limits the levels of certain potentially hazardous substances in new electric and electronic equipment for sale in the European Union (EU). &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/rohs-home"&gt;Find out about RoHS on the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority also acts as the UK Batteries Regulations enforcement body, to ensure compliance with the Batteries and Accumulators (Placing on the Market) Regulations 2008. This limits the levels of cadmium and mercury in new batteries for sale within the EU, controls the marking of batteries and sets design requirements for battery-operated electrical and electronic equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/batteries-home"&gt;Find out about the Batteries Regulations on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also the Market Surveillance Authority (MSA), under the EU Energy Using Products (EuP) and Energy Labelling Framework (ELF) Directives. This means the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; ensures that manufactures meet their product claims under energy labelling - eg A-rated fridges - and minimum energy standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/ecodesign"&gt;Find out about EuP on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/elf-home"&gt;Find out about ELF on the Energy Labelling website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-enforcement-partners"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; enforcement partners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with various other public and private sector organisations that help to enforce weights and measures regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the local level, the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with the Local Government Regulation (formerly the Local Authorities Coordinators of Regulatory Services), the local government central body responsible for overseeing local authority regulatory and related services in the UK, the Trading Standards Institute and regional groups of local authorities’trading standards departments and inspectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notified bodies are local weights and measurements authorities (LWMA) that assess whether weighing and measuring equipment meets CE marking requirements. CE marking is a manufacturer’s declaration that the product complies with the standards set out in relevant European directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Find a local notified body to evaluate your weighing/measuring equipment with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approved verifiers have permission from the Secretary of State to test, pass, stamp and verify weighing and measuring equipment that they manufacture, install or repair. Approval may be for non-automatic weighing instruments or for measuring instruments that come under the EU Measuring Instruments Directive. A condition of approval is that the verifier operates an acceptable quality system and receives regular audits and inspections from both the LWMA and the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Apply to become an approved verifer with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legal-and-regulatory-activities"&gt;Legal and regulatory activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) works with trading standards departments in local authorities to deliver enforcement of most of the UK’s weights and measures legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weights and measurements regulations help ensure consumers have accurate information about their purchases. This protects them from being sold short measures. The regulations also protect businesses against dishonest competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-enforcement/guidance-and-reference-documents/legislation-guidance-notes"&gt;find weights and measures legislation guidance notes on the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Search for legislation on weights, measures and hallmarking which may affect your business with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hallmarking"&gt;Hallmarking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is responsible for the sponsorship of the British Hallmarking Council. This involves the testing and marking of items of precious metal to indicate they conform to legal standards of purity (fineness), across four assay offices in the UK (London, Birmingham, Sheffield and Edinburgh).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="water-gas-and-electricity-metering"&gt;Water, gas and electricity metering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; also regulates the metrology of water, gas and electricity meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="better-regulation"&gt;Better regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; complies with Statutory Code of Practice for Regulators (the Regulators’ Compliance Code). This requires regulators to plan regulation and inspections in a way that causes the least disruption to businesses, to impose sanctions and penalties in a transparent and proportionate way and to report annually on their enforcement activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file45019.pdf"&gt;download Regulators’ Compliance Code from the BIS website (PDF, 107K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultancy-and-consulting-services"&gt;Consultancy and consulting services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) offers individually tailored consultancies for UK and international organisations, providing a range of highly skilled engineers and a network of specialist collaborators covering the whole range of legal metrology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It carries out consultations on weights and measures policy and regulatory issues. It has signed up to the government’s Code of Practice on Consultation. This outlines best practice in running public consultation exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file47158.pdf"&gt;download the Code of Practice on Consultation from the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website (PDF, 223K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=366%20"&gt;find out about previous consultancy projects on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="measurement-for-innovators-scheme"&gt;Measurement for Innovators scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Measurement for Innovators (MfI) scheme is a BIS programme helping small and medium-sized enterprises to develop and improve new weighing and measuring products, processes and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=495"&gt;Find MfI information on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="product-certification"&gt;Product certification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;), &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services provides product certification services to businesses and public sector organisations in the UK and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services is a notified body under European directives relating to Non-Automatic Weighing Instruments (NAWI) 2009/23/EC and Measuring Instruments (MID) 2004/22/EC. As a notified body, it can issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Commission (EC) Type Approval Certificates (TACs) for weighing and measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a range of the International Organisation of Legal Metrology (OIML) certificates of conformity - which bring instrument approval in many countries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK National Approvals - under section 12 of the Weights &amp;amp; Measures Act 1985&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s product certificates cover a wide range of weighing and measuring equipment. If you are unsure whether your product will pass the certification process, you can submit your instruments to &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s pre-assessment service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;apply for pre-assessment with the online industry service forms from the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out about notified bodies, see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;legal and regulatory activities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nawis"&gt;NAWIs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can issue European TACs for all electronic and most mechanical NAWIs. These are valid throughout Europe. If you want to sell your NAWI outside Europe, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can approve it in accordance with the relevant OIML recommendations. In this case, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; issues an OIML Certificate of Conformity and test report. These are valid in countries which are signed up to the OIML mutual acceptance arrangements (MAAs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to submit your NAWI for &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; certification processes, you will need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fill in an application form - which you can do online&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;forward your supporting documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;send in your equipment for testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To simplify the process, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can test separate modules of a NAWI and issue individual Test Certificates (TCs). You can quote these TCs in a TAC. This modular approach is useful for indicators, load cells and point of sale devices, and peripheral devices, such as computers and printers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;apply for product certification with the online industry service forms from the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring instruments covered by MID include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automatic weighing instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fuel dispensers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;material measures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;water meters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a period of 10 years from 30 October 2006, existing European Economic Community and UK National TACs will remain valid for instruments that now come under the MID Directive. You can contact the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; to find out how to convert an existing TAC to an MID approval, as well as applying for approval for a new instrument under MID. However, you should note that the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is not a notified body for gas and electricity meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="temperature-and-humidity-testing-equipment"&gt;Temperature and humidity testing equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can test and certify temperature testing equipment from 55°C to -25°C, and humidity testing equipment up to 95 per cent relative humidity. You can access the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s environmental test chambers for research or pre-compliance testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="uk-national-type-approvals"&gt;UK National Type approvals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All measuring instruments that are used for trade purposes in the UK require a UK National Type Approval certificate. These include measuring instruments for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intoxicating liquor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dynamic axle weighers - automatic vehicle weighbridges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cubic measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can apply to the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; for product certification or for pre-assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-enquiry-line"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enquiry Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7272&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lacors-helpline"&gt;LACORS Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 7665 3888&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-direct"&gt;Consumer Direct&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;08454 040 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-measurement-office-enquiry-service"&gt;National Measurement Office Enquiry Service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7227&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-certification-services-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7282&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="npl-helpline"&gt;NPL Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 6880&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-cubic-measures-type-approval-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Cubic Measures Type Approval Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7294&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://resource.npl.co.uk/international_office/metrologyinshort.pdf"&gt;Download legal metrology introductory guidance from the National Physical Laboratory website (PDF, 1.52MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=231"&gt;Services to industry information on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rohs.gov.uk/content.aspx?id=9"&gt;RoHS Regulations, Directives and Guidance and other useful links on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/batteries-home"&gt;Batteries regulations guidance on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/ecodesign"&gt;Eco-design of EuPs guidance on the BIS website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oiml.org/"&gt;OIML contact details on the OIML website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.welmec.org/pubs.asp"&gt;Legal metrology guides on the WELMEC website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file45019.pdf"&gt;Download Regulators’ Compliance Code from the BIS website (PDF, 107K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-enforcement/guidance-and-reference-documents/legislation-guidance-notes"&gt;Weights and measures legislation guidance notes on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/packaged-goods"&gt;Weights and Measures (Packaged Goods) Regulations 2006 guidance on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/bispartners/nmo/docs/legislation/legislation/pc-guidance-note-version-3-2009.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the UK’s implementation of a European directive deregulating specified quantities (fixed pack sizes) from the BIS website (PDF, 122K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/metrication"&gt;Guidance on the business use of Metric Units of Measurement and the EC Units of Measurement Directive on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/equipment-regulation"&gt;Equipment regulated under the Weights and Measures Act explained on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Search our business support finder for grants, loans, expertise and advice for which your business may be eligible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/certification-services/product-certification/certificates-database"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; MID certificates database on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/bispartners/nmo/docs/services/type-approval/guidance-notes-for-type-examination--consultancy-2.pdf"&gt;Download product certification (type approval) and pre-assessment guidance and requirements from the BIS website (PDF, 95K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61122</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-commenting-on-the-latest-ucas-2013-cycle-applicant-figures"/>
    <title>Press Release: Commenting on the latest UCAS 2013 cycle applicant figures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Department for Business, Innovation and Skills spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is too early to form a definitive picture about university applications for the 2013/14 academic year. Traditionally fewer than 50 per cent of applicants have submitted their applications by this point in the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that no one is put off applying to university because they do not have information about the student support available to them. Most new students will not pay upfront, there will be more financial support for those from poorer families and everyone will make lower loan repayments than they do now once they are in well paid jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/61088</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge: Retail and Manufacturing Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The purpose of this consultation was to seek views on the amendment and removal of statutory instruments which were identified under the Retail and Manufacturing Red Tape Challenge spotlight process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s response to the consultation was published on the 16th July. This confirms the proposals we intend to take forward which include the revocation of the following measures on the 1st October 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imitation Dummies (Safety) Regulations 1993 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas cooking Appliances (Safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating Appliances (Fireguards) (Safety) Regulations 1991 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Catalytic Heaters (safety) Regulations 1984 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All-Terrain Motor Vehicle (safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking Utensils (Safety) Regulations 1972 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indication of Prices (Beds) Order 1978 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child Resistant Packaging and Tactile Danger Warning (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1992 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands for Carry-cots (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1996 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magnetic Toys (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second Government response was published on the 30th November. This confirms the amendment and revocation of the following regulations on the 6 April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/61141</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:42:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:42:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/building-materials-and-components-statistics-october-2012"/>
    <title>Building materials and components statistics: October 2012</title>
    <category>Statistical data set</category>
    <summary>Statistics and analysis on the construction sector</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This edition, published on 7 November 2012, presents information on selected building materials, including monthly data on price indices, bricks, cement and concrete blocks. It also presents quarterly data on sand and gravel, slate, concrete roofing tiles, ready-mixed concrete and imports and exports of construction products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62547"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43589/12-313j-construction-building-materials-bulletin-october-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43589/thumbnail_12-313j-construction-building-materials-bulletin-october-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43589/12-313j-construction-building-materials-bulletin-october-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/12/313J&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;494 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;40 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62548"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43592/12-313j-data-construction-building-materials-tables-october-2012.xls" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43592/12-313j-data-construction-building-materials-tables-october-2012.xls"&gt;Building materials and components: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/12/313J&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;722 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62549"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43595/12-p125j-construction-building-materials-commentary-october-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43595/thumbnail_12-p125j-construction-building-materials-commentary-october-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43595/12-p125j-construction-building-materials-commentary-october-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components commentary: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;12/P125J&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;113 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60955</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:30:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-choices-better-deals"/>
    <title>Better choices, better deals</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A radical new approach to give more power to consumers in their relationships with business.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumer Minister Edward Davey has announced today new plans on how businesses will provide key information to their customers on how they use and buy goods and services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help people get the best deal possible, and make business more dynamic in response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new approach is published in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/better-choices-better-deals-strategy-helping-consumers-make-better-choices"&gt;Better Choices, Better Deals: Consumers Powering Growth&lt;/a&gt; and marks a shift away from legislating to make change happen. Instead it announces new ways to help consumers help themselves and challenges business to innovate, which in turn will drive growth in the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="midata"&gt;Midata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the initiative published today will be a project called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"&gt;midata&lt;/a&gt;, which will assess how to give people their personal data in a format that is safe to pass onto third parties, such as price comparison sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an application or website can pick out the one perfect deal based on your user information, this will help to make consumer choices simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Davey said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an important new initiative that will radically change how consumers relate to business. By giving you more power in your relationship with businesses you will be better placed to get the deal you want, and that deal may put a bit of money back in your pocket.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will in turn reward the most competitive and innovative businesses.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-people-are-saying-about-better-choices-better-deals"&gt;What people are saying about ‘Better Choices: Better Deals’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Professor Nigel Shadbolt, Chair of Midata: **   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Information about how we shop, travel, communicate and live our lives is a powerful source of insight, so it’s important that each of us should be able to access our own data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am very much looking forward to chairing the mydata group, which aims to make accessing this data much simpler, and should be a watershed on how we use data to get a better deal every day.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Gillian Guy, Citizens Advice Chief Executive: **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Citizens Advice is an active champion for consumers. We help people get a better deal and make it simpler and easier to get information and advice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are thrilled to be part of this new consumer empowerment strategy alongside Citizens Advice Scotland and Consumer Focus.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In particular we are really pleased to see recognition that in new technology is not good news for everyone. Some vulnerable groups can be excluded from best value deals and methods of redress.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our experience helping over 2 million clients a year shows that consumers have many varied needs. We look forward to helping ensure that provision for consumers really is inclusive and services and products are equally available to all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christine Farnish, Chair of Consumer Focus, said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘It’s good news that government is looking at how more powerful consumers can create more effective markets and public services. While there are companies who want to provide better value and service, the truth is that if you don’t have demanding consumers, then you won’t have responsive markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A challenge for the government strategy is how it removes the barriers and opens the field for consumers to take action. This also needs to go hand in hand with making the most effective use of regulation and tackling the wider problems exhibited by consumer markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since its creation Consumer Focus has campaigned for better customer information and complaints handling. Increasingly we have been pushing new ways to unlock the ability of consumers to band together and either discipline poor companies or reward good ones. The opportunity for coordinated consumer action through online and social media is growing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The success of this approach will depend on whether it really helps consumers to mobilise their market power by coming together and showing companies the benefits of providing the value and customer service that people want.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Richard Thaler, co-author of Nudge: Improving Decisions About Health, Wealth, and Happiness: &lt;br&gt;
** &lt;br&gt;
“This is a very exciting initiative that shows how modern technology can create entirely new ways of thinking about the government’s role in business regulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is of course true that we cannot replace all laws and regulations with nudges. However, this approach will give honest, high quality firms an edge in their battle with competitors who use obfuscation as their chief marketing strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Simple electronic disclosure is not costly for large firms to provide, and can provide enormous benefits to consumers. Eventually, this approach has the potential for replacing much more intrusive and burdensome regulations that firms inevitably find ways to evade.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Mayo, Secretary General of Co-operatives UK:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the growing interest in collective purchasing, from both government and from consumers. We are pleased to be working with BIS to launch the Innovation Prize. The best way to empower consumers is to enable them to come together co-operatively.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chris Wermann, Director of Corporate Affairs - Home Retail Group, Argos:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Argos always puts the customer first. Being at the forefront of multi-channel retailing in the UK we believe any successful retailer will need to evolve their product range, services and accessibility to ensure the customers get the best choice and value most suited to their needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government’s consumer empowerment programme is a great way to enable this to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Chan, CEO, Barclaycard Consumer Europe:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Barclaycard believes that digital technology - through simple online tools such as mybarclaycard, its award winning online servicing site which enables customers to analyse their spending, has the potential to really empower consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just imagine if people could easily access and review all their financial transaction data from all their banks, in one place, using simple web-based tools. We believe that could make a real difference to people, and that’s why we support mydata.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419163&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"&gt;Consumer issues at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/better-choices-better-deals-report-on-progress-on-the-consumer-empowerment-strategy"&gt;Better choices: better deals. Report on progress on the consumer empowerment strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/61135</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:29:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:29:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/building-materials-and-components-statistics-november-2012"/>
    <title>Building materials and components statistics: November 2012</title>
    <category>Statistical data set</category>
    <summary>Statistics and analysis on the construction sector</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This edition, published on 5 December 2012, presents information on selected building materials, including monthly data on price indices, bricks, cement and concrete blocks. It also presents quarterly data on sand and gravel, slate, concrete roofing tiles, ready-mixed concrete and imports and exports of construction products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62532"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43602/12-313k-construction-building-materials-bulletin-november-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43602/thumbnail_12-313k-construction-building-materials-bulletin-november-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43602/12-313k-construction-building-materials-bulletin-november-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components: November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/12/313K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;475 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;40 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62533"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43603/12-313k-data-construction-building-materials-tables-november-2012.xls" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43603/12-313k-data-construction-building-materials-tables-november-2012.xls"&gt;Building materials and components: November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/12/313K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;704 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_62534"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43610/12-p125k-construction-building-materials-commentary-november-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43610/thumbnail_12-p125k-construction-building-materials-commentary-november-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43610/12-p125k-construction-building-materials-commentary-november-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components commentary: November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/12/P125J&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;102 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61079</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/30-million-boost-as-start-up-loans-for-young-entrepreneurs-expanded"/>
    <title>£30 million boost as Start-Up Loans for young entrepreneurs expanded</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Thousands more young people have the opportunity to apply for government loans to turn their business ideas into reality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has today announced a boost to the government’s Start-Up loans scheme, with funding being increased by £30 million to £110 million over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also said that due to demand from those who had just missed out on the scheme, and the challenges faced to secure loans to start a business, the age limit for applying will now be extended from 24 to 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-Up Loans provide budding entrepreneurs a range of support to get their business idea off the ground, including access to a business mentor as well as funding in the region of £2,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 3000 people have applied or registered an interest in a Start-Up loan; when their business plan is robust and approved, applicants are able to access the financial support, with a repayment period of up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that the scheme has been live over £1.5 million worth of loans have been approved, helping over 460 new businesses get off the ground. Around 100 new businesses a week are expected to reach approval stage in January, with thousands more in the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Start-Up Loans scheme forms an integral part of the Business in You campaign, which encourages the start up and growth of new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startuploans.co.uk/"&gt;Visit the Start-Up Loans Company for more information and details on how to apply.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business"&gt;Tools and guidance for businesses on Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/start-up-loans-scheme-expanded/"&gt;Read the full story on the Number 10 website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61065</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:56:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:56:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-innovation-workshop"/>
    <title>Support for Innovation Workshop</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A series of one day workshops about government support for business R&amp;D and innovation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A series of one day workshops about government support for business &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; and innovation are being organised over the next few months for small and medium sized enterprises and their professional advisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas covered include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the world-class level of &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credit relief to invest more in your &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;planning for the reduced (10%) rate of corporation tax on profits attributable to patents  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; grants available  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;networking with your peers in &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising government procurement opportunities for your &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maximising the value of intellectual property for competitive advantage  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using design to add value and help your business grow &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each session will be led by a representative from the relevant delivery body, and will allow ample time for Q&amp;amp;As. The day is supported by manned stands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government hopes that one of the outcomes of the workshops will be to increase take-up of &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credits by companies in sectors in which claims are low such as agri-food and also the energy and water industries. The government would also like to increase awareness that &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credit claims can be made for design work where this involves &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops are organized by the Department for Business Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) and HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (&lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dates-and-venues"&gt;Dates and venues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details, including a link to the booking site, are below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please Note: A light lunch will be provided. If you have any food allergies that you would like us to be aware of please forward this information separately to &lt;a href="mailto:andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disabled access: if you have any special requirements please forward this information separately to &lt;a href="mailto:andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="midlands"&gt;MIDLANDS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January 16, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birmingham Science Park Aston Ltd, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FW 8a, Faraday Wharf, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holt Street Birmingham, B7 4BB &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://bsp-a.com/contact/"&gt;View map and Directions&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: basement car park, charges ₤5/car 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=birmingham&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;submit=Search+Events"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="north-east"&gt;NORTH EAST&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January 30 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle                                                &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bewick Hall &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle City Library &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;33 New Bridge St West &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle upon Tyne, NE1 8AX &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetmap.co.uk/map.srf?x=425037&amp;amp;y=564547&amp;amp;z=0&amp;amp;sv=NE18AX&amp;amp;st=2&amp;amp;pc=NE1+8AX&amp;amp;mapp=map.srf&amp;amp;searchp=ids.srf"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt;: located in central Newcastle close to metro, national rail and bus links.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking: there are around 10,000 parking places within five minutes walk. 
Note: this workshop is presented as part of the Newcastle Business and IP Centre programme of activities. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Newcastle+Upon+Tyne&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;date_from=30%2F01%2F2013&amp;amp;date_to=30%2F01%2F2013&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;ds_business_stage=&amp;amp;price_min=&amp;amp;price_max=&amp;amp;organiser_name=&amp;amp;text=&amp;amp;sort=location_distance.asc"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="north-west"&gt;NORTH WEST&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February 13 
STFC Daresbury Laboratory                    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecture Theatre &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daresbury Science and Innovation Campus &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrington &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WA4 4AD &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sci-techdaresbury.com/location/"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: Free, but names of all attendees have to be provided in advance 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Warrington&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;submit=Search+Events"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="solent-and-south"&gt;SOLENT and SOUTH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February 20 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coach House                                   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilworth Manor Hotel, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilworth Southampton SO16 7PT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bestwestern.co.uk/Hotels/Chilworth-Manor-Hotel-Southampton-83920/Meetings/Default.aspx?ImageType=Meeting&amp;amp;Microsite=Business"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: ample, free parking. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Southampton&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;date_from=20%2F02%2F2013&amp;amp;date_to=20%2F02%2F2013&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;ds_business_stage=&amp;amp;price_min=&amp;amp;price_max=&amp;amp;organiser_name=&amp;amp;text=&amp;amp;sort=location_distance.asc"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wales"&gt;WALES&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 6 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zen Room &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ATRiuM &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardiff School of Creative &amp;amp; Cultural Industries &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Glamorgan &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Street &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardiff &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CF24 2FN &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places avaliable: 70&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: A representitive of the Welsh Government will discuss SMARTCymru RD&amp;amp;I Funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nearest rail station is Cardiff Queen Street however Cardiff Central Station is also within walking distance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking There is a large car park opposite ATRiuM Building on Adam Street 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://profile.glam.ac.uk/findus/"&gt;more information and driving directions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="booking"&gt;Booking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A link to the booking site will be made available shortly. 
This workshop is being organised by BIS and &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; together with the Welsh Government in partnership with the University of Glamorgan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="scotland"&gt;SCOTLAND&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 20 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eden Court &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bishop’s Road &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inverness IV3 5SA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information including a link to the booking site will be made available shortly. 
This workshop is being organised by BIS and &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; together with the Scottish Government&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agenda&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09.30 Registration and manned stalls open &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00 Welcome &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10.10 Introduction by BIS &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10.20 &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; Presentation - &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credits scheme / Patent box &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11.10 Coffee/ networking and chance to visit manned stands &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11.40 Technology Strategy Board Presentation - Supports available and 
how to access them including: Grants and net-working &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:20 Intellectual Property Office Presentation - Supports available to 
protect and maximise value from intellectual property &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:00 Design Council - Presentation - how design can add value / 
Designing Demand programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:40 Concluding comments &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:45 Lunch - plus opportunity to network and visit manned stands &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14:50 Close&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="business-in-you"&gt;Business in You&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops are part of the Business in You campaign – a partnership between private enterprise and government to highlight support for start-ups and growing businesses and encourage entrepreneurial spirit. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Further information at the Business in You website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/7104</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T17:02:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T17:02:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/get-started-with-companies-house-filings-for-agents"/>
    <title>Get started with Companies House filings for agents</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many agents and advisers set up and file documents on behalf of companies. If you are about to start filing company documents such as accounts and annual returns with Companies House, this guide will help you to understand what you need to do and where to go for more help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide will also introduce you to some of the useful online tools and resources that make filing faster and simpler. These include Companies House Software, WebFiling and the search facility WebCHeck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="companies-house-annual-return-for-agents"&gt;Companies House annual return for agents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every company must send an annual return to Companies House each year. It provides important company information, in a prescribed format, which is then made available to the public. Annual returns must be sent to Companies House by a specific ‘made up’ date - usually the anniversary of the company’s date of incorporation or the anniversary of the last annual return filed at Companies House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about the annual return in our guide: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;topicId=1073869071"&gt;Companies House annual return&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="companies-house-annual-accounts-guidance-for-agents"&gt;Companies House annual accounts guidance for agents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All companies, both private and public, must keep accounting records. Limited companies and limited liability partnerships must send a copy of their annual accounts to Companies House each year. Most companies use professional firms of accountants to produce their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you produce and file accounts on behalf of a company, you must ensure they are signed or authenticated by the accountants (if appropriate) and the company’s directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about what information is needed and how to submit it in our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;topicId=1073859917"&gt;filing accounts with Companies House: dates and checklist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="submitting-documents-to-companies-house"&gt;Submitting documents to Companies House&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are delivering statutory information to Companies House on behalf of your clients, the most secure way is to use their electronic and online filing services. You can read more about this on the page in this guide about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1085037698&amp;amp;r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;using Companies House electronic and online services&lt;/a&gt;. Although you need to register for this, the process is straightforward and free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out which forms can be filed electronically and online, and a list of filing exceptions see our page on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://online.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/openpopup?itemId=1082022100&amp;amp;r.i=1085037135&amp;amp;r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;r.t=RESOURCES&amp;amp;type=ONEOFFPAGE"&gt;WebFiling forms and exceptions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also deliver documents by post, courier, Document Exchange Service or Legal Post (in Scotland), and by using software from a number of commercial software suppliers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hmrc.gov.uk/online/internet-filing-index.htm"&gt;Find commercial filing software information on the HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (HMRC) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will receive an acknowledgement from Companies House, provided you send a copy of your covering letter and a pre-paid addressed return envelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="using-companies-house-electronic-and-online-services"&gt;Using Companies House electronic and online services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To save you time and expense, Companies House provides two electronic and online filing services - Software Filing and WebFiling. The Companies House WebCHeck service also allows you to search the company names index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="web-incorporation-service"&gt;Web incorporation service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can incorporate a company yourself online. To do this &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086687162&amp;amp;r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;type=PIP"&gt;use the Companies House web incorporation service&lt;/a&gt;. This service currently can only be used to incorporate a private company limited by shares adopting model articles in their entirety with a proposed non-sensitive name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="software-filing"&gt;Software filing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This service allows external companies to develop software packages to manage the submission of a range of forms and documents required by Companies House. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/toolsToHelp/efilingfaq.shtml"&gt;Find out about the Software Filing service on the Companies House website&lt;/a&gt;. You can also &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/toolsToHelp/efSoftwareSupp.shtml"&gt;access a list of software suppliers and formation agents on the Companies House website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="webfiling"&gt;WebFiling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a safe and reliable way to file company information online. Most information can be filed free of charge, so it also saves money for your clients. The service can also be used seven days a week, 24 hours a day, so it is also very convenient. You can find out more information in our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;topicId=1082194051"&gt;how to use WebFiling to file company information online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get extra protection against corporate identity fraud by using the PROtected Online Filing service. For more information, see the page on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1082203775&amp;amp;r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;PROtected Online Filing service&lt;/a&gt; in our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;topicId=1082194051"&gt;how to use WebFiling to file company information online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="webcheck"&gt;WebCHeck&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This free service enables you to search company details and look at filing histories online for all limited companies registered in the UK. You can order documents and reports, and monitor companies, for which a small fee is charged. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1081930072&amp;amp;r.l1=1081986989&amp;amp;r.l2=1087252345&amp;amp;r.l3=1087442424&amp;amp;r.l4=1085030976&amp;amp;type=PIP"&gt;search company information using the WebCHeck service at Companies House&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="companies-house-contact-centre"&gt;Companies House Contact Centre&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0303 1234 500&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/forms/introduction.shtml"&gt;Forms and guidance from Companies House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/toolsToHelp/efSoftwareSupp.shtml"&gt;Software suppliers contact details from Companies House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hmrc.gov.uk/online/internet-filing-index.htm"&gt;Commercial filing software advice from HMRC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/7108</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T16:50:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T16:50:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/japanese-knotweed-giant-hogweed-and-other-invasive-plants"/>
    <title>Japanese knotweed, giant hogweed and other invasive plants</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several hundred invasive plants in the UK. Japanese knotweed, giant hogweed and Himalayan balsam are invasive plants that your business might come into contact with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must not plant invasive plants intentionally and if you have invasive plants on your property you must not allow them to spread off site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invasive non-native plants can cause problems for native UK species and reduce biodiversity (the variety of living organisms). Invasive non-native species are now widely recognised as the second biggest threat to biodiversity worldwide. Japanese knotweed can block footpaths and damage concrete, tarmac, flood defences and the stability of river banks. Giant hogweed can cause harm to human health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Injurious weeds are native species, which cause problems for farming. They are harmful to livestock and must not be allowed to spread to agricultural land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide describes how to identify and control invasive plants using methods such as spraying, digging up, cutting and burning. You will find details of your legal responsibility for dealing with invasive plants and how to remove and dispose of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="your-legal-responsibilities-for-invasive-plants-and-injurious-weeds"&gt;Your legal responsibilities for invasive plants and injurious weeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invasive non-native plants are species which have been brought into the UK that has the ability to spread causing damage to the environment, the economy, our health and the way we live. Injurious weeds are native species, which have been deemed to cause a problem to farming productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have invasive plants or injurious weeds on your premises you have a responsibility to prevent them spreading into the wild or causing a nuisance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must not plant or otherwise cause to grow in the wild any plant listed on schedule 9 of the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/publications/files/wildlife-countryside-act.pdf"&gt;Download further guidance from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) website (PDF, 153K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="invasive-plants"&gt;Invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have invasive plants on land that you own or occupy, you must comply with specific legal responsibilities, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spraying herbicides - see the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086737527&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;spraying invasive plants with herbicide&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;burning invasive plants - see the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738241&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;cutting and burning invasive plants&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;burial of soil containing invasive plant material - see the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738496&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;burying invasive plant material on site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;off-site waste disposal - see the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738692&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;disposing of invasive plants and contaminated soil off site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You do not need to notify anyone about the invasive plants on your land. However, you should &lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/index.cfm?sectionid=81"&gt;report certain non-native species on the Non-native Species Secretariat (NNSS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/downloadDocument.cfm?id=375"&gt;Download a consolidated list of invasive plants from the NNSS website (PDF, 89K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not obliged to remove or treat invasive plants, but you must not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allow invasive plants to spread onto adjacent land - the owner of that land could take legal action against you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plant or encourage the spread of invasive plants outside of your property - this can include moving contaminated soil from one place to another or incorrectly handling and transporting contaminated material and plant cuttings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are a farmer and receiving the Single Farm Payment, you must not allow an infestation of an invasive non-native species on your land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="injurious-weeds"&gt;Injurious weeds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Injurious weeds are those that are considered able to cause harm to agricultural pasture. The five species of ‘injurious weed’ are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;common ragwort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spear thistle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creeping or field thistle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;curled dock&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;broadleaved dock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have any injurious species on your land, you are responsible for controlling them. You must prevent them from spreading onto adjoining land. You could be served with an enforcement notice to make sure you do this and fined if you don’t comply. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/wildlife-pets/wildlife-management/weeds-act-1959/"&gt;Find details on ragwort and injurious weeds on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="identifying-invasive-plants"&gt;Identifying invasive plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that you can identify invasive plants on your premises. This will allow you to manage and deal with them in the most appropriate way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying invasive plants on a site early lets developers assess and cost options for destroying, disposing of and managing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing land infested by invasive plants in a timely and appropriate way can avoid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;excessive cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;potential prosecution and compensation claims&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;physical damage to buildings and hard surfaces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;harm to the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="identifying-japanese-knotweed"&gt;Identifying Japanese knotweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese knotweed begins to grow in early spring and can grow in any type of soil, no matter how poor. It can grow as much as 20 centimetres per day, and can reach a height of 1.5 metres by May and 3 metres by June. It does not produce viable seeds in the UK, but instead spreads through rhizome (underground root-like stem) fragments and cut stems. Japanese knotweed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;produces fleshy red tinged shoots when it first breaks through the ground&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has large, heart or spade-shaped green leaves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has leaves arranged in a zig-zag pattern along the stem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has a hollow stem, like bamboo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can form dense clumps that can be several metres deep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;produces clusters of cream flowers towards the end of July&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dies back between September and November, leaving brown stems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Leisure/Knotweed_CoP.pdf"&gt;Download the Japanese knotweed code of practice from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 2.06MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="identifying-giant-hogweed"&gt;Identifying giant hogweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should take great care when identifying giant hogweed. Contact with the plant, particularly the sap, can lead to severe blistering and scarring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant hogweed closely resembles native cow parsley or hogweed. It can take four years to reach its full height of 3-5 metres and flower. Giant hogweed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a reddish purple stem with fine spines that make it appear furry - like a stinging nettle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has hollow stems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has spotted leaf stalks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has leaves up to 1.5 metres wide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flowers in June and July&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has flower heads that are usually 50 centimetres wide - each flower head is capable of producing 50,000 seeds every year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has seeds that can stay in the soil for several years before they develop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="identifying-himalayan-balsam"&gt;Identifying Himalayan balsam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Himalayan balsam is often found on river banks, growing up to 2 metres in height. Each plant lasts for one year and dies at the end of the growing season. Himalayan balsam:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has reddish coloured stems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has dark green, lance-shaped leaves with jagged edges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flowers from June to October&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has large, brightly coloured flowers that are usually in variable shades from purple to pale pink&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can produce around 2,500 seeds per plant each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has explosive seed pods that can throw seeds over 6 metres away from the plant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="identifying-other-invasive-plants"&gt;Identifying other invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other species of invasive plants in the UK include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;floating pennywort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;parrot’s feather&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creeping water primrose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Zealand pigmyweed (also known as Australian swamp stonecrop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;curly waterweed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nuttall’s waterweed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Canadian pondweed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;water fern (also known as fairy fern)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To find out how to identify some of these invasive weeds, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0410BSBR-e-e.pdf"&gt;download guidance on managing invasive non-native plants from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 581K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/index.cfm?sectionid=47"&gt;Find identification sheets on invasive non-native species on the Non-native Species Secretariat (NNSS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-invasive-plants-spread"&gt;How invasive plants spread&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remove invasive plants from your premises or to stop them from spreading, it helps to understand how new plants grow and spread. This will help you decide what action to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you employ a contractor to do the work for you, you should understand what they intend to do and why. This could help you decide what you actually need and could save you money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-japanese-knotweed-spreads"&gt;How Japanese knotweed spreads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese knotweed does not spread from seeds in the UK. It is spread when small pieces of the plant or rhizomes (underground root-like stems) are broken off. One piece of rhizome or plant the size of a fingernail can produce a new plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pieces of plant or rhizome can be transported to a new location by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;water - if the parent plant is close to a river or stream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving soil which contains them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fly-tipping cut or pulled stems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual plants can cover several square metres of land, joined up below ground by an extensive rhizome network. Herbicide treatment can be a very effective way of controlling Japanese knotweed, but a lack of regrowth does not mean the underground rhizome is dead. If the soil is disturbed, knotweed often regrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-giant-hogweed-spreads"&gt;How giant hogweed spreads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant hogweed produces large, umbrella-like flowers, each of which can produce up to 50,000 seeds. These seeds fall typically within 4 metres of the parent plant. Seeds can be transported by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vehicles - particularly along roads and railways&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;water - if the parent plant is close to a river or stream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;footwear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving soil which contains them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The seeds can remain dormant in the soil for 15 years. Even if you treat the plants with herbicides and they die, several thousand seeds are waiting in the ground below for the opportunity to take their place. Any control programme needs to continue for several years, including checks for new growth. When managing giant hogweed it is important to maintain a healthy grass sward, either by using selective herbicides or by sowing grass mixes. A dense grass sward helps to prevent giant hogweed seeds from germinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant hogweed contains sap that is released when the plant is cut or by brushing against the plant. Contact with the sap causes skin to become sensitive to sunlight, resulting in painful blisters which appear up to two days after contact and may reoccur for several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-himalayan-balsam-spreads"&gt;How Himalayan balsam spreads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Himalayan balsam plants can produce around 2,500 seeds each year. The seedpods open in such a way that the seeds are thrown up to 7 metres away from the parent plant, helping the species to quickly spread. Seeds can also be transported by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;water - if the parent plant is close to a river or stream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tracked vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;footwear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving soil which contains them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even if you remove these plants, or treat them with herbicides and they die, several hundred seeds can be waiting in the ground below for the opportunity to take their place. The seeds can survive for several years, so any control programme needs to continue for a couple of years, including checks for new growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="handling-and-working-with-invasive-plants"&gt;Handling and working with invasive plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not manage invasive plants correctly, they will spread over time and they could cause damage to structures, such as building foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have invasive plants on your site you should put up signs, where appropriate, to warn employees and the public about the invasive species that are present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put up posters in offices and communal areas to explain to employees what the problems are and what they need to do. Include pictures of the invasive plants you have on your site. This is particularly important for giant hogweed, as contact with sap from the plant can lead to skin burns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="handling-japanese-knotweed"&gt;Handling Japanese knotweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure your staff can identify Japanese knotweed rhizomes (underground root-like stems). This can reduce waste costs and improve how you manage Japanese knotweed on site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should minimise the amount of soil containing Japanese knotweed material that you excavate. Soil containing Japanese knotweed material that has been treated can be reused for landscaping the site, but should not be taken off site, unless to landfill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a choice of herbicides that are effective against Japanese knotweed, depending on your situation. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086737527&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;spraying invasive plants with herbicides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On development sites you should fence Japanese knotweed where possible, using clear signs so that only appropriately briefed personnel enter the enclosure to deal with the infestation and resulting waste. This includes areas with waste plant material or soil contaminated with Japanese knotweed. The fence should be at least 7 metres away from the plants. Put up restricted access signs around these fenced areas (poster available in Appendix VII of the Japanese knotweed code of practice). You must not use tracked vehicles within the affected area, and make sure any vehicles leaving the area are pressure washed. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Leisure/Knotweed_CoP.pdf"&gt;Download the Japanese knotweed code of practice from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 2.06MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must never strim areas containing Japanese knotweed. If you are going to clear areas where Japanese knotweed is present, make sure you remove all cut stems. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738692&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;disposing of invasive plants and contaminated soil off site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not try to compost Japanese knotweed material - it will produce new plants. You must not put cut plant material directly onto the ground. If you must stockpile cut material, make sure it does not come into contact with soil - for example, by placing it on top of a barrier membrane. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738241&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;cutting and burning invasive plants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep soil containing Japanese knotweed material separate from clean soil. This will reduce the volume of soil that you need to treat and dispose of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="handling-giant-hogweed"&gt;Handling giant hogweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When giant hogweed sap comes into contact with skin, it reacts with sunlight and causes chemical skin burns. Giant hogweed sap becomes more toxic as the year progresses and the plant is exposed to more sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stem and underside of the leaves have hairs like a stinging nettle. Brushing against giant hogweed can be enough to get sap on your skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have giant hogweed on your premises, you must ensure that the public and your employees are protected from the hazards of its toxic sap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should control giant hogweed before it seeds. You must not use a strimmer on giant hogweed. The sap from the plant may get onto your skin or into your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are going to get close to or handle giant hogweed, you should wear full protective clothing with gloves, a hood and a full-face visor. You should wash down your protective clothing before you take it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get sap on your skin, cover it to keep it out of the sun. Go indoors immediately and wash the sap off your skin with soap and lots of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="spraying-invasive-plants-with-herbicide"&gt;Spraying invasive plants with herbicide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treating invasive plants with herbicide can be a very effective method of treatment. You will have to respray. It usually takes at least three years to treat Japanese knotweed until it is dormant. Giant hogweed seeds can continue germinating for 15 years after the last seed fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the plant is in or near to water you must have agreement from the Environment Agency to use the herbicide. The herbicide must be approved for use in or near water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The herbicide’s effectiveness depends on the type used. An advisor certified by BASIS (the registration, standards and certification scheme for pesticides and fertilisers) will be able to advise you on the most suitable type of herbicide for your situation and when best to apply it. You can also &lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/index.cfm?sectionid=53"&gt;find management examples and information on the Non-native Species Secretariat (NNSS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.basis-reg.co.uk"&gt;Find information on pesticide and fertiliser registration, standards and certification on the BASIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant hogweed and Himalayan balsam both drop large quantities of seeds. A control programme will need to continue for several years, with checks carried out throughout the growing season. If you are trying to eradicate these plants from a riverbank it is important to ensure that any plants upstream are also treated to avoid seeds being washed onto the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese knotweed has a large underground network of rhizomes (underground root-like stems). To eradicate the plant you must kill the rhizomes. Picking the right herbicide is essential, as it must travel through the plant and into the rhizome system below. Several herbicides can treat Japanese knotweed successfully - you will need to pick the right herbicide for your situation. Glyphosate is effective because it penetrates through the whole plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="using-herbicides"&gt;Using herbicides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person doing the spraying must hold a certificate of technical competence for herbicide use or work under the direct supervision of a certificate holder. If you plan to spray in or near water, the person carrying out or supervising the spraying must have the appropriate aquatic part of the qualification. The sprayer must also comply with the pesticide product label and meet all of its conditions. Before you spray in or near water you must check that the product is approved for use near water. There are formulations of glyphosate and 2.4-D amine that can be used in or near water and are effective against many invasive plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a certificate of technical competence by attending a short course at an agricultural college or similar institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For herbicide to be effective, make sure you use it at the correct time of year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese knotweed is best sprayed in late summer from flowering onwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giant hogweed should be sprayed in April or May, before the plants flower.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Himalayan balsam should be sprayed in spring before flowering, but strimming or hand pulling should be your preferred option for control of this plant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must follow the guidance in the statutory code of practice for plant protection products. If you follow its advice you should stay within the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pesticides.gov.uk/safe_use.asp?id=64"&gt;Read the code of practice for plant protection products on the Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive (HSE) Chemicals Regulation Directorate website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the invasive plants are near a watercourse, you should not use herbicides as the first option. If you are planning to use herbicide in or near to a watercourse, you must complete herbicide form AqHerb01 and send it to the Environment Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0110BRZI-e-e.pdf"&gt;Download form AqHerb01 - agreement to use herbicides in or near water from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 499K)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0110BRZK-E-e.pdf"&gt;Download guidance notes for form AqHerb01 from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 326K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also carry out a Control of Substances Hazardous to Health (COSHH) assessment for any activities that involve herbicides. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/coshh/index.htm"&gt;Read about COSHH on the HSE website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="dispose-of-waste-herbicides-correctly"&gt;Dispose of waste herbicides correctly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must make sure that all your waste is stored, transported and disposed of safely. Waste herbicides are likely to be classed as hazardous waste. You must keep this separate from other waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herbicide containers must either be rinsed or handled as herbicides. Check product labels to see if your waste containers should be rinsed. Water used for rinsing empty containers is classed as dilute pesticides or biocides. You may need an environmental permit, registered waste exemption or trade effluent consent to dispose of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1086778448"&gt;pesticides and biocides - your environmental responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="digging-up-invasive-plants"&gt;Digging up invasive plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearing the leaves and stems of Japanese knotweed or giant hogweed that are above ground and then removing soil contaminated with roots, rhizomes (underground root-like stems) and seeds can provide faster results than just spraying with herbicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to minimise the amount of waste you generate that contains invasive plants, or their seeds and rhizomes. Any waste you do produce should be treated on site where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any waste that is taken off site must be taken by a licensed waste carrier and must go to a suitably authorised landfill site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you intend to bury invasive plant waste on your property you must contact the Environment Agency to check you are allowed to do this at your location. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086738496&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;burying invasive plant material on site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should not remove soil from river banks, as this can cause water pollution. If you are planning to carry out work near a river you should contact the Environment Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your site floods, the seeds will be spread further across the site, so you will need to manage a larger area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="digging-up-giant-hogweed"&gt;Digging up giant hogweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clear ground contaminated with giant hogweed, you may need to remove soil up to 4 metres away from the plants and to a depth of 0.5 metres. You will need to check for regrowth regularly. You should spray regrowth with the herbicide glyphosate before the plants flower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="digging-up-japanese-knotweed"&gt;Digging up Japanese knotweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rhizome system beneath a stand of Japanese knotweed can be over 4 metres deep and could extend for at least 7 metres around the stand. If you are going to dig out the rhizome system you will need to remove all of the plant material. You should use the rhizome identification guide in the knotweed code of practice, or ask a specialist, to help you identify the plant material. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Leisure/Knotweed_CoP.pdf"&gt;Download the Japanese knotweed code of practice from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 2.06MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to check any cleared areas regularly for regrowth. You can spray any regrowth with herbicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="digging-up-himalayan-balsam"&gt;Digging up Himalayan balsam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clear ground contaminated with Himalayan balsam, you may need to remove soil up to 6 metres from the parent plant and to a depth of 0.5 metres. You should not remove soil while the seed pods are present. You will need to check for regrowth regularly. You should pull by hand or strim regrowth before the plants flower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as seeds remain viable in the soil for several years, annual cutting, mowing or grazing or annual herbicide treatment during the spring growing season can be an effective control for this plant. You must also carry out follow up checks for late germinating seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-you-must-do-when-digging-up-invasive-plants"&gt;What you must do when digging up invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never stockpile contaminated soil or plant material within 10 metres of a watercourse, and it should not be stockpiled within 7 metres of your site boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collect any water you use for cleaning vehicles that are used in contaminated areas. If it is contaminated with seeds or plant material, you must not discharge it to a watercourse. You could treat the water by passing it through a settlement tank to remove any soil before passing it through a very fine mesh sieve to remove seeds or plant material. Settlement alone may not be adequate because seeds and plant material float. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/PMHO0307BMDX-e-e.pdf"&gt;Download Pollution prevention guideline: Vehicle washing and cleaning (PPG13) from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 176K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be able to deposit material sieved from water used for vehicle washing in a controlled area on your land and monitor it for regrowth. You should speak to the Environment Agency to determine your best option. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/contactus/default.aspx"&gt;Find Environment Agency contact details on the Environment Agency website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our guides on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1080374134"&gt;preventing water pollution&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1086676178"&gt;discharging trade effluent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="good-practice-for-digging-up-invasive-plants"&gt;Good practice for digging up invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should clearly mark out any areas of your land that contain invasive plants. Fence them off until you intend to clear them. Put the fence at least 7 metres away from the plants to contain any contaminated soil or roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you clear contaminated areas, take care to ensure contaminated soil, seeds and plant material are not spread to unaffected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limit the use of tracked machinery where possible. Seeds and plant material can get caught in the tracks and moved around the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are developing your land, consider creating a haul road using a strong geotextile overlain with hardcore as a base for vehicles to travel on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover all lorries, dumpers or haulage vehicles carrying contaminated soil or plant material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoroughly clean tracked machinery when it leaves contaminated areas of the site. Do this within a designated area that is as close as possible to the contaminated area on which the machinery has been working. Always carry out a visual inspection of wheel arches and tracks before the vehicle leaves the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look out for regrowth by roads and areas where vehicles have been parked or cleaned. Spray any regrowth with herbicide if required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working between November and March in an area where invasive plants are known to be present, look for dead canes from the previous year to identify infected areas. Even if there is no growth evident above ground, seeds from giant hogweed and Himalayan balsam, and Japanese knotweed rhizome will still be present. Try to inspect a development site for evidence of invasive species before it is cleared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cutting-and-burning-invasive-plants"&gt;Cutting and burning invasive plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting down or digging up invasive plants and burning the waste plant material can be a useful, low-tech means of control. It can reduce the volume of waste that you need to dispose of off site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cutting-invasive-plants"&gt;Cutting invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting Japanese knotweed will, over time, weaken the plant, but it will not kill the rhizomes (underground root-like stems). It can be used as part of other control practices. You must handle and dispose of cut plant material carefully. Burning alone may not be sufficient to kill the plant material. You should place burnt material on top of a membrane and monitor it for regrowth. You must not use a strimmer on Japanese knotweed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting giant hogweed before the plants flower will help to prevent further seeds being deposited on the ground. This is an effective way of removing these species but it can take many years. You must not use a strimmer on giant hogweed. You must avoid contact with giant hogweed, particularly its sap, as it can cause chemical skin burns. You should wear full protective clothing when working near it or handling it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulling up Himalayan balsam before the plants flower is the most effective method of control. Do not cut the plants before they flower as this can result in a more bushy plant that produces more flowers. The best time to cut is late May. Cut the plant below the first nodule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="burning-invasive-plants"&gt;Burning invasive plants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burning waste materials is a type of waste disposal. If you burn waste in the open you may require an environmental permit or registered waste exemption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had a waste exemption registered before 6 April 2010, you may need to register a new exemption from environmental permitting or apply for an environmental permit. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Business/Table_of_transitional_provisions_-_only.pdf"&gt;Download an exemption and permit timetable from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 62K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may qualify for a D7 exemption to burn certain waste plant tissue and untreated wood if you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;burn the waste at the place where it was produced&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;burn no more than 10 tonnes in a 24-hour period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have an exemption, you must comply with the exemption conditions and register this exemption with the Environment Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also ensure that your activity does not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;endanger human health or cause pollution to water, air or soil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;constitute a risk to plants or animals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cause a nuisance, eg in terms of noise or odour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adversely affect the countryside or places of special interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/business/topics/permitting/116165.aspx"&gt;Find guidance on the waste exemption for burning waste in the open on the Environment Agency website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must notify the Environment Agency at least a week before you intend burning plant material. You should also notify your local authority environmental health officer before you begin burning plant material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you burn waste in an incinerator or other similar plant, you may need an environmental permit. See our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1086913916"&gt;burning waste - your environmental responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="good-practice"&gt;Good practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burning plant material should only give rise to white smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell the local fire brigade before you begin burning and again when you finish, so that they are not called out unnecessarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can leave cut stems to dry out in the sun rather than burning them. Make sure you place cut Japanese knotweed and Himalayan balsam material on a membrane and not in direct contact with the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant hogweed sap remains toxic after the plant has been cut down. Do not leave cut stems where they could harm people or livestock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="burying-invasive-plant-material-on-site"&gt;Burying invasive plant material on site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking plant material and soil containing plant material away for disposal off site uses valuable landfill capacity and increases the likelihood of the spread of invasive plants. Another option is to bury this soil and plant material on your own land because, without sunlight, plants cannot survive and seeds will not germinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this material will need to remain buried for several years to ensure that it will not grow again. Giant hogweed seeds can be viable for up to 15 years and Japanese knotweed rhizome (underground root-like stems) is believed to survive for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-you-must-do"&gt;What you must do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you bury invasive plant waste on your property you must contact the Environment Agency to check you are allowed to do this at your location. The Environment Agency may want to look at your site and may visit while the works are undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil and plant material containing Japanese knotweed may need to be buried 5 metres below ground level. You should place a barrier membrane on top of the material and fill the hole with clean soil. Alternatively, the knotweed code of practice describes how you can bury it less deeply. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Leisure/Knotweed_CoP.pdf"&gt;Download the Japanese knotweed code of practice from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 2.06MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil containing Himalayan balsam and giant hogweed seeds should be buried at least 1 metre below ground level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must not bury anything other than plant material and soil containing invasive plants that have originated on site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must make sure that deep burial does not interfere with the ground water level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buried soil and plant material that have been treated with a herbicide that does not break down in the environment could cause groundwater pollution. If you intend to bury treated material, you should treat it with glyphosate herbicide only. Check with the Environment Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herbicides that do not break down in the environment are described as persistent. Those that do break down are described as biodegradable or non-persistent. The herbicide packaging or safety data sheet will state whether it is persistent or non-persistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil contaminated with some persistent herbicides will be classed as hazardous and so will need to be disposed of as hazardous waste. See our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1080466581"&gt;managing your hazardous waste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must follow the guidelines for spraying plants with herbicide and digging up plants. See the pages in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086737527&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;spraying invasive plants with herbicide&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086737854&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;digging up invasive plants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="good-practice-1"&gt;Good practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should bury the material in an area where it is not likely to be disturbed. You should keep records of the quantity of material that you have buried and a map showing the location of the burial pit and its depth. Use signs to mark the burial pit and keep heavy tracked machinery off the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should not bury materials deeply within 7 metres of an adjacent landowner’s site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="disposing-of-invasive-plants-and-contaminated-soil-off-site"&gt;Disposing of invasive plants and contaminated soil off site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should try to minimise the amount of waste you generate that contains invasive plants or their seeds, roots and rhizomes (underground root-like stems). Any waste you do produce should be treated on site where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any waste taken off site must be taken by a licensed waste carrier and go to a suitably authorised landfill site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-you-must-do-1"&gt;What you must do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you transport invasive plants and soil contaminated with invasive plants, make sure that the vehicle is covered or sheeted so that seeds and plant material cannot blow away. If you allow contaminated soil or plant material to escape, you could be prosecuted and fined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must have waste transfer notes (WTNs) for any material leaving your site. You must list any material that contains invasive plants or their seeds on the WTN. Your waste carrier can only take the waste containing invasive weeds to sites authorised to accept it. Plant material, or soil containing plant material or seeds, is likely to be classed as non-hazardous waste - this is a different category from inert waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a duty of care for waste that affects all businesses. You must make sure that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your waste is stored, handled, recycled or disposed of safely and legally by licensed individuals or businesses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you record all transfers of waste between your business and another business - using a WTN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you keep all WTNs, signed by both businesses, for at least two years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you record any transfer of hazardous waste between your business and another business using a consignment note&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you keep all consignment notes, signed by both businesses, for at least three years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must take waste plant material or contaminated soil to a site that has an environmental permit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conditions of the permit must allow the disposal of invasive plants at the site. You should check with the waste site in advance to make sure they can accept material containing invasive plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waste site may need notice so that an area can be prepared. For example, a landfill site will need an area away from the landfill liner for material containing invasive plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tax-relief-for-disposing-of-soil-containing-japanese-knotweed"&gt;Tax relief for disposing of soil containing Japanese knotweed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese knotweed and giant hogweed are considered to be pollutants and used to have a landfill tax exemption from HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (HMRC). You can no longer apply for a new exemption, but existing exemptions may be valid until 31 March 2012. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://customs.hmrc.gov.uk/channelsPortalWebApp/channelsPortalWebApp.portal?_nfpb=true&amp;amp;_pageLabel=pageExcise_ShowContent&amp;amp;id=HMCE_CL_000509&amp;amp;propertyType=document&amp;amp;lang=_e"&gt;Read about landfill tax on the HMRC website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Land remediation relief (LRR) is a corporation tax relief scheme introduced to help bring land that has been ruined by various industrial uses or long-term neglect back into productive use. You may be able to claim LRR for removing contamination arising from Japanese knotweed. You will not be able to claim LRR if disposing of material containing Japanese knotweed to landfill. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hmrc.gov.uk/manuals/cirdmanual/CIRD60000.htm"&gt;Find guidance on land remediation relief on the HMRC website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="invasive-plants-environmental-legislation"&gt;Invasive plants environmental legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page provides links to the full text of key pieces of environmental legislation relating to invasive weeds. The websites hosting the legislation may list amendments separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are setting up an environmental management system (EMS) for your business, you can use this list to start compiling your legal register. Your legal adviser or environmental consultant will be able to tell you if other environmental legislation applies to your specific business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about EMS, see our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1079422683"&gt;environmental management systems (EMS) - the basics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Permitting (England and Wales) Regulations SI 2010/675. Provides a consolidated system for environmental permits and exemptions for industrial activities, mobile plant, waste operations, mining waste operations, water discharge activities, groundwater activities and radioactive substances activities. It also sets out the powers, functions and duties of the regulators. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/675/contents/made"&gt;Find the Environmental Permitting (England and Wales) Regulations 2010 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environmental Protection Act 1990. Defines the legal framework for duty of care for waste, contaminated land and statutory nuisance. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1990/43/contents"&gt;Find the Environmental Protection Act 1990 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ragwort Control Act 2003. Inserts into the Weeds Act 1959 a new section enabling the government to make a code of practice on preventing the spread of ragwort. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/40"&gt;Find the Ragwort Control Act 2003 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weeds Act 1959. Enables land occupiers where injurious weeds (including ragwort) are growing to be ordered to take action to stop them spreading and fined if the order is not complied with. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Eliz2/7-8/54"&gt;Find the Weeds Act 1959 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981. Bans certain methods of killing or taking wild animals, including birds, and restricts the introduction and sale of certain non-native animals and plants. Also sets out the amended laws relating to public rights of way. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1981/69/contents"&gt;Find the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 (Variation of Schedule 9) (England and Wales) Order SI 2010/609. Amends the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 by adding new species to the list of plants not to be planted or allowed to grow in the wild, including Himalayan balsam, floating pennywort and cotoneaster. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/609/made"&gt;Find the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 (Variation of Schedule 9) (England and Wales) Order 2010 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may also need to know about and comply with legislation on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pesticides - see the page on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086806329&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;pesticides and biocides environmental legislation&lt;/a&gt; in our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1086778448"&gt;pesticides and biocides - your environmental responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;water pollution - see the page on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1082476989&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;water pollution legislation&lt;/a&gt; in our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1080374134"&gt;preventing water pollution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;duty of care - see our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1082900123&amp;amp;r.l3=1086726920&amp;amp;topicId=1079431917"&gt;duty of care - your waste responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/current/63594.aspx"&gt;Find other current environmental legislation that may affect your business on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/future/63657.aspx"&gt;Find guidance about future environmental legislation on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-agency-helpline"&gt;Environment Agency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;03708 506 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="natural-england-enquiry-service"&gt;Natural England Enquiry Service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0845 600 3078&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/home/index.cfm"&gt;Non-native invasive weed species information on the Non-native Species Secretariat website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/homeandleisure/wildlife/31350.aspx"&gt;Invasive weed species information on the Environment Agency website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0410BSBR-e-e.pdf"&gt;Download managing invasive non-native plants guidance from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 581K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/wildlife-pets/wildlife-management/weeds-act-1959/"&gt;Ragwort and injurious weeds information on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://secure.fera.defra.gov.uk/nonnativespecies/beplantwise/"&gt;Be Plant Wise campaign information on the NNSS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/homeandleisure/wildlife/130079.aspx"&gt;Japanese knotweed information on the Environment Agency website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.basis-reg.co.uk"&gt;Pesticide and fertiliser registration, standards and certification information on the BASIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pesticides.gov.uk/safe_use.asp?id=64"&gt;Plant protection products code of practice on the HSE Chemicals Regulation Directorate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/coshh/index.htm"&gt;COSHH regulations guidance on the HSE website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0110BRZI-e-e.pdf"&gt;Download agreement to use herbicides in or near water (form AqHerb01) from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 499K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.environment-agency.gov.uk/pdf/GEHO0110BRZK-E-e.pdf"&gt;Download form AqHerb01 guidance notes from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 326K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/static/documents/Business/Table_of_transitional_provisions_-_only.pdf"&gt;Download a waste exemption transitional timetable from the Environment Agency website (PDF, 62K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://customs.hmrc.gov.uk/channelsPortalWebApp/channelsPortalWebApp.portal?_nfpb=true&amp;amp;_pageLabel=pageExcise_ShowContent&amp;amp;id=HMCE_CL_000509&amp;amp;propertyType=document&amp;amp;lang=_e"&gt;Landfill tax guidance on the HMRC website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hmrc.gov.uk/manuals/cirdmanual/CIRD60000.htm"&gt;LRR information on the HMRC website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/current/63594.aspx"&gt;Current environmental legislation lists on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/future/63657.aspx"&gt;Future environmental legislation guidance on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
