<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64041</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-specific-learner-groups"/>
    <title>24+ advanced learning loans: specific learner groups</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Research on a proposal for learners aged 24 and above, studying at level 3 and above, to pay higher contributions towards costs.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports research findings on the government’s proposal for adults aged 24 and above, who study for qualifications at level 3 and above, to make greater contributions to the costs of their learning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government proposes to remove grant funding for these further education learners and courses. This will allow the government to focus investment on younger and lower-qualified learners who are less likely to invest in themselves. Instead, the government will provide income-contingent loans to cover the resulting upfront costs, in line with its principles of promoting fairness and personal responsibility. These 24+ Advanced Learning Loans will be made available to new learners from the 2013/14 academic year, with the first full year expected to be the 2014/15 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS carried out an impact assessment to show the economic costs and benefits of this proposal, and an equality impact assessment to look at how the proposal will affect different types of learners. This report explores these assessments, and looks at how learners are likely to respond to the 24+ Advanced Learning Loans proposal, and how its impact on their decisions and behaviours could be minimised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research provides a greater understanding of four specific learner groups: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;those aged 40+, and particularly those out of work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those with mental or physical disabilities or learning difficulties have particular needs regarding communication and information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those seeking to take up Advanced/Higher Apprentices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Muslim learners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This research indicated that most learner groups are unlikely to be put off by the loans proposition, provided it is communicated effectively. It also highlighted groups which are likely to face specific issues and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS research report no.100.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/61055</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:26:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:26:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/global-science-and-innovation-network"/>
    <title>Global Science and Innovation Network</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Science and innovation play a key role in promoting prosperity and growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Science and innovation are at the heart of government strategy for promoting sustainable UK economic recovery. International collaboration in science and innovation is vital for meeting policy challenges on a global scale. Challenges such as pandemic disease, climate change, and food security, require the ability to engage other governments with, and through, sound science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills and the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office jointly fund a network of Science Officers overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science and Innovation Network consists of around 90 staff, based in 40 British Embassies, High Commissions and Consulates, across 25 countries around the world. SIN officers engage with the local science and innovation community in support of UK policy overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with FCO &amp;amp; BIS priorities, the work of the SIN is guided by the following objectives: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="influence"&gt;Influence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science and innovation policies of governments, businesses and academia are influenced to benefit the UK through lobbying and deployment of robust scientific evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK policy development is informed through identifying good practice internationally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="opportunity"&gt;Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International science collaboration of best with best is facilitated to the benefit of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;International innovation collaboration is facilitated to augment UK capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Science and Innovation Network works closely with a wide range of partners from government, business and academia. It aims to complement the work of other key partners such as UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI), The British Council, Research Councils UK (RCUK) and the Department for International Development (DFID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sin-priorities"&gt;SIN Priorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The priorities and activities of SIN teams will vary from country to country, but main responsibilities include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reporting and advising major UK partners on opportunities and developments in science and innovation overseas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Influencing key players overseas on UK aims and priorities in science and innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting overseas visits by ministers and senior officials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identifying leading edge capabilities overseas, promoting UK efforts on R&amp;amp;D and breaking down barriers to collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hosting and supporting conferences, seminars and workshops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The S&amp;amp;I Network does not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fund or allocate resources for research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;intervene in commercial disputes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;undertake market research or commercially specific reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-contact-sin"&gt;How to contact SIN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To contact the Science and Innovation Network please email &lt;a href="mailto:sean.kelly@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Sean Kelly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/7130</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T15:58:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T15:58:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/managing-fluorinated-gases-and-ozone-depleting-substances"/>
    <title>Managing fluorinated gases and ozone-depleting substances</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) are a group of chemicals containing fluorine. F-gases are powerful greenhouse gases that trap heat in the atmosphere and contribute to global warming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ozone-depleting substances (ODS) are gases which damage the ozone layer in the upper atmosphere. They are being phased out, but can be found in older equipment. There are also a few exceptions for certain uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common uses for ODS and F-gases include refrigeration and air-conditioning equipment, aerosols, solvents, foam blowing agents, firefighting fluids and high voltage switchgear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture, supply, use, install or service equipment containing F-gases or ODS, or if you manufacture or supply F-gases, you must comply with legislation which aims to limit such releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide explains what F-gases and ODS are, how different types of businesses can comply with the F-gas and ODS legislation, and how the legislation is enforced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-are-fluorinated-gases-and-ozone-depleting-substances"&gt;What are fluorinated gases and ozone-depleting substances?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) are a family of gases containing fluorine. They are powerful greenhouse gases that trap heat in the atmosphere and contribute to global warming. They are stronger than naturally occurring greenhouse gases and their use is regulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main types of F-gases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;perfluorocarbons (PFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sulphur hexafluoride (SF6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ozone-depleting substances (ODS) are chemicals that, if allowed to escape, damage the ozone layer in the upper atmosphere. Some ODS also have a global warming potential so they contribute to climate change. F-gases are often used as a replacement for ODS. Many ODS are banned or being phased out. ODS include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;carbon tetrachloride (used to make CFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;halons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;methyl chloroform and methyl bromide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can only produce and market ODS as a feedstock for producing non-ODS substances (eg Teflon) and for laboratory and analytical work. You must clearly label feedstock ODS and indicate that it can only be used for that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some equipment still in use may contain banned or controlled ODS, and may also be traded illegally. You should be aware of which are banned, where you might find them and what to do if you discover them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="main-uses-of-f-gases-and-ods"&gt;Main uses of F-gases and ODS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;F-gases and ODS are used in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pump (RAC) equipment are some of the largest sources of F-gas emissions in the UK. See the pages in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084061937&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;stationary refrigeration and air conditioning: F-gas controls&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086763932&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;stationary refrigeration and air conditioning: ODS controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some stationary fire protection systems and portable fire extinguishers currently use HFCs. See the pages in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084062397&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;fire protection equipment: F-gas controls&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1086764355&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;fire protection equipment: ODS controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile air conditioning in cars and light vans currently uses HFCs. Other air-conditioned and refrigerated transport currently uses both F-gases and ODS. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084063080&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;mobile air conditioning: F-gas controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solvents containing F-gases are used to clean components, eg in the electronics and aerospace industries. The use of solvents containing ODS is now banned. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084063156&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;solvent cleaning: F-gas and ODS controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;F-gases and ODS have many specialist uses such as in the production of magnesium, different types of foam and high voltage switchgear. See the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084063662&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;specialist uses of F-gases and ODS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For information about manufacturing, importing and exporting F-gases, see the page in this guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1084063941&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;producing and supplying fluids: F-gas and ODS controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="f-gas-support"&gt;F-Gas Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;F-Gas Support is a government-funded group that provides guidance on complying with F-gas and ODS regulations for manufacturers, operators and others working with F-gases, ODS and related equipment. You can email them at &lt;a href="mailto:fgas-support@enviros.com"&gt;fgas-support@enviros.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stationary-refrigeration-air-conditioning-and-heat-pumps-f-gas-controls"&gt;Stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pumps: F-gas controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pump (RAC) systems are one of the largest sources of fluorinated greenhouse gas (F-gas) emissions. F-gases commonly used in RAC systems are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs) - HFC 23, HFC 134a, HFC 152a&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;perfluorocarbons (PFCs) - PFC 218, R 218, Refrigerant 218&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="responsibility-for-f-gas-obligations"&gt;Responsibility for F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the key F-gas obligations lie with the operator. An operator is a person or business who has actual power over the technical functioning of the equipment. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;free access to the system, eg supervising its components or functioning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;control over the day-to-day running or function&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;powers, including financial, to decide on technical modifications, F-gas quantity modifications or have repairs carried out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The owner of the equipment is usually the operator unless such functions have been transferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="key-f-gas-obligations"&gt;Key F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you operate RAC equipment containing F-gases, you must meet legal obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevent leakage - where it is technically feasible and does not entail disproportionate cost, you must prevent leakage of F-gas refrigerants, and repair any discovered leaks as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check leaks regularly - how often you are required to check (using certified personnel) depends on the type of system and the quantity of F-gas refrigerants used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leak-testing-frequencies"&gt;Leak testing frequencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Frequency&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Normal systems&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Systems labelled as hermetically sealed&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 3 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 6 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Annual&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Six-monthly*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Quarterly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;*Half this frequency if fitted with automatic leak detection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system must be checked within a month after a leak has been repaired to ensure that the repair has been effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install automatic leak detection systems - you must fit a leak detection system to equipment containing 300 kilograms or more of F-gas refrigerant. This system must be checked once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining records - you must keep records on systems with 3 kilograms or more of F-gases including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quantity and type of F-gas in the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantity of refrigerant added to the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantity of refrigerant recovered through servicing, maintenance and disposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identity of business or personnel servicing or maintaining the system, and the dates and results of leak checks and leak detection system checks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recover gas - if F-gas refrigerant is removed from any system, it must be properly recovered by appropriately certified personnel during servicing and decommissioning. You must also ensure that all F-gases that are not recycled or reclaimed are disposed of correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get certified - any personnel carrying out leak checking, gas recovery, installation, maintenance or servicing of equipment containing F-gas must be appropriately qualified. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-rac5.pdf"&gt;Download RAC qualification and certification guidance from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) website (PDF, 325K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person physically taking delivery of F-gas containers does not need to be qualified unless they also perform installation, servicing or repair work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold company certificates - businesses that install, maintain or service the equipment must also hold the relevant company certification. The designated certification bodies in the UK are Refcom, Quidos, Bureau Veritas and Stroma. To get a company certificate you must be able to show that your staff who perform the relevant work hold the correct F-gas qualification, you have the correct tools and procedures available and you have enough staff to cover the work you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-rac5.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on company certification in the RAC sector from the Defra website (PDF, 325K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Label systems - new systems must be correctly labelled, stating the type and quantity of refrigerant used. The label must be located near to the service point. In addition, instruction manuals that come with the equipment must have similar information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit reports - you must complete a report and send it to the European Commission and Defra if you produce, import or export more than 1 tonne of F-gases per year. This is only relevant for imports from and exports to countries outside the European Union. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;Find the F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t use non-refillable containers - use of non-refillable containers for transporting and storing F-gases is banned. You must not place non-refillable containers on the market, except for those manufactured (filled with refrigerant) before 4 July 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="alternatives-to-f-gases"&gt;Alternatives to F-gases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wish to consider alternatives to F-gases. However, alternatives may also have restrictions on their use and you should consider the overall environmental impact (eg taking into account energy efficiency) and factors such as health and safety when making your choice. Commonly used alternative refrigerants include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ammonia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;carbon dioxide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hydrocarbons, eg butane and propane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/srac/"&gt;find guidance on F-gas and ODS controls on RAC systems on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.realzero.org.uk/"&gt;Read about minimising leaks and carbon emissions from refrigeration systems on the Real Zero website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stationary-refrigeration-air-conditioning-and-heat-pumps-ods-controls"&gt;Stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pumps: ODS controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ozone-depleting substances (ODS) were once widely used in the manufacture of refrigeration and air conditioning systems. The substances most commonly used were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hydrochlorofluorcarbons (HCFCs), including HCFC blends&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;halons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some cases, refrigeration equipment also used insulating foam that contained ODS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The supply and use of CFCs and halons in refrigeration equipment is banned throughout the European Union (EU). This means that you can’t use them in the manufacture of new equipment or to maintain existing equipment. If you have equipment designed to use CFCs, you should have stopped using this type of refrigerant by either retro-filling existing systems with an alternative or replacing old equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virgin HCFCs can’t be used in any new refrigeration equipment or to maintain and service existing systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For plant maintenance until 31 December 2014 you may use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reclaimed HCFC refrigerants that have been labelled as reclaimed with information on the batch number and details of the reclamation facility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recycled HCFC refrigerants recovered from similar equipment by those carrying out the servicing operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture or maintain refrigeration equipment you must make sure you don’t use banned ODS. You should always try to use alternatives to CFCs and HCFCs, such as hydrofluorocarbons. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29101.pdf"&gt;download guidance on CFC and HCFC phase-out and alternatives in refrigeration and air conditioning systems from the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you own or operate stationary refrigeration or air conditioning equipment you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use only permitted refrigerants in servicing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make efforts to prevent, minimise and repair any refrigerant leaks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure ODS are recovered when servicing, maintaining and decommissioning equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow only qualified technicians to maintain and decommission equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transport ODS in refillable containers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;label containers as reclaimed ODS, with the batch number and source of the ODS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="test-for-leaks"&gt;Test for leaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must test for leaks regularly - how often you are required to check (using certified personnel) depends on the type of system and the quantity of ODS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Frequency&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Normal systems&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Systems labelled as hermetically sealed&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 3 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 6 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Annual&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Six-monthly*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Quarterly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;*Half this frequency if fitted with automatic leak detection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system must be checked within a month after a leak has been repaired to ensure that the repair has been effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hold-qualifications-to-work-with-ods"&gt;Hold qualifications to work with ODS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must hold a minimum qualification to carry out specific tasks on certain types of refrigeration and air conditioning equipment if it contains ODS. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/216/schedule/1/made"&gt;Find a list of qualifications in schedule 1 of the Ozone-Depleting Substances (Qualifications) Regulations 2009 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="dispose-of-refrigeration-equipment-containing-ods-safely"&gt;Dispose of refrigeration equipment containing ODS safely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dispose of equipment containing ODS you must comply with the duty of care for waste and use a specialist fridge disposal business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wastedirectory.org.uk/"&gt;Find licensed waste sites on the NetRegs Waste Directory website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, local traders or charities may accept refrigeration equipment that is in good working order. Check your local telephone directory for details. Refrigeration units may be refurbished for sale anywhere within the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils do not have to accept waste refrigeration equipment from businesses, but they may be able to offer advice. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://online.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/findcontactbrowse?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;topicId=1074537118"&gt;Find contact details for your local authority in our Contacts Directory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-protection-equipment-f-gas-controls"&gt;Fire protection equipment: F-gas controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) are used in certain types of fire protection systems - such as specialised buildings serving computers or telecommunications. F-gases used in fire protection systems include hydrofluorocarbons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of perfluorocarbons in firefighting equipment is now banned, except for military and aviation uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="responsibility-for-f-gas-obligations-1"&gt;Responsibility for F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the key F-gas duties lie with the operator. An operator is a person or business who has actual power over the technical functioning of the equipment. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;free access to the system, eg supervising its components or functioning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;control over the day-to-day running or function&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;powers, including financial, to decide on technical modifications, F-gas quantity modifications or have repairs carried out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The owner of the equipment is usually the operator unless such functions have been transferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="key-f-gas-obligations-1"&gt;Key F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an operator of fire protection equipment, you must comply with a number of obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevent leakage - where it is technically possible and does not involve disproportionate cost, you must prevent leakage of F-gas from stationary fire protection systems and repair any discovered leaks as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check for leaks regularly - how often you are required to check (using certified personnel) depends on the quantity of F-gases in the system and whether a leak detection system has been installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leak-testing-frequencies-1"&gt;Leak testing frequencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Frequency&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Normal systems&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Systems labelled as hermetically sealed&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 3 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Less than 6 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Annual&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 kilograms - 29 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Six-monthly*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 kilograms - 299 kilograms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Quarterly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300 kilograms or more&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;*Half this frequency if fitted with automatic leak detection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system must be checked within a month after a leak has been repaired to ensure that the repair has been effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install automatic leak detection systems - you must fit a leak detection system to equipment with 300 kilograms or more of F-gases is fitted with a leakage detection system. This system must be checked once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing in accordance with the BS EN15004 standard will satisfy the F-gas obligations, as all gaseous fire protection systems should be checked every six months to meet the standard’s requirements. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://shop.bsigroup.com/en/ProductDetail/Post.aspx?id=161025&amp;amp;epslanguage=EN&amp;amp;pid=000000000030116814"&gt;Find BS EN15004 information on the British Standards Institution (BSI) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintain records - you must keep records on systems with 3 kilograms or more of F-gases including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quantity and type of F-gas in the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantity of F-gas added to the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantity of F-gas recovered through servicing, maintenance and disposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identity of business or personnel servicing or maintaining the system, and the dates and results of leak checks and leak detection system checks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recover gases - if F-gases are removed from any fire protection system or fire extinguisher, they must be properly recovered by appropriately certified personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold personnel qualifications - any personnel carrying out leak checking, gas recovery, installation, maintenance or servicing of equipment containing F-gases must hold an appropriate recognised qualification issued in the UK or the rest of the European Union (EU). &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fia.uk.com/en/Training/"&gt;Read about the F-gas fire protection system qualification on the Fire Industry Authority (FIA) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person physically taking delivery of F-gas containers does not need to be qualified unless they also perform servicing or repair work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold company certificates - businesses that install, maintain or service the equipment must also hold a company certificate. The designated certification body in Great Britain is the FIA. To get a company certificate you must be able to show your staff hold the correct F-gas qualification, you have the correct tools and procedures available and you have enough staff to cover the work you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labelling - new systems must be correctly labelled, stating the type and quantity of refrigerant used. The label must be located near to the service point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit reports - producers, importers or exporters of more than 1 tonne per year of F-gases must complete a report and send it to the European Commission and the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra). This is only relevant for imports from and exports to countries outside the EU. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;Find the F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t use non-refillable containers - use of non-refillable containers for transporting and storing F-gases is banned. The placing on the market of non-refillable containers is banned, except for those manufactured (filled with F-gas) before 4 July 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/fire-protection/"&gt;find further guidance on F-gas obligations relating to fire protection equipment on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-protection-equipment-ods-controls"&gt;Fire protection equipment: ODS controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ozone-deleting substances (ODS) were once used widely in firefighting equipment. Halons were used to fill equipment like hand-held fire extinguishers and built-in total flooding systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of halons in firefighting equipment is now banned, except for military and aviation uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ods-obligations"&gt;ODS obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you discover any old firefighting equipment filled with halons or other ODS you must decommission it and dispose of the equipment safely as hazardous waste. Fire extinguishers should be labelled on the outside with what they are filled with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29105.pdf"&gt;download guidance on the phasing out of halons from the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website (PDF, 361K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To decommission fire protection systems and fire extinguishers, you must use a technician who holds the following qualifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;British Fire Protection Systems Association Competence Certificate Course, Class I&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fire industry Competence Certificate Course, Class I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must dispose of the equipment as hazardous waste at a licensed facility. See our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;topicId=1080466581"&gt;managing your hazardous waste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wastedirectory.netregs.gov.uk/"&gt;search a directory of authorised waste sites on the NetRegs Waste Directory website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mobile-air-conditioning-f-gas-controls"&gt;Mobile air conditioning: F-gas controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are legal controls on fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) in mobile air conditioning (MAC) equipment in cars and light vans. These will affect your business if you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;manufacture cars or vans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supply MAC or refrigerant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maintain cars and vans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;service MAC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="servicing-and-dismantling-obligations"&gt;Servicing and dismantling obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you service and dismantle MAC systems already installed in vehicles, you must comply with a number of obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recover gases - only appropriately qualified personnel must remove F-gases from MAC systems during maintenance and at the end of the vehicle’s life to ensure the F-gases are recycled, reclaimed or destroyed. You must also recover residual F-gases from refillable and non-refillable containers to ensure they are recycled, reclaimed or destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check and repair leaks - it is good practice to check for leaks in MAC systems regularly. If you find abnormal leakage you must not refill the system until the leak is repaired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t use non-refillable containers - use of non-refillable containers for transporting and storing F-gases is banned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have qualified personnel - any personnel carrying out F-gas recovery from MAC equipment during servicing or dismantling must have an appropriate qualification. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-mac5.pdf"&gt;Download MAC qualification and certification guidance from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) website (PDF, 211K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your business must not take delivery of F-gas containers unless your personnel who recover gases are appropriately qualified. The person physically taking delivery of F-gas containers does not need to be qualified unless they also perform servicing, repair or recovery work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-vehicle-obligations"&gt;New vehicle obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must not sell new cars or light vans fitted with air-conditioning systems containing refrigerants with a global warming potential of more than 150 unless they meet refrigerant leakage rates for their air conditioning systems. These are 40 grams per year for single evaporator systems and 60 grams per year for dual evaporator systems. The use of these refrigerants will be phased out between 2011 and 2017, by vehicle type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key refrigerant affected is HFC-134a. It is also called Genetron 134a, HFA-134a, HFC-134a, Forane 134a, KLEA 134a, R-134a, Suva 134a and Norflurane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/mobile-air-conditioning/"&gt;find guidance for MAC service and manufacturers on complying with F-gas regulations on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="solvent-cleaning-f-gas-and-ods-controls"&gt;Solvent cleaning: F-gas and ODS controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solvent users need to comply with certain fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gas) and ozone-depleting substance (ODS) obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ods-obligations-1"&gt;ODS obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of solvents containing ODS is banned for any solvent cleaning activities, eg of electronic circuit boards, high precision metal components (used in sectors like aerospace) and optical components. This includes hydrochlorofluorocarbons, chlorofluorocarbons, 1,1,1-trichloroethane, chlorobromomethane and carbon tetrachloride. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29104.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on phasing out of ozone-depleting solvents from the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website (PDF, 353K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you discover any ozone-depleting solvents you must dispose of them safely as hazardous waste. See our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;topicId=1080466581"&gt;managing your hazardous waste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="f-gas-obligations"&gt;F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfluorocarbons (PFCs) and certain hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs) such as HFC-4310mee and HFC-365mfc are used as solvents and are covered by F-gas obligations. Trade names for these products include Vertrel, Lenium ‘F’ Series, Solvokane, Electrolube and Flutec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some F-gas solvents have a high global warming potential (GWP). GWP measures the strength of a gas in warming the atmosphere. This is a measure of how many times more powerful the gas is in contributing to global warming than CO2. CO2 has a GWP of one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should check with your supplier whether you use solvents containing F-gases that are covered by F-gas regulations and what the GWP of the solvent is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the GWP of a solvent is at or near 150 as it is used its GWP may increase above the 150 threshold and the obligations in the F-gas regulations will apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use F-gas solvents covered by F-gas regulations you must comply with a number of obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recover solvent - only appropriately qualified personnel must recover F-gas solvent from equipment during plant servicing and maintenance and at their end of life. You must also send recovered solvents for reprocessing or destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t knowingly release solvents - You must not knowingly release F-gas solvent vapours to the atmosphere or pour solvents into the drains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold personnel qualifications - any personnel carrying out solvent recovery activities must hold an appropriate recognised qualification issued in the UK or the rest of the European Union (EU). The designated certification body is Fraser Technologies Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your business must not take delivery of F-gas containers unless your personnel who recover solvents are appropriately qualified. The person physically taking delivery does not need to be qualified unless they also perform recovery work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-sv1.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas guidance for businesses using cleaning solvents from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) website (PDF, 87K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="specialist-uses-of-f-gases-and-ods"&gt;Specialist uses of F-gases and ODS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some specialist manufacturing activities use fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) or ozone-depleting substances (ODS). Ensure that you comply with any F-gas or ODS obligations that apply to your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="metered-dose-inhalers-mdis-and-electronics-manufacturers"&gt;Metered dose inhalers (MDIs) and electronics manufacturers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture or supply MDIs, or produce electronics components, you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;report annually to the European Commission if you are directly importing more than 1 tonne of F-gas from outside the European Union (EU), and send a copy to the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recover any F-gas fluid at the end of life of containers used to supply F-gases, but not MDIs themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;employ appropriately qualified staff if you perform recovery work and take delivery of containers of F-gas - the person physically taking delivery doesn’t need to be qualified if they don’t perform recovery work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-mdi1.pdf"&gt;download F-gas guidance for MDI suppliers from the Defra website (PDF, 76K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-e1.pdf"&gt;download F-gas guidance for electronics manufacturers from the Defra website (PDF, 76K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;find the F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="aerosols-and-one-component-foam-ocf"&gt;Aerosols and One Component Foam (OCF)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OCF manufacturers must no longer use F-gases. OCF importers and distributors must not source OCF manufactured after 4 July 2008 that contain F-gases. Retailers must not sell OCF containing F-gas if it was manufactured after 4 July 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using F-gas as a propellant in novelty aerosols is also banned. However, it can still be used in technical aerosols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-ocf1.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas guidance for OCF suppliers from the Defra website (PDF, 70K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="magnesium-smelters-and-sand-casters"&gt;Magnesium smelters and sand casters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die casters are banned from using sulphur hexafluoride (SF6), except where they use less than 850 kilograms per year (kg/year). If you are a magnesium smelter or sand caster using less than 850kg/year of SF6, you should still consider using an alternative gas. This will have less impact on global warming and may also save you money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your business performs recovery work and takes delivery of F-gas containers you must employ appropriately qualified personnel to do such work. The person physically taking delivery doesn’t need to be qualified if they don’t perform recovery work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import or export more than 1 tonne of F-gases, you must report any relevant data about the quantities to the European Commission. You must also send a copy to Defra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-mg1.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas guidance for magnesium smelters, sand casters and die casters from the Defra website (PDF, 70K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="insulation-foam"&gt;Insulation foam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you produce or use insulation foam containing F-gases or ODS, you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not use chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) or hydrochlorofluorocarbon (HCFC) blowing agents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recover blowing agent from waste containers used to supply F gases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recover blowing agent at the end of life of containers used to supply F-gases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recover F-gas and ODS from waste foam, where this is technically possible and does not entail disproportionate cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;comply with obligations relating to labelling, training and taking deliveries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you directly import more than 1 tonne per year of F-gas, or preparations containing F-gas where the preparation has a global warming potential of 150 or more, for use in foam production from outside the EU, you must report it to the European Commission. You must also send a copy of the report to Defra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-fm1.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas guidance for the foam blowing sector from the Defra website (PDF, 86K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fumigation"&gt;Fumigation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of methyl bromide is banned. You are only allowed to use methyl bromide in emergencies, where unexpected outbreaks of particular pests and diseases occur. To use methyl bromide in an emergency you must first gain approval from the Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive Chemicals Regulation Directorate (CRD) and have the support of Defra to apply for an authorisation from the European Commission. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pesticides.gov.uk/corporate.asp?id=74"&gt;Find CRD contact details on the CRD website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use methyl bromide you or your supervisor must have completed specific British Pest Control Association (BPCA) training modules that relate to the work. For further details, contact the BPCA Training Officer on Tel 01332 225113.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="high-voltage-switchgear"&gt;High voltage switchgear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High voltage switchgear is mainly used in the electricity supply industry. If you operate high voltage switchgear that contains SF6 you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recover SF6 correctly from switchgear and SF6 containers during maintenance and at end of life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;employ appropriately qualified personnel if you perform recovery work and take delivery of SF6 containers - the person physically taking delivery doesn’t need to be qualified if they don’t perform recovery work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensure new switchgear is fitted with clear labels that state the type and quantity of SF6, and that the equipment contains an F-gas with a high global warming potential&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not use non-refillable containers for transporting or storing SF6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is good practice to keep records for switchgear containing 3 kilograms or more of F-gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/high-voltage-switchgear/"&gt;find further F-gas information for high voltage switchgear operators and servicers on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="producing-and-supplying-fluids-f-gas-and-ods-controls"&gt;Producing and supplying fluids: F-gas and ODS controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture, import, export or supply fluids containing fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) or ozone-depleting substances (ODS) you must comply with a number of obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="key-f-gas-obligations-2"&gt;Key F-gas obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you produce, or import into or export out of the European Union, more than 1 tonne of F-gas per year, you must report to the European Commission before 31 March each year. You must present the information in a standard template. You must also send a copy to the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra). &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;Find the F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must label F-gas containers ‘placed on the market’ showing the type and quantity of fluid. Labels must show the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;text ‘contains fluorinated greenhouse gases covered by the Kyoto Protocol’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abbreviated chemical names of the F-gases contained&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantity of F-gases in kilograms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;text ‘hermetically sealed’ where applicable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must make sure that the label is clearly legible, in English and securely fixed to the container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other obligations relating to labels and instruction manuals. For further information, contact &lt;a href="mailto:fgas-support@enviros.com"&gt;F-gas Support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluid retained in the container must be properly removed by certified personnel at the end of the container’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All personnel, including contractors or subcontractors, who carry out F-gas handling and recovery activities must be properly qualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your business checks for leaks, maintains or services refrigeration, air conditioning, heat pump equipment or fire protection systems containing F-gases, or recovers F-gas from certain types of equipment, you can only take delivery of F-gas if the personnel doing the work are appropriately qualified. The person physically taking delivery doesn’t need to be qualified if they don’t perform recovery work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of non-refillable containers for transporting or storing F-gas is banned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="key-ods-obligations"&gt;Key ODS obligations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases the import and export of ODS is banned. Where they are permitted, trade can only be conducted with approved countries. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/faq.htm#article5"&gt;check a list of countries approved for trade in ODS on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can only import and export ODS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for laboratory and analytical uses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be used as a feedstock or as a processing agent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be destroyed and reclaimed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for metered dose inhalers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for critical uses, eg halons in firefighting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for emergency use (methyl bromide)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must not import products and equipment, such as refrigerators, that contain or rely on banned substances unless they are products containing hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs) to be repackaged and subsequently re-exported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importers of HCFCs or products and equipment that contain or rely on HCFCs need a licence. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/ods_import.htm"&gt;find out how to become a licensed importer of ODS on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products and equipment that contain or rely on ODS cannot be exported unless they are for laboratory, analytical or destruction purposes. Some metered dose inhalers containing chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) can also be exported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are able to export your goods you will need a licence. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/ods_export.htm"&gt;find out how to become a licensed exporter of ODS on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only ODS you can repackage and export for these purposes are HCFCs until 31 December 2020. The HCFCs must have been repackaged before 31 December 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you repackage and export HCFCs you must have a licence from the European Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture or supply chemical substances you must comply with the Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations (CHIP) and the Classification, Labelling and Packaging of Substances and Mixtures (CLP) Regulation. See the page on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1087521619&amp;amp;r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;classifying and labelling chemicals&lt;/a&gt; in our guide &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;topicId=1087520983"&gt;hazardous substance responsibilities for chemical manufacturers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-f-gas-and-ods-regulations-are-enforced"&gt;How F-gas and ODS regulations are enforced&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several organisations enforce the fluorinated greenhouse gas (F-gas) and ozone-depleting substance (ODS) regulations. If you do not comply you can be fined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations regulating F-gas and ODS equipment and processes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulating organisation Type of equipment/machinery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils
Commercial and retail businesses/
Industrial sites not covered by the Environment Agency&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environment Agency
Industrial facilities with environmental permits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills
Offshore oil, gas, water and wind installations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulating organisations can ensure compliance with F-gas and ODS legislation by serving information notices, enforcement notices or prohibition notices. Failure to comply with a notice can result in a fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-notices"&gt;Information notices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These may be issued to people by regulators in order to obtain further information within set deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enforcement-notices"&gt;Enforcement notices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulators issue enforcement notices if they suspect that businesses are in breach of the regulations. They include a description of the problem, how it can be solved and the date by which it must be fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="prohibition-notices"&gt;Prohibition notices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulators can serve prohibition notices if they believe specific requirements of the regulations have been or are in danger of being breached, leading to an imminent danger of serious pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prohibition notices include a description of the problem, how it can be solved and the date by which it must be fixed. They may require you to take action immediately. Prohibition notices can include an order to close down a piece of equipment or a whole site. They will explain the damage that pollution is causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="advice-and-guidance"&gt;Advice and guidance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;F-gas Support provide targeted advice and guidance to help businesses comply with their legal requirements. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/"&gt;Find F-gas Support contact details on the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="f-gas-and-ods-environmental-legislation"&gt;F-gas and ODS environmental legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page provides links to the full text of key pieces of environmental legislation relating to fluorinated greenhouse gases (F-gases) and ozone-depleting substances (ODS). The websites hosting the legislation may list amendments separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are setting up an environmental management system (EMS) for your business, you can use this list to start compiling your legal register. Your legal adviser or environmental consultant will be able to tell you if other environmental legislation applies to your specific business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about EMS, see our guide on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.l1=1079068363&amp;amp;r.l2=1086048482&amp;amp;r.l3=1084058363&amp;amp;topicId=1079422683"&gt;environmental management systems (EMS) - the basics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="f-gas-legislation"&gt;F-gas legislation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Community (EC) Regulation on certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 842/2006. Aims to reduce emissions of fluorinated greenhouse gases through measures for their containment, use, recovery and destruction. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2006:161:0001:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Find the EC F-gases Regulation on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing the format for the report to be submitted by producers, importers and exporters of certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 1493/2007. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32007R1493:EN:HTML"&gt;Find EC Regulation 1493/2007 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing the form of labels and additional labelling requirements as regards products and equipment containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 1494/2007. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32007R1494:EN:HTML"&gt;Find EC Regulation 1494/2007 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing standard leakage checking requirements for stationary fire protection systems containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 1497/2007.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32007R1497:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 1497/2007 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing standard leakage checking requirements for stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pump equipment containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 1516/2007.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32007R1516:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 1516/2007 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing minimum requirements and the conditions for mutual recognition for the certification of companies and personnel as regards stationary refrigeration, air conditioning and heat pump equipment containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 303/2008.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0303:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 303/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing minimum requirements and the conditions for mutual recognition for the certification of companies and personnel as regards stationary fire protection systems and fire extinguishers containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 304/2008.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0304:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 304/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing minimum requirements and the conditions for mutual recognition for the certification of personnel recovering certain fluorinated greenhouse gases from high-voltage switchgear 305/2008.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0305:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 305/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing minimum requirements and the conditions for mutual recognition for the certification of personnel recovering certain fluorinated greenhouse gas-based solvents from equipment 306/2008.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0306:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 306/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing minimum requirements for training programmes and the conditions for mutual recognition of training attestations for personnel as regards air-conditioning systems in certain motor vehicles containing certain fluorinated greenhouse gases 307/2008.&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0307:EN:HTML"&gt; Find EC Regulation 307/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation establishing the format for notification of training and certification programmes 308/2008. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0308:EN:HTML"&gt;Find EC Regulation 308/2008 on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fluorinated Greenhouse Gas Regulations SI 2009/261. Replaces and amends the Fluorinated Greenhouse Gas Regulations 2008. Creates offences and penalties for not complying with recovery of F-gases legislation, labelling, qualifications and certificates required to work with products or equipment containing them. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/261/contents/made"&gt;Find the Fluorinated Greenhouse Gas Regulations 2009 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Motor Vehicles (Refilling of Air Conditioning Systems by Service Providers) Regulations SI 2009/2194. Makes it an offence (for which you can be fined) for anyone servicing a vehicle air-conditioning system to refill it with fluorinated gases if there has been an abnormal leak of refrigerant and before repairs have been completed. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/2194/contents/made"&gt;Find the Motor Vehicles (Refilling of Air Conditioning Systems by Service Providers) Regulations 2009 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Road Vehicles (Construction and Use) Regulations SI 1986/1078. Lays down requirements to reduce the environmental impact of constructing, maintaining and using road vehicles, particularly smoke, vapour and gas emissions. Not available online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Road Vehicles (Construction and Use) (Amendment) (No. 3) Regulations SI 2009/2196. Amends 1986/1078 by inserting a new regulation which restricts the retrofitting and refilling of vehicle air conditioning systems containing F-gases. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/2196/contents/made"&gt;Find the Road Vehicles (Construction and Use) (Amendment) (No. 3) Regulations 2009 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="ods-legislation"&gt;ODS legislation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EC regulation on ozone-depleting substances 1005/2009. Allows governments to impose new requirements on handling, use, import, export, recovery, recycling, reclaiming, destruction and trading of listed substances. Sets out plans to phase out production, trade and use of hydrochlorofluorocarbons. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:286:0001:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Find the EC ODS Regulation on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EC Regulation 744/2010 amending EC Regulation 1005/2009 on ozone-depleting substances. Bans the use of halons in firefighting equipment except for military and aviation uses. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32010R0744:EN:HTML"&gt;Find the EC ODS Amending Regulation on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ozone-Depleting Substances (Qualifications) Regulations SI 2009/216. Amends qualifications needed to recover, recycle or destroy ODS. Makes it an offence to, or employ someone to, work with controlled substances or methyl bromide unless qualified. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2009/216/contents/made"&gt;Find the Ozone-Depleting Substances (Qualifications) Regulations 2009 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environmental Protection (Controls on Ozone-Depleting Substances) Regulations SI 2011/1543. Replaces the Environmental Protection (Controls on Ozone-Depleting Substances) Regulations 2002 (as amended), and enforces the provisions of EC Regulation 1005/2009. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/1543/contents/made"&gt;Find the Environmental Protection (Controls on Ozone-Depleting Substances) Regulations 2011 on the Legislation.gov.uk website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/current/63594.aspx"&gt;Find other current environmental legislation that may affect your business on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/future/63657.aspx"&gt;Find guidance about future environmental legislation on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information-1"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fraser-technology-helpline"&gt;Fraser Technology Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;01506 443 058&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/"&gt;F-gas information on the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-gen3.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas markets and equipment information from the Defra website (PDF, 97K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fgas.org/page/1/home"&gt;F-gas industry information on the FGAS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/ozone/index.htm"&gt;Ozone layer information on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/index.htm"&gt;Ozone layer protection initiatives explained on the Europa website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/srac/"&gt;F-gases in RAC systems information on the Defra website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.realzero.org.uk/"&gt;Minimising leaks and carbon emissions from refrigeration systems explained on the Real Zero website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29101.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on CFC and HCFC phase-out and alternatives in refrigeration and air-conditioning systems from the BIS website (PDF, 360K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29100.pdf"&gt;Download ODS in refrigeration and air conditioning advice for suppliers and users from the BIS website (PDF, 584K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/fire-protection/"&gt;F-gas information for fire protection equipment operators on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fia.uk.com/en/Training/"&gt;Fire Industry Authority training course information on the FIA website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thefpa.co.uk/Services/Training/Training+Introduction.htm"&gt;Fire safety training details on the Fire Protection Association website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://wastedirectory.netregs.gov.uk/"&gt;Licensed waste site directory on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29105.pdf"&gt;Halons phase-out guidance for firefighting equipment on the BIS website (PDF, 361K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/mobile-air-conditioning/"&gt;F-gas information for MAC servicers and manufacturers on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file29104.pdf"&gt;Download phasing out of ozone-depleting solvents guidance from the BIS website (PDF, 353K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://archive.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/documents/fgassupport-sv1.pdf"&gt;Download F-gas guidance for businesses using cleaning solvents from the Defra website (PDF, 87K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/specialist-sectors/"&gt;F-gas use and supply guidance for specialist sectors on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ec.europa.eu/environment/climat/fluor/reporting_en.htm"&gt;F-gas standard reporting template on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/environment/quality/air/fgas/high-voltage-switchgear/"&gt;F-gas information for high voltage switchgear operators and servicers on the Defra website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/faq.htm#article5"&gt;Countries approved for trade in ODS listed on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/ods_import.htm"&gt;ODS import guidance on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/ozone/ods_export.htm"&gt;ODS export guidance on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/current/63594.aspx"&gt;Current environmental legislation lists on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/legislation/future/63657.aspx"&gt;Future environmental legislation guidance on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56666</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england"/>
    <title>Boosting private sector employment in England</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Supporting businesses to create and protect jobs in the private sector, particularly where public sector employment is reducing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain parts of the country are too dependent on the public sector for employment. The government wants to increase the number of lasting, private sector jobs - by supporting the private sector to expand and ensuring that government cash delivers jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re funding large projects that have the potential to create or protect long-term jobs in the private sector, and programmes where partner organisations choose smaller projects to support, which will deliver sustainable jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re doing this through the Regional Growth Fund (&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt;). We have a total of £2.46 billion to give to businesses by 2016 to spend on projects such as capital investment, research and development, or training. (Please note: businesses cannot currently apply to the fund.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects we’ve chosen must attract private funding to match the public funding we provide, and the projects that programmes choose to support must also include investment of private money. We provide grants, loans and loan guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt; is a competitive fund – this means that in order to get our support, businesses must apply during a bidding round explaining how much money they need and what they will use it for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bids are then considered by an expert panel who recommend to ministers which bids to support. Ministers then choose the bids that they believe will give the best value for money to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cross-government fund and is jointly administered by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detail, see &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/understanding-the-regional-growth-fund"&gt;Understanding the Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money was allocated in 3 rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-1-april-2011"&gt;Round 1, April 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£450 million was allocated to 50 bids, attracting £2.5 billion in private sector investment. The projects will create or safeguard over 27,000 direct jobs, with around 100,000 more in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-2-october-2011"&gt;Round 2, October 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£950 million was invested in 126 bids, attracting nearly £6 billion of private investment. Around 200,000 jobs will be created or protected: around 37,000 direct jobs, with more than 164,000 in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-3-october-2012"&gt;Round 3: October 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£1.055 billion was allocated to 130 bids, attracting £6 billion of private investment. The projects will create or safeguard 240,000 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="process"&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations had to apply for a minimum of £1 million funding. Projects were assessed on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value for money for taxpayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ability to create jobs in the private sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;project management expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;state aid rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Projects had to comply with the &lt;a href="/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/supporting-pages/state-aid-rules"&gt;EU’s rules on state aid&lt;/a&gt; to make sure any funding did not give a company an unfair competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/r/12-1291-regional-growth-fund-confirmatory-due-diligence.pdf"&gt;Regional growth fund - confirmatory due diligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/d/declaration-for-due-diligence-providers.doc"&gt;Regional growth fund - declaration for due diligence providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64070</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T18:18:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-junior-staff-numbers-and-payscales-30-september-2012"/>
    <title>BIS junior staff numbers and payscales: 30 September 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>
BIS junior staff numbers and pay, as of 30 September 2012 
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to setting new standards for transparency so the public can more easily see how and where taxpayers’ money is being spent and hold politicians, government departments and public bodies to account.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64069</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T18:18:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-senior-staff-posts-and-pay-30-september-2012"/>
    <title>BIS senior staff posts and pay: 30 September 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>BIS senior staff posts and pay, as of 30 September 2012. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to setting new standards for transparency so the public can more easily see how and where taxpayers’ money is being spent and hold politicians, government departments and public bodies to account.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64022</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T17:09:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-finance-guarantee"/>
    <title>Enterprise Finance Guarantee</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) is a loan guarantee scheme to facilitate additional lending to viable small and medium size enterprises lacking adequate security or proven track record for a normal commercial loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Enterprise Finance Guarantee Scheme was launched in January 2009 to facilitate additional lending to viable businesses lacking adequate security or proven track record for a standard commercial loan. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over 19,700 SMEs have been offered EFG loans with a total value in excess of £2 billion. 
EFG is a demand led scheme complimentary to commercial lending – not a replacement. EFG accounts for 1% to 2% of total SME lending.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Businesses that meet the basic eligibility criteria do not have an automatic entitlement to receive an EFG guaranteed loan.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decision making on individual loans is fully delegated to the participating lenders and is integrated with the commercial decision to lend. Where the lender determines the business is viable (able to meet the monthly loan repayments and repay the loan in full) but is lacking adequate security to meet the lenders standard lending requirements, they can consider providing a loan under EFG. The government plays no role in the loan decision process. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government provides the lender with a guarantee for 75% of each individual loan, subject to a cap set by an Annual Claim Limit. The borrower pays a 2% per annum pro-rata premium to BIS as a contribution towards the cost of providing the government guarantee. The borrower is responsible for repayment of 100% of the loan, not just the 25% outside the coverage of the government guarantee. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the case of default, lenders are required to follow their standard commercial recovery procedures, including the realisation of available security before a claim can be made against the guarantee. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under EFG, lenders are entitled to take security, including personal guarantees. This is standard commercial practice and an established mechanism for ensuring a degree of personal commitment to repayment of the loan by the business. In EFG this means there is a three-way risk sharing between borrower, lender and the government. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lenders are expressly prohibited from taking a charge over a principal private residence for an EFG facility. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="efg-eligibility-criteria"&gt;EFG eligibility criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses that meet the basic eligibility criteria do not have an automatic entitlement to receive an EFG guaranteed loan. Eligibility for EFG will be determined by the lender. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a guideline only. EFG is open to viable businesses that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;operate in the UK &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have a turnover of up to £41 million &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are seeking finance between £1,000 and £1million &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repayment terms from 3 months to 10 years (less for overdraft and invoice finance facilities) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;operate in a sector that is eligible for EFG (most sectors are eligible) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EFG is subject to certain sector restrictions arising from the EU de minimis State Aid rules under which it operates. A list of the main sector restrictions is provided in the EFG Business Sectors attachment below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_68436"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48812/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Business_Sectors_and_Purposes.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68436-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48812/thumbnail_Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Business_Sectors_and_Purposes.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48812/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Business_Sectors_and_Purposes.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68436-accessibility-help"&gt;Enterprise Finance Guarantee Business Sectors and Purposes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;35.6 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;6 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-68436-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20Business%20Sectors%20and%20Purposes%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20Business%20Sectors%20and%20Purposes%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Enterprise Finance Guarantee Business Sectors and Purposes").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Industrial Development Act 1982 provides the legal basis for EFG. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that neither BIS nor Capital for Enterprise Ltd (CfEL) who oversees the running of EFG on behalf of BIS can advise on individual eligibility queries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="types-of-efg-facilities-available"&gt;Types of EFG facilities available&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following facilities are available under EFG, repayable over a period of 3 months to 10 years unless otherwise stated: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new term loans (unsecured and partially secured) for working capital or investment purposes including R&amp;amp;D. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;refinancing of existing term loans, where the loan is at risk due to deteriorating value of security or where for cash flow reasons the borrower is struggling to meet existing loan repayments. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conversion of part of or all an existing utilised overdraft onto a term loan in order to release capacity in the overdraft to meet working capital requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invoice finance guarantee providing a guarantee on invoice finance facilities to support an agreed additional advance on a SMEs debtor book, to supplement the invoice finance facility on commercial terms already in place (available for terms up to three years). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overdraft guarantee providing a guarantee on new or increased overdraft borrowing where the SME is viable but has inadequate security to meet a lender’s normal requirements for the level of overdraft requested (available for terms up to two years). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that participating lenders are under no obligation to offer the full range of products. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="application-process"&gt;Application process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses seeking debt finance can approach one or more of the participating lenders shown in the attachment below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_68440"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48816/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_List_of_Lenders.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68440-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48816/thumbnail_Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_List_of_Lenders.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48816/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_List_of_Lenders.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68440-accessibility-help"&gt;Enterprise Finance Guarantee List of Lenders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;15.4 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;2 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-68440-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20List%20of%20Lenders%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20List%20of%20Lenders%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Enterprise Finance Guarantee List of Lenders").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;EFG loans typically require all the same information that banks need to process a commercial loan application. Participating lenders will advise you of their specific requirements (failure to provide the required information may delay the loan decision or lead to a loan decline). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders will typically assess loan applications against their standard lending criteria to determine whether they wish to lend. Where the lender determines the business is viable (able to meet the monthly loan repayments and repay the loan in full) but is lacking adequate security to meet the lenders normal lending requirements, they can consider providing a loan under EFG. The government plays no role in the loan decision process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the lender has determined that use of EFG is likely to be appropriate, they confirm eligibility and record details of the borrower and their facility via a secure Web Portal. An overview of the EFG application process is available below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_68441"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48817/EFG_Backed_Loan_Application_Process.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68441-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48817/thumbnail_EFG_Backed_Loan_Application_Process.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48817/EFG_Backed_Loan_Application_Process.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68441-accessibility-help"&gt;EFG Backed Loan Application Process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;365 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;2 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-68441-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20EFG%20Backed%20Loan%20Application%20Process%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27EFG%20Backed%20Loan%20Application%20Process%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("EFG Backed Loan Application Process").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Businesses that do not meet the lenders viability requirements are not suitable for EFG. EFG is intended to support lending to businesses which can ultimately repay their loan in full, not prop up unviable businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-government-guarantee"&gt;The government guarantee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By providing lenders with a government-backed guarantee for 75% of the value of each individual loan, subject to a cap set by an Annual Claim Limit, EFG facilitates lending that would otherwise not take place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guarantee provides protection to the lender in the event of default by the borrower – it is not insurance for the borrower in the event of their inability to repay the loan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The borrower is responsible for repayment of 100% of the EFG facility, not just the 25% outside the coverage of the government guarantee. Where defaults occur, the lender is obliged to follow their standard commercial recovery procedure, including the realisation of security, before they can make a claim against the government guarantee. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the costs and fees charged by the lender, businesses supported under EFG are required to pay an additional 2% annual premium which partially covers the cost of providing the guarantee. The premium is assessed and collected quarterly in advance throughout the life of the loan based on the outstanding capital balance of the loan (for invoice finance and overdraft guarantees the premium is assessed on the agreed facility limit). The borrower is provided with a premium schedule by the lender as part of their loan documentation and collection is made by Direct Debit under the description “BIS LOAN GUARANTEE”. The interest rate charged and any other fees and charges applied to the loan are a commercial matter for the lender. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="security--personal-guarantees"&gt;Security / personal guarantees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under EFG, lenders are entitled to take security, including personal guarantees. This is standard commercial practice and an established mechanism for ensuring a degree of personal commitment to repayment of the loan by the business. In EFG this means there is a three-way risk sharing between borrower, lender and the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When taking security, lenders are required to apply their normal commercial policies in determining the extent and value of security available. The exception from normal commercial practice is that lenders are expressly prohibited from taking a charge over a principal private residence for an EFG facility. 
A personal guarantee should not be taken or attributed, solely or preferentially to cover the 25% of the EFG loan not covered by the Government guarantee. The borrower is liable for repayment of 100% of the loan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EFG should not be seen by borrowers or their advisers as a mechanism for putting personal assets beyond consideration (principal private residence excluded for the purposes of EFG). If the lender refuses to offer EFG on the basis that the borrower had access to security which they were not prepared to put forward, then the lenders decision would be fully supported by BIS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="enterprise-finance-guarantee-further-help"&gt;Enterprise Finance Guarantee: further help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery of EFG, including the decision on whether or not it is appropriate to use it in connection with any specific lending transaction, is fully delegated to the participating lenders. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121017180846/http:/www.capitalforenterprise.gov.uk/" title="Information about Capital for Enterprise Limited"&gt;Capital for Enterprise Limited&lt;/a&gt; oversees the running of EFG on behalf of BIS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="for-lenders"&gt;For lenders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals within a participating lender should contact their central processing team or other designated internal EFG expert who can obtain further information from CfEL if required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="for-businesses"&gt;For businesses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses may wish to consider approaching one or more of the participating lenders to discuss their borrowing needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses that have any issues relating to an EFG loan, including premium collection or alterations to their repayment profile, should raise them with their lender and not with BIS or CfEL. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_68442"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48818/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Statistics.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68442-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48818/thumbnail_Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Statistics.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48818/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_Statistics.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68442-accessibility-help"&gt;Enterprise Finance Guarantee Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;50.1 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;4 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-68442-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20Statistics%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20Statistics%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Enterprise Finance Guarantee Statistics").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_68443"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48819/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_FAQs.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68443-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48819/thumbnail_Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_FAQs.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48819/Enterprise_Finance_Guarantee_FAQs.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-68443-accessibility-help"&gt;Enterprise Finance Guarantee FAQs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;37.4 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;8 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-68443-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20FAQs%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Enterprise%20Finance%20Guarantee%20FAQs%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Enterprise Finance Guarantee FAQs").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="loan-declines-and-complaints"&gt;Loan declines and complaints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that neither BIS nor CfEL will intervene in the commercial relationship between borrower and lender in the event of disputes. Customers dissatisfied with the experience of dealing with their bank should raise their concerns through the bank’s own customer complaints procedure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses that have loan applications declined have the right to appeal the decision. This can be done through banks existing complaints procedures. Further information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121017180846/http:/www.betterbusinessfinance.co.uk/help-support/factsheets/appeals-process" title="Further information on the appeals process"&gt;appeals process is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If businesses do not feel that their complaint has been handled appropriately, those with a turnover of under €2 million and fewer than ten employees have the option of taking their complaint to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121017180846/http:/www.fos.org.uk/" title="Information about the Financial Ombudsman Service"&gt;Financial Ombudsman Service&lt;/a&gt; or on 0845 080 1800. Businesses may also wish to seek legal advice if there is a contractual dispute. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="alternative-sources-of-finance"&gt;Alternative sources of finance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a wide range of financial products and support available from a broad spectrum of providers including banks, business angels, Community Development Finance Institutions, venture capitalists and trade and asset finance specialists. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/6620</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:49:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:49:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"/>
    <title>National Measurement Office</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) - previously known as the National Weights and Measures Laboratory (NWML) - regulates the development and use of weighing and measuring equipment to ensure that weights and measures are accurate, fair and legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain and enforce weights and measures regulations, the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with local authorities’ trading standards departments and inspectors, local weights and measures authorities and approved verifiers of weights and measures equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s consulting services help small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) to develop specific measuring products, processes or services. It also helps SMEs to understand the regulations covering their weighing and measuring instruments and how to comply with the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; still provides services under the name of NWML including product certification, quality management systems certification and calibration services to several sectors of industry and local government, all or most of which have some element of weighing or measuring either in their manufacturing processes or in their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with WELMEC (the European co-operation in legal metrology) and OIML (the International Organisation of Legal Metrology) to maintain UK consumer and business confidence in legal measurement abroad. It also takes part in preparing OIML recommendations and represents the UK at the OIML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide also outlines the work of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority, the part of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; responsible for enforcement work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-work-of-the-national-measurement-office"&gt;The work of the National Measurement Office&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) - previously known as the National Weights and Measures Laboratory (NWML) - is an executive agency of the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is responsible for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;policy on measuring instruments that are used in trade - eg preparing legislation under the Weights and Measures Act 1985 and European Communities Act 1972, and proposals for reforming Weights and Measures Act&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that the UK implements European directives on measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legal metrology - ie requirements for legal verification of measuring instruments - in the UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal metrology makes it possible to buy and sell accurate quantities of goods. Without accurate measurements, there would be no possibility of a fair marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; helps ensure the accuracy of the majority of measuring instruments used for trade and pre-packaged goods in the UK - including pre-packaged goods in supermarkets, check-out scales, petrol pumps and beer glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; provides guidance to industry and the public, and enforces UK and European Union weights and measures legislation. Key regulations include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Weights and Measures Act 1985 and secondary legislation, including the Weights and Measures (Packaged Goods) Regulations 2006&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Deregulation (Weights and Measures) Order 1999&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Measuring Instruments Directive 2004/22/EC and the Non-Automatic Weighing Instruments Regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;, the National Measurement System (NMS) unit is responsible for scientific and industrial metrology. Scientific metrology deals with the organisation, development and maintenance of measurement standards. Industrial metrology ensures the adequate functioning of measurement instruments used in industry, production and testing processes. The NMS carries out its tasks in a UK network of measurement laboratories, which include the National Physical Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=484"&gt;Read information on the National Measurement system on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nwml-services"&gt;NWML Services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NWML Calibration Team, approved under the UK Accreditation Service maintains standards for mass, volume and length measurement. In addition to calibration, NWML provides testing, product and QMS certification services for industry and local authorities - eg local authority Trading Standards. For more information, see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;product certification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also provides a consultancy service to manufacturers that are developing new weighing and measuring equipment. For more information, you can also see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;consultancy and consulting services&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses should be aware that NWML Certification Services is changing its name to &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services as of 1 April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Access the industry service forms offered from the NWML&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nmo-enforcement-authority"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the role of the National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) has expanded to include the enforcement of regulations aimed at protecting the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority, part of the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;, is responsible for enforcing environmental legislation under the Restriction of the Use of Certain Hazardous Substances in Electrical and Electronic Equipment Regulations 2008 (RoHS Regulations) which limits the levels of certain potentially hazardous substances in new electric and electronic equipment for sale in the European Union (EU). &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/rohs-home"&gt;Find out about RoHS on the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enforcement Authority also acts as the UK Batteries Regulations enforcement body, to ensure compliance with the Batteries and Accumulators (Placing on the Market) Regulations 2008. This limits the levels of cadmium and mercury in new batteries for sale within the EU, controls the marking of batteries and sets design requirements for battery-operated electrical and electronic equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/batteries-home"&gt;Find out about the Batteries Regulations on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also the Market Surveillance Authority (MSA), under the EU Energy Using Products (EuP) and Energy Labelling Framework (ELF) Directives. This means the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; ensures that manufactures meet their product claims under energy labelling - eg A-rated fridges - and minimum energy standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/ecodesign"&gt;Find out about EuP on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/elf-home"&gt;Find out about ELF on the Energy Labelling website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-enforcement-partners"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; enforcement partners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with various other public and private sector organisations that help to enforce weights and measures regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the local level, the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; works with the Local Government Regulation (formerly the Local Authorities Coordinators of Regulatory Services), the local government central body responsible for overseeing local authority regulatory and related services in the UK, the Trading Standards Institute and regional groups of local authorities’trading standards departments and inspectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notified bodies are local weights and measurements authorities (LWMA) that assess whether weighing and measuring equipment meets CE marking requirements. CE marking is a manufacturer’s declaration that the product complies with the standards set out in relevant European directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Find a local notified body to evaluate your weighing/measuring equipment with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approved verifiers have permission from the Secretary of State to test, pass, stamp and verify weighing and measuring equipment that they manufacture, install or repair. Approval may be for non-automatic weighing instruments or for measuring instruments that come under the EU Measuring Instruments Directive. A condition of approval is that the verifier operates an acceptable quality system and receives regular audits and inspections from both the LWMA and the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Apply to become an approved verifer with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legal-and-regulatory-activities"&gt;Legal and regulatory activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) works with trading standards departments in local authorities to deliver enforcement of most of the UK’s weights and measures legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weights and measurements regulations help ensure consumers have accurate information about their purchases. This protects them from being sold short measures. The regulations also protect businesses against dishonest competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-enforcement/guidance-and-reference-documents/legislation-guidance-notes"&gt;find weights and measures legislation guidance notes on the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Search for legislation on weights, measures and hallmarking which may affect your business with the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hallmarking"&gt;Hallmarking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is responsible for the sponsorship of the British Hallmarking Council. This involves the testing and marking of items of precious metal to indicate they conform to legal standards of purity (fineness), across four assay offices in the UK (London, Birmingham, Sheffield and Edinburgh).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="water-gas-and-electricity-metering"&gt;Water, gas and electricity metering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; also regulates the metrology of water, gas and electricity meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="better-regulation"&gt;Better regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; complies with Statutory Code of Practice for Regulators (the Regulators’ Compliance Code). This requires regulators to plan regulation and inspections in a way that causes the least disruption to businesses, to impose sanctions and penalties in a transparent and proportionate way and to report annually on their enforcement activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file45019.pdf"&gt;download Regulators’ Compliance Code from the BIS website (PDF, 107K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultancy-and-consulting-services"&gt;Consultancy and consulting services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) offers individually tailored consultancies for UK and international organisations, providing a range of highly skilled engineers and a network of specialist collaborators covering the whole range of legal metrology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It carries out consultations on weights and measures policy and regulatory issues. It has signed up to the government’s Code of Practice on Consultation. This outlines best practice in running public consultation exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file47158.pdf"&gt;download the Code of Practice on Consultation from the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) website (PDF, 223K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=366%20"&gt;find out about previous consultancy projects on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="measurement-for-innovators-scheme"&gt;Measurement for Innovators scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Measurement for Innovators (MfI) scheme is a BIS programme helping small and medium-sized enterprises to develop and improve new weighing and measuring products, processes and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=495"&gt;Find MfI information on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="product-certification"&gt;Product certification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the National Measurement Office (&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;), &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services provides product certification services to businesses and public sector organisations in the UK and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services is a notified body under European directives relating to Non-Automatic Weighing Instruments (NAWI) 2009/23/EC and Measuring Instruments (MID) 2004/22/EC. As a notified body, it can issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European Commission (EC) Type Approval Certificates (TACs) for weighing and measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a range of the International Organisation of Legal Metrology (OIML) certificates of conformity - which bring instrument approval in many countries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK National Approvals - under section 12 of the Weights &amp;amp; Measures Act 1985&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s product certificates cover a wide range of weighing and measuring equipment. If you are unsure whether your product will pass the certification process, you can submit your instruments to &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s pre-assessment service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;apply for pre-assessment with the online industry service forms from the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out about notified bodies, see the page in this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/national-measurement-office"&gt;legal and regulatory activities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nawis"&gt;NAWIs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can issue European TACs for all electronic and most mechanical NAWIs. These are valid throughout Europe. If you want to sell your NAWI outside Europe, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can approve it in accordance with the relevant OIML recommendations. In this case, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; issues an OIML Certificate of Conformity and test report. These are valid in countries which are signed up to the OIML mutual acceptance arrangements (MAAs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to submit your NAWI for &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; certification processes, you will need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fill in an application form - which you can do online&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;forward your supporting documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;send in your equipment for testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To simplify the process, &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can test separate modules of a NAWI and issue individual Test Certificates (TCs). You can quote these TCs in a TAC. This modular approach is useful for indicators, load cells and point of sale devices, and peripheral devices, such as computers and printers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;apply for product certification with the online industry service forms from the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring instruments covered by MID include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automatic weighing instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fuel dispensers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;material measures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;water meters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a period of 10 years from 30 October 2006, existing European Economic Community and UK National TACs will remain valid for instruments that now come under the MID Directive. You can contact the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; to find out how to convert an existing TAC to an MID approval, as well as applying for approval for a new instrument under MID. However, you should note that the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; is not a notified body for gas and electricity meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="temperature-and-humidity-testing-equipment"&gt;Temperature and humidity testing equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; can test and certify temperature testing equipment from 55°C to -25°C, and humidity testing equipment up to 95 per cent relative humidity. You can access the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s environmental test chambers for research or pre-compliance testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="uk-national-type-approvals"&gt;UK National Type approvals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All measuring instruments that are used for trade purposes in the UK require a UK National Type Approval certificate. These include measuring instruments for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intoxicating liquor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dynamic axle weighers - automatic vehicle weighbridges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cubic measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can apply to the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; for product certification or for pre-assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-enquiry-line"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Enquiry Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7272&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lacors-helpline"&gt;LACORS Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 7665 3888&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-direct"&gt;Consumer Direct&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;08454 040 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-measurement-office-enquiry-service"&gt;National Measurement Office Enquiry Service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7227&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-certification-services-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Certification Services Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7282&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="npl-helpline"&gt;NPL Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 6880&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nmo-cubic-measures-type-approval-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Cubic Measures Type Approval Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8943 7294&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://resource.npl.co.uk/international_office/metrologyinshort.pdf"&gt;Download legal metrology introductory guidance from the National Physical Laboratory website (PDF, 1.52MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmo.bis.gov.uk/content.aspx?SC_ID=231"&gt;Services to industry information on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rohs.gov.uk/content.aspx?id=9"&gt;RoHS Regulations, Directives and Guidance and other useful links on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/batteries-home"&gt;Batteries regulations guidance on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/enforcement/ecodesign"&gt;Eco-design of EuPs guidance on the BIS website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oiml.org/"&gt;OIML contact details on the OIML website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.welmec.org/pubs.asp"&gt;Legal metrology guides on the WELMEC website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file45019.pdf"&gt;Download Regulators’ Compliance Code from the BIS website (PDF, 107K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-enforcement/guidance-and-reference-documents/legislation-guidance-notes"&gt;Weights and measures legislation guidance notes on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/packaged-goods"&gt;Weights and Measures (Packaged Goods) Regulations 2006 guidance on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/bispartners/nmo/docs/legislation/legislation/pc-guidance-note-version-3-2009.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the UK’s implementation of a European directive deregulating specified quantities (fixed pack sizes) from the BIS website (PDF, 122K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/metrication"&gt;Guidance on the business use of Metric Units of Measurement and the EC Units of Measurement Directive on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/regulation/weights-and-measures-legislation/equipment-regulation"&gt;Equipment regulated under the Weights and Measures Act explained on the BIS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weights-measures-and-packaging-the-law"&gt;Search our business support finder for grants, loans, expertise and advice for which your business may be eligible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/nmo/certification-services/product-certification/certificates-database"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; MID certificates database on the &lt;abbr title="National Measurement Office"&gt;NMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/bispartners/nmo/docs/services/type-approval/guidance-notes-for-type-examination--consultancy-2.pdf"&gt;Download product certification (type approval) and pre-assessment guidance and requirements from the BIS website (PDF, 95K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61122</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-commenting-on-the-latest-ucas-2013-cycle-applicant-figures"/>
    <title>Press Release: Commenting on the latest UCAS 2013 cycle applicant figures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Department for Business, Innovation and Skills spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is too early to form a definitive picture about university applications for the 2013/14 academic year. Traditionally fewer than 50 per cent of applicants have submitted their applications by this point in the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that no one is put off applying to university because they do not have information about the student support available to them. Most new students will not pay upfront, there will be more financial support for those from poorer families and everyone will make lower loan repayments than they do now once they are in well paid jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/61088</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge: Retail and Manufacturing Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The purpose of this consultation was to seek views on the amendment and removal of statutory instruments which were identified under the Retail and Manufacturing Red Tape Challenge spotlight process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s response to the consultation was published on the 16th July. This confirms the proposals we intend to take forward which include the revocation of the following measures on the 1st October 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imitation Dummies (Safety) Regulations 1993 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas cooking Appliances (Safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating Appliances (Fireguards) (Safety) Regulations 1991 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Catalytic Heaters (safety) Regulations 1984 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All-Terrain Motor Vehicle (safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking Utensils (Safety) Regulations 1972 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indication of Prices (Beds) Order 1978 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child Resistant Packaging and Tactile Danger Warning (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1992 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands for Carry-cots (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1996 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magnetic Toys (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second Government response was published on the 30th November. This confirms the amendment and revocation of the following regulations on the 6 April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
