<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-24T08:30:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60855</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T08:30:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T08:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-repeal-of-the-property-misdescriptions-act-1991"/>
    <title>Consultation on the repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills is seeking views on the possible repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991 (PMA). The PMA makes it an offence to make false or misleading statements in the course of an estate agency or property development business about property offered for sale. The Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (CPRs) provide similar protections for consumers. This duplication may be unnecessary; putting additional burdens on business, without providing additional protection for consumers. The consultation considers whether the Government should repeal the PMA, now that the CPRs are in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/11-505-consultation-repeal-property-misdescriptions-act.pdf"&gt;Consultation on the repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991 (PDF, 304 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/60818</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T16:52:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T16:52:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/processes-for-tackling-anti-competitive-activity--2"/>
    <title>Processes for dealing with anti-competitive activity</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>A guide to how we deal with anti-competitive activity in business. Includes information on competition authorities and sectoral regulation</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets provide the best means of ensuring that the economy’s resources are put to their best use by encouraging enterprise and efficiency, widening choice and contributing to our international competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, timely and effective enforcement is essential to identify any anti-competitive practices or structures that may develop and lead to a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/business_leaflets/general/oft911.pdf"&gt;loss of competition in markets&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/speeches/spe0304.pdf"&gt;abuse of market power&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-competition-authorities"&gt;Current competition authorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills sets the overall policy framework for competition, it is regulated by the UK’s independent competition authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 4 main competition bodies responsible for investigating and enforcing decisions on competition matters in the UK market:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-office-of-fair-trading"&gt;The Office of Fair Trading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/"&gt;Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; is the principal competition authority. Its responsibility is to enforce competition and make markets work well for the benefit of consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; derives most of its powers from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2002/40/contents"&gt;Enterprise Act 2002&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1998/41/contents"&gt;Competition Act 1998&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; investigates mergers and anti-competitive practices in markets and also enforces consumer law – see &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/business_leaflets/competition_law/oft442.pdf"&gt;Modernisation – Understanding Competition Law&lt;/a&gt; for further information. Large mergers with a European dimension may be covered by the European Community Merger Regulation (&lt;abbr title="European Community Merger Regulation"&gt;ECMR&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-competition-commission"&gt;The Competition Commission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Commission (&lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; conducts in-depth inquiries into mergers, markets and the regulation of certain industries such as utilities and communications. However, the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; only undertakes its inquiries where they have been referred by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;, one of the sectoral regulators, or in exceptional circumstances the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-competition-appeal-tribunal"&gt;The Competition Appeal Tribunal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.catribunal.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Appeal Tribunal (&lt;abbr title="Competition Appeal Tribunal"&gt;CAT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; is a specialist judicial body whose function is to hear and rule on appeals of decisions made by the competition authorities. The &lt;abbr title="Competition Appeal Tribunal"&gt;CAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has a cross-disciplinary expertise in law, economics, business, competition and economic regulatory issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-european-commission"&gt;The European Commission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/index_en.html"&gt;European Commission&lt;/a&gt; (Directorate General for Competition) has exclusive powers to act on certain large mergers with a European dimension. It also has powers to investigate anti-competitive practices when trade between members of the European Community, or in some cases the European Economic Area (EEA), is affected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sectoral-regulators"&gt;Sectoral regulators&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of sectoral regulators have a specific role in promoting or facilitating competition within their sectors. Some also have the power to apply the Competition Act 1998 concurrently with the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The regulators with such ‘concurrent powers’ are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofgem.gov.uk/Pages/OfgemHome.aspx"&gt;Ofgem&lt;/a&gt; - in the energy markets &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/"&gt;Ofwat&lt;/a&gt; - in the water industry &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/"&gt;Ofcom&lt;/a&gt; - in the communications sector &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - for railway services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.caa.co.uk/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - in relation to air traffic services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.niaur.gov.uk/"&gt;Utility Regulator&lt;/a&gt; - for gas and electricity in Northern Ireland &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.monitor-nhsft.gov.uk/monitors-new-role"&gt;Monitor&lt;/a&gt; - for NHS Foundation Trusts. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="oft-market-studies-and-cc-market-investigations"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; market studies and &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; market investigations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) market studies are detailed investigations of markets that are not operating well for consumers, but where neither consumer regulation enforcement by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; nor competition enforcement through a referral to the Competition Commission (&lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;) is likely to resolve the issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where those studies make recommendations to government, the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) co-ordinates government responses and ensures that they take account not only of competition and consumer interests but wider public policy objectives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Market studies will usually be performed under section 5 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/Acts/acts2002/ukpga_20020040_en_1"&gt;Enterprise Act 2002&lt;/a&gt; in order to identify whether perceived problems should be addressed through the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s other functions. There is a range of possible outcomes of a study including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving the market a clean bill of health (ie a decision that intervention is not appropriate on the evidence available) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publishing information to help consumers &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging firms to take voluntary action &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging a consumer code of practice &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making recommendations to the government or regulators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investigation or enforcement action against companies or individuals suspected of breaching consumer law or competition law &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a market investigation reference to the Competition Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; conducts in-depth inquiries into markets – market investigations – undertaken in response to a reference made by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; or sectoral regulator and, in certain limited circumstances, by the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills. The market studies and market investigations where &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has played an active role are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;medicines distribution &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pharmaceutical price regulation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sale and rent back &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;payment protection insurance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supply of airport services in the UK by BAA &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rolling stock leasing (ROSCOs) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;property searches &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commercial use of public information (CUPI) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supply of groceries in the UK &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To find information on these and other market studies, go to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20090703093314/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/whatwedo/businesslaw/competition/market-studies/page17610.html"&gt;National Archives market studies pages&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mergers"&gt;Mergers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper framework for control of mergers is important to ensure that competition is not damaged when businesses come together. UK mergers are considered by the competition authorities under the Enterprise Act 2002. Public interest considerations are specified in the Act as being national security, media plurality and stability of the UK financial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, mergers will be considered by the UK competition authorities if the annual UK turnover of the enterprise being taken over exceeds £70 million, or the merger creates a 25% share or more in a market for goods or services in the UK or a substantial part of it. There is no statutory requirement to pre-notify mergers to the UK competition authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investigation-by-the-oft"&gt;Investigation by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; investigates mergers in the first instance and, with the exception of public interest cases, decides whether or not they should be referred to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; for further investigation. The test is whether the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; believes a merger has resulted or may be expected to result in a substantial lessening of competition.
In making decisions, the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; will either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;refer to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; for further investigation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear the merger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear it subject to undertakings in lieu of a reference to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details of mergers investigated by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investigation-by-the-cc"&gt;Investigation by the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a merger is referred to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;, it has to determine whether it has resulted in a substantial lessening of competition and to take the action it considers reasonable and practicable to address any adverse effects arising from the merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; reports are published. Details of mergers investigated by the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Commission&lt;/a&gt; website. Companies can also obtain &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/mergers/"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; and informal advice from the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; on its merger procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="mergers-between-water-and-sewerage-companies"&gt;Mergers between water and sewerage companies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special regime exists for mergers between water and sewerage companies. These are considered under sections 32-35 of the Water Industry Act 1991, as amended by the Enterprise Act and the Water Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-community-merger-regulation"&gt;European Community Merger Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large mergers with a European dimension that breach certain jurisdictional thresholds of the European Community Merger Regulation (&lt;abbr title="European Community Merger Regulation"&gt;ECMR&lt;/abbr&gt;) – Council Regulation No. 139/2004 – fall to the European Commission for investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking, mergers involving enterprises with an aggregate worldwide turnover of more than €5 billion (around £4 billion) and where the aggregate Community-wide turnover of each of at least 2 of the enterprises concerned is more than €250 million (around £200 million) will be investigated by the European Commission taking into account the views of member states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, those mergers where more than two-thirds of the Community-wide turnover of each enterprise concerned falls within one and the same member state, are not caught by the EC Merger Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; will normally advise the EC on competition issues it sees relevant to cases being considered under the EC Merger Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on individual cases under the &lt;abbr title="European Community Merger Regulation"&gt;ECMR&lt;/abbr&gt; can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/index_en.html"&gt;Commission’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="public-interest-cases-under-the-ec-merger-regulation"&gt;Public interest cases under the EC Merger Regulation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State may also intervene on public interest grounds in mergers being considered under the EC Merger Regulation, where the public interest consideration in question is also recognised in the EC Merger Regulation. In such cases the European Commission will continue to consider the competition issues whilst the UK authorities consider public interest aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-processes-and-competition-authorities-from-april-2014"&gt;New processes and competition authorities from April 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s 2011 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-competition-regime-for-growth-a-consultation-on-options-for-reform"&gt;consultation on competition reform&lt;/a&gt; confirmed that many aspects of the UK’s competition regime are world class, but it also highlighted some significant challenges for the current system and made a number of proposals to enhance the regime’s performance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012, set out the reforms that will come into effect from April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms - currently being considered by Parliament in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill – will bring together the best of the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; into a single Competition and Markets Authority (&lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt;) to become a world-leading competition authority, advocating competition both at home and abroad. It will have a greater role in ensuring competition in regulated sectors is being addressed, through enhanced cooperation and information sharing between itself and the sector regulators. It will make better use of public resources, and business will benefit from having a single agency to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-markets-and-mergers-regimes"&gt;1) The Markets and Mergers regimes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; is set up, we shall maintain the separation of decision-making between the 2 phases of market and merger investigations [see page 94 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;]. Currently the 2 phases of an investigation are carried out by separate organisations: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Phase 1”, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/;jsessionid=8200B8DBE569E41858F3F97E2DFC0CAF"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which can undertake an initial study into a merger or market to see if there is a competition issue to be addressed. If so, it can refer the case to:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/our-work"&gt;Competition Commission&lt;/a&gt;, “Phase 2”, which will carry out a deeper study to get to the nub of the problem and impose remedies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The separation of Phase 1 and Phase 2 decision-making on regulatory appeals will also be maintained and provided for in legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; will have powers, additionally, to conduct investigations into practices that impact on more than one market [see page 30 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;], such as extended warranties and other secondary point of sale practices, without the need to make multiple market investigation references. These powers will enable the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; to take a more targeted approach to tackling recurring sources of consumer complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; will have discretion to stop a proposed merger [see page 42 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] where there are concerns the merger may be anti-competitive, and to consider with the companies involved whether the merger should be allowed to proceed. Legislation will clarify that the Authority can reverse mergers that have already taken place where this is deemed appropriate after investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also proposes to improve remedies by enabling the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; to require parties to appoint an independent third party [see page 48 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] to monitor, arbitrate, and/or implement remedies; and by giving the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; the power to require parties to publish certain non-price information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="streamlining-and-strengthening-the-competition-tools"&gt;Streamlining and strengthening the competition tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minor change will give the Secretary of State the power to request the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; to investigate public interest issues [see page 30of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] alongside competition issues in a market investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to ensure greater certainty and to reduce the burden to business, the government proposes introducing or reducing statutory time limits at all stages of market investigations. This will be supported by information gathering powers at all stages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory time limits will also be introduced at all stages of the mergers process [see page 44 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="anti-trust-and-cartels"&gt;2) Anti-trust and Cartels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system for enforcing the legal prohibitions in anti-trust (abuse of market dominance and other anti-competitive agreements) and cartel cases (eg agreement between companies to fix prices) contained in the Competition Act 1998 (‘anti-trust’) is being strengthened. Proposals include statutory change to bolster separation between investigation and decision making and new powers for the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; to improve the efficiency of investigations and transparency of the decision making process [see page 54 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is work currently carried out by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Appeals against decisions by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; (and the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; once the reforms have been fully introduced) can be made to the Competition Appeal Tribunal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sectoral-regulation-and-concurrency"&gt;3) Sectoral regulation and ‘concurrency’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sectoral regulators already have the power to refer cases to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; but rarely use them. We want to encourage the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; to be a more proactive central resource for these regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectoral regulators have ‘concurrent competition powers’, ie they have a choice between using their own sectoral powers and making use of the 1998 Competition Act to refer issues to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. We want to strengthen the primacy of the Competition Act by requiring sectoral regulators with concurrent powers to consider that route first; and also to give the &lt;abbr title="Competition and Markets Authority"&gt;CMA&lt;/abbr&gt; the power to take Competition Act cases from the sectoral regulators where it is better placed to proceed with the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="competition-complaints"&gt;Competition complaints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe a company or group of companies are acting anti-competitively, then you may wish to consider making a complaint to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; via its special hotline and email address for complaints under the Competition Act:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition Act Enquiry Line: 08457 22 44 99
e-mail enquiries: &lt;a href="mailto:enquiries.competitionact@oft.gov.uk"&gt;enquiries.competitionact@oft.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a detailed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/advice_and_resources/resource_base/legal/competition-act-1998/complaints"&gt;how to complain section&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website. This gives examples of behaviour which may indicate that a company is breaching the Competition Act. It also gives information on what to do in order to complain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/60306</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T11:52:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T11:52:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/office-for-life-sciences"/>
    <title>Office for Life Sciences</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>The Office for Life Sciences is part of BIS - it ensures a competitive UK life sciences industry and secures investment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="strategy-for-uk-life-sciences---one-year-on"&gt;Strategy for UK Life Sciences - One Year On&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has launched &lt;a href="/government/publications/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;Strategy for life sciences - One Year On&lt;/a&gt;, a report which summarises progress made in the first 12 months since last year’s launch of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/s/11-1429-strategy-for-uk-life-sciences.pdf"&gt;‘Strategy for UK life sciences’&lt;/a&gt;. Health Life Sciences is one of the 11 sectors that have been prioritised as part of the government’s industrial strategy. &lt;a href="/government/speeches/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;See David Willetts’ speech relating to the report.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategy for UK life sciences is based on three pillars: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a UK life sciences ecosystem: the government is making it easier for researchers to commercialise academic research, placing clinical research at the heart of the NHS, and empowering patients to participate in research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attracting, developing and rewarding talent: the government is introducing measures to attract and nurture world-leading talent and develop scientific excellence (these measures are ensuring that the UK offers exciting and rewarding careers for clinicians, scientists and technicians from all around the world)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overcoming barriers and creating incentives for the promotion of healthcare innovation: the government is introducing measures to incentivise early-stage investment and nurture the best innovations through the translational funding gap to a point at which they can secure follow-on investment - we’ll continue to reduce the bureaucracy of setting up clinical trials to ensure that patients have access to promising, cost-effective, new treatments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One Year On reports the substantial progress made this year in implementing these measures. In order to strengthen networks between academia, industry and the NHS, the government is investing £1 billion a year through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500 million in our translational research infrastructure in the NHS. The £180 million Biomedical Catalyst was introduced to bridge the ‘valley of death’ between the bench and the clinic, and the early response from industry is that this funding is already having the intended impact of stimulating innovative research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from the progress made to date, One Year On announces the government’s commitment to the sequencing of 100,000 whole genomes from NHS patients over the next three to five years. This work will initially focus on cancer patients, patients with rare diseases and infectious disease. We are working across government to ensure that research, academia and industry are key players in promoting the adoption of genomic technology to provide better healthcare and help the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="life-sciences-in-the-uk"&gt;Life Sciences in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy for UK life sciences was launched alongside, and is being implemented in collaboration with, the NHS chief executive’s review: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_131299"&gt;Innovation, health and wealth: accelerating adoption and diffusion in the NHS&lt;/a&gt;. The update to this report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/health/2012/12/ihw-creating-change/"&gt;Creating Change: Innovation, Health and Wealth One Year On&lt;/a&gt;, was published on 10 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also published on 10 December 2012 was the latest report on the bioscience and health technology database, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/s/12-p90-strength-and-opportunity-2012-medical-technology-sectors.pdf"&gt;Strength and opportunity 2012&lt;/a&gt;, and also &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/investintheuk/sectoropportunities/lifesciences.html"&gt;The New UK Life Science Prospectus Life sciences in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has one of the strongest and most productive life sciences industries in the world, contributing to patient well-being as well as supporting growth. UK life science industries generate turnover of over £50bn and employ 167,500 people in over 4,500 companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry is high-tech, innovative and highly diverse, spanning pharmaceuticals, medical technology, biotechnology, and industrial biotechnology and has applications across many other sectors. Through the development of innovative medicines, medical technologies and services, its businesses contribute to a stronger and fairer society, helping people enjoy better health, well-being and quality of life. They are also helping the UK improve its sustainability and increase rates of decarbonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is building on and fostering these strengths and responding to the changing global commercial environment. We want to make the UK the location of choice for pioneering life sciences research and development (&lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;) and manufacturing investment, so that life sciences will continue to be vibrant in the UK and a key contributor to sustained economic growth and health improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Office for Life Sciences (&lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt;) works closely with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Health&lt;/a&gt;, championing biotechnology and the pharmaceutical and medical technology industries. We also work with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department for Energy and Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; and other departments, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mhra.gov.uk"&gt;Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency (&lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk"&gt;NHS&lt;/a&gt; and the life sciences industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="views-on-the-use-of-animals-in-scientific-research"&gt;Views on the use of animals in scientific research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ipsos MORI report &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/i/ipsos-mori-views-on-use-of-animals-in-scientific-research-september-2012.pdf"&gt;‘Views on the use of animals in scientific research’&lt;/a&gt; presents the findings of a 2012 survey on awareness of, and public attitudes towards, the use of animals in scientific research. This survey has been carried out since 1999 on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that 85% of the representative sample conditionally accept the use of animals in scientific research. While this year’s findings show a decline in overall public acceptance, it also identifies that a significant proportion of the representative sample (40%) would like to know more information about the use of animals in scientific research before forming a firm opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has challenged the scientific community to respond to these findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="areas-of-work-for-the-ols"&gt;Areas of work for the &lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of the &lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt; is focused on 2 areas: healthcare and the bio-economy. The healthcare team works with the following sectors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pharmaceutical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical technology – devices and diagnostics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bio-economy team works with the following sectors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;industrial biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;agricultural biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These teams work across a range of policy areas supporting business growth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NHS market access&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finance and tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bio-economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="nhs-market-access"&gt;NHS market access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Te market access team works closely with the other &lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; teams, the Department of Health, and other departments and agencies. The NHS is a major contributor to economic growth, and we work together to maximise this contribution and to address any barriers to innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main areas of interest for the market access team are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reforms to the NHS, including the introduction of value-based pricing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the NHS procurement strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engaging with &lt;abbr title="Department of Health"&gt;DH&lt;/abbr&gt;’s delivery of [‘Innovation, health and wealth: accelerating uptake and diffusion of innovation in the NHS’[(http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_131299).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, we are considering how these will create opportunities for the business environment and support the growth agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="innovation"&gt;Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our focus is to ensure that industry has the right environment to innovate and in particular to remove barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regenerative-medicine"&gt;Regenerative medicine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the impact of the £25 million &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukrmp.org.uk/"&gt;UK Regenerative Medicine Platform&lt;/a&gt; which addresses the technical and scientific challenges associated with translating promising scientific discoveries in this area towards clinical impact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contributing to the House of Lords Select Committee inquiry into Regenerative Medicine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="medicines-licensing"&gt;Medicines licensing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; on the government’s commitment to consult on an Early Access Scheme for Medicines &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exploring more progressive approaches to medicines regulations, including adaptive licensing, through the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; Expert Group on Healthcare Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clinical-trials-environment"&gt;Clinical trials environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; on the European Commission’s plans to replace the European Clinical Trials Directive with a Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="open-innovation"&gt;Open innovation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the changing &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; landscape and a growing interest in new ways of partnership working, we organised a seminar on Open Innovation in May 2012. Relevant public sector organisations including the Intellectual Property Office, Technology Strategy Board, Clinical Practice Research Datalink as well as private sector interest (AstraZeneca (PPT, 2.6 Mb), Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst and Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson discussed the opportunities of the approach to the life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="infrastructure-projects"&gt;Infrastructure projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; is co-funding 2 key investment projects to stimulate further growth and address market failures by providing incubation facilities for new companies. These bioincubators are based in Stevenage in Hertfordshire, alongside the GlaxoSmithKline &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; headquarters, and on the Edinburgh BioQuarter site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has also co-funded the Industrial Biotechnology 10,000 litre Demonstrator in Wilton, an open access facility to enable companies, especially small- and medium-sized enterprises, to trial different biomass feedstock and processes to manufacture biobased products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="stevenage-bioscience-catalyst"&gt;Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.stevenagecatalyst.com/"&gt;Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst&lt;/a&gt; will be the first purpose-built, open innovation campus for drug discovery and development. It will maximise the economic impact of academic and science expertise and foster a successful open innovation model between big pharmaceutical and small bioscience companies. It will act as a catalyst to position the UK at the forefront of scientific innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst will be located alongside the GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; Headquarters in Stevenage and is being developed in stages. Phase 1 comprises the construction of BioIncubator and Accelerator buildings for early-stage bioscience companies. Phase 1 is being funded by &lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;, the East of England Development Agency (EEDA), the Technology Strategy Board (TSB), GSK and the Wellcome Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future phases will bring the catalyst up to 45,000 square metres by 2016, assuming that the market demand is as expected. This is forecast to create 1500 new jobs and stimulate the creation of up to 5 new businesses. All future phases will be commercially funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="edinburgh-bioquarter---bioincubator"&gt;Edinburgh BioQuarter - BioIncubator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.edinburghbioquarter.com/"&gt;Edinburgh BioQuarter&lt;/a&gt; is a landmark life sciences hub that is establishing Edinburgh and Scotland as one of the world’s top 10 centres for biomedical research and commercialisation. The project is a long-term life science property and commercialisation partnership between Scottish Enterprise, the University of Edinburgh, the NHS and US-based private sector partner, Alexandria Real Estate Equities, Inc. The 100-acre site already houses the University of Edinburgh Queen’s Medical Research Institute and the 870-bed Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh teaching hospital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Scottish Enterprise are co-funding the creation of the BioIncubator. This investment is expected to leverage almost £210m of additional investment and create or retain over 700 high-value jobs. This will enhance the global reputation of the UK as a place for leading life science innovation, by creating an infrastructure for supporting industry to collaborate with academic and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Edinburgh is aiming to produce 18 new life sciences companies over the next 5 years which will add a considerable pipeline of demand for the BioIncubator. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="industrial-biotechnology-demonstrator"&gt;Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in Wilton in the Tees Valley, the new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk-cpi.com/industrial-biotechnology/demonstrator"&gt;National Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator&lt;/a&gt; is an open access facility of a unique scale of 10,000-litre working volume capacity. The demonstrator has 2 main applications: it can be used as a proof of concept facility to scale-up the production of materials to near commercial levels; and as a product manufacturing facility for clients experiencing temporary capacity restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator"&gt;NIBF&lt;/abbr&gt; will allow biotechnology companies to de-risk product and process development. By exploring and then optimising processes, companies will be are able to calculate the most cost-effective combination of materials; process steps and sequences; and the equipment needed to manufacture profitably. Consequently, they will minimise the risk of investing in the wrong capital equipment, using inefficient processes or facing unexpected costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60294</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T10:35:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-business-survey-october-2012"/>
    <title>English Business Survey October 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The English business survey will provide Ministers and officials with information about the current economic and business conditions across England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60195</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluation-of-the-deepened-co-location-trials"/>
    <title>Evaluation of the deepened co-location trials</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 jobcentres that took part in joint location trials with Next Steps.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 98. Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 Jobcentres that took part in the joint location trials with Next Step (now known as the National Careers Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It highlights key issues arising from the research with a view to contributing to the success of the wider roll out of joint location in Jobcentres in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/60105</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T16:57:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:57:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"/>
    <title>Providing better information and protection for consumers</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is changing some laws to help consumers</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government believes that consumers who are well-informed about their rights and what they’re buying are more confident and more likely to spend money. We also think that consumers who feel properly protected by the law are more likely to spend money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to give consumers more confidence - and legal back-up - to deal with bad service or shoddy goods. We also want to encourage consumers to spend money, as this will help the economy grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-bill-of-rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to simplify and clarify consumer law with a new bill (Act of Parliament). This will contain a clear list of rights for consumers, along with new measures to protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-bill-of-rights" title="Consumer bill of rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/a&gt; will also contain remedies for when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform"&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘consumer landscape’ is the network of organisations that help consumers - Citizens Advice, for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘competition landscape’ is the network of organisations that deal with competition issues and anti-competitive activities in business – the Office of Fair Trading, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning to reorganise both the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="consumer and competition landscapes"&gt;consumer and competition landscapes&lt;/a&gt; between now and 2014, to make them both simpler to understand and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-201183eu"&gt;Implementing the Consumer Rights Directive 2011/83/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-2011-83-eu" title="Consumer Rights Directive."&gt;Consumer Rights Directive (CRD)&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; measure. All &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CRD gives consumers additional rights when buying in the UK and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. We’re aiming to make the CRD part of UK law by June 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="misleading-and-aggressive-selling"&gt;Misleading and aggressive selling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/misleading-and-aggressive-selling" title="Misleading and aggressive selling."&gt;improving the rights of people who have been misled into buying something&lt;/a&gt;, or who have been pressured into buying something. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="personal-data"&gt;Personal data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re helping consumers make better buying decisions by giving them improved access to the personal data companies hold about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/personal-data"&gt;midata project.&lt;/a&gt;. We’re working with business, consumer and privacy groups. The project is led by an independent data expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midata project runs on a voluntary basis, but we’ll pass a law to make industry cooperation compulsory if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-buying"&gt;Community buying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers can combine their buying power to buy goods and services together. This can get them better deals. The government is supporting community buying in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by providing clear advice to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/community-buying" title="Community groups"&gt;community groups&lt;/a&gt; who want to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by running the ‘Buy better together challenge’, which has a £60,000 fund to be shared amongst innovative collective purchasing projects - the challenge was won by Smarterbuys, an organisation that helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so they can buy essential goods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="who-can-i-contact-for-help-and-advice"&gt;Who can I contact for help and advice?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t help with individual problems – but here are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/consumer-protection-rights" title="Help and advice"&gt;some people who can.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/" title="Trading Standards."&gt;Trading Standards&lt;/a&gt; have worked on mainly local cases and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://oft.gov.uk/" title="Office of Fair Trading."&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/a&gt; (OFT) worked on some national ones. A National Audit Office (NAO) report was critical of this split and the ‘enforcement gap’ it caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews."&gt;Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews&lt;/a&gt; were published in spring 2012. They recommended a number of changes including transferring the main responsibility for consumer advice to the Citizens Advice service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consulted in June 2011 with proposals for reforming consumer institutions – the ‘consumer landscape’. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/empowering-and-protecting-consumers?cat=closedwithresponse" title="Empowering and Protecting Consumers: Consultation"&gt;Empowering and protecting consumers&lt;/a&gt; had 184 responses and closed in September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted in summer 2012 about whether we should have an ‘order-making power’ for midata. This power would give us the legal authority to make businesses release personal data to their customers. Following the consultation, we announced that we would legislate if companies didn’t release customers’ data voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital.pdf" title="proposals to update and simplify consumer law"&gt;proposals to update and simplify consumer law.&lt;/a&gt;  How would they affect consumers and businesses? That consultation closed on 5 October 2012. We’ll publish the results in spring 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital" title="Goods, services, digital content"&gt;Consultation on the supply of goods, services and digital content (July 2012)&lt;/a&gt; here and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-961-supply-of-digital-content-impact.pdf" title="Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content."&gt;Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1008-consultation-ban-above-cost-payment-surcharges" title="Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges."&gt;Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 15 October with the government response due in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-999-consultation-implementation-of-consumer-rights-directive.pdf" title="Consumer rights consultation"&gt;implementation of the Consumer Rights Directive&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 1 November. The government response is due in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-543-enhancing-consumer-confidence-effective-enforcement-consultation.pdf" title="Consumer law enforcement powers"&gt;Simplifying consumer law enforcement powers.&lt;/a&gt; The government response is expected in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re consulting on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending" title="Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law."&gt;Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;. This opened on 2 November and closes on 31 December with government response due early in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to know your views on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending"&gt;Give your views about extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked with a number of partners to produce our ‘Guide for community buying groups’. All of the organisations below contributed or checked material for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acre.org.uk/"&gt;Action with Communities in Rural England (ACRE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.allenvalleys.co.uk/oil/"&gt;Allen Valleys Oil Buying Co-operative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.brighterliving.org.uk/"&gt;Brighter Living Partnership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/"&gt;Citizens Advice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oxonrcc.org.uk/"&gt;Oxfordshire Rural Community Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://socialinnovation.typepad.com/silk/2009/10/bulk-buying-project.html"&gt;The R Shop Bulk Buying Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solar 100 Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sustainweb.org/"&gt;Sustain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up2Us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also worked with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://lawcommission.justice.gov.uk/"&gt;Law Commission&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scotlawcom.gov.uk/"&gt;Scottish Law Commission,&lt;/a&gt; who both did studies on misleading and aggressive selling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60119</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T16:48:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:48:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/uk-government-oil-and-gas-sector-strategy-call-for-industrys-views"/>
    <title>UK government oil and gas sector strategy: call for industry's views</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its industrial strategy, the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) announced that there will be, initially, 10 sector strategies, of which oil and gas would be one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry’s input is essential as &lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Department of Energy and Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="The Department of Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt;) develop this work in partnership with Oil &amp;amp; Gas UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sector strategies will be co-developed and implemented with industry to be durable and will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be long-term in focus: developing a vision for the sector and what needs to happen from both government and business to get there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be co-created with industry: committing both business and government to specific actions to maintain and develop long-term capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a whole of government approach: looking across all of government to identify barriers and levers which have the biggest impacts and align these to deliver growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engage across the totality of the sector: working with industry and identifying actions which benefit business across the whole supply chain whether they are large, medium or small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publication is expected in late March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry’s views are very much welcomed particularly through January 2013 and can be fed into either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; – Tom Worsley – &lt;a href="Tom.Worsley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Tom.Worsley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; – 020 7215 6480&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="The Department of Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt; – Audrey Banner – &lt;a href="Audrey.banner@decc.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Audrey.banner@decc.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; – 01224 254104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/60176</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:21:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:21:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/product-safety-for-manufacturers"/>
    <title>Product safety for manufacturers</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Technical and legal requirements for safety, design, packaging and insurance, to ensure products are safe and fit for purpose.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design and manufacturing processes are essential to ensure you meet these technical and legal requirements. They can also give your business a competitive edge and save costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide sets out the key safety, design, packaging and insurance issues you need to consider in relation to your products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="your-legal-responsibilities"&gt;Your legal responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Sale of Goods Act 1979, all products must be ‘fit for purpose’, be of satisfactory quality and fit its description. This means that your products must fulfil the purpose the customer has been led to expect and the reasons that led them to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act also covers any purpose that a customer asks about when the product is purchased and is guaranteed by the retailer to meet that purpose when it is sold. If a product is not fit for purpose, the customer is within their rights to have the goods replaced or repaired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act guidance on the Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, good design will lead to safe design. While meeting your legal obligations is the minimum required, it is a good idea to go further and take best practice on board throughout the design, production, supply and disposal stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a manufacturer or supplier you could be held liable in any legal action for harm caused to consumers or businesses as a result of unintended side-effects or the failure of products manufactured or supplied by you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your manufacturing and processing systems must comply with environmental law. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/"&gt;read guidance to help you keep up with your environmental responsibilities on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="products-covered-by-specific-safety-regulations"&gt;Products covered by specific safety regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a manufacturer’s claim that its product meets specified essential safety requirements set out in relevant European directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain categories of products must bear &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you intend to sell them in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;member states of the European Economic area (&lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;) - Iceland, Liechtenstein and Norway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following categories of products require &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you wish to sell them within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or member states of the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electrical products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;construction products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure vessels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;telecommunications equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;machinery, equipment and safety components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;personal protective equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;satellite station equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gas appliances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appliances (other than gas)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-automatic weighing instruments and equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recreational craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lift machinery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;equipment and protective systems for explosive atmospheres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in vitro diagnostic medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marine equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety components and subsystems for incorporation into cableway installations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cableway equipment (ski tows etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The requirement for &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the exact process you will need to go through varies from product to product. Different types of product are governed by different European directives. For example, the trade of certain machinery, equipment and safety components is governed by the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations 2008. The regulations implement a European directive aimed at removing technical barriers to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the regulations, products that conform to the relevant safety standards are &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked and can be placed on the market across the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Responsibility for ensuring compliance with the regulations rests with the manufacturer of the machinery, equipment or components in question. Failure to do so can result in prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations (PDF, 424KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where an item of equipment is covered by more than one directive, it must be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked under all applicable directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply consumer products which aren’t covered by these specific directives, they must not be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked. However, you still have a general duty to ensure they are safe for normal or reasonably foreseeable use under the General Product Safety Regulations 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fireworks---information-for-suppliers-retailers-and-display-event-organisers"&gt;Fireworks - information for suppliers, retailers and display event organisers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireworks are available throughout the year from shops licensed to supply them. They become widely available at certain times of the year, mainly a few days before New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year, and in the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night on 5 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply or sell fireworks or if you organise display events you must be aware of your responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-as-a-firework-manufacturer-or-importer"&gt;Your responsibilities as a firework manufacturer or importer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks or import category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks which are manufactured outside the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, you must ensure they conform to European safety standards before supplying them for sale to the public. To do this, you need to ensure that the fireworks have been tested by a notified body (&lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the &lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt; has approved them, the products must carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and be correctly labelled with details of the manufacturer and importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyrotechnics that were manufactured or imported before 4 July 2010 and that complied with British Standard BS 7114 can continue to be sold without the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark until 4 July 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 3 fireworks must not exceed 120 decibels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 4 display fireworks that are not intended for supply to consumers must be marked accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import fireworks, you must ensure they comply with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards, carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and supply information at the point of entry to ensure that fireworks are legally stored and distributed. This information should be given to HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs and will then be sent to the relevant authorities responsible for storage licences so they can check on deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licensing authorities can ask to see information relating to transactions of fireworks exceeding 50 kilograms of net explosive content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56790"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/thumbnail_10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf"&gt;Guidance for manufacturers, importers and distributors on firework safety rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;79 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-if-you-are-a-fireworks-retailer"&gt;Your responsibilities if you are a fireworks retailer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to sell fireworks to the public, you need to register your shop or obtain a licence from your local authority. The penalties for not registering or being licensed are a fine of up to £5,000, a prison sentence of up to 3 months, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is illegal for retailers to sell caps, cracker snaps, novelty matches, party poppers, serpents and throwdowns to anyone who is under 16 and to sell all other fireworks to anyone who is under 18 - it is recommended that proof of age is sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must display a large notice reminding customers about the law with regard to underage sales and possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can only sell fireworks that conform to &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards (or British Standard BS 7114 if they were produced before 4 July 2010) and which carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and meet certain noise conditions. They must have the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark or BS 7114 printed on each item or on the retail packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also supply fireworks with any safety instructions provided by the manufacturer or importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxes of fireworks must not be split and sold separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you have a special licence, you can only sell fireworks during the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night, New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Find a fireworks storage risk assessment checklist and information about storing and selling fireworks in retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;Find &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cosmetic-products-safety-regulations"&gt;Cosmetic Products Safety Regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All cosmetic products supplied in the UK, whether for consumer or professional use, must comply with the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008 (as amended). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 13 July 2013 a new directly applicable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:342:0059:0209:EN:PDF"&gt;European Regulation (EC/1223/2009)&lt;/a&gt; enters into force, replacing the existing legislation, (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new notification procedure, which requires every product placed on the market to be notified to the European Commission is already in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guidance notes explain all aspects of the Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56791"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56791-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/thumbnail_10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56791-accessibility-help"&gt;A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;220 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;42 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56791-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Regulations require that finished cosmetic products must undergo a safety assessment by a suitably qualified person before they can be placed on the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file50357.pdf"&gt;The Cosmetics Directive&lt;/a&gt; on which the Regulations are based is updated periodically, reflecting changes to the prohibitions and restrictions on certain substances, and subsequent amendments to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1284/contents/made"&gt;Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt; are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/"&gt;OPSI website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amendments since then are contained, available on the same website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2173 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2566 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/796 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/1346 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No3) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/2562 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No4) Regulations 2009. S.I. 2009/3367 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2010, S.I. 2010/1150 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2010. S.I. 2010/1927 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2011, S.I. 2012/3037&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 31 October 2012 a new directive enters into force, which is mirrored in S.I. 2012/2263, and which liberalises the use of hydrogen peroxide at up to 6% for tooth whitening purposes, subject to first use by a dentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition various hair dye substances are due to be restricted from 1 September 2013, under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:208:0008:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Directive 2012/21/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is not intending to transpose this because it will be overtaken by the new European Regulation (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-european-regulation"&gt;The European Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has firstly altered the procedure for notification of each product, requiring notification direct to the European Commission using the Cosmetics Product Notification Portal, (CPNP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is operational now and can be used, although it does not become mandatory until the Regulation enters into force: see the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_new_en.pdf"&gt;Cosmetics Products Notification Portal document&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_user_manual_en.pdf"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Regulation is directly applicable and it changes various elements, relating to the safety assessment, the responsible person in respect of that, and nanomaterials. There will be further guidance issued, as details which have still to be negotiated are finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-regulations-for-childrens-products"&gt;Safety regulations for children’s products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys supplied in the UK must meet the requirements of the Toys (Safety) Regulations 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations define a toy as ‘any product or material designed or clearly intended for use in play by children of less than 14 years of age, but excluding those products specified in Schedule 3 [of the regulations]’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;download a guide to the Toys (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that a revised European directive will come into force on 20 July 2011. The directive substantially amends the existing regulations across virtually all safety aspects. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:170:0001:0037:EN:PDF"&gt;download the text of the new Directive 2009/48/EC from the EUR-Lex website (PDF, 995K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ce-marking-on-toys"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys presented for sale in the UK must bear the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the name and address of the person who first placed the toy on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a declaration by the manufacturer that the product satisfies essential safety requirements and can be sold within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. For more information see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authority trading standards officers can remove a toy from the market if they believe it to be unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="testing-for-toys"&gt;Testing for toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture a toy in accordance with the regulations - and the standards cover all aspects relating to the toy - then it can be self-certified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the standards do not cover all aspects relating to the toy, a sample must be submitted for type examination by an approved body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import toys you are responsible for their safety, whether or not they already bear a &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark. You might want to consider having them tested to ensure they are safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-child-safety-regulations"&gt;Other child safety regulations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other laws relating to child safety include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flammability - tough performance requirements regarding flammability are compulsory for children’s nightdresses and dressing gowns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;choking risks - toys intended for children under 36 months must not present a choking risk - the test uses the ‘small parts cylinder’ (toys or parts of toys that can fit entirely inside the cylinder are identified as choking hazards)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;magnetic parts - magnets which have a flux of more than 50 kG2mm2 (0,5 T2mm2) and fit entirely in the small parts cylinder are not permitted for use in toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chemicals - the revised European Directive 2009/48/EC will limit the amounts of certain chemicals that may be contained in materials used for toys - these parts of the directive relating to chemical content will come into force on 20 July 2013 (there is also a ban on the use of six phthalates in toys and products for children under 3 years of age)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other products - hood cords, bunk beds and prams and pushchairs are subject to specific safety regulations, namely the Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976, the Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 and the Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="general-product-safety-regulations"&gt;General Product safety regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General product safety is regulated by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/1803/contents/made"&gt;General Product Safety Regulations 2005 (GPS Regulations)&lt;/a&gt;. They apply to all products (new and second-hand) used by consumers. Product-specific legislation continues to take precedence in areas where the provisions have similar objectives to the GPS Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPS Regulations maintain the general duty placed on producers and distributors to place on the market (or supply) only products that are safe in normal or reasonable foreseeable use. The principal responsibility for day-to-day enforcement of the Regulations lies with local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPS Regulations recognise certain technical standards as carrying a presumption of conformity with the general safety requirement, meaning that products that comply with them are deemed to be safe. An up-to-date list of European Standards is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/euro_standards/index_en.htm"&gt;European Commission Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rapid-alert-system-for-non-food-consumer-products-rapex"&gt;Rapid Alert System for non-food consumer products (RAPEX)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAPEX is the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; rapid alert system for dangerous consumer products – with the exception of food, pharmaceutical and medical devices which are covered by other mechanisms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It facilitates the rapid exchange of information between Member States and the Commission on measures to prevent or restrict the marketing or use of products posing a serious risk to the health and safety of consumers. Both measures ordered by national authorities and measures taken voluntarily by producers and distributors are reported by RAPEX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-does-rapex-work"&gt;How does RAPEX work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a product (eg a toy, childcare article or household appliance) is found to be dangerous, the competent national authority takes appropriate action to eliminate the risk. It can withdraw the product from the market, recall it, or issue warnings. The National Contact Point then informs the European Commission (Directorate-General for Health and Consumer Protection) about the product, the risks it poses to consumers and the measures taken by the authority to prevent risks and accidents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission disseminates the information that it receives to the National Contact Points of all other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; countries. It publishes weekly overviews of dangerous products and the measures taken to eliminate the risks on the internet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Contact Points in each &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; country ensure that the authorities responsible check whether the newly notified dangerous product is present on the market. If so, the authorities take measures to eliminate the risk, either by requiring that the product be withdrawn from the market, by recalling it from consumers or by issuing warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weekly overview of the dangerous products reported by the national authorities (the RAPEX notifications) is published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/dyna/rapex/rapex_archives_en.cfm"&gt;Commission Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="product-recall"&gt;‘Product recall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trading Standards Central web site contains &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/advice-recall-list.cfm"&gt;a list of product safety notices and recalls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are concerned about the safety of a product, make your concern clear to the retailer, manufacturer or local trading standards department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a producer or distributor of consumer products on sale in the European Union (&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;), the attached guide gives you general advice about what you should do if you have evidence that one of your products may be unsafe. It is a voluntary guide to carrying out corrective actions for product safety, supported by the market surveillance authorities in Member States and consumer and trade organisations within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;.  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/cons_safe/action_guide_en.pdf"&gt;Product Safety in Europe: A Guide to corrective action including recalls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unsafe-product-notification"&gt;Unsafe product notification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producers and distributors have a duty to notify local authorities when they become aware they have placed on the market, or distributed, an unsafe product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20100125143037/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/files/file23032.pdf"&gt;General Product Safety Regulations 2005 - notification guidance for producers and distributors&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20100125143037/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/files/file23040.doc"&gt;Producer and Distributor Form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make this process simpler a business application form has been designed. There are two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the notification form - which the producer or distributor should fill in &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the online database - used exclusively by the authorities of Member States to view and process notifications (in the case of the UK the National Contact Point for RAPEX at &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance and the form can be accessed on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://webgate.ec.europa.eu/gpsd-ba/index.do;jsessionid=MGycbGHrnV9ZQCdsDhYv0PLQB0GqQ7c47X4J6gqy2chSsc69nny5!443991619"&gt;the EUROPA Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authority enforcers have a duty to inform &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; of products placed on the market that either present a:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serious risk in need of urgent intervention &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-serious risk requiring some intervention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance for local authorities on informing &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; about products is available by following the links below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/rapex/docs/rapex_guid_26012010_en.pdf"&gt;Operational (Member State market surveillance) RAPEX guidelines&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/rapex/guidelines_states_en.htm"&gt;Member State Rapex Guidelines and Risk Assessment&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Risk Categories for RAPEX notification form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56914"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39622/standard-notification-form-risk-categories.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-56914-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39622/standard-notification-form-risk-categories.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-56914-accessibility-help"&gt;Standard notification risk form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;96.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56914-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Standard%20notification%20risk%20form%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Standard%20notification%20risk%20form%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Standard notification risk form").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RAPEX notification form (for local authority use) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56902"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39610/rapex-notification-form-xlt.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-56902-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39610/rapex-notification-form-xlt.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-56902-accessibility-help"&gt;Rapex notification form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;73 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56902-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Rapex%20notification%20form%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Rapex%20notification%20form%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Rapex notification form").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reaction to RAPEX notification form (for local authority use)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56904"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39612/reaction-to-rapex.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-56904-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39612/reaction-to-rapex.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-56904-accessibility-help"&gt;Reaction to Rapex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;62 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56904-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Reaction%20to%20Rapex%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Reaction%20to%20Rapex%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Reaction to Rapex").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local authorities - please note the Rapex and Reaction forms above are MS-Excel spreadsheet templates. See the following points on using and saving the forms to your PC: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From weblink click ‘Save’ without opening, ensure document is saved with .XLT at end ofocument name. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double click the template to open a new MS-Excel spreadsheet based on the template to complete and save as a general spreadsheet document with .XLS at end of document name. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only use the .XLT template to open a new spreadsheet to complete. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enquiries"&gt;Enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should contact your local Trading Standards office, which is responsible for enforcing safety legislation within your area. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Find contact details for your local office on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-concerns-in-the-early-stages-of-design"&gt;Safety concerns in the early stages of design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking into account the safety aspects of your products from the outset of design can help limit your liabilities as you may find it easier to comply with current and future legislation if your products are easier to produce, use, maintain and dispose of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the research and design of your products during the early stages of development may also boost your competitiveness through a number of ways such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efficient use of raw materials and resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improved product quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing or removing hazardous materials from your processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better preparation for the end of your product’s lifecycle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased market share and better customer relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While you are creating your product, check that no harm will be caused to makers and consumers by any of the materials or finishing techniques used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a sample of your product is ready for use, check that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is strong enough to support any loads involved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can’t produce any toxic, harmful, or adverse effects on the user or consumer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the materials used are suitable for the purpose and safe for users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all hazards have been sufficiently controlled, eg electrical insulation, moving parts, folding components, noise and poor ergonomic design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you dispose of a product, check that the parts and materials can be dismantled without causing harm or releasing toxic or harmful substances. Ensure that the recycling of any parts or materials will not release toxic or harmful substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasingly there is pressure from stakeholders such as the government, regulators, the supply chain and customers to design products that don’t have a negative impact on the environment or society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="packaging-concerns"&gt;Packaging concerns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packaging includes all products used to contain, protect, handle, deliver or present goods. It includes returnable and non-returnable items such as boxes, pallets, labels, containers, tubes, bags, sacks, timber, glass, metals, plastics and ceramics. It can also include tape, wrapping, binding and tying materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should check that your packaging is designed with safety in mind. The packaging should protect your product in transit and protect your customer from potential injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By opting to use a safety-led choice of packaging, your business will benefit from meeting legal demands, saving money and promoting an efficient image to suppliers and customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the GB’s Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009 (&lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) govern the labelling and packaging of hazardous/dangerous chemicals. Suppliers must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify the hazards of the chemical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give information to their customers about the hazards/dangers, usually on the package itself (such as a label) and provide a safety data sheet (SDS) if the chemicals are to be used at work (provision of an SDS comes under the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and restriction of CHemicals Regulation - REACH)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;package the chemical safely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; has applied to the labels and packaging of hazardous substances since 1 December 2010. It will apply to the labels and packaging of mixtures (called preparations under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) from 1 June 2015 - however, &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; labels and packaging can be used for mixtures prior to that date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulations were amended to bring them into line with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; and REACH regulations. The eventual aim is to have a globally harmonised system for the classification and labelling of hazardous chemicals. Once the &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; requirements for mixtures apply, it is anticipated that the &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; regulations will be repealed. For more information see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/chemicals"&gt;chemicals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://echa.europa.eu/clp/labelling_sds_en.asp"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must take further action if you want to transport dangerous goods. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/moving-goods-by-road"&gt;moving goods by road&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food packaging and labelling is strictly controlled to protect consumers and provide traceability. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/food-labelling-and-packaging"&gt;packaging foods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must keep your use of packaging to a minimum, avoid the use of heavy metals and enable packaging to be recovered. If your business handles more than 50 tonnes of packaging in a year and has a turnover of more than £2 million, you must recover and recycle set amounts of packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="product-liability-and-taking-out-insurance"&gt;Product liability and taking out insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a criminal offence for manufacturers to supply unsafe products. They may also be liable under civil law for any harm such products cause - which could result in costly legal proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Protection Act 1987 makes manufacturers strictly liable for death, injury, loss or damage caused by defective (unsafe) products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a finished product contains a defect in a particular component, both the product manufacturer and component manufacturer may be liable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;download the guide to the product liability and safety provisions of the Consumer Protection Act 1987 from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other suppliers, such as wholesalers and retailers, are not liable unless they fail to identify the producer when asked to do so by a person who has suffered harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But customers can sue retailers under laws on the sale of goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should take positive action to monitor the safety of your products. You should also make sure you are covered by product liability insurance if you manufacture or repair products, and possibly if you sell them, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurance will provide valuable protection for your business against any costs or compensation awarded. Although it’s not a legal requirement to have this type of insurance, it could mean the survival of your business should a claim be made against you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can visit the Association of British Insurers website to download &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.abi.org.uk/Information/Business/15310.pdf"&gt;liability insurance guidance for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-to-get-more-help"&gt;Where to get more help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following links will provide further information on product liability, product safety and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Design Council encourages businesses to understand the design process and to incorporate it into their strategic planning. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/businessandpublicsectorresources"&gt;Read about where to get help on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; has a section on its website called ‘Designers Can Do More’ that looks at issues such as legislation, training and best practice in the design process. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/press/2003/e03234a.htm"&gt;Read information for designers on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; provides wide-ranging support for businesses. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Read about support for businesses on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; provides useful information relating to standards, certification and legislation, together with comprehensive details of &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;Read about standards and &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme) provides a broad range of information and advice on environmental issues including eco-design and packaging. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://envirowise.wrap.org.uk/"&gt;Read information and advice on environmental issues on their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also contact the Envirowise Advice Line on 0800 585 794 for two hours of free advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bsi-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8996 9001&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="communities-and-local-government-helpline"&gt;Communities and Local Government Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0303 444 0000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wrap-resource-efficiency-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; Resource Efficiency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0808 100 2040&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-agency-helpline"&gt;Environment Agency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;03708 506 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biba-consumer-helpline"&gt;BIBA Consumer Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0870 950 1790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Product safety and product recall regulations information on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukas.com/about-accreditation/accredited-bodies"&gt;United Kingdon Accreditation Service Accredited Bodies information on the UKAS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act resources on the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsigroup.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 424K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance"&gt;Download manufacturers, importers and distributors guidance on firework safety rules from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 81K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eig.org.uk/guides/Guide%20to%20the%20Pyrotechnic%20Articles%20(Safety)%20Regulations.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on pyrotechnics regulations from the EIG website (PDF, 3.15MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Fireworks storage risk assessment and guidance for retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;Download Toys (Safety) Regulations guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/sectors/toys/index_en.htm"&gt;Toy sector information on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file25392.pdf"&gt;Download a ‘Choking Risks to Children’ research report from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 419K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Local office contact details on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/our-work/challenges/The-Environment/"&gt;Sustainable design advice on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.venturenavigator.co.uk/assessment/available/2/10"&gt;Product design assessment tool on the Venture Navigator website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Chemical packaging safety guidance on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;Download Consumer Protection Act 1987 product liability and safety guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
