<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-09T14:25:08+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/64318</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T14:25:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:25:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair"/>
    <title>Making the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is changing employment laws to encourage companies to hire staff while protecting employee rights. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses say current employment laws are difficult to cope with and put them off taking on staff. This slows the growth of businesses and the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simpler, more flexible employment laws will make it easier for companies to hire and manage staff, while protecting basic workers’ rights. This should encourage employers to create new jobs, supporting enterprise and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair the government is: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/reviewing-employment-law" title="to make them more flexible for employers and employees"&gt;reviewing employment laws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/introducing-more-flexible-working-practices" title="introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers"&gt;introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/setting-and-enforcing-the-national-minimum-wage" title="setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates"&gt;setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates&lt;/a&gt;  to protect workers from exploitation and businesses from unfair competition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/encouraging-modern-workplaces-and-flexible-working" title="making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments"&gt;making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/providing-guidance-on-employment-law" title="providing better guidance on employment law"&gt;providing better guidance on employment law&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/enforcing-standards-in-employment-agencies-and-employment-businesses-and-recruitment-agencies" title="enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies"&gt;enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies&lt;/a&gt; to better protect workers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/researching-the-labour-market" title="researching the labour market"&gt;researching the labour market&lt;/a&gt; to produce data on employment relations, the labour market and equality at work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We agreed to review employment law in May 2010 as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition-agreement-may-2010_0.pdf" title="Coalition Agreement"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulations launched in April 2011 and includes a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/employment-related-law/" title="review of employment law"&gt;review of employment law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extended the time you need to be employed to be able to claim for unfair dismissal from 1 to 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-bill-policy-paper" title="Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill"&gt;Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill&lt;/a&gt; which will make changes to the employment tribunal system, including ensuring all employment tribunal claims go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acas.org.uk/index.aspx?articleid=1461" title="Acas"&gt;Acas&lt;/a&gt; and introducing a simpler process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removed the compulsory retirement age, making it easier for older people to carry on working&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;launched a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Regional-Mediation-Pilot-Schemes-up-and-running-67b90.aspx"&gt;pilot scheme&lt;/a&gt; encouraging the use of mediation to resolve disputes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reviewed how employment rights are enforced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-consulting"&gt;Who we are consulting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out consultations on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/r/11-511-resolving-workplace-disputes-consultation"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt; more quickly without having to go to an employment tribunal &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules" title="Collective Redundancies: Consultation on changes to the rules"&gt;changing the rules on large-scale redundancies&lt;/a&gt;  so that employers can restructure more effectively while also carrying out good quality consultations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/e/12-1037-ending-the-employment-relationship-consultation.pdf" title="changing the rules on ending the employment relationship"&gt;changing the rules on ending the employment relationship&lt;/a&gt;, the use of settlement agreements and changes to the compensation limit in unfair dismissal cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/employment-tribunal-rules-review-by-mr-justice-underhill"&gt;changing employment tribunal rules&lt;/a&gt; to make them more flexible and effective and to get better value for the taxpayer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out an impact assessment on the benefits of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/r/11-1381-resolving-workplace-disputes-final-impact-assessment"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt;. We estimate these changes will save businesses £40 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64952</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T13:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T13:15:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-viscount-younger-of-leckie-appointed-as-business-minister"/>
    <title>The Viscount Younger of Leckie appointed as Business Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Lord Younger appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger was appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills, by the Prime Minister today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger will be responsible for all of the  Department for Business Innovation and Skills business in the House of Lords, in particular steering the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill through its final stages in the Lords. He will also have responsibility for the Intellectual Property portfolio. Lord Younger was previously a Government Whip in the House of Lords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Lord Younger said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have been asked by the Prime Minister to do this important job; the business department is central to the Government’s drive for balanced and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I look forward to making a real contribution to supporting business to generate new private sector employment and boost our international competiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to entering the House of Lords Lord Younger had a 25 year career in the human resources industry and financial services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Full list of Lord Younger’s Ministerial responsibilities will be published shortly. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/64300</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"/>
    <title>Countering weapons proliferation </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Securing global safety by preventing countries and terrorists access to the materials needed for weapons of mass destruction.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of weapons of mass destruction (&lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;) poses a threat to the UK and the international community. Indiscriminate trade in conventional arms and the use of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (&lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt;) weapons and ballistic missiles raises serious humanitarian and security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working around the world to champion and implement UK policies as set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the spread of &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; weapons and ballistic missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works with international partners and through organisations such as the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, G8, NATO and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce terrorists’ ability to create, obtain or use &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; materials and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the FCO’s tools to combat these threats is our Counter-Proliferation Programme. In the financial year 2012 to 13, the value of the programme is £3 million. This funding is used to support projects around the world which increase political will or technical capacity to reduce the threat of weapons proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-counter-proliferation-strategy"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in March 2012. The strategy’s main aims are to deny terrorists the materials and expertise to make and use &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;; to stop countries such as Iran and North Korea from obtaining &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt; or advanced conventional weapons; and to build up the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/About/"&gt;International Atomic Energy Agency (&lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; and other organisations and treaties that help us meet our goals through the international community and which help to protect global security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemical-weapons"&gt;Chemical weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the destruction of remaining chemical weapons stocks and works to encourage full national implementation of the Chemical Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;) by all countries. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/the-chemical-weapons-convention"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention&lt;/a&gt; bans the development, production, stockpiling and use of chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biological-weapons"&gt;Biological weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has signed up to the global implementation of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/04FBBDD6315AC720C1257180004B1B2F?OpenDocument"&gt;Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of the convention is to help prevent states acquiring or keeping biological and toxin weapons, and prevent them ever being used by states or terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt; doesn’t have a verification system like that of the &lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Participating countries are required to submit relevant data and declarations, or confidence-building measures, to the United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs. This increases openness and gives participating countries confidence that others are complying with the convention. The UK’s confidence building measures are published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/CEC2E2D361ADFEE7C12572BC0032F058?OpenDocument"&gt;Implementation Support Unit website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-weapons"&gt;Nuclear weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;. The UK is one of 189 states that have signed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The treaty aims to stop the spread of nuclear weapons and ultimately eliminate them. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; has three equally important ‘pillars’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to work towards non-proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to champion nuclear disarmament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nuclear-security"&gt;Nuclear security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK will continue work to strengthen international nuclear security by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the security of fissile materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing the number of sites containing nuclear and radiological material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing the acquisition of proliferation-relevant information and expertise by terrorists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through the successful development of the UK’s Global Threat Reduction Programme we are reducing the threats posed by nuclear and radiological materials and expertise in vulnerable locations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting the full implementation of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sc8076.doc.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Resolution 1540&lt;/a&gt;, which requires all states to refrain from supporting non-government agents from developing, acquiring, manufacturing, possessing, transporting, transferring or using nuclear, chemical or biological weapons and their delivery systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK also supports and contributes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nti.org/treaties-and-regimes/global-partnership-against-spread-weapons-and-materials-mass-destruction-10-plus-10-over-10-program/"&gt;Global Partnership Against the Spread of Weapons and Materials of Mass Destruction&lt;/a&gt;, agreed at the G8 Summit at Kananaskis, Canada in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-programmes"&gt;State programmes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the international legal framework, conventions and treaties, some countries have active programmes to develop and produce &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Of particular concern is Iran’s nuclear programme; the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s nuclear programme and willingness to provide weapons to other countries; and Syria’s possession of chemical and biological weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works through various international organisations to seek peaceful means to reduce the threat from these programmes and the networks that support them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arms-trade-treaty"&gt;Arms Trade Treaty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a legitimate arms trade, there is also an urgent need for more effective and coherent international regulation of that trade. The UK is working to achieve an international arms trade treaty to provide clearer and more effective control of the illegal arms trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; conference in July 2012 was unable to adopt an Arms Trade Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, the UK will continue to play a leading role in future negotiations to help to secure one. An &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to reduce the flow of weapons from legitimate trade to the illicit market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; process towards an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; and submissions from states (including the UK’s views on an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/first/63/documentation.shtml"&gt;United Nations General Assembly website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="export-licensing"&gt;Export licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has joined other governments around the world to pursue &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/3849543/eu-arms-export"&gt;collective implementation of export controls&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the proliferation of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The 4 main export control regimes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.australiagroup.net/en/index.html"&gt;Australia Group&lt;/a&gt; - designed to harmonise export control measures aimed at curtailing the unhindered proliferation of chemical weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mtcr.info/english/index.html"&gt;Missile Technology Control Regime&lt;/a&gt; - an informal and voluntary association of countries that share the goal of non-proliferation of unmanned delivery systems of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/Leng/default.htm"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt; - responsible for making sure nuclear export controls work in practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt; - established to promote transparency and greater responsiblity in transfers of conventional arms and dual-use goods and technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read further details about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s regulatory authority responsible for assessing and issuing strategic export licences to UK exporters is the Export Control Organisation (ECO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS). Read more about the UK’s policies and procedures for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2"&gt;controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;) was born out of fear that the Cold War era would lead to a nuclear arms race and is still the basis of the international nuclear non-proliferation regime. All states are now party to it apart from India, Israel, Pakistan and South Sudan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; provides for a Review Conference every 5 years, both to review developments over the previous 5 years and to look ahead to the future. At the last &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;Review Conference in 2010&lt;/a&gt; a series of action plans were agreed to enhance implementation of the treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/"&gt;The International Atomic Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt; was set up as the world’s ‘Atoms for Peace’ organisation in 1957 within the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; family, and supports the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The agency is at the centre of international efforts to address Iran’s nuclear dossier and to ensure the benefits of safe and secure peaceful nuclear energy are accessible to everyone, not just to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thenuclearsecuritysummit.org/eng_main/main.jsp"&gt;Seoul Nuclear Security Summit&lt;/a&gt; assembled 53 countries, the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; and Interpol, to continue work to secure vulnerable nuclear material around the world within 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 December 2008 in the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly, 133 States voted in favour of a draft resolution ‘Towards an Arms Trade Treaty’. There was a clear majority view that, working together, the international community can shape an Arms Trade Treaty into an effective legally binding mechanism to regulate the international trade in arms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our detailed guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-embargoes-and-restrictions"&gt;sanctions, embargoes and restrictions.&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/current-arms-embargoes-and-other-restrictions"&gt;Current arms embargoes and other restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the Common Foreign and Security Policy (&lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; applies restrictive measures in pursuit of the specific &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; objectives set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/treaties/index.htm"&gt;Treaty on European Union.&lt;/a&gt; (see particularly Article 11)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; External Action website&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of restrictive measures adopted in the framework of the &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; that are currently in force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/sc/committees/list_compend.shtml"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Sanctions Committees website&lt;/a&gt; contains links to the latest versions of all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council targeted sanctions lists. The individuals and entities included in these lists are subject to the relevant measures imposed by the Security Council, and all member states are obliged to implement these measures. Each separate list is maintained by the relevant Security Council Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64302</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/building-materials-and-components-statistics-december-2012"/>
    <title>Building materials and components statistics: December 2012</title>
    <category>Statistical data set</category>
    <summary>Statistics and analysis on the construction sector
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presents information on selected building materials, including monthly data on price indices, bricks, cement and concrete blocks. It also presents quarterly data on sand and gravel, slate, concrete roofing tiles, ready-mixed concrete and imports and exports of construction products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69439"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/thumbnail_13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/313A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;481 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;40 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69440"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48974/13-313a-data-construction-building-materials-tables-december-2012.xls" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48974/13-313a-data-construction-building-materials-tables-december-2012.xls"&gt;Building materials and components: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/313A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;687 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69441"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/thumbnail_13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components commentary: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/P125A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;102 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64915</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:27:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-workforce-management-april-2012-to-october-2012"/>
    <title>BIS workforce management: April 2012 to November 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Management information on staff numbers and paybill costs in BIS, its agencies and executive non-departmental public bodies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For workforce numbers, both payroll and non-payroll (contingent labour, including consultants) information is provided, split between full-time equivalents (FTE) and headcount, with payroll staff numbers mapped to standard Civil Service grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For costs, payroll paybill information is broken down into its component parts i.e. salaries, allowances, employers pensions contributions etc. For non-payroll costs, these are split between costs for consultancy and those of other non-payroll workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covers April to November of the financial year 2012 to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64919</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-workforce-management-november-2012"/>
    <title>BIS workforce management: November 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Management information on staff numbers and paybill costs in BIS, its agencies and executive non-departmental public bodies</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For workforce numbers, both payroll and non-payroll (contingent labour, including consultants) information is provided, split between full-time equivalents (FTE) and headcount, with payroll staff numbers mapped to standard Civil Service grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For costs, payroll paybill information is broken down into its component parts ie salaries, allowances, employers pensions contributions etc. For non-payroll costs, these are split between costs for consultancy and those of other non-payroll workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covers November of the financial year 2012 to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64247</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-geraint-jones-appointed-as-reviewer-for-the-office-for-fair-access"/>
    <title>Press Release: Geraint Jones appointed as reviewer for the Office For Fair Access</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, announced today that he is appointing Geraint Jones as the statutory reviewer for OFFA. Should a university or college object to a provisional decision by the Director of Fair Access, the reviewer can be asked to assess the case impartially. He may recommend that there are grounds for the Director to reconsider his decision.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geraint Jones QC was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge before going to the Bar in 1976. He took silk in 2001 and is now recognised as a leading commercial and Chancery practitioner with extensive experience of judicial review work. He has an undoubted reputation for fearless independence and impartiality in upholding the rule of law. He sits as a Recorder and as a part-time Judge of the Tax Tribunal. He is also an arbitrator at the International Court of Arbitration for Sport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that Geraint Jones will be the reviewer for OFFA, his skills and experience, if called upon, will be of great value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The position of statutory reviewer for OFFA has been in place since OFFA was established in 2004. So far there has been no need to call upon the services of the statutory reviewer. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the ‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB), published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/64200</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T13:24:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T13:24:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/product-safety-for-manufacturers"/>
    <title>Product safety for manufacturers</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Technical and legal requirements for safety, design, packaging and insurance, to ensure products are safe and fit for purpose.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design and manufacturing processes are essential to ensure you meet these technical and legal requirements. They can also give your business a competitive edge and save costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide sets out the key safety, design, packaging and insurance issues you need to consider in relation to your products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="your-legal-responsibilities"&gt;Your legal responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Sale of Goods Act 1979, all products must be ‘fit for purpose’, be of satisfactory quality and fit its description. This means that your products must fulfil the purpose the customer has been led to expect and the reasons that led them to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act also covers any purpose that a customer asks about when the product is purchased and is guaranteed by the retailer to meet that purpose when it is sold. If a product is not fit for purpose, the customer is within their rights to have the goods replaced or repaired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act guidance on the Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, good design will lead to safe design. While meeting your legal obligations is the minimum required, it is a good idea to go further and take best practice on board throughout the design, production, supply and disposal stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a manufacturer or supplier you could be held liable in any legal action for harm caused to consumers or businesses as a result of unintended side-effects or the failure of products manufactured or supplied by you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your manufacturing and processing systems must comply with environmental law. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/"&gt;read guidance to help you keep up with your environmental responsibilities on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="products-covered-by-specific-safety-regulations"&gt;Products covered by specific safety regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a manufacturer’s claim that its product meets specified essential safety requirements set out in relevant European directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain categories of products must bear &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you intend to sell them in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;member states of the European Economic area (&lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;) - Iceland, Liechtenstein and Norway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following categories of products require &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you wish to sell them within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or member states of the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electrical products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;construction products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure vessels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;telecommunications equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;machinery, equipment and safety components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;personal protective equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;satellite station equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gas appliances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appliances (other than gas)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-automatic weighing instruments and equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recreational craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lift machinery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;equipment and protective systems for explosive atmospheres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in vitro diagnostic medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marine equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety components and subsystems for incorporation into cableway installations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cableway equipment (ski tows etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The requirement for &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the exact process you will need to go through varies from product to product. Different types of product are governed by different European directives. For example, the trade of certain machinery, equipment and safety components is governed by the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations 2008. The regulations implement a European directive aimed at removing technical barriers to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the regulations, products that conform to the relevant safety standards are &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked and can be placed on the market across the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Responsibility for ensuring compliance with the regulations rests with the manufacturer of the machinery, equipment or components in question. Failure to do so can result in prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations (PDF, 424KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where an item of equipment is covered by more than one directive, it must be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked under all applicable directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply consumer products which aren’t covered by these specific directives, they must not be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked. However, you still have a general duty to ensure they are safe for normal or reasonably foreseeable use under the General Product Safety Regulations 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fireworks---information-for-suppliers-retailers-and-display-event-organisers"&gt;Fireworks - information for suppliers, retailers and display event organisers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireworks are available throughout the year from shops licensed to supply them. They become widely available at certain times of the year, mainly a few days before New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year, and in the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night on 5 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply or sell fireworks or if you organise display events you must be aware of your responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-as-a-firework-manufacturer-or-importer"&gt;Your responsibilities as a firework manufacturer or importer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks or import category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks which are manufactured outside the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, you must ensure they conform to European safety standards before supplying them for sale to the public. To do this, you need to ensure that the fireworks have been tested by a notified body (&lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the &lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt; has approved them, the products must carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and be correctly labelled with details of the manufacturer and importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyrotechnics that were manufactured or imported before 4 July 2010 and that complied with British Standard BS 7114 can continue to be sold without the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark until 4 July 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 3 fireworks must not exceed 120 decibels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 4 display fireworks that are not intended for supply to consumers must be marked accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import fireworks, you must ensure they comply with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards, carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and supply information at the point of entry to ensure that fireworks are legally stored and distributed. This information should be given to HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs and will then be sent to the relevant authorities responsible for storage licences so they can check on deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licensing authorities can ask to see information relating to transactions of fireworks exceeding 50 kilograms of net explosive content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69159"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48948/13-551-pyrotechnic-articles-regulations-guidelines-on-notified-bodies1.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48948/thumbnail_13-551-pyrotechnic-articles-regulations-guidelines-on-notified-bodies1.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48948/13-551-pyrotechnic-articles-regulations-guidelines-on-notified-bodies1.pdf"&gt;The Pyrotechnic Articles (Safety) Regulations 2010: guidelines on the appointment of UK notified bodies to undertake conformity assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;188 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;23 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-if-you-are-a-fireworks-retailer"&gt;Your responsibilities if you are a fireworks retailer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to sell fireworks to the public, you need to register your shop or obtain a licence from your local authority. The penalties for not registering or being licensed are a fine of up to £5,000, a prison sentence of up to 3 months, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is illegal for retailers to sell caps, cracker snaps, novelty matches, party poppers, serpents and throwdowns to anyone who is under 16 and to sell all other fireworks to anyone who is under 18 - it is recommended that proof of age is sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must display a large notice reminding customers about the law with regard to underage sales and possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can only sell fireworks that conform to &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards (or British Standard BS 7114 if they were produced before 4 July 2010) and which carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and meet certain noise conditions. They must have the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark or BS 7114 printed on each item or on the retail packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also supply fireworks with any safety instructions provided by the manufacturer or importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxes of fireworks must not be split and sold separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you have a special licence, you can only sell fireworks during the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night, New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Find a fireworks storage risk assessment checklist and information about storing and selling fireworks in retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;Find &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cosmetic-products-safety-regulations"&gt;Cosmetic Products Safety Regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All cosmetic products supplied in the UK, whether for consumer or professional use, must comply with the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008 (as amended). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 13 July 2013 a new directly applicable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:342:0059:0209:EN:PDF"&gt;European Regulation (EC/1223/2009)&lt;/a&gt; enters into force, replacing the existing legislation, (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new notification procedure, which requires every product placed on the market to be notified to the European Commission is already in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guidance notes explain all aspects of the Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69155"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-69155-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/thumbnail_10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-69155-accessibility-help"&gt;A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;220 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;42 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69155-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Regulations require that finished cosmetic products must undergo a safety assessment by a suitably qualified person before they can be placed on the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file50357.pdf"&gt;The Cosmetics Directive&lt;/a&gt; on which the Regulations are based is updated periodically, reflecting changes to the prohibitions and restrictions on certain substances, and subsequent amendments to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1284/contents/made"&gt;Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt; are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/"&gt;OPSI website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amendments since then are contained, available on the same website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2173 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2566 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/796 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/1346 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No3) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/2562 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No4) Regulations 2009. S.I. 2009/3367 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2010, S.I. 2010/1150 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2010. S.I. 2010/1927 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2011, S.I. 2012/3037&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 31 October 2012 a new directive enters into force, which is mirrored in S.I. 2012/2263, and which liberalises the use of hydrogen peroxide at up to 6% for tooth whitening purposes, subject to first use by a dentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition various hair dye substances are due to be restricted from 1 September 2013, under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:208:0008:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Directive 2012/21/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is not intending to transpose this because it will be overtaken by the new European Regulation (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-european-regulation"&gt;The European Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has firstly altered the procedure for notification of each product, requiring notification direct to the European Commission using the Cosmetics Product Notification Portal, (CPNP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is operational now and can be used, although it does not become mandatory until the Regulation enters into force: see the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_new_en.pdf"&gt;Cosmetics Products Notification Portal document&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_user_manual_en.pdf"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Regulation is directly applicable and it changes various elements, relating to the safety assessment, the responsible person in respect of that, and nanomaterials. There will be further guidance issued, as details which have still to be negotiated are finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-regulations-for-childrens-products"&gt;Safety regulations for children’s products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys supplied in the UK must meet the requirements of the Toys (Safety) Regulations 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations define a toy as ‘any product or material designed or clearly intended for use in play by children of less than 14 years of age, but excluding those products specified in Schedule 3 [of the regulations]’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;download a guide to the Toys (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that a revised European directive will come into force on 20 July 2011. The directive substantially amends the existing regulations across virtually all safety aspects. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:170:0001:0037:EN:PDF"&gt;download the text of the new Directive 2009/48/EC from the EUR-Lex website (PDF, 995K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ce-marking-on-toys"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys presented for sale in the UK must bear the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the name and address of the person who first placed the toy on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a declaration by the manufacturer that the product satisfies essential safety requirements and can be sold within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. For more information see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authority trading standards officers can remove a toy from the market if they believe it to be unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="testing-for-toys"&gt;Testing for toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture a toy in accordance with the regulations - and the standards cover all aspects relating to the toy - then it can be self-certified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the standards do not cover all aspects relating to the toy, a sample must be submitted for type examination by an approved body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import toys you are responsible for their safety, whether or not they already bear a &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark. You might want to consider having them tested to ensure they are safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-child-safety-regulations"&gt;Other child safety regulations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other laws relating to child safety include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flammability - tough performance requirements regarding flammability are compulsory for children’s nightdresses and dressing gowns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;choking risks - toys intended for children under 36 months must not present a choking risk - the test uses the ‘small parts cylinder’ (toys or parts of toys that can fit entirely inside the cylinder are identified as choking hazards)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;magnetic parts - magnets which have a flux of more than 50 kG2mm2 (0,5 T2mm2) and fit entirely in the small parts cylinder are not permitted for use in toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chemicals - the revised European Directive 2009/48/EC will limit the amounts of certain chemicals that may be contained in materials used for toys - these parts of the directive relating to chemical content will come into force on 20 July 2013 (there is also a ban on the use of six phthalates in toys and products for children under 3 years of age)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other products - hood cords, bunk beds and prams and pushchairs are subject to specific safety regulations, namely the Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976, the Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 and the Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="general-product-safety-regulations"&gt;General Product safety regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General product safety is regulated by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/1803/contents/made"&gt;General Product Safety Regulations 2005 (GPS Regulations)&lt;/a&gt;. They apply to all products (new and second-hand) used by consumers. Product-specific legislation continues to take precedence in areas where the provisions have similar objectives to the GPS Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPS Regulations maintain the general duty placed on producers and distributors to place on the market (or supply) only products that are safe in normal or reasonable foreseeable use. The principal responsibility for day-to-day enforcement of the Regulations lies with local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPS Regulations recognise certain technical standards as carrying a presumption of conformity with the general safety requirement, meaning that products that comply with them are deemed to be safe. An up-to-date list of European Standards is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/euro_standards/index_en.htm"&gt;European Commission Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rapid-alert-system-for-non-food-consumer-products-rapex"&gt;Rapid Alert System for non-food consumer products (RAPEX)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAPEX is the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; rapid alert system for dangerous consumer products – with the exception of food, pharmaceutical and medical devices which are covered by other mechanisms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It facilitates the rapid exchange of information between Member States and the Commission on measures to prevent or restrict the marketing or use of products posing a serious risk to the health and safety of consumers. Both measures ordered by national authorities and measures taken voluntarily by producers and distributors are reported by RAPEX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-does-rapex-work"&gt;How does RAPEX work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a product (eg a toy, childcare article or household appliance) is found to be dangerous, the competent national authority takes appropriate action to eliminate the risk. It can withdraw the product from the market, recall it, or issue warnings. The National Contact Point then informs the European Commission (Directorate-General for Health and Consumer Protection) about the product, the risks it poses to consumers and the measures taken by the authority to prevent risks and accidents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission disseminates the information that it receives to the National Contact Points of all other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; countries. It publishes weekly overviews of dangerous products and the measures taken to eliminate the risks on the internet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Contact Points in each &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; country ensure that the authorities responsible check whether the newly notified dangerous product is present on the market. If so, the authorities take measures to eliminate the risk, either by requiring that the product be withdrawn from the market, by recalling it from consumers or by issuing warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weekly overview of the dangerous products reported by the national authorities (the RAPEX notifications) is published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/dyna/rapex/rapex_archives_en.cfm"&gt;Commission Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="product-recall"&gt;‘Product recall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trading Standards Central web site contains &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/advice-recall-list.cfm"&gt;a list of product safety notices and recalls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are concerned about the safety of a product, make your concern clear to the retailer, manufacturer or local trading standards department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a producer or distributor of consumer products on sale in the European Union (&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;), the attached guide gives you general advice about what you should do if you have evidence that one of your products may be unsafe. It is a voluntary guide to carrying out corrective actions for product safety, supported by the market surveillance authorities in Member States and consumer and trade organisations within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;.  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/cons_safe/action_guide_en.pdf"&gt;Product Safety in Europe: A Guide to corrective action including recalls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unsafe-product-notification"&gt;Unsafe product notification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producers and distributors have a duty to notify local authorities when they become aware they have placed on the market, or distributed, an unsafe product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20100125143037/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/files/file23032.pdf"&gt;General Product Safety Regulations 2005 - notification guidance for producers and distributors&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20100125143037/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/files/file23040.doc"&gt;Producer and Distributor Form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make this process simpler a business application form has been designed. There are two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the notification form - which the producer or distributor should fill in &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the online database - used exclusively by the authorities of Member States to view and process notifications (in the case of the UK the National Contact Point for RAPEX at &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance and the form can be accessed on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://webgate.ec.europa.eu/gpsd-ba/index.do;jsessionid=MGycbGHrnV9ZQCdsDhYv0PLQB0GqQ7c47X4J6gqy2chSsc69nny5!443991619"&gt;the EUROPA Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authority enforcers have a duty to inform &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; of products placed on the market that either present a:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serious risk in need of urgent intervention &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-serious risk requiring some intervention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance for local authorities on informing &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; about products is available by following the links below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/rapex/docs/rapex_guid_26012010_en.pdf"&gt;Operational (Member State market surveillance) RAPEX guidelines&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/safety/rapex/guidelines_states_en.htm"&gt;Member State Rapex Guidelines and Risk Assessment&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Risk Categories for RAPEX notification form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69158"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39622/standard-notification-form-risk-categories.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-69158-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39622/standard-notification-form-risk-categories.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-69158-accessibility-help"&gt;Standard notification risk form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;96.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69158-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Standard%20notification%20risk%20form%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Standard%20notification%20risk%20form%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Standard notification risk form").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RAPEX notification form (for local authority use) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69156"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39610/rapex-notification-form-xlt.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-69156-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39610/rapex-notification-form-xlt.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-69156-accessibility-help"&gt;Rapex notification form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;73 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69156-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Rapex%20notification%20form%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Rapex%20notification%20form%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Rapex notification form").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reaction to RAPEX notification form (for local authority use)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69157"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39612/reaction-to-rapex.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-69157-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39612/reaction-to-rapex.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-69157-accessibility-help"&gt;Reaction to Rapex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;62 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69157-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Reaction%20to%20Rapex%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Reaction%20to%20Rapex%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Reaction to Rapex").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local authorities - please note the Rapex and Reaction forms above are MS-Excel spreadsheet templates. See the following points on using and saving the forms to your PC: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From weblink click ‘Save’ without opening, ensure document is saved with .XLT at end ofocument name. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double click the template to open a new MS-Excel spreadsheet based on the template to complete and save as a general spreadsheet document with .XLS at end of document name. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only use the .XLT template to open a new spreadsheet to complete. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enquiries"&gt;Enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should contact your local Trading Standards office, which is responsible for enforcing safety legislation within your area. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Find contact details for your local office on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-concerns-in-the-early-stages-of-design"&gt;Safety concerns in the early stages of design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking into account the safety aspects of your products from the outset of design can help limit your liabilities as you may find it easier to comply with current and future legislation if your products are easier to produce, use, maintain and dispose of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the research and design of your products during the early stages of development may also boost your competitiveness through a number of ways such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efficient use of raw materials and resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improved product quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing or removing hazardous materials from your processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better preparation for the end of your product’s lifecycle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased market share and better customer relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While you are creating your product, check that no harm will be caused to makers and consumers by any of the materials or finishing techniques used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a sample of your product is ready for use, check that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is strong enough to support any loads involved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can’t produce any toxic, harmful, or adverse effects on the user or consumer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the materials used are suitable for the purpose and safe for users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all hazards have been sufficiently controlled, eg electrical insulation, moving parts, folding components, noise and poor ergonomic design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you dispose of a product, check that the parts and materials can be dismantled without causing harm or releasing toxic or harmful substances. Ensure that the recycling of any parts or materials will not release toxic or harmful substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasingly there is pressure from stakeholders such as the government, regulators, the supply chain and customers to design products that don’t have a negative impact on the environment or society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="packaging-concerns"&gt;Packaging concerns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packaging includes all products used to contain, protect, handle, deliver or present goods. It includes returnable and non-returnable items such as boxes, pallets, labels, containers, tubes, bags, sacks, timber, glass, metals, plastics and ceramics. It can also include tape, wrapping, binding and tying materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should check that your packaging is designed with safety in mind. The packaging should protect your product in transit and protect your customer from potential injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By opting to use a safety-led choice of packaging, your business will benefit from meeting legal demands, saving money and promoting an efficient image to suppliers and customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the GB’s Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009 (&lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) govern the labelling and packaging of hazardous/dangerous chemicals. Suppliers must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify the hazards of the chemical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give information to their customers about the hazards/dangers, usually on the package itself (such as a label) and provide a safety data sheet (SDS) if the chemicals are to be used at work (provision of an SDS comes under the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and restriction of CHemicals Regulation - REACH)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;package the chemical safely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; has applied to the labels and packaging of hazardous substances since 1 December 2010. It will apply to the labels and packaging of mixtures (called preparations under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) from 1 June 2015 - however, &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; labels and packaging can be used for mixtures prior to that date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulations were amended to bring them into line with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; and REACH regulations. The eventual aim is to have a globally harmonised system for the classification and labelling of hazardous chemicals. Once the &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; requirements for mixtures apply, it is anticipated that the &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; regulations will be repealed. For more information see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/chemicals"&gt;chemicals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://echa.europa.eu/clp/labelling_sds_en.asp"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must take further action if you want to transport dangerous goods. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/moving-goods-by-road"&gt;moving goods by road&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food packaging and labelling is strictly controlled to protect consumers and provide traceability. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/food-labelling-and-packaging"&gt;packaging foods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must keep your use of packaging to a minimum, avoid the use of heavy metals and enable packaging to be recovered. If your business handles more than 50 tonnes of packaging in a year and has a turnover of more than £2 million, you must recover and recycle set amounts of packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="product-liability-and-taking-out-insurance"&gt;Product liability and taking out insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a criminal offence for manufacturers to supply unsafe products. They may also be liable under civil law for any harm such products cause - which could result in costly legal proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Protection Act 1987 makes manufacturers strictly liable for death, injury, loss or damage caused by defective (unsafe) products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a finished product contains a defect in a particular component, both the product manufacturer and component manufacturer may be liable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;download the guide to the product liability and safety provisions of the Consumer Protection Act 1987 from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other suppliers, such as wholesalers and retailers, are not liable unless they fail to identify the producer when asked to do so by a person who has suffered harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But customers can sue retailers under laws on the sale of goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should take positive action to monitor the safety of your products. You should also make sure you are covered by product liability insurance if you manufacture or repair products, and possibly if you sell them, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurance will provide valuable protection for your business against any costs or compensation awarded. Although it’s not a legal requirement to have this type of insurance, it could mean the survival of your business should a claim be made against you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can visit the Association of British Insurers website to download &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.abi.org.uk/Information/Business/15310.pdf"&gt;liability insurance guidance for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-to-get-more-help"&gt;Where to get more help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following links will provide further information on product liability, product safety and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Design Council encourages businesses to understand the design process and to incorporate it into their strategic planning. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/businessandpublicsectorresources"&gt;Read about where to get help on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; has a section on its website called ‘Designers Can Do More’ that looks at issues such as legislation, training and best practice in the design process. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/press/2003/e03234a.htm"&gt;Read information for designers on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; provides wide-ranging support for businesses. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Read about support for businesses on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; provides useful information relating to standards, certification and legislation, together with comprehensive details of &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;Read about standards and &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme) provides a broad range of information and advice on environmental issues including eco-design and packaging. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://envirowise.wrap.org.uk/"&gt;Read information and advice on environmental issues on their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also contact the Envirowise Advice Line on 0800 585 794 for two hours of free advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bsi-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8996 9001&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="communities-and-local-government-helpline"&gt;Communities and Local Government Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0303 444 0000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wrap-resource-efficiency-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; Resource Efficiency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0808 100 2040&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-agency-helpline"&gt;Environment Agency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;03708 506 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biba-consumer-helpline"&gt;BIBA Consumer Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0870 950 1790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Product safety and product recall regulations information on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukas.com/about-accreditation/accredited-bodies"&gt;United Kingdon Accreditation Service Accredited Bodies information on the UKAS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act resources on the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsigroup.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 424K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance"&gt;Download manufacturers, importers and distributors guidance on firework safety rules from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 81K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eig.org.uk/guides/Guide%20to%20the%20Pyrotechnic%20Articles%20(Safety)%20Regulations.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on pyrotechnics regulations from the EIG website (PDF, 3.15MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Fireworks storage risk assessment and guidance for retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;Download Toys (Safety) Regulations guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/sectors/toys/index_en.htm"&gt;Toy sector information on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file25392.pdf"&gt;Download a ‘Choking Risks to Children’ research report from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 419K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Local office contact details on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/our-work/challenges/The-Environment/"&gt;Sustainable design advice on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.venturenavigator.co.uk/assessment/available/2/10"&gt;Product design assessment tool on the Venture Navigator website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Chemical packaging safety guidance on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;Download Consumer Protection Act 1987 product liability and safety guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64214</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T11:41:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T11:41:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-chief-executive-designate-appointed-to-the-competition-and-markets-authority"/>
    <title>Press Release: Chief Executive Designate appointed to the Competition and Markets Authority</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alex Chisholm was today appointed the new Chief Executive of the Competition and Markets Authority by the Business Secretary Vince Cable.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a single, streamlined authority, the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) will drive competition policy. There are substantial economic benefits from a tough regime cracking down hard and quickly on cartels and monopolies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very pleased that Mr Chisholm is joining the CMA as Chief Executive, to lead the organisation alongside the Chair, Lord Currie. His expertise in economic regulation and wider experience in business and the public sector will play a crucial role strengthening the UK’s world class competition regime, building on the excellent record of the Office of Fair Trading and Competition Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMA Chair, Lord David Currie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I greatly look forward to working with Alex Chisholm to make the Competition and Markets Authority a world class competition and consumer protection body, that will generate major benefits for the British economy and for consumers and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMA Chief Executive Designate Alex Chisholm said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have the opportunity to lead the establishment of the Competition and Markets Authority, which has a vital part to play in helping competition and markets to thrive during this time of significant economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I look forward to working with the Office of Fair Trading and the Competition Commission, and with the wider government, business and consumer communities, to ensure the new authority is dynamic, efficient and accountable”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Chisholm will take up his five year appointment on 25 March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="biography"&gt;Biography&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since October 2007 Alex Chisholm has been Commissioner at the Commission for Communications Regulation (ComReg) Ireland, and Chairperson of the Commission since February 2010. Since April 2011, Mr Chisholm has also served as Chair of the Economic Regulators Network in Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining ComReg, Mr Chisholm held a number of executive positions in the media, IT and communications industries, including Chief Executive of Ecceleration Ltd, Ecommerce Director at eCountries Inc, Publisher and General Manager in the Financial Times Group, and Development Manager at Pearson plc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also served for six years in the UK’s Department of Trade &amp;amp; Industry and Office of Fair Trading, specialising in competition policy and the media, communications and financial services sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm holds an MBA from INSEAD Business School (1997) and an MA from Oxford University (1989). In August 2012 he completed the Senior Managers in Government programme at the Harvard Kennedy School. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm is also currently involved in charitable work as Trustee and Deputy Chairman of the international charity Breadline Africa. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive will be the Accounting Officer for the CMA and a member of the CMA Board. He will lead the organisational design of the CMA and shaping of its competition processes. The Chief Executive will take ownership of the shadow organisation and along with the Chair Designate, will drive forward the creation of the CMA in bringing together the Office of Fair Trading (OFT) and the Competition Commission (CC) as a single, unified body by April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive’s appointment will be subject to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill receiving Royal Assent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive’s remuneration will be £190k per annum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The appointment was made on merit in accordance with the Civil Service Commissioner’s Recruitment Principles.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm has no current conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government announced its plans for the creation of the CMA in March 2012. It will bring together the CC and the competition, markets and some consumer protection functions of the OFT to become a world-leading unitary authority, advocating competition both at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government recognises and values the close relationship between competition problems and consumer activities.  The CMA will therefore have the OFT and Competition Commission’s full competition toolkit and consumer protection enforcement powers.  It will have the power to tackle practices and market conditions that make it difficult for consumers to exercise choice in an otherwise competitive market.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unified CMA will bring about significant benefits to business and consumers, including greater coherence, flexibility, speed and transparency in the operation of the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
