<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Transport</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56774</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-ec-392-2009"/>
    <title>Consultation on the implementation of EU Regulation (EC) 392/2009</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the UK’s draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation gives effect, within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention to create parity for the passenger shipping industry and help ensure that UK citizens have access to the same levels of compensation when travelling between two different &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states. Furthermore, it increases the limits of liabilities for death or personal injuries to passengers being carried by sea; requires carriers to have compulsory insurance, and provides claimants with the right of taking direct action against the insurers. The intended effect is to provide an enhanced framework of compensation in the event of death or personal injury to a passenger, or the loss or damage to luggage when travelling on a sea journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation also brings into scope certain domestic passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56725</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"/>
    <title>Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation guidance for suppliers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of it comes from sustainable renewable sources. Guidance has been in place to assist suppliers with compliance since the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; was first introduced. Obligated suppliers are consulted each year on revisions to the guidance. These have taken into account the latest European and domestic legislative developments and experience in operating the obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"&gt;Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56290</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/industry-launches-new-rail-technical-strategy"/>
    <title>Industry launches new rail technical strategy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail industry leaders have outlined a 30 year vision for the railway through a new edition of the ‘Rail technical strategy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Rail technical strategy’ describes how technology can help the railway increase capacity, improve reliability, cut carbon emissions and reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy has been developed by the Technical Strategy Leadership Group – a cross-industry expert body with representatives from across the rail industry – and endorsed by the Rail Delivery Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.futurerailway.org"&gt;Read the Rail technical strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Transport  Simon Burns MP welcomed the strategy saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the industry picking up the baton to develop this Rail technical strategy. Technology has a vital role to play in improving the railway’s performance, cutting its costs along with carbon emissions and delivering a better travelling experience for passengers. By setting in place a 30 year vision, the railway is demonstrating that it has a bright and exciting future, and the potential to support our economy and society for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57003</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"/>
    <title>Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport asked Ecofys to produce a report on the current animal fat (tallow) market to assess whether there has been any impact from allowing double counting of biodiesel produced from category 1 tallow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to explain the issue, the risks, and the available data relating to the tallow market to enable the department to set out its approach to monitoring impacts and also seek stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"&gt;Consultation about the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation suppliers’ guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56448</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T17:28:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:28:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/revisions-to-the-levels-of-funding-required-by-goods-and-public-service-vehicle-licence-holders"/>
    <title>Revisions to the levels of funding required by goods and public service vehicle licence holders</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has given notice of revisions to the levels of funding required by holders of goods and public service vehicle operators’ licences operating for hire or reward. This is a requirement of EU Regulation 1071/2009 which affects holders of standard national and standard international licences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Traffic Commissioners retain their discretion to set the financial standing levels for restricted licence holders (not covered by the regulation) and they propose to maintain the current rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revised figures are set out below and are based on the euro exchange rate on the first working day in October 2012 – as prescribed by EU Regulation 1071/2009. The new rates will come into force on 1 January 2013 and will remain in place until the 31 December 2013 (previous rates are in brackets). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Minimum financial level requirement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standard national and standard international licences&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a. first vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,200 (£7,700)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b. each additional vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,000, ( £4,200)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Restricted licences&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a. first vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,100 ( £3,100)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b. each additional vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,700 ( £1,700)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="note-to-editors"&gt;Note to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The financial limits set by EU Regulation 1071/2009 are 9000 euros for the first vehicle and 5000 euros for each subsequent vehicle. For member states not participating in monetary union, the regulation requires the equivalent in their currencies to be revised every year, using the euro exchange rate published in the Official Journal of the European Union on the first working day of October in the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55970</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-for-everyone"/>
    <title>Transport for everyone </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker is calling on operators and local authorities to work with government to put accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help them to do this, the Department for Transport has published 2 action plans which set out priorities, as well as highlighting areas where action is in the pipeline or already underway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Transport for everyone’ outlines how operators, local councils and the Department can help to make it easier for people using public transport – particularly those with disabilities - to get to where they need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action plan builds on the success achieved in improving accessibility on public transport during the Olympics and Paralympics. At the heart of the plan is the importance of improving door-to-door journeys rather than addressing issues in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s equality action plan looks at how we can encourage a more inclusive transport network and underlines the importance of ensuring that policy makers at all levels are alive to the particular needs and concerns of different groups in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include affordability issues for young people and pensioners and the ability for all people to travel in safety and free from harassment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good transport system allows people to access jobs, opportunities and vital services - it needs to work for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the concerns that specific groups of people have about public transport and so we have pulled together ideas from across the transport sector on how these concerns can be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The action plans will help policy makers, as well as transport operators, to tackle problems head on and - more importantly - to level the playing field for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Sayce OBE, Disability Rights UK Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An accessible transport infrastructure is essential for what Disability Rights UK wants to achieve – disabled people playing a full and equal part in society. Over the past 20 years we have come a long way as our practical guide ‘Doing transport differently’ shows but there are still too many attitudinal, communication and physical barriers facing disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Action plan’ is a step change towards making further progress. We welcome the commitment that the Department for Transport will continue to work in partnership with disabled people and our organisations to ensure the most effective steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Accessibility action plan’ builds on the transport successes of the Olympic and Paralympic Games and aims to create a long lasting legacy of improved access and information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Olympic and Paralympic Games, public transport operators carried thousands of spectators with disabilities and work was done to ensure that the travelling public had easy access to information. One of the aims of the ‘Accessibility action plan’ will be to build on the Games Spectator Journey Planner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new planner would cover a wider geographical area and more types of transport as well as being made accessible to people with visual impairments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other measures outlined in the plan include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considering where £100 million of extra funding might be best spent in the long term to improve accessibility of railway stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible further amendments to the Blue Badge scheme to tackle abuse and fraud in this area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building on guidance for mobility scooters and powered wheelchairs to encourage training for those using this equipment &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Equality action plan’ sets out in one place what the department is doing to ensure people from all parts of society have the option to use public transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points addressed in the plan include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessibility to public transport for young people, older people and those living in rural areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety and personal security for women travellers, particularly at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling hate crime and bullying on buses and other public transport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promoting employment of under-represented groups within the transport industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both documents include lists of issues and the actions that have been, or will be, taken to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Accessibility action plan’&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;‘Equality action plan’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the interests of transparency and to enable as many people as possible to have their say, the ‘Equality action plan’ will be open for comment until 15 February. These will feed in to a final version of the document which will be published in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55904</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T10:01:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T10:01:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-accepts-proposals-to-improve-garage-standards"/>
    <title>Government accepts proposals to improve garage standards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists are being encouraged to find out if their garage is approved by a set of industry-standard codes to make sure they are getting value for money.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call comes after the government accepted a number of proposals made by industry experts to help drive up standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Motorists’ Forum has set out a raft of recommendations aimed at making sure motorists have the best possible consumer experience when having their vehicles serviced or repaired in a report released today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will promote the wider adoption of self-regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;-&lt;abbr title="Trading Standards Institute"&gt;TSI&lt;/abbr&gt;) codes of practice by garages and encourage greater publication of information regarding services they offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an AA survey*, 78% of people always use the same garage meaning that only a minority of motorists shop around. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the work carried out by the Motorists’ Forum and believe the recommendations will help build on existing best practice in the industry without the burden of extra legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that consumers feel confident in the quality and the value for money of the services they are receiving from garages. The Forum’s report has offered some useful proposals for how this can be achieved more consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would urge motorists to find out if their local garage has been approved by the codes to ensure they are getting a fair service and value for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills will now use their strong relationships with the industry and stakeholders to promote the adopted recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK car service and repair sector is worth around £6.9 billion per year to the GB economy with 150,000 MOT tests taking place every working day.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="note-to-editors"&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Motorists’ Forum report on garage customer experience can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-report-of-the-motorists-forum-sub-group-on-improving-customer-service-experience-at-garages"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s response can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/government-response-to-motorists-forum-report-on-garage-customer-experience"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Motorists’ Forum is made up of a group of experts convened by the DfT. Organisations include the AA, RAC, &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, Centre for Automotive Management, &lt;abbr title="compulsory basic training"&gt;CBT&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Transport for London"&gt;TfL&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Association Of British Insurers"&gt;ABI&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Freight Transport Association"&gt;FTA&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Vehicle Rental and Leasing Association"&gt;BVRLA&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Parliamentary Advisory Council for Transport Safety"&gt;PACTS&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders"&gt;SMMT&lt;/abbr&gt; as well as representatives from the DfT and Highways Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Trading Standards Institute (&lt;abbr title="Trading Standards Institute"&gt;TSI&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be taking over responsibility for the consumer codes approval scheme from the Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;). The new scheme will maintain the rigour of the current scheme, but will streamline the approval process and make it self-funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Responsibility for vehicle roadworthiness and testing lies with DfT and &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; administers the MOT scheme. Responsibility for consumer protection legislation lies with the Department for Business Innovation and Skills (BIS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is already considerable consumer protection legislation in place to cover the practices of garages which choose to trade unfairly or who are not competent to trade; both from the perspective of individual consumer rights through sale of goods and services legislation, and through the application of criminal sanctions, principally via the Consumer Protection from unfair trading regulations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*AA Survey Outcome, Car Service/Repair, May 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55824</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:34:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:34:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-13-december-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 13 December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) has published the following transport statistics: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/transport-statistics-great-britain-2012"&gt;transport statistics Great Britain: 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/quarterly-bus-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;quarterly bus statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/vehicle-licensing-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;vehicle licensing statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/national-travel-survey-2011"&gt;national travel survey: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agencys-motorway-and-a-road-network-october-2012"&gt;reliability of journeys on the Highways Agencys motorway and ‘A’ road network: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See statistics at &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; for details on all &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/55840</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:30:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:30:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/tsgb10"/>
    <title>TSGB10 - Olympics</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;
&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51520"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35761/tsgb_2012_-_olympics_summary.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51520-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35761/thumbnail_tsgb_2012_-_olympics_summary.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35761/tsgb_2012_-_olympics_summary.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51520-accessibility-help"&gt;Olympics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;243 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51520-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Olympics%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Olympics%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Olympics").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51534"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36591/TSGB1001.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51534-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36591/TSGB1001.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51534-accessibility-help"&gt;TSGB1001 Sea Passenger statistics at United Kingdom ports, July - September, 2011 and 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;TSGB1001&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;48 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51534-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20TSGB1001%20Sea%20Passenger%20statistics%20at%20United%20Kingdom%20ports%2C%20July%20-%20September%2C%202011%20and%202012%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20TSGB1001%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27TSGB1001%20Sea%20Passenger%20statistics%20at%20United%20Kingdom%20ports%2C%20July%20-%20September%2C%202011%20and%202012%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("TSGB1001 Sea Passenger statistics at United Kingdom ports, July - September, 2011 and 2012"), and its reference (Unique reference: TSGB1001).
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51516"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35757/TSGB1002.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51516-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35757/TSGB1002.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51516-accessibility-help"&gt;TSGB1002 Air traffic at United Kingdom airports, July-September, 2011 and 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;TSGB1002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;59 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51516-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20TSGB1002%20Air%20traffic%20at%20United%20Kingdom%20airports%2C%20July-September%2C%202011%20and%202012%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20TSGB1002%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27TSGB1002%20Air%20traffic%20at%20United%20Kingdom%20airports%2C%20July-September%2C%202011%20and%202012%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("TSGB1002 Air traffic at United Kingdom airports, July-September, 2011 and 2012"), and its reference (Unique reference: TSGB1002).
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51517"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35758/TSGB1003.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51517-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35758/TSGB1003.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51517-accessibility-help"&gt;TSGB1003 Punctuality at selected United Kingdom airports, July-August, 2011 and 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;TSGB1003&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;52.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51517-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20TSGB1003%20Punctuality%20at%20selected%20United%20Kingdom%20airports%2C%20July-August%2C%202011%20and%202012%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20TSGB1003%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27TSGB1003%20Punctuality%20at%20selected%20United%20Kingdom%20airports%2C%20July-August%2C%202011%20and%202012%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("TSGB1003 Punctuality at selected United Kingdom airports, July-August, 2011 and 2012"), and its reference (Unique reference: TSGB1003).
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51518"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35759/TSGB1004.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51518-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35759/TSGB1004.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51518-accessibility-help"&gt;TSGB1004 National Rail Games Tickets (NRGT) revenue and sales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;TSGB1004&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;53.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51518-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20TSGB1004%20National%20Rail%20Games%20Tickets%20%28NRGT%29%20revenue%20and%20sales%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20TSGB1004%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27TSGB1004%20National%20Rail%20Games%20Tickets%20%28NRGT%29%20revenue%20and%20sales%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("TSGB1004 National Rail Games Tickets (NRGT) revenue and sales"), and its reference (Unique reference: TSGB1004).
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51519"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35760/TSGB1005.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51519-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35760/TSGB1005.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-51519-accessibility-help"&gt;TSGB1005 Average week day speed (miles per hour) on local 'A' roads in the six London Host Boroughs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;TSGB1005&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;44.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51519-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20TSGB1005%20Average%20week%20day%20speed%20%28miles%20per%20hour%29%20on%20local%20%27A%27%20roads%20in%20the%20six%20London%20Host%20Boroughs%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20TSGB1005%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27TSGB1005%20Average%20week%20day%20speed%20%28miles%20per%20hour%29%20on%20local%20%27A%27%20roads%20in%20the%20six%20London%20Host%20Boroughs%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;webmasterdft@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("TSGB1005 Average week day speed (miles per hour) on local 'A' roads in the six London Host Boroughs"), and its reference (Unique reference: TSGB1005).
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16746</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"/>
    <title>Port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This publication presents provisional summary statistics on freight handled by major UK ports, updated quarterly. Provisional annual statistics are updated in June and detailed final annual statistics are published in September. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total port traffic (tonnage) in the year ending quarter 3 2012 (497 million tonnes) was down 2% on the year ending quarter 3 2011 (509 million tonnes). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of units of all types handled in the year ending quarter 3 2012  (20.8 million units) was down 3% compared with the year ending quarter 3 2011 (21.4 million units).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tonnage in quarter 3 of 2012 (124 million tonnes) was down 3% compared with quarter 3 2011 (127 million tonnes).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of units of all types handled in quarter 3 2012 (5.98 million units) was down 4% compared with quarter 3 2011 (6.21 million units). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="technical-information"&gt;Technical information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on port freight statistics, including the pre-release access list, and related technical documentation &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats#Port-statistics"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone: 020 7944 4131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
