<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56571</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets are the best way of making sure a country’s resources are put to their best use. They encourage enterprise and widen choice for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can develop in any economy. They can harm consumers and stifle innovation and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an anti-competitive activity would be when two companies agree to charge the same price for a similar product. This protects the companies’ profits but means consumers get less choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can be very bad for consumers. That’s why they have to be identified and stopped as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the government’s three growth objectives is that the UK should become the best place to start, finance and grow a business. Reforming and improving the laws on anti-competitive activities is a major part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-competition-law"&gt;Changing competition law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is reforming the laws that cover competition and anti-competitive activities in business, including those relating to mergers, markets and illegal activities such as price-fixing and cartels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also reforming the institutions that police competition and anti-competitive activities, and strengthening their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These laws, institutions and powers are collectively known as the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="competition-landscape"&gt;Competition landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re making changes to the organisations that deal with competition and anti-competitive activities in business. We’re doing this between now and the end of 2014. This work is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and competition landscape reforms."&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reforms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="setting-up-a-new-watchdog-for-the-grocery-industry"&gt;Setting up a new watchdog for the grocery industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re creating a new watchdog for the grocery industry. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/groceries-code-adjudicator" title="Groceries Code."&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt; will give suppliers, including farmers supplying the bigger supermarket chains, more protection against anti-competitive activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-legal-challenges-easier"&gt;Making legal challenges easier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to make it easier for consumers and small businesses to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/private-actions-pro-tem" title="Private Action."&gt;challenge anti-competitive behaviour&lt;/a&gt; by bringing a legal challenge (also known as a private action) against anti-competitive activities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-aid"&gt;State aid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re modernising the rules on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State aid is when a public body (such as a local authority) or publicly funded body (such as the Big Lottery) provides a business, charity or other organisation with financial help that could give them an advantage over another business. This kind of financial help is generally outlawed by the European treaty, as it’s an anti-competitive practice. State aid regulations set legal ways to give this kind of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"&gt;detailed guide on state aid&lt;/a&gt; for public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different rules - also covered in the detailed guide - apply to agriculture, aquaculture, fisheries, transport and maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK competition law has to comply with EU law. Article 101 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/antitrust/overview_en.html"&gt;Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU)&lt;/a&gt; bans any agreements between businesses ‘which have as their object… the prevention [or] restriction… of competition within the common market.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57079</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The EFG scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving SMEs the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EFG scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for SMEs, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the EFG scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the EFG scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but EFG lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of EFG loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of EFG loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the EFG scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57049</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-boost-for-business-as-government-sets-out-plans-to-update-employment-legislation"/>
    <title>Press Release: Boost for business as government sets out plans to update employment legislation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to collective redundancies rules to help employees and businesses were announced by Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government announced it plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the current 90 day minimum period, before very large scale redundancies can take place, to 45 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legislate to make clear that fixed term contracts which have reached the end of their natural life are excluded from obligations for collective redundancies consultation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce new non-statutory Acas guidance to address a number of key issues affecting collective redundancies consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK has a labour market that is flexible, efficient and fair but some of our laws need reform to respond to an ever changing employment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to improve the quality of consultations by making sure that there are tools available to help employers manage this process fairly and successfully to deliver the best possible outcomes for all parties.  Acas will be working with stakeholders to produce non-statutory guidance that will be designed to help improve the quality of consultations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have listened to stakeholders and there is a strong argument for shortening the minimum period which is backed up by hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The process is usually completed well within the existing 90-day minimum period, which can cause unnecessary delays for restructuring, and make it difficult for those affected to get new jobs quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our reforms will strike an appropriate balance between making sure employees are engaged in decisions about their future and allowing employers greater certainty and flexibility to take necessary steps to restructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement responds to a consultation launched in June and to calls for improvements to the way collective redundancies rules operate and for the processes involved to be made easier to understand. It also forms part of the Government’s commitment to review employment law to support business and concentrate on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replacement of the current 90 day period to 45 days will still allow full employee engagement and offer employee representatives a statutory right to contribute to the process. The new 45 day period will be a minimum period, and businesses may consult for longer where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will be made through secondary legislation. Draft regulations will be laid in the New Year and the changes are expected to be made by 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition government started a systematic review of employment law in 2010. This Employment Law Review (ELR) is now half way through its work and aims to provide clarity, certainty and give businesses the confidence to manage their workforce effectively. The Review sits alongside the Employment Law-related Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulatory burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the government’s response to Collective
Redundancies can be found at
&lt;a href="/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill sets out a comprehensive series of reforms aimed at supporting businesses, developers, and first time buyers by slashing red tape that delays or discourages business investment, development or job creation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe
Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56903</id>
    <published>2012-08-06T11:25:59+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-06T11:25:59+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/duty-suspensions-and-tariff-quotas"/>
    <title>Duty suspensions and tariff quotas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/getting-the-right-licences-for-international-trading"&gt;information on duty suspensions and tariff quotas, including information on making an application, and other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; schemes involving duty relief here.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest list of applications for duty suspensions and tariff quotas can also be found below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="duty-suspensions-and-tariff-quotas"&gt;Duty suspensions and tariff quotas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union (&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;) temporary duty suspensions and tariff quotas regime allows the duty free importation into the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; of raw materials, components and semi-finished products which cannot be supplied (or supplied in sufficient quantities) from &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or Turkish manufacturers and are used in a process to make another product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This regime cannot be used simply to import for resale. Suspensions allow unlimited quantities to be imported into the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; whereas quotas allow limited quantities to be imported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once granted, a suspension or quota can be used by any business in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; - it is not specific to the company which applied. If your product is covered by an existing suspension or quota, you do not need to make a new request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission Communication detailing the rules for this regime, and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulations containing the current duty suspensions and tariff quotas in force can be found below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guidance-timelines-and-forms"&gt;Guidance, timelines and forms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-are-the-application-criteria"&gt;What are the application criteria?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can apply for a duty suspension or tariff quota if the component you are importing cannot be sourced - or supplied in sufficient quantity - from within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or Turkey, and is to be further processed in an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; factory, and the level of import duty is saving at least €15,000 per year&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="who-can-make-an-application"&gt;Who can make an application?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can make an application if you are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a business established in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturing user of the component in question &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a distributor applying on behalf of &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturing customers &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; company subsidiaries outside of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or Turkey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an agent (lawyer, accountant or consultant) representing one of the above - note that applications from agents must also include the name of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; user to be considered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="when-can-i-apply"&gt;When can I apply?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 application periods per year for this regime. The annual deadlines are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;new/amendment requests&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;new/amendment requests&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;prolongation requests&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;1st application period&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;2nd application period&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;application period&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;UK requests deadline&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24 February&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24 August&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15 April&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; requests deadline&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15 March&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15 September&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15 April&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1st &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting to discuss requests&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2nd &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting to discuss requests&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting to discuss requests&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optional additional meeting to discuss requests&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;September&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;September&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Entry into force of requested tariff suspensions or quotas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 July&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 January&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Requests to increase the volume of an existing tariff quota can be submitted at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-do-i-apply"&gt;How do I apply?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please complete the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/s/suspension-application-form-2012.doc"&gt;application form&lt;/a&gt; and email it to &lt;a href="mailto:dutysuspensionsandquotas@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;dutysuspensionsandquotas@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/s/suspension-request-form-guidance-2012.doc"&gt;guidance notes&lt;/a&gt; to help you complete the form, and note the following important message from the European Commission concerning the submission of new requests:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;all boxes on the application form must be filled in with sufficient detail. For example, you will have to detail the efforts you have made to find &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; production (“no known &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; production” is not an acceptable response). Another example of this issue is connected with the pigments, where the applicants were aware of &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; production given the number of objections to their requests in the last round. Therefore, at the very least it was expected to see evidence that showed that the applicants had contacted the objectors from the previous round and the results of these contacts&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;requests for tariff suspensions or quotas should be submitted by the Member States on behalf of Customs Union processing or manufacturing companies, identified by name, which are adequately equipped to use the imported goods in their production processes&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;further detailed information including commercial denomination, packaging, mode of operation, intended use of the imported product type of product in which it is to be incorporated and end use of that product has to be directly connected with the applying Union processing or manufacturing companies&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the non-exclusive trading declarations cannot be signed by a third party acting on behalf of the applicant as only the applicant is in a position to know the trade and money flows as well as its contractual agreements and thereby make such declaration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;as the requests have to be pre-checked by MS on whether or not they comply with the rules it is advisable that the national deadlines are set before the ones of the Commission in order to allow sufficient time for such checks&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;no suspensions are granted for finished products, even if they become a part of a whole system (eg finished monitors)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;in case of re-submissions the application has to explain in detail what changes (for example, market situation, withdrawal of objections) took place since the submission of the original request&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the Commission will do a pre-check of all incoming requests from next round onwards and will reject the incorrect and incomplete requests directly to reduce the waste of resources for the Commission and Member States. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-does-this-regime-work"&gt;How does this regime work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your application will be submitted to the European Commission. A list of all the requests for each round (tariff codes and description only) is posted on the European Commission website and on this website. The UK also sends this list to Trade Associations. This is to enable us to check if there is any &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturing of the components for which a duty suspension has been requested. The name of the applicant is not made public nor is any of the information on an application other than the tariff code and description requested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Requests are discussed at 3 working group meetings in Brussels (Economic Tariff Questions Group – ETQG). The results of each meeting are published on this website. We will contact you if we require further information about your request, or to advise you on the receipt of an objection to your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_53609"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37005/12_December_2012_Upate_on_progress_of_requests_for_duty_suspensions_round_1_7_2013.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-53609-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37005/12_December_2012_Upate_on_progress_of_requests_for_duty_suspensions_round_1_7_2013.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-53609-accessibility-help"&gt;Status of current requests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;672 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-53609-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Status%20of%20current%20requests%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Status%20of%20current%20requests%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Status of current requests").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successful duty suspensions requests are valid for 5 years. After 5 years they are reviewed under the “prolongation” scheme where they can be renewed for a further 5 years. Tariff quotas are valid for twelve months and automatically renewed for the same quantity each year. Objections to tariff suspensions or quotas can be made at anytime during the validity period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="but-i-make-these-components-already"&gt;But I make these components already…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture goods in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; for which a duty suspension or quota is being requested or is currently in force, you can have it stopped by submitting a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/s/suspensions-opposition-form-2012.doc"&gt;suspension objection form&lt;/a&gt;. You will have to prove that you currently make the required goods in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; (for example by making a sales offer to the applicant company). Price is not a consideration when oppositions are considered. Discussions between you and the applicant company should also take place to see if any compromise is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you receive an objection from another member state company to your request, you must contact the objecting company to discuss a compromise solution, as unless their objection is withdrawn your request will not be granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadlines for objections to new requests or current measures are:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;new requests&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;current measures&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;objection deadline&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2nd &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1st &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="renewal-of-existing-suspensions-prolongation"&gt;Renewal of existing suspensions (prolongation)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using a duty suspension that is reaching the end of its five year validity, you will need to request its renewal if you wish to continue to use it. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/c/council-regulation-1255-96-consolidated-tariff%20duties-industrial-agricultural-fisheries-products.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; duty suspension regulation&lt;/a&gt; contains the renewal dates of all duty suspensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual list of current duty suspensions subject to review can be viewed using the related link to the right of this page. Any duty suspension that has duty savings of more than €750,000 Euros is automatically renewed by the European Commission and no renewal request needs to be made. A list of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/l/12-629-list-tariff-suspensions-below-threshold-automatic-prolongation.pdf"&gt;prolongation suspensions&lt;/a&gt; is published annually on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To request the renewal of a duty suspension for a further 5 years, please complete the request for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/s/suspension-prolongation-form-2012.doc"&gt;prolongation of a tariff suspension&lt;/a&gt; form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57029</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/uk-government-oil-and-gas-sector-strategy-call-for-industrys-views"/>
    <title>UK government oil and gas sector strategy: call for industry's views</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its industrial strategy, the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) announced that there will be, initially, 10 sector strategies, of which oil and gas would be one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry’s input is essential as &lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Department of Energy and Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="The Department of Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt;) develop this work in partnership with Oil &amp;amp; Gas UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sector strategies will be co-developed and implemented with industry to be durable and will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be long-term in focus: developing a vision for the sector and what needs to happen from both government and business to get there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be co-created with industry: committing both business and government to specific actions to maintain and develop long-term capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a whole of government approach: looking across all of government to identify barriers and levers which have the biggest impacts and align these to deliver growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engage across the totality of the sector: working with industry and identifying actions which benefit business across the whole supply chain whether they are large, medium or small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publication is expected in late March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry’s views are very much welcomed particularly through January 2013 and can be fed into either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="The DEpartment for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; – Tom Worsley – &lt;a href="Tom.Worsley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Tom.Worsley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; – 020 7215 6480&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="The Department of Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt; – Audrey Banner – &lt;a href="Audrey.banner@decc.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Audrey.banner@decc.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; – 01224 254104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57071</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"/>
    <title>Number and value of Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) scheme loans drawn.</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number and value of EFG loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/57077</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"/>
    <title>Update on Enterprise Finance Guarantee lending  </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures by individual bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to ensuring that viable small and medium-size enterprises can obtain the finance they need for working capital and investment. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; plays an important part in this, with over 9,900 &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; being offered loans with a value in excess of £1 billion since May 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has made a number of important changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme during the last twelve months. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans are now available to an additional 3,800 businesses with an increase in the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million. The maximum £1 million lifetime scheme limit has been replaced by a rolling £1 million limit. We also raised by 7%, the level of lenders &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; annual loan portfolios to which the Government guarantee applies from 13% to 20%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was made to address the legitimate concern of lenders that they would breach their annual claim limit. In doing this, the Government committed to a more even share of the risk of default with the lenders, with the aim of removing that as a barrier to lending &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; is a demand led scheme, accounting for one to two per cent of overall &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; lending. While utilisation is directly linked to subdued demand for credit in the wider economy, overall &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending levels are disappointing. There have been some positive signs, with a number of the main banks increasing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending this financial year, albeit from a low level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that banks lend responsibly and make use of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; when it is appropriate to do so, but it is clear from the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures that a number of lenders could and should be doing more. The publication of individual bank &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures is intended to help achieve this. In parallel, we are exploring with the banks ways of flexing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; to address debt serviceability, which is the principal reason behind loan declines. Further detail will be provided in the New Year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, already publishes a wide range of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures, which are updated on a quarterly basis. Publication of individual &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures will further enhance this, allowing business customers to identify which banks are making most use of the scheme, and also enable participating lenders and new market entrants to identity new opportunities, thus increasing choice and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a further step towards greater transparency in bank lending, specifically to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"&gt;The full list of available &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/55764</id>
    <published>2012-09-11T14:35:31+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-11T14:35:31+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/licence-types-faqs"/>
    <title>Licence types: FAQs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are exporting controlled goods outside the UK, there are a number of different licences you can use, issued by the Export Control Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;). These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/open-general-licences-an-overview"&gt;Open General Licences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/european-union-general-export-authorisations"&gt;European Union General Export Authorisations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/standard-individual-export-licences"&gt;Standard Individual Export Licences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/open-individual-export-licences"&gt;Open Individual Export Licences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide explains the answers to commonly asked questions about applying for and using these different types of licences. For more details about each licence type, please refer to the relevant guidance pages directly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-general-licences-faqs"&gt;Open General Licences: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about registering to use Open General Licences (OGLs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-do-i-register-for-ogls"&gt;How do I register for OGLs?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/espire/LOGIN/login"&gt;apply for an export licence using SPIRE.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After logging into SPIRE, you need to select the option for ‘new application’ and then from the list of licensing types, select ‘&lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;/EU GEA’. You will then see a drop down box from which you need to select the appropriate licence you need to register for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before registering you need to ensure that you can meet all of the licence terms and conditions. To check conditions you should use &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ecochecker.bis.gov.uk"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Open General Export Licence"&gt;OGEL&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker tools website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="do-i-have-to-wait-for-you-to-acknowledge-my-ogl-registration-before-i-can-use-the-licence"&gt;Do I have to wait for you to acknowledge my &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt; registration before I can use the licence?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally you should wait to receive an acknowledgement letter via your SPIRE workbasket confirming your registration since this will include the unique SPIRE reference number confirming your &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt; registration, which you need to quote on any customs documentation, such as in Box 44 of the CHIEF declaration screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an overview of registering for OGLs, see the page in the guide on registering for Open General Licences. You can also access further guidance about exactly how to register on SPIRE for an &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/docs/RegisterOGLs.pdf"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt; registration guidance from the SPIRE website (DOC, 680K).&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/compliance-checks-and-enforcement-of-export-controls-on-strategic-goods-and-technology"&gt;compliance and enforcement of export controls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="is-theeugeneral-export-authorisation-an-ogl"&gt;Is the EU General Export Authorisation an &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EU GEA is the European Union equivalent of an &lt;abbr title="Open General Licences"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;. The EU currently publishes six EU GEAs. For more information see the guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/controls-on-dual-use-goods"&gt;controls on dual-use goods&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/european-union-general-export-authorisations"&gt;European Union General Export Authorisation (EU GEAa)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="standard-individual-export-licences-siels-faqs"&gt;Standard Individual Export Licences (SIELs): FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section answers common queries raised at export control seminars about SIELs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-siels-be-issued-quicker-than-20-working-days"&gt;Can SIELs be issued quicker than 20 working days?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes licences may be issued quicker but this will depend on the goods and the destination. Processing of licences for sanctioned or highly sensitive destinations is likely to take significantly longer than the standard 20 working day target. To determine the current licence processing timescales by destination you are advised to access the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.exportcontroldb.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/sdb/SDBHOME"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Reports and Statistics website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve your chances of a licence being issued within the target time or sooner, you need to ensure that your application includes  full technical specifications and remember to attach appropriate &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/end-user-and-consignee-undertakings-for-siels-and-oiels"&gt;end-user documentation&lt;/a&gt;. Any missing information or incomplete details will risk in &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; sending you a request for further information (RFI) via SPIRE with consequent delays in processing your application. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/submitting-export-licence-applications-correctly"&gt;submitting export licence applications correctly&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-control-licensing-process-and-how-to-appeal"&gt;export control licensing process and how to appeal&lt;/a&gt; which includes details of &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s performance in meeting licence processing targets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-the-quantity-stated-on-a-siel-application-be-for-more-than-is-required-at-the-time-of-the-application"&gt;Can the quantity stated on a &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; application be for more than is required at the time of the application?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but it must match the information provided in the &lt;abbr title="End User Undertakings"&gt;EUU&lt;/abbr&gt; and it must be reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information, see the guide: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/end-user-and-consignee-undertakings-for-siels-and-oiels"&gt;end-user and stockist undertakings for SIELs and consignee undertakings for &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licences"&gt;OIELs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-a-licence-be-amended-once-it-is-issued"&gt;Can a licence be amended once it is issued?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Export licences are not transferable and may not be altered except by the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some minor changes can be made by &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; in case of a change of company name or address. If either an exporter’s or consignee’s name and address change then you need to notify &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="why-have-i-received-a-no-licence-required-nlr-letter-in-response-to-my-application"&gt;Why have I received a No Licence Required (&lt;abbr title="No Licence Required"&gt;NLR&lt;/abbr&gt;) letter in response to my application?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you definitely know your goods are not listed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-and-import-licences-for-controlled-goods-and-trading-with-certain-countries"&gt;UK Strategic Export Control Lists&lt;/a&gt;, then you should only apply for a licence if you have concerns over the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the guides on  &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/military-end-use-control-guidance-notes"&gt;Military End-Use Control&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weapons-of-mass-destruction-wmd-end-use-control"&gt;Weapons of Mass Destruction End-Use Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a service called the End-User Advice Service which is available via &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;. For more details please refer to guidance about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/do-your-goods-need-an-export-licence"&gt;strategic exports: when to request an export licence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-long-are-nlr-letters-valid-for"&gt;How long are &lt;abbr title="No Licence Required"&gt;NLR&lt;/abbr&gt; letters valid for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no validity date given on &lt;abbr title="No Licence Required"&gt;NLR&lt;/abbr&gt; letters - they represent the opinion of &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; at the time they are given. However, they do expect exporters to keep up to date with changes to the legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the guide about the: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-strategic-export-control-lists-the-consolidated-list-of-strategic-military-and-dual-use-items"&gt;UK Strategic Export Control List&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For regular news and updates about changes to export control licences and legislation, you should &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/exportcontrol"&gt;subscribe to the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Notices to Exporters.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-the-original-siel-be-used-to-return-items-that-have-been-sent-back-to-repair"&gt;Can the original &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; be used to return items that have been sent back to repair?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, provided there is sufficient quantity left on the licence. However, doing this may mean you cannot fulfil the original order if the licence becomes exhausted before you ship the quantity you originally intended. If the licence has been exhausted or the quantity remaining is insufficient, then no, you cannot use the original licence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, you should consider the relevant repair Open General Export Licence (&lt;abbr title="Open General Export Licence"&gt;OGEL&lt;/abbr&gt;) - that may suit your purpose and if so you should use that licence. If not, and you need to use a &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt;, and you may have to think about applying for an additional &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; to ensure you can fulfil the order after the first &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; is exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/dual-use-open-general-export-licences-explained"&gt;Dual-Use Open General Export Licences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-individual-export-licences---faqs"&gt;Open Individual Export Licences - FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section answers common queries raised at export control seminars about &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licences"&gt;OIELs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="under-what-circumstances-will-an-oiel-be-issued"&gt;Under what circumstances will an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; be issued?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; is a concessionary form of licence, which are issued in certain circumstances. The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; usually look for a minimum of 20 Standard Individual Export Licence applications per year. They will, however, also consider applications if there is a business case detailing why an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; is the most appropriate licence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-long-does-it-take-to-get-an-oiel"&gt;How long does it take to get an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; aims to process 60 per cent of &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; applications within 60 working days. You should expect a timescale of three to six months for an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; to be issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-an-oiel-be-amended-to-include-additional-goods-or-destinations"&gt;Can an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; be amended to include additional goods or destinations?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. You would need to apply for a new &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; to incorporate both the existing and new goods and/or destinations. When the new &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; has been re-issued, &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will cancel the old one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="can-an-oiel-application-be-made-before-all-consignee-or-end-user-details-are-known"&gt;Can an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; application be made before all consignee or end-user details are known?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. If you are applying for an &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licence"&gt;OIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; then you are not required to obtain consignee or end-user details up front at the time of application. You will however need to obtain the details within a month of receiving the goods. You will need to keep and produce originals (not copies) of the required documentation for compliance audits. You will also need to ensure that the undertaking is not out of date when the shipment is made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information, see the guide: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/end-user-and-consignee-undertakings-for-siels-and-oiels"&gt;end-user and stockist undertakings for SIELs and consignee undertakings for &lt;abbr title="Open Individual Export Licences"&gt;OIELs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bis-eco-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 7215 4594&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Apply for an export licence using SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/exportcontrol"&gt;Subscribe to the Export Control Organisation’s Notices to Exporters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/export-control-organisation/eco-contact-details"&gt;Contact details for the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ecochecker.bis.gov.uk"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.exportcontroldb.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/sdb/SDBHOME"&gt;Access quarterly licensing statistics on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Reports and Statistics website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/55773</id>
    <published>2012-09-12T12:27:44+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-12T12:27:44+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/faqs-licensing-of-controlled-goods-faqs"/>
    <title>Licensing of controlled goods: FAQs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide addresses some frequently asked questions raised in export control training seminars about how to determine whether your goods are controlled by the Export Control Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide should be read in conjunction with further guidance about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/do-your-goods-need-an-export-licence"&gt;strategic exports: when to request an export licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rating-your-goods"&gt;Rating your goods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listed below are some common queries raised at Export Control Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;) seminars about the ‘rating’ or classification of military and dual-use goods and about &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s advisory services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘rating’ or ‘control list entry heading’ refers to whether items are listed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-strategic-export-control-lists-the-consolidated-list-of-strategic-military-and-dual-use-items"&gt;UK Strategic Export Control Lists&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; offers a service - called the Control List Classification Advice Service - available throught SPIRE, the export licensing database, which allows exporters to seek advice on whether an item is listed on the Control Lists. For those exporters who already know that their items are not listed then a further service - the End-User Advice Service is also available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Make either a Control List Classification or End-User Advice Service request using SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the ‘rating’ depend on the destination country or identity of the end-user?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally, no, although certain goods are controlled only when exported to a certain country (such as &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-on-iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/a&gt;). The identity of the end-user comes into play under End-Use Controls.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the ‘rating’ depend on the actual end-use of the goods?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, it is purely based on the specification of the goods in question. However, even where goods are not normally controlled, they can be made licensable, where there are either &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/weapons-of-mass-destruction-wmd-end-use-control"&gt;Weapons of Mass Destruction (WMD) End-Use Control&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/military-end-use-control-guidance-notes"&gt;Military End-Use Control&lt;/a&gt; concerns. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why can we only have four items on a rating enquiry?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is simply a resource issue.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What items require an export licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should refer to the guide on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-strategic-export-control-lists-the-consolidated-list-of-strategic-military-and-dual-use-items"&gt;UK Strategic Export Control Lists - the consolidated list of strategic military and dual-use items.&lt;/a&gt;. You should also be aware that items might also require a licence under either the End-Use Controls or because of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business/imports-exports/embargoes-and-sanctions"&gt;embargoes and sanctions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can we determine if the products are controlled?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can check the control lists and identify how to self-rate your own goods - &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/do-your-goods-need-an-export-licence"&gt;strategic exports: when to request an export licence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ecochecker.bis.gov.uk"&gt;use the Goods Checker on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/espire/LOGIN/login"&gt;use the Control List Classification Search Tool on SPIRE&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The UK Trade Tariff only provides a broad initial indication of whether some goods are restricted. You should not use the Tariff as your unique reference point to determine if your goods are controlled but should check the Control Lists themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is best to check whether your items are controlled as early as possible and build this into your management processes. This may be well in advance of any specific enquiry or order and can be at the design or development stage of a new product. For further best practice advice you can download the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Compliance Code of Practice document - refer to guidance on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/compliance-checks-and-enforcement-of-export-controls-on-strategic-goods-and-technology"&gt;compliance and enforcement of export controls&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For military goods, you should also be aware of the MOD F680 procedures on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/mod-f680-applications"&gt;MOD F680 applications&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a company makes their own ‘rating’ decision and that turns out to be wrong are we liable?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. You are advised to take out insurance against this happening and speak to your insurer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if I have a specific export order to fulfil and am unsure about whether the goods require a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have confirmed business and envisage an export in the near future then it is best that you apply for a licence. &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will decide whether to grant a licence, refuse it, or say if it is not required.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In each instance, the final licence response will advise you of the status of your goods. If you are advised that no licence is required then you should use the End-User Advice Service for future queries relating to shipments to specific end-users of non-listed goods.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are components on the Control Lists always controlled?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should check the wording of control entries very carefully since some entries include all specially designed components (including most of the Military List) while others include only those components listed and some do not control components at all.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For more information, refer to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-strategic-export-control-lists-the-consolidated-list-of-strategic-military-and-dual-use-items"&gt;UK Strategic Export Control Lists.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does ‘specially designed or modified for military use’ mean?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This means the original design intent of the goods.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does painting an item green make it ‘modified’ for military use?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the paint used is standard, plain green paint then no. If the paint has been modified in some way - for instance, to make it infra-red reflective - then yes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are dual-use goods?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are goods that have both military and dual-use applications.
*See more information in the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/controls-on-dual-use-goods"&gt;controls on dual-use goods&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on the product you are looking to export you might be able to use an Open General Licence (OGL) or a European Union General Export Authorisation (EU GEA) which provides licensing coverage for specific dual-use goods being exported to less restricted destinations. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For more information, see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/dual-use-open-general-export-licences-explained"&gt;Dual-Use Open General Export Licences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if we don’t know what the items were originally designed for, for instance if they were designed a long time ago, or if the manufacturer has ceased to exist?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to do your own due diligence and make an informed decision on the knowledge that you possess at the time. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If in doubt, contact the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/espire/LOGIN/login"&gt;make either a Control List Classification Advice Service request or apply for a licence using SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If my product is not described on the Control Lists does that mean a licence is not required?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No. There might be either Military or Weapons of Mass Destruction (WMD) End-Use Controls.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What sort of details do I need to provide to get End-User Advice?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to provide details of who you are, your UK address and the identity and address of any overseas entities that you are dealing with. You do not need to provide details of the goods that you are intending to export.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your request for end-user advice needs to be completed online via &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/espire/LOGIN/login"&gt;SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will I be able to get a ‘No Licence Required’ letter related to my request for a technical assessment via the Control List Classification Advice Service?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No. The previous Ratings Service is now discontinued and we no longer issue old style ‘No Licence required’ letters.  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But my bank or insurer demands that I get an NLR style letter before they release payment. What can I do?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not correct. Organisations representing banks and the insurance industry have been advised of the current procedures. If banks make these demands upon you then refer them to this guidance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What sort of details will exporters have to present to HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (&lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt;)?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; require a range of general documentation for exports and their requirements are not affected by the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s advisory service procedures.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the Control List Classification Advice has confirmed that you need a licence, you will need to apply for one.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; has advised you that your goods are not listed then you should ensure that you include this notification in the package of documents that you put before &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; to accompany the export. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If, in addition, you have sought End-User Advice and &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; has confirmed that it has no concerns with the named entities then you need to also include this notification.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The important aspect is to demonstrate to &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; that you have taken appropriate steps.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;18. &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; has issued end user advice saying that it has no concerns with my goods. However, the goods still get stopped at customs. Why?
* &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; do checks based on their own intelligence and risk assessment.This process is entirely independent of exporters seeking &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; advice. It is only at the frontier that we have the possibility of checking that goods exported match those that have been declared.
* If &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; decide to detain an export then the process of clearing should run more smoothy if you have all the right documents together, as set out above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long is End-User advice valid for?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End-User advice is valid at the time it is given but it can change in the future because information about companies changes from day to day. The nearer the advice is given to the date of export the greater the likelihood that it remains valid.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does End-User Advice consitute a legal ‘inform’?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not in the usual sense but if exporters are advised to get a licence in response to a request for End-User Advice they may well be deemed to have suspicions about end use which would require them to apply for licences.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; provided End-User Advice relate to advice provided by HM Treasury in relation to financial sanctions?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advice provided by the Treasury in relation to financial sanctions is totally independent of the advice provided by the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; in relation to export control related sanctions and end users. You will have to comply with all relevant sanctions that apply to your business.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How often are the Control Lists updated?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes&lt;/a&gt; are recognised forums of like-minded countries who meet and discuss changes to the Control Lists throughout the year. Depending on the particular regime this is generally achieved by plenary sessions once a year and additional working groups. Any resulting and agreed changes are fed into one major change to the Control Lists. &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To keep informed about changes to the Control Lists, you should &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/exportcontrol"&gt;subscribe to the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Notices to Exporters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bis-eco-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 7215 4594&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Apply for an export licence using SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/exportcontrol"&gt;Subscribe to the Export Control Organisation’s Notices to Exporters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/export-control-organisation/eco-contact-details"&gt;Contact details for the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ecochecker.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Goods Checker on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/55785</id>
    <published>2012-09-04T18:31:34+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-04T18:31:34+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/faqs-specific-controls"/>
    <title>Specific export controls: FAQs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, export control requirements apply when you trade in a number of different types of goods, and in many different situations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;goods that have a military end-use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;goods that can be used for capital punishment or torture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;military goods passing from one third country to another&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;controlled goods that are passing through the UK&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information and technology already in the public domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sting sticks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide contains answers to frequently asked questions relating to these licensing situations. For further information about each of these issues you should read the relevant related guides. For a high level overview about export controls, read about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/beginners-guide-to-export-controls"&gt;export controls: an introductory guide&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="military-end-use-control-faqs"&gt;Military End-Use Control: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section provides a list of questions asked at exporter seminars about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/military-end-use-control-guidance-notes"&gt;Military End-Use Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will I be informed that I require an export licence because of the Military End-Use Control?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normally, you would be told by the Export Control Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;) by telephone, email, fax or letter.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can I challenge a decision to apply for the Military End-Use Control?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. If you believe the assessment is wrong, you should ask for it to be reconsidered. Your reasons should be clearly supported.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I have been informed that an export may be controlled under the Military End-Use Control, must I apply for a licence if I still intend to export?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I am aware that the export meets, or may meet, any of the above criteria, should I apply for a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the regulation you are required to inform the authorities so that they can decide whether to make the export subject to an authorisation (export licence). If they do, the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will inform you accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I apply for a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the same way as for any export licence. See the guide on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-control-licensing-process-and-how-to-appeal"&gt;export control licensing process and how to appeal&lt;/a&gt;.
All licence applications should be made via the SPIRE licensing system. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk/eng/fox/espire/LOGIN/login"&gt;apply for an export licence using SPIRE.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; informs me that no licence is required, does that advice apply to all exports of those items to that destination?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s advice would apply to that export only.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens after I apply for a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will process the licence application in the usual way. It will be checked to ensure it has been completed fully and correctly and that the necessary technical specifications and documentation on End-Use and end-user have been supplied.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; and their advisers will then consider the application and, because you would not have applied for a licence unless you had been informed or were aware of the possible or intended Military End-Use of the export in question, they will give it particular scrutiny. The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will consider your licence application in the light of the information you provide and any other information available to them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I likely to get a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A licence is likely to be refused if - after detailed assessment - there is judged to be a risk that either the proposed export of dual-use items not otherwise subject to control is or may be intended, in its entirety or in part, for incorporation into military items listed in the military list of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states, for its development, production or maintenance, or for use in a plant for producing it, and the destination is subject to an arms embargo decided by a common position or joint action adopted by the Council; a decision of the Organisation for Security and Co-operation in Europe; or an arms embargo imposed by a binding resolution of the Security Council of the United Nations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The licence is also likely to be refused if there is judged to be a risk that the proposed export of Dual-Use items is intended for use as parts or components of military items listed in the military list of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state that have been exported from that member state without authorisation, whatever the destination&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But what, if after being told we do not need a licence, the items are stopped at the port?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (&lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt;) have responsibility for the enforcement of export controls and may wish to check whether any items that are to be exported require a licence. If you applied for a licence but were advised that no licence was required, you must inform &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt;. You should quote your &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; or licence application reference number or include with your export documentation a copy of the letter stating that the items do not appear to require a licence.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; still believe that there may be grounds for suspicion, they will seek advice from the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;. If the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; find that there are sufficient concerns about the destination or End-Use, appropriate action will be taken, depending on the circumstances. This might include informing you that you should apply for a licence under the Military End-Use Control.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So, for example, if I am exporting civil vehicle parts to Pakistan which will be incorporated into something military, which will then be supplied to Uzbekistan (a country embargoed by the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, but not by Pakistan), will I need a UK export licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. If the immediate destination of your goods wishes to supply a destination subject to a UK-observed embargo that is a matter for them. If you are aware or are informed, however, that your goods are intended to ultimately be supplied as part of an item described in the UK Military List to a destination subject to an embargo observed by the UK you would require a UK export licence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if I’m uncertain about how the law applies in a particular case?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If in doubt, seek expert technical and legal advice.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="eu-torture-regulation-scope-of-goods-faqs"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Torture Regulation scope of goods: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about the scope of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_200/l_20020050730en00010019.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation on Products used for Capital Punishment and Torture (the Torture Regulation)&lt;/a&gt;, as amended. Further guidance is available in the related guide about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/controls-on-torture-goods"&gt;controls on torture goods&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the Regulation weaken national export control restrictions?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The scope of the controls in the Regulation is generally greater than the former UK controls. For instance, there are now controls on gallows and guillotines, electric chairs, air-tight vaults, thumb cuffs and thumb screws. The Regulation raises the level of export control across Europe as many member states previously had no controls in this area.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why was it necessary to remove national controls once the Regulation entered into force?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competence on the export of goods listed in the Regulation now rests with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. As the Regulation is directly applicable in all &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states, overlapping national legislation was revoked. This does not reduce the level of control, but simply ensures that &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; and national legislation mesh together properly.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why can’t we simply add extra torture equipment to our national legislation where this is identified as not covered by the Regulation?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Regulation is now the prime source of European controls on the export of goods used for capital punishment or torture. To be most effective, agreement to control the export of such goods should be sought from all the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The list of controlled goods is very limited, there must be many items which can be used for capital punishment or torture and are not listed. Will member states be able to introduce a wider range of military, security and police equipment into the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Trade Regulation?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The list of goods in the Regulation was proposed by the European Commission and negotiated with the member states in the Council. The preamble (23) in the Regulation indicates that the list of goods in the Regulation should be kept under review and Articles 12 and 15 set out the procedures for making changes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The UK works with other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states to introduce additional equipment for control under the Regulation where appropriate and necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the national control on electric shock dart guns be maintained?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. The government will maintain its controls on exports on electric shock dart guns to all destinations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By deleting PL5001.g from national controls and relying instead on the more restricted definition contained in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Trade Regulation, will some electro-shock devices cease to be controlled, eg electro-shock devices which operate at a voltage level below 10,000 volts?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reference to no-load voltage exceeding 10,000 volts relates to electric shock dart guns. All electric shock dart guns, whether with a no-load voltage, above or below 10,000 volts, will continue to be controlled in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will export controls on ‘ordinary handcuffs’ be added to the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Trade Regulation?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Regulation is now the prime source of control for handcuffs with the exception of the derogation for handcuffs between 240 and 280 millimetres. It is now for the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to decide on any changes to the Regulation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will UK national controls on individual cuffs, controlled under PL5001c.5, be maintained, and will the UK encourage the European Commission and &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states to include this equipment description in Annex III of the Trade Regulation?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The control in the Regulation applies to individual cuffs irrespective of size and goes further than the PL5001.c 5 control, which is limited by the internal dimensions of the cuffs. Therefore, it is unnecessary to maintain the national control.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the UK government consider that having leg-irons or leg-cuffs in Annex III in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Trade Regulation contradicts UK support for Article 33 of the UN Standard Minimum Rules for the Treatment of Prisoners in relation to the use, and export, of leg-irons or leg-cuffs?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This point was considered during the negotiation of the Regulation. Article 7(1) of the Regulation allows member states to maintain national prohibition on these goods. The UK will maintain a national prohibition.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="eu-torture-regulation-trade-controls-and-other-licensing-situations-faqs"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Torture Regulation trade controls and other licensing situations: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about trade controls and other aspects of licensing under the 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_200/l_20020050730en00010019.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation on Products used for Capital Punishment and Torture (the ‘Torture’ Regulation)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="trade-controls"&gt;Trade controls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the Regulation now in force are the existing controls on trafficking and brokering (trade) of ‘torture equipment’ maintained?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. The Regulation does not control trade, but the provisions on trade controls in the Export Control Order 2008 are applied to the goods controlled by the Regulation, as well as maintaining all existing national trade controls. Therefore, a trade licence will be required before trafficking and brokering can be carried out.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the UK be working to introduce effective brokering controls across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The UK supports brokering controls, and continues to apply national trade controls to equipment in the Regulation and encourage other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states to do the same.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the UK government use the options in the Regulation to ensure that the strict export controls introduced in July 1997 and brokering controls implemented in April 2004 are retained?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. The Regulation allows member states to impose stricter controls on the goods which are specified in Articles 7(1) and (2). Article 7(1) allows member states to maintain a prohibition on the export of leg-irons, gang chains and portable electric shock devices. Article 7(2) allows member states to impose an authorisation requirement on the export of handcuffs exceeding 240 millimetres when locked. The UK will apply these provisions.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The Regulation does not control brokering but the UK will continue to apply trade controls as explained above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="other-licensing-situations"&gt;Other licensing situations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about controls on intra-&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; transfers?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now there is a harmonised regime on exports from the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, there is no need in principle for controls on transfers to other member states. However, they are maintained in certain cases where the UK has tougher controls than the Regulation or to maintain previous national controls.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why does the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation only apply to non-&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As with all &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; export regulations, the Torture Regulation only deals with external trade to and from the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What about transhipment controls?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Regulation controls the transhipment in and out of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; of goods listed in Annex II of the Regulation. For goods in Annex III where transhipment controls currently exist in the UK, these will be maintained where this is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Could the lack of transit controls be in breach of &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states’ obligations under the United Nations Convention Against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transit controls apply in respect of goods in Annex II. For goods listed in Article 7(1) national transhipment controls can be maintained. The UK will continue to maintain transit controls on Article 7(1) goods, ie leg-irons, gang-chains and portable electric shock devices.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Trade Regulation control technical assistance whereby person(s) supply such assistance once they have travelled outside the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; territory?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical assistance controls apply (see Articles 3 and 4 of the Regulation) to those Annex II goods prohibited for import and export.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="trade-controls-trafficking-and-brokering-of-military-goods-faqs"&gt;Trade Controls (Trafficking and Brokering) of military goods: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the trade controls?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade means trafficking and brokering of military goods, in other words, the UK involvement in deals which result in the movement of military goods from one third country to another.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For more information, see our page on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/trade-controls-military-goods-on-trade-fairs-and-exhibitions"&gt;current guidance on trade in military goods&lt;/a&gt; in the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-controls-on-controlled-military-goods"&gt;trafficking and brokering (trade controls)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we have a trade licence in place for a certain deal, will we still need to obtain an export licence from the source destination for the goods to leave that country?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if we are arranging for technology for military goods to be moved from one third country to another?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The trade controls do not apply to software or technology, unless it relates to ‘restricted goods’ or movement to an embargoed destination as ‘any act calculated to promote…’ would probably include the transferral of related technology.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="transit-or-transhipment-goods-faqs"&gt;Transit or transhipment goods: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about licensing requirements for goods transiting the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you mean by transit/transhipment?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This means that goods are passing through the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I need a licence for goods in transit/being transhipped?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This varies. Most controlled goods do not need a licence provided certain conditions are met. There are also a number of exceptions.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See more information on transhipment licences in the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/transit-and-transhipment"&gt;transit and transhipment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if software is added to the goods when they arrive in the UK?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then work will be done on the goods, they will have been imported into the UK and an export licence will be needed to export the goods from the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-export-of-technology-faqs"&gt;The export of technology: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a selection of common questions which are often raised at the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s exporter seminars and workshops. See also further guidance about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-of-technology"&gt;export of technology&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you explain what you mean by ‘technology’?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Technology’ is information relating to goods and software. For example, blueprints, plans, diagrams, models, formulae, tables, designs, specifications, manuals and instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is all technology controlled?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Except in certain cases, technology is only controlled if it is required for the development, production or use of listed goods or software, or if the technology itself is specifically described in the UK Strategic Export Control Lists. See the guide on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-strategic-export-control-lists-the-consolidated-list-of-strategic-military-and-dual-use-items"&gt;UK strategic export control lists - the consolidated list of strategic military and dual-use items&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;‘Required’, ‘development’, ‘production’ and ‘use’ are themselves defined terms which need to be understood in order to determine whether a piece of ‘information’ is controlled. In addition, there are exemptions for technology ‘in the public domain’, which is ‘basic scientific research’ or is the minimum necessary for making patent applications.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens if the technology can be used both for licensable and No Licence Required (NLR) goods?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the technology is capable of being ‘required’ for licensable goods, then a licence will be needed, even if it is being exported or transferred in connection with NLR goods.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can technology be transferred?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology can be transferred by physical means, such as posting or hand-carrying a document overseas, or by carrying a laptop or memory device on which the technology is stored.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It can also be transferred by electronic means such as email, fax, file downloads and transfers, or by remote access from overseas.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I therefore need to apply for a licence every time I want to send an email?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No. A licence is issued to cover a project or series of transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does a telephone conversation constitute a transfer of technology?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only if you are reading out a document word for word and it is being transcribed at the other end.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is an export licence required when I place information on a server in the UK if the information is going to be accessed from overseas?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes, since it involves the act of being accessed overseas.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to place data on a server which is physically located overseas but the data will only be accessed by UK-based employees. Do I need an export licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can ensure that information is not accessed from outside the UK (including by system administrators), then you would not need a licence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I require an export licence for information which is in my head?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does providing a service such as repair, training or consultancy constitute technology transfer?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No. This is known as Technical Assistance. However, if a service engineer takes documentation overseas in servicing goods or technology then the documentation would be licensable. You would need to consider this aspect if using technology.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When do we need to have licences to transfer technology within the UK?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the technology meets the definition of ‘any relevant use’ and is going to be used for that purpose outside the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, a licence will be needed to transfer the technology within the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; control electronic transfers?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; expects companies to demonstrate compliance. Whilst it is hard to police this and prove when an electronic transfer is made, emails can be tracked and examined. &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; will use intelligence reports to identify those not complying with the controls. Essentially, if the technology needs a licence to be exported or transferred, get a licence in place and ensure full compliance.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You should be aware that you risk prosecution - either a fine or a jail sentence - along with attendance of loss of business reputation - for misuse of technology. For further information see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/compliance-checks-and-enforcement-of-export-controls-on-strategic-goods-and-technology"&gt;compliance and enforcement of export controls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do licences for technology have a time limit?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only Open General Licence (&lt;abbr title="Open General Licence"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;) that has a time limit is the remote access &lt;abbr title="Open General Licence"&gt;OGL&lt;/abbr&gt;. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/military-goods-ogels"&gt;Military Goods Open General Export Licences&lt;/a&gt;. Those using it have to be out of the country for a period of time of less than three months. Open Individual Licences are usually valid for up to five years.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does ‘in the public domain’ mean?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the public domain means the information is made available without any restrictions, other than copyright, being placed on further dissemination. For instance, information you place on your website that anyone can download or that you publish in a sales brochure would be ‘in the public domain’.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;However, if the information has a security classification or you require a non-disclosure agreement to be in place before you share it or if there are any other intellectual property restrictions, then the information is clearly not in the public domain.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a drawing is ‘in the public domain’, but the goods it refers to are licensable, does the drawing need a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, technology ‘in the public domain’ does not need a licence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The information needed to design our type of product is all available in text books. Surely then our technology is in the public domain? 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only if your specific technology is freely available without restriction is it considered to be in the public domain. The availability of generic information or of similar information from other sources is irrelevant. You would need a licence in both cases.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our product contains software which is open source. Does that mean our product does not need a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The answer to both questions is the same.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="public-domain-faqs"&gt;Public domain: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about information said to be in the public domain. See also guidance about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/export-control-legislation-for-uk-academics-and-researchers"&gt;export control legislation for UK academics and researchers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does ‘in the public domain’ mean?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘In the public domain’ means the information is made available without any restrictions, other than copyright, being placed on further dissemination. For instance, information you place on your website that anyone can download or that you publish in a sales brochure would be ‘in the public domain’.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;However, if the information has a security classification or you require a non-disclosure agreement to be in place before you share it or if there are any other intellectual property restrictions, then the information is clearly not in the public domain.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a drawing is ‘in the public domain’, but the goods it refers to are licensable, does the drawing need a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, technology ‘in the public domain’ does not need a licence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The information needed to design our type of product is all available in text books. Surely then our technology is in the public domain?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You still need a licence. Only if your specific technology is freely available without restriction is it considered to be in the public domain. The availability of generic information or of similar information from other sources is irrelevant. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our product contains software which is open source. Does that mean our product does not need a licence?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You still need a licence. Only if your specific technology is freely available without restriction is it considered to be in the public domain. The availability of generic information or of similar information from other sources is irrelevant. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="sting-sticks-faqs"&gt;Sting sticks: FAQs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some frequently asked questions about sting sticks (which are specific goods used for torture). See also guidance about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/controls-on-torture-goods"&gt;controls on torture goods&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a ‘sting stick’?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the purpose of these controls a ‘sting stick’ is any type of hand-held, spiked baton.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why has the government decided to introduce controls on the export and trading of so called sting sticks?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Following the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20090902183635/berr.gov.uk/whatwedo/europeandtrade/strategic-export-control/legislation/export-control-act-2002/review/index.html"&gt;review of export control legislation 2007&lt;/a&gt;, which included an extensive public consultation exercise, the government made a commitment in its initial response to the views and recommendations it received to extend the current export and trade controls to cover sting sticks.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The government considers that sting sticks are, by their nature, designed for the purposes of torture or similar inhumane acts and have no other legitimate use. Therefore, the government believes that, in common with other equipment of a similar nature, the UK should apply the most stringent level of controls on the export and trading of sting sticks.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will there be new controls on the import and domestic possession of sting sticks?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controls on the import and domestic possession of sting sticks will not be introduced as part of this amendment. However, the government will consider whether an import prohibition should be introduced on sting sticks in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do these controls apply extraterritorially?
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes. These controls apply to the export of sting sticks from the UK and the trading of sting sticks between one third country and another third country, where any part of that trading takes place within the UK, or where it takes place anywhere in the world if carried out by a UK person.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bis-eco-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 7215 4594&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.spire.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Apply for an export licence using SPIRE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/exportcontrol"&gt;Subscribe to the Export Control Organisation’s Notices to Exporters &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/export-control-organisation/eco-contact-details"&gt;Contact details for the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ecochecker.bis.gov.uk"&gt;Goods Checker on the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Checker website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
