<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T16:32:43+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/60033</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T16:32:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:32:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/office-for-life-sciences"/>
    <title>Office for Life Sciences</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="life-sciences-in-the-uk"&gt;Life sciences in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has one of the strongest and most productive life sciences industries in the world, contributing to patient well-being as well as supporting growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry is high-tech, innovative and highly diverse, spanning pharmaceuticals, medical technology, biotechnology, and industrial biotechnology and has applications across many other sectors. Through the development of innovative medicines, medical technologies and services, its businesses contribute to a stronger and fairer society, helping people enjoy better health, well-being and quality of life. They are also helping the UK improve its sustainability and increase rates of decarbonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is building on and fostering these strengths and responding to the changing global commercial environment. We want to make the UK the location of choice for pioneering life sciences &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; and manufacturing investment, so that life sciences will continue to be vibrant in the UK and a contributor to sustained economic growth and health improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;Strategy for UK Life Sciences: One Year On&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has launched &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on--2"&gt;Strategy for Life Sciences - One Year on&lt;/a&gt;, a report which summarises progress made in the first 12 months since last year’s launch of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/s/11-1429-strategy-for-uk-life-sciences.pdf"&gt;‘Strategy for UK life sciences’&lt;/a&gt;. Health Life Sciences is one of the 11 sectors that have been prioritised as part of the Government’s industrial strategy. The Strategy for UK Life Sciences is based on three pillars: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a UK life sciences ecosystem: the Government is making it easier for researchers to commercialise academic research, placing clinical research at the heart of the NHS, and empowering patients to participate in research &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attracting, developing and rewarding talent: the Government is introducing measures to attract and nurture world-leading talent and develop scientific excellence. These measures are ensuring that the UK offers exciting and rewarding careers for clinicians, scientists and technicians from all around the world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overcoming barriers and creating incentives for the promotion of healthcare innovation: the Government is introducing measures to incentivise early-stage investment and nurture the best innovations through the translational funding gap to a point at which they can secure follow-on investment. The Government will continue to reduce the bureaucracy of setting up clinical trials to ensure that patients have access to promising, cost-effective, new treatments. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One Year On reports the substantial progress made this year in implementing these measures. In order to strengthen networks between academia, industry and the NHS, the Government is investing £1bn per annum through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500m in our translational research infrastructure in the NHS. The £180m Biomedical Catalyst was introduced to bridge the ‘valley of death’ between the bench and the clinic, and the early response from industry is that this funding is already having the intended impact of stimulating innovative research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from the progress made to date, One Year On announces the Government’s commitment to the sequencing of 100,000 whole genomes from NHS patients over the next 3-5 years. This work will initially focus on cancer patients, patients with rare diseases and infectious disease. We are working across Government to ensure that research, academia and industry are key players in promoting the adoption of genomic technology to provide better healthcare and help the wider economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategy for UK Life Sciences was launched alongside, and is being implemented in collaboration with, the NHS Chief Executive’s Review: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_131299"&gt;Innovation, health and wealth: accelerating adoption and diffusion in the NHS&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest report on the bioscience and health technology database, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/s/12-p90-strength-and-opportunity-2012-medical-technology-sectors.pdf"&gt;Strength and opportunity 2012&lt;/a&gt;, was published on 10 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt; works closely with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Health&lt;/a&gt;, championing biotechnology and the pharmaceutical and medical technology industries. We also work with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department for Energy and Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; and other departments, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mhra.gov.uk"&gt;Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency (&lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk"&gt;NHS&lt;/a&gt; and the life sciences industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="views-on-the-use-of-animals-in-scientific-research"&gt;Views on the use of animals in scientific research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ipsos MORI report &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/i/ipsos-mori-views-on-use-of-animals-in-scientific-research-september-2012.pdf"&gt;‘Views on the use of animals in scientific research’&lt;/a&gt; presents the findings of a 2012 survey on awareness of, and public attitudes towards, the use of animals in scientific research. This survey has been carried out since 1999 on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that 85% of the representative sample conditionally accept the use of animals in scientific research. While this year’s findings show a decline in overall public acceptance, it also identifies that a significant proportion of the representative sample (40%) would like to know more information about the use of animals in scientific research before forming a firm opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has challenged the scientific community to respond to these findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strategy-for-uk-life-sciences"&gt;Strategy for UK life sciences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 December 2011, the Prime Minister launched the government’s strategy to help life sciences businesses grow and succeed. The strategy focuses on the health-related aspects of the sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a long-term strategy, looking forward 10 to 15 years and building on the March 2011 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for growth’&lt;/a&gt;. It was launched alongside, and is being implemented in collaboration with, the NHS Chief Executive’s Review: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_131299"&gt;‘Innovation, health and wealth: accelerating adoption and diffusion in the NHS’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy for UK life sciences is based on 3 aims:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;building a UK life sciences ‘ecosystem’ - the government is making it easier for researchers to commercialise academic research, placing clinical research at the heart of the NHS, and empowering patients to participate in research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attracting, developing and rewarding talent - the government is introducing measures to attract and nurture world-leading talent and develop scientific excellence; these measures will ensure that the UK offers exciting and rewarding careers for clinicians, scientists and technicians from all around the world &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overcoming barriers and creating incentives for the promotion of healthcare innovation - the government is introducing measures to incentivise early-stage investment and nurture the best innovations and will also continue to reduce the bureaucracy of setting up clinical trials to ensure that patients have access to promising, cost-effective, new treatments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report on the bioscience and health technology database, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/s/11-p90-strength-and-opportunity-2011-medical-technology-sectors.pdf"&gt;‘Strength and opportunity 2011’&lt;/a&gt; was published on 5 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="areas-of-work-for-the-ols"&gt;Areas of work for the &lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of the &lt;abbr title="Office of Life Sciences"&gt;OLS&lt;/abbr&gt; is focused on 2 areas: healthcare and the bio-economy. The healthcare team works with the following sectors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pharmaceutical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical technology – devices and diagnostics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bio-economy team works with the following sectors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;industrial biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;agricultural biotechnology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These teams work across a range of policy areas supporting business growth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NHS market access&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finance and tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bio-economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nhs-market-access"&gt;NHS market access&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market access team works closely with the other &lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; teams, the Department of Health, and other departments and agencies. The NHS is a major contributor to economic growth, and we work together to maximise this contribution and to address any barriers to innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main areas of interest for the market access team are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reforms to the NHS, including the introduction of value-based pricing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the NHS procurement strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engaging with &lt;abbr title="Department of Health"&gt;DH&lt;/abbr&gt;’s delivery of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_131299"&gt;‘Innovation, health and wealth: accelerating uptake and diffusion of innovation in the NHS’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, we are considering how these will create opportunities for the business environment and support the growth agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation"&gt;Innovation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our focus is to ensure that industry has the right environment to innovate and in particular to remove barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="regenerative-medicine"&gt;Regenerative medicine&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the impact of the £25 million &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukrmp.org.uk/"&gt;UK Regenerative Medicine Platform&lt;/a&gt; which addresses the technical and scientific challenges associated with translating promising scientific discoveries in this area towards clinical impact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contributing to the House of Lords Select Committee inquiry into Regenerative Medicine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="medicines-licensing"&gt;Medicines licensing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; on the government’s commitment to consult on an Early Access Scheme for Medicines &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exploring more progressive approaches to medicines regulations, including adaptive licensing, through the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; Expert Group on Healthcare Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="clinical-trials-environment"&gt;Clinical trials environment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency"&gt;MHRA&lt;/abbr&gt; on the European Commission’s plans to replace the European Clinical Trials Directive with a Regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="open-innovation"&gt;Open innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the changing &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; landscape and a growing interest in new ways of partnership working, we organised a seminar on Open Innovation in May 2012. Relevant public sector organisations including the Intellectual Property Office, Technology Strategy Board, Clinical Practice Research Datalink as well as private sector interest (AstraZeneca (PPT, 2.6 Mb), Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst and Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson discussed the opportunities of the approach to the life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="infrastructure-projects"&gt;Infrastructure projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; is co-funding 2 key investment projects to stimulate further growth and address market failures by providing incubation facilities for new companies. These bioincubators are based in Stevenage in Hertfordshire, alongside the GlaxoSmithKline &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; headquarters, and on the Edinburgh BioQuarter site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has also co-funded the Industrial Biotechnology 10,000 litre Demonstrator in Wilton, an open access facility to enable companies, especially small- and medium-sized enterprises, to trial different biomass feedstock  and processes to manufacture biobased products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="stevenage-bioscience-catalyst"&gt;Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.stevenagecatalyst.com"&gt;Stevenage Bioscience Catalyst&lt;/a&gt; will be the first purpose-built, open innovation campus for drug discovery and development. It will maximise the economic impact of academic and science expertise and foster a successful open innovation model between big pharmaceutical and small bioscience companies. It will act as a catalyst to position the UK at the forefront of scientific innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst will be located alongside the GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; Headquarters in Stevenage and is being developed in stages. Phase 1 comprises the construction of BioIncubator and Accelerator buildings for early-stage bioscience companies. Phase 1 is being funded by &lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;, the East of England Development Agency (EEDA), the Technology Strategy Board (TSB), GSK and the Wellcome Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future phases will bring the catalyst up to 45,000 square metres by 2016, assuming that the market demand is as expected. This is forecast to create 1500 new jobs and stimulate the creation of up to 5 new businesses. All future phases will be commercially funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="edinburgh-bioquarter---bioincubator"&gt;Edinburgh BioQuarter - BioIncubator&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.edinburghbioquarter.com"&gt;Edinburgh BioQuarter&lt;/a&gt; is a landmark life sciences hub that is establishing Edinburgh and Scotland as one of the world’s top 10 centres for biomedical research and commercialisation. The project is a long-term life science property and commercialisation partnership between Scottish Enterprise, the University of Edinburgh, the NHS and US-based private sector partner, Alexandria Real Estate Equities, Inc. The 100-acre site already houses the University of Edinburgh Queen’s Medical Research Institute and the 870-bed Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh teaching hospital.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department of Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Scottish Enterprise are co-funding the creation of the BioIncubator.  This investment is expected to leverage almost £210m of additional investment and create or retain over 700 high-value jobs. This will enhance the global reputation of the UK as a place for leading life science innovation, by creating an infrastructure for supporting industry to collaborate with academic and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Edinburgh is aiming to produce 18 new life sciences companies over the next 5 years which will add a considerable pipeline of demand for the BioIncubator. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="industrial-biotechnology-demonstrator"&gt;Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in Wilton in the Tees Valley, the new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk-cpi.com/industrial-biotechnology/demonstrator"&gt;National Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator&lt;/a&gt; is an open access facility of a unique scale of 10,000-litre working volume capacity. The demonstrator has 2 main applications: it can be used as a proof of concept facility to scale-up the production of materials to near commercial levels; and as a product manufacturing facility for clients experiencing temporary capacity restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Industrial Biotechnology Demonstrator"&gt;NIBF&lt;/abbr&gt; will allow biotechnology companies to de-risk product and process development. By exploring and then optimising processes, companies will be are able to calculate the most cost-effective combination of materials; process steps and sequences; and the equipment needed to manufacture profitably. Consequently, they will minimise the risk of investing in the wrong capital equipment, using inefficient processes or facing unexpected costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/59997</id>
    <published>2012-10-09T13:17:55+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-09T13:17:55+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/product-safety-for-manufacturers"/>
    <title>Product safety for manufacturers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design and manufacturing processes are essential to ensure you meet these technical and legal requirements. They can also give your business a competitive edge and save costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide sets out the key safety, design, packaging and insurance issues you need to consider in relation to your products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="your-legal-responsibilities"&gt;Your legal responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Sale of Goods Act 1979, all products must be ‘fit for purpose’, be of satisfactory quality and fit its description. This means that your products must fulfil the purpose the customer has been led to expect and the reasons that led them to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act also covers any purpose that a customer asks about when the product is purchased and is guaranteed by the retailer to meet that purpose when it is sold. If a product is not fit for purpose, the customer is within their rights to have the goods replaced or repaired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act guidance on the Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, good design will lead to safe design. While meeting your legal obligations is the minimum required, it is a good idea to go further and take best practice on board throughout the design, production, supply and disposal stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a manufacturer or supplier you could be held liable in any legal action for harm caused to consumers or businesses as a result of unintended side-effects or the failure of products manufactured or supplied by you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your manufacturing and processing systems must comply with environmental law. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/netregs/"&gt;read guidance to help you keep up with your environmental responsibilities on the NetRegs website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="products-covered-by-specific-safety-regulations"&gt;Products covered by specific safety regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a manufacturer’s claim that its product meets specified essential safety requirements set out in relevant European directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain categories of products must bear &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you intend to sell them in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;member states of the European Economic area (&lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;) - Iceland, Liechtenstein and Norway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following categories of products require &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking if you wish to sell them within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or member states of the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electrical products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;construction products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure vessels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;telecommunications equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;machinery, equipment and safety components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;personal protective equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;satellite station equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gas appliances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pressure equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appliances (other than gas)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-automatic weighing instruments and equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measuring instruments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recreational craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lift machinery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;equipment and protective systems for explosive atmospheres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in vitro diagnostic medical devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marine equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety components and subsystems for incorporation into cableway installations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cableway equipment (ski tows etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The requirement for &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the exact process you will need to go through varies from product to product. Different types of product are governed by different European directives. For example, the trade of certain machinery, equipment and safety components is governed by the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations 2008. The regulations implement a European directive aimed at removing technical barriers to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the regulations, products that conform to the relevant safety standards are &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked and can be placed on the market across the &lt;abbr title="European Economic area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Responsibility for ensuring compliance with the regulations rests with the manufacturer of the machinery, equipment or components in question. Failure to do so can result in prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations (PDF, 424KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where an item of equipment is covered by more than one directive, it must be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked under all applicable directives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply consumer products which aren’t covered by these specific directives, they must not be &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marked. However, you still have a general duty to ensure they are safe for normal or reasonably foreseeable use under the General Product Safety Regulations 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fireworks---information-for-suppliers-retailers-and-display-event-organisers"&gt;Fireworks - information for suppliers, retailers and display event organisers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireworks are available throughout the year from shops licensed to supply them. They become widely available at certain times of the year, mainly a few days before New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year, and in the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night on 5 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you supply or sell fireworks or if you organise display events you must be aware of your responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-as-a-firework-manufacturer-or-importer"&gt;Your responsibilities as a firework manufacturer or importer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks or import category 1, 2 or 3 fireworks which are manufactured outside the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, you must ensure they conform to European safety standards before supplying them for sale to the public. To do this, you need to ensure that the fireworks have been tested by a notified body (&lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the &lt;abbr title="notified body"&gt;NB&lt;/abbr&gt; has approved them, the products must carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and be correctly labelled with details of the manufacturer and importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyrotechnics that were manufactured or imported before 4 July 2010 and that complied with British Standard BS 7114 can continue to be sold without the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark until 4 July 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 3 fireworks must not exceed 120 decibels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category 4 display fireworks that are not intended for supply to consumers must be marked accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import fireworks, you must ensure they comply with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards, carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and supply information at the point of entry to ensure that fireworks are legally stored and distributed. This information should be given to HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs and will then be sent to the relevant authorities responsible for storage licences so they can check on deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licensing authorities can ask to see information relating to transactions of fireworks exceeding 50 kilograms of net explosive content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56376"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/thumbnail_10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/14784/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance.pdf"&gt;Guidance for manufacturers, importers and distributors on firework safety rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;79 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h3 id="your-responsibilities-if-you-are-a-fireworks-retailer"&gt;Your responsibilities if you are a fireworks retailer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to sell fireworks to the public, you need to register your shop or obtain a licence from your local authority. The penalties for not registering or being licensed are a fine of up to £5,000, a prison sentence of up to 3 months, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is illegal for retailers to sell caps, cracker snaps, novelty matches, party poppers, serpents and throwdowns to anyone who is under 16 and to sell all other fireworks to anyone who is under 18 - it is recommended that proof of age is sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must display a large notice reminding customers about the law with regard to underage sales and possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can only sell fireworks that conform to &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; safety standards (or British Standard BS 7114 if they were produced before 4 July 2010) and which carry the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark and meet certain noise conditions. They must have the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark or BS 7114 printed on each item or on the retail packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also supply fireworks with any safety instructions provided by the manufacturer or importer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxes of fireworks must not be split and sold separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you have a special licence, you can only sell fireworks during the weeks leading up to Bonfire Night, New Year’s Eve, Diwali and Chinese New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Find a fireworks storage risk assessment checklist and information about storing and selling fireworks in retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;Find &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cosmetic-products-safety-regulations"&gt;Cosmetic Products Safety Regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All cosmetic products supplied in the UK, whether for consumer or professional use, must comply with the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008 (as amended). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 13 July 2013 a new directly applicable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:342:0059:0209:EN:PDF"&gt;European Regulation (EC/1223/2009)&lt;/a&gt; enters into force, replacing the existing legislation, (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new notification procedure, which requires every product placed on the market to be notified to the European Commission is already in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guidance notes explain all aspects of the Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56381"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56381-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/thumbnail_10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39334/10-761-guide-to-cpsr.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56381-accessibility-help"&gt;A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;220 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;42 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56381-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27A%20guide%20to%20the%20Cosmetic%20Products%20%28Safety%29%20Regulations%202008%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("A guide to the Cosmetic Products (Safety) Regulations 2008").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Regulations require that finished cosmetic products must undergo a safety assessment by a suitably qualified person before they can be placed on the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file50357.pdf"&gt;The Cosmetics Directive&lt;/a&gt; on which the Regulations are based is updated periodically, reflecting changes to the prohibitions and restrictions on certain substances, and subsequent amendments to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1284/contents/made"&gt;Cosmetics Products (Safety) Regulations 2008&lt;/a&gt; are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/"&gt;OPSI website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amendments since then are contained, available on the same website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2173 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2008, S.I. 2008/2566 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/796 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/1346 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No3) Regulations 2009, S.I. 2009/2562 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No4) Regulations 2009. S.I. 2009/3367 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2010, S.I. 2010/1150 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment No2) Regulations 2010. S.I. 2010/1927 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cosmetic Products (Safety) (Amendment) Regulations 2011, S.I. 2012/3037&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 31 October 2012 a new directive enters into force, which is mirrored in S.I. 2012/2263, and which liberalises the use of hydrogen peroxide at up to 6% for tooth whitening purposes, subject to first use by a dentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition various hair dye substances are due to be restricted from 1 September 2013, under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:208:0008:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Directive 2012/21/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is not intending to transpose this because it will be overtaken by the new European Regulation (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-european-regulation"&gt;The European Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has firstly altered the procedure for notification of each product, requiring notification direct to the European Commission using the Cosmetics Product Notification Portal, (CPNP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is operational now and can be used, although it does not become mandatory until the Regulation enters into force: see the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_new_en.pdf"&gt;Cosmetics Products Notification Portal document&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/files/pdf/cpnp_user_manual_en.pdf"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Regulation is directly applicable and it changes various elements, relating to the safety assessment, the responsible person in respect of that, and nanomaterials. There will be further guidance issued, as details which have still to be negotiated are finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-regulations-for-childrens-products"&gt;Safety regulations for children’s products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys supplied in the UK must meet the requirements of the Toys (Safety) Regulations 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations define a toy as ‘any product or material designed or clearly intended for use in play by children of less than 14 years of age, but excluding those products specified in Schedule 3 [of the regulations]’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;download a guide to the Toys (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that a revised European directive will come into force on 20 July 2011. The directive substantially amends the existing regulations across virtually all safety aspects. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:170:0001:0037:EN:PDF"&gt;download the text of the new Directive 2009/48/EC from the EUR-Lex website (PDF, 995K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ce-marking-on-toys"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All toys presented for sale in the UK must bear the &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and the name and address of the person who first placed the toy on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark is a declaration by the manufacturer that the product satisfies essential safety requirements and can be sold within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. For more information see this guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/ce-marking"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authority trading standards officers can remove a toy from the market if they believe it to be unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="testing-for-toys"&gt;Testing for toys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manufacture a toy in accordance with the regulations - and the standards cover all aspects relating to the toy - then it can be self-certified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the standards do not cover all aspects relating to the toy, a sample must be submitted for type examination by an approved body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you import toys you are responsible for their safety, whether or not they already bear a &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; mark. You might want to consider having them tested to ensure they are safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-child-safety-regulations"&gt;Other child safety regulations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other laws relating to child safety include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flammability - tough performance requirements regarding flammability are compulsory for children’s nightdresses and dressing gowns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;choking risks - toys intended for children under 36 months must not present a choking risk - the test uses the ‘small parts cylinder’ (toys or parts of toys that can fit entirely inside the cylinder are identified as choking hazards)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;magnetic parts - magnets which have a flux of more than 50 kG2mm2 (0,5 T2mm2) and fit entirely in the small parts cylinder are not permitted for use in toys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chemicals - the revised European Directive 2009/48/EC will limit the amounts of certain chemicals that may be contained in materials used for toys - these parts of the directive relating to chemical content will come into force on 20 July 2013 (there is also a ban on the use of six phthalates in toys and products for children under 3 years of age)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other products - hood cords, bunk beds and prams and pushchairs are subject to specific safety regulations, namely the Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976, the Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 and the Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="enquiries"&gt;Enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should contact your local Trading Standards office, which is responsible for enforcing safety legislation within your area. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Find contact details for your local office on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="safety-concerns-in-the-early-stages-of-design"&gt;Safety concerns in the early stages of design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking into account the safety aspects of your products from the outset of design can help limit your liabilities as you may find it easier to comply with current and future legislation if your products are easier to produce, use, maintain and dispose of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the research and design of your products during the early stages of development may also boost your competitiveness through a number of ways such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efficient use of raw materials and resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improved product quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing or removing hazardous materials from your processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better preparation for the end of your product’s lifecycle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased market share and better customer relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While you are creating your product, check that no harm will be caused to makers and consumers by any of the materials or finishing techniques used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a sample of your product is ready for use, check that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is strong enough to support any loads involved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can’t produce any toxic, harmful, or adverse effects on the user or consumer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the materials used are suitable for the purpose and safe for users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all hazards have been sufficiently controlled, eg electrical insulation, moving parts, folding components, noise and poor ergonomic design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you dispose of a product, check that the parts and materials can be dismantled without causing harm or releasing toxic or harmful substances. Ensure that the recycling of any parts or materials will not release toxic or harmful substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasingly there is pressure from stakeholders such as the government, regulators, the supply chain and customers to design products that don’t have a negative impact on the environment or society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="packaging-concerns"&gt;Packaging concerns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packaging includes all products used to contain, protect, handle, deliver or present goods. It includes returnable and non-returnable items such as boxes, pallets, labels, containers, tubes, bags, sacks, timber, glass, metals, plastics and ceramics. It can also include tape, wrapping, binding and tying materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should check that your packaging is designed with safety in mind. The packaging should protect your product in transit and protect your customer from potential injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By opting to use a safety-led choice of packaging, your business will benefit from meeting legal demands, saving money and promoting an efficient image to suppliers and customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the GB’s Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009 (&lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) govern the labelling and packaging of hazardous/dangerous chemicals. Suppliers must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify the hazards of the chemical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give information to their customers about the hazards/dangers, usually on the package itself (such as a label) and provide a safety data sheet (SDS) if the chemicals are to be used at work (provision of an SDS comes under the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and restriction of CHemicals Regulation - REACH)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;package the chemical safely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; has applied to the labels and packaging of hazardous substances since 1 December 2010. It will apply to the labels and packaging of mixtures (called preparations under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt;) from 1 June 2015 - however, &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; labels and packaging can be used for mixtures prior to that date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulations were amended to bring them into line with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-wide &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; and REACH regulations. The eventual aim is to have a globally harmonised system for the classification and labelling of hazardous chemicals. Once the &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; requirements for mixtures apply, it is anticipated that the &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; regulations will be repealed. For more information see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/chemicals"&gt;chemicals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://echa.europa.eu/clp/labelling_sds_en.asp"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="Classification, Labelling and Packaging of substances and mixtures Regulation"&gt;CLP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Read about safety issues for chemicals packaging under &lt;abbr title="GB's Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) Regulations 2009"&gt;CHIP&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must take further action if you want to transport dangerous goods. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/moving-goods-by-road"&gt;moving goods by road&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food packaging and labelling is strictly controlled to protect consumers and provide traceability. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/food-labelling-and-packaging"&gt;packaging foods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must keep your use of packaging to a minimum, avoid the use of heavy metals and enable packaging to be recovered. If your business handles more than 50 tonnes of packaging in a year and has a turnover of more than £2 million, you must recover and recycle set amounts of packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="product-liability-and-taking-out-insurance"&gt;Product liability and taking out insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a criminal offence for manufacturers to supply unsafe products. They may also be liable under civil law for any harm such products cause - which could result in costly legal proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Protection Act 1987 makes manufacturers strictly liable for death, injury, loss or damage caused by defective (unsafe) products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a finished product contains a defect in a particular component, both the product manufacturer and component manufacturer may be liable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;download the guide to the product liability and safety provisions of the Consumer Protection Act 1987 from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other suppliers, such as wholesalers and retailers, are not liable unless they fail to identify the producer when asked to do so by a person who has suffered harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But customers can sue retailers under laws on the sale of goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should take positive action to monitor the safety of your products. You should also make sure you are covered by product liability insurance if you manufacture or repair products, and possibly if you sell them, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurance will provide valuable protection for your business against any costs or compensation awarded. Although it’s not a legal requirement to have this type of insurance, it could mean the survival of your business should a claim be made against you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can visit the Association of British Insurers website to download &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.abi.org.uk/Information/Business/15310.pdf"&gt;liability insurance guidance for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-to-get-more-help"&gt;Where to get more help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following links will provide further information on product liability, product safety and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Design Council encourages businesses to understand the design process and to incorporate it into their strategic planning. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/businessandpublicsectorresources"&gt;Read about where to get help on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; has a section on its website called ‘Designers Can Do More’ that looks at issues such as legislation, training and best practice in the design process. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/press/2003/e03234a.htm"&gt;Read information for designers on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; provides wide-ranging support for businesses. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Read about support for businesses on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; provides useful information relating to standards, certification and legislation, together with comprehensive details of &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;Read about standards and &lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme) provides a broad range of information and advice on environmental issues including eco-design and packaging. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://envirowise.wrap.org.uk/"&gt;Read information and advice on environmental issues on their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also contact the Envirowise Advice Line on 0800 585 794 for two hours of free advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bsi-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;020 8996 9001&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="communities-and-local-government-helpline"&gt;Communities and Local Government Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0303 444 0000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wrap-resource-efficiency-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="(Waste &amp;amp; Resources Action Programme"&gt;WRAP&lt;/abbr&gt; Resource Efficiency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0808 100 2040&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-agency-helpline"&gt;Environment Agency Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;03708 506 506&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biba-consumer-helpline"&gt;BIBA Consumer Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0870 950 1790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsi-global.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety"&gt;Product safety and product recall regulations information on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukas.com/about-accreditation/accredited-bodies"&gt;United Kingdon Accreditation Service Accredited Bodies information on the UKAS website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/business-advice/treating-customers-fairly/sogahome/"&gt;Sale of Goods Act resources on the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bsigroup.com/en/ProductServices/About-CE-Marking/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="compliance with EU safety, health and environmental requirements"&gt;CE&lt;/abbr&gt; marking and Kitemarks information on the &lt;abbr title="British Standards Institution"&gt;BSI&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file52968.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on the Supply of Machinery (Safety) Regulations from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 424K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/10-1106-pyrotechnic-regulations-guidance"&gt;Download manufacturers, importers and distributors guidance on firework safety rules from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 81K) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eig.org.uk/guides/Guide%20to%20the%20Pyrotechnic%20Articles%20(Safety)%20Regulations.pdf"&gt;Download guidance on pyrotechnics regulations from the EIG website (PDF, 3.15MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/product-safety/firework-regulations/fireworks-resources"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; fireworks resources and safety codes on the National Archives website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/explosives/fireworks/industry.htm"&gt;Fireworks storage risk assessment and guidance for retail premises on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file11286.pdf"&gt;Download Toys (Safety) Regulations guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 100K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/sectors/toys/index_en.htm"&gt;Toy sector information on the Europa website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file25392.pdf"&gt;Download a ‘Choking Risks to Children’ research report from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 419K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/advice/index.cfm"&gt;Local office contact details on the Trading Standards website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/our-work/challenges/The-Environment/"&gt;Sustainable design advice on the Design Council website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.venturenavigator.co.uk/assessment/available/2/10"&gt;Product design assessment tool on the Venture Navigator website (registration required)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/chip/index.htm"&gt;Chemical packaging safety guidance on the &lt;abbr title="Health &amp;amp; Safety Executive"&gt;HSE&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file22866.pdf"&gt;Download Consumer Protection Act 1987 product liability and safety guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 207K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/59915</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"/>
    <title>Reducing the impact of regulation on business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regulations are ineffective and unnecessary. Complying with them costs businesses time and money, and can restrict growth. Red tape can also make running charities and community groups more difficult than it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure all regulations are fair and effective. We want to strike the right balance between protecting people’s rights, health and safety and freeing them from unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure regulations in the UK are fair and effective, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;controlling the number of new regulations by &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;operating a ‘one in, two out’ rule for business regulation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/assessing-the-impact-of-new-regulation"&gt;assessing the impact of each regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reviewing-the-effectiveness-of-government-regulations"&gt;reviewing the effectiveness of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-regulation-for-small-businesses"&gt;reducing regulation for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/improving-enforcement-of-government-regulations"&gt;improving enforcement of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/using-alternatives-to-regulation-education-campaigns-economic-instruments"&gt;using alternatives to regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-the-cost-of-eu-regulation-on-uk-business"&gt;reducing the cost of EU regulation on UK business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We publish &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publication_filter_option=guidance&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=department-for-business-innovation-skills"&gt;guidance for all government policymakers&lt;/a&gt; to help design better regulations or find other options instead of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, regulations - and the inspections and bureaucracy that go with them - have piled up. Businesses say the amount of new regulation is one of their biggest problems, preventing them from growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2010, we said that we would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut red tape for businesses and individuals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not rely on rules and regulations by themselves to get things done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re running a series of reviews called ‘Focus on enforcement’ to get businesses’ views on how we could improve the way we enforce regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/"&gt;Have your say on how we enforce regulations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also running the Red Tape Challenge, asking businesses and the public which regulations they think could be removed or improved. See what businesses are saying: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Tell us which regulations you think should be removed or improved.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56575</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the single market more effective</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the EU expanded to include more states, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate acheived by other EU states. However, the European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at a rate as low as just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the EU and other dynamic markets, such as South Korea, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the EU as a whole. To achieve higher growth and increased employment, all member states and the EU institutions will need to take action. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which encourages all member states to reinforce financial stability, create jobs and improve competitiveness, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong single market creates jobs and benefits all member states. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234 billion, went to the EU. The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other EU prime ministers, urged the EU to improve the single market, concentrating on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update EU single market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting EU consumers in cyberspace. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;.  Member States must implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013. E-invoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-invoicing within the EU could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;EU-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; which came into force on 1 July 2011 is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for EU exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act (2011)&lt;/a&gt; sets out twelve ways to boost growth and improve confidence in European business. In October 2012 the European Commission proposed a second set of actions, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smact/docs/single-market-act2_en.pdf"&gt;Single Market Act II&lt;/a&gt;, to further develop the single market’s economic opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act II (2012)&lt;/a&gt; describes the EU’s goals of improving the digital economy, including e-commerce and electronic invoicing, and creating more efficient transport and energy networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/u/11-760-uk-response-single-market-act"&gt;response to The Single Market Act&lt;/a&gt; in February 2011 looks at how the UK will work with other member states on reforms that will create the most jobs and economic growth at the lowest cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a study, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/e/11-517-economic-consequences-of-completing-single-market"&gt;The economic consequences for the UK and the EU of completing the single market&lt;/a&gt;, in February 2011. This paper considers the benefits of the single market and the negative effects of the UK opting out of future European trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; published a study in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/feeds/~/media/568CC723188C40DFBB02E868353B40B9.ashx"&gt;The UK and the single market: trade and investment analytical papers topic 4 of 18&lt;/a&gt;, that examines the importance of the EU for British exporters and investors. The analysis found that businesses have benefited from the opportunities provided by the single market. Such benefits include: better connected and cheaper networks; mutual recognition of standards; and easier access to cheap and competitive inputs for British manufacturers. In addition greater competition within the single market has fostered innovation. For consumers, the single market has created more choice and lowered prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/59916</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/permanent-secretary-individual-performance-objectives-2012-to-2013"/>
    <title>Permanent Secretary individual performance objectives 2012 to 2013</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defines the role and objectives of Martin Donnelly, the Permanent Secretary, for the 2012 to 2013 period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60015</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/one-in-one-out-third-statement-of-new-regulation"/>
    <title>One-in, one-out: third statement of new regulation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, one-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January 2012 and 30 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect. It provides an overview of the net costs and benefits to business and civil society organisations, and forecasts a further reduction in new burdens on businesses by an estimated £4.17 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60031</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on--2"/>
    <title>Strategy for UK Life Sciences – One Year On</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update on progress implementing measures in the ‘Strategy for UK life sciences’ (URN 11/1429). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy set out a long-term programme with a range of practical measures that the government will take to improve the environment for large and small health life science companies in the UK. It included providing support from discovery right through to the commercialisation of medicines, diagnostics and devices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one year on report describes substantial progress made this year in implementing these measures. It also announces the government’s intention to commit to sequencing 100,000 whole genomes over the next 3-5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of continuing government efforts to develop the UK’s position as a global life sciences hub.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56571</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets are the best way of making sure a country’s resources are put to their best use. They encourage enterprise and widen choice for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can develop in any economy. They can harm consumers and stifle innovation and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an anti-competitive activity would be when two companies agree to charge the same price for a similar product. This protects the companies’ profits but means consumers get less choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can be very bad for consumers. That’s why they have to be identified and stopped as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the government’s three growth objectives is that the UK should become the best place to start, finance and grow a business. Reforming and improving the laws on anti-competitive activities is a major part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-competition-law"&gt;Changing competition law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is reforming the laws that cover competition and anti-competitive activities in business, including those relating to mergers, markets and illegal activities such as price-fixing and cartels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also reforming the institutions that police competition and anti-competitive activities, and strengthening their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These laws, institutions and powers are collectively known as the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="competition-landscape"&gt;Competition landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re making changes to the organisations that deal with competition and anti-competitive activities in business. We’re doing this between now and the end of 2014. This work is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and competition landscape reforms."&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reforms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="setting-up-a-new-watchdog-for-the-grocery-industry"&gt;Setting up a new watchdog for the grocery industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re creating a new watchdog for the grocery industry. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/groceries-code-adjudicator" title="Groceries Code."&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt; will give suppliers, including farmers supplying the bigger supermarket chains, more protection against anti-competitive activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-legal-challenges-easier"&gt;Making legal challenges easier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to make it easier for consumers and small businesses to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/private-actions-pro-tem" title="Private Action."&gt;challenge anti-competitive behaviour&lt;/a&gt; by bringing a legal challenge (also known as a private action) against anti-competitive activities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-aid"&gt;State aid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re modernising the rules on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State aid is when a public body (such as a local authority) or publicly funded body (such as the Big Lottery) provides a business, charity or other organisation with financial help that could give them an advantage over another business. This kind of financial help is generally outlawed by the European treaty, as it’s an anti-competitive practice. State aid regulations set legal ways to give this kind of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"&gt;detailed guide on state aid&lt;/a&gt; for public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different rules - also covered in the detailed guide - apply to agriculture, aquaculture, fisheries, transport and maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK competition law has to comply with EU law. Article 101 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/antitrust/overview_en.html"&gt;Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU)&lt;/a&gt; bans any agreements between businesses ‘which have as their object… the prevention [or] restriction… of competition within the common market.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57424</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past 5 years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57049</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-boost-for-business-as-government-sets-out-plans-to-update-employment-legislation"/>
    <title>Press Release: Boost for business as government sets out plans to update employment legislation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to collective redundancies rules to help employees and businesses were announced by Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government announced it plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the current 90 day minimum period, before very large scale redundancies can take place, to 45 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legislate to make clear that fixed term contracts which have reached the end of their natural life are excluded from obligations for collective redundancies consultation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce new non-statutory Acas guidance to address a number of key issues affecting collective redundancies consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK has a labour market that is flexible, efficient and fair but some of our laws need reform to respond to an ever changing employment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to improve the quality of consultations by making sure that there are tools available to help employers manage this process fairly and successfully to deliver the best possible outcomes for all parties.  Acas will be working with stakeholders to produce non-statutory guidance that will be designed to help improve the quality of consultations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have listened to stakeholders and there is a strong argument for shortening the minimum period which is backed up by hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The process is usually completed well within the existing 90-day minimum period, which can cause unnecessary delays for restructuring, and make it difficult for those affected to get new jobs quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our reforms will strike an appropriate balance between making sure employees are engaged in decisions about their future and allowing employers greater certainty and flexibility to take necessary steps to restructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement responds to a consultation launched in June and to calls for improvements to the way collective redundancies rules operate and for the processes involved to be made easier to understand. It also forms part of the Government’s commitment to review employment law to support business and concentrate on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replacement of the current 90 day period to 45 days will still allow full employee engagement and offer employee representatives a statutory right to contribute to the process. The new 45 day period will be a minimum period, and businesses may consult for longer where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will be made through secondary legislation. Draft regulations will be laid in the New Year and the changes are expected to be made by 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition government started a systematic review of employment law in 2010. This Employment Law Review (ELR) is now half way through its work and aims to provide clarity, certainty and give businesses the confidence to manage their workforce effectively. The Review sits alongside the Employment Law-related Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulatory burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the government’s response to Collective
Redundancies can be found at
&lt;a href="/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill sets out a comprehensive series of reforms aimed at supporting businesses, developers, and first time buyers by slashing red tape that delays or discourages business investment, development or job creation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe
Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
