<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56742</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training"/>
    <title>Improving the quality of further education and skills training</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The further education (&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt;) system – the colleges and training providers that teach vocational qualifications and skills – needs to guarantee students high quality teaching and courses to help students into jobs or university and create the skilled workforce employers need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve quality and efficiency in &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; and skills training, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing a new funding system based on student loans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freeing colleges from central government control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; teacher training more professional&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing better careers advice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for funding post-16 learning in England is shared between the Department for Education (16-18 year olds) and the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (19 year olds and over).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, an independent review of further education, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.education.gov.uk/publications/eOrderingDownload/The%20Wolf%20Report.pdf"&gt;the Review of Vocational Education&lt;/a&gt; made a number of recommendations including that we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move to ‘per-student’ funding instead of ‘per-qualification’ funding, to make institutions more accountable to learners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the quality of apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government then carried out a public consultation to invite opinions on these recommendations &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/new-challenges-new-chances-next-steps-in-implementing-the-further-education-reform-programme"&gt;New challenges, new chances: next steps in implementing the further education reform programme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the responses to the consultation, the government published its plans, in December 2011, for the &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; sector in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-investment-statement-for-2011-to-2014-new-challenges-new-chances" title="New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan"&gt;New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will shortly publish an update on ‘New challenges, new chances’. This will explain the progress we have made in reforming the further education and skills system. We have already published a number of reports and plans on aspects of the system, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-for-sustainable-growth-strategy-document"&gt;Skills for Sustainable Growth&lt;/a&gt;, which sets out the national skills strategy for England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/11-1380-further-education-skills-system-reform-plan.pdf"&gt;Our plan for further education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/s/12-p172-skills-funding-statement-2012-2015.pdf"&gt;Skills Funding Statement 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;, which contains our budget for skills and the numbers of learners it will support for the next 2 years, set out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our strategy for investing £550 million in college facilities in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/12-1340-further-education-college-capital-investment-strategy-plan.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; College Capital Investment Strategy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jason Holt’s independent report on apprenticeships and small businesses, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/making-apprenticeships-more-accessible-to-small-and-medium-sized-enterprises-a-review-by-jason-holt"&gt;Making apprenticeships more accessible to small and medium-sized enterprises: a review by Jason Holt&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doug Richard’s independent report for the government on the future of apprenticeships, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-richard-review-of-apprenticeships"&gt;The Richard review of apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans to set up chartered status for the further education sector, to help institutions celebrate their success and reputation, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/chartered-status-for-the-further-education-sector-proposals-to-create-a-chartered-status-scheme-for-further-education-institutions-consultation"&gt;Chartered Status for the Further Education Sector&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="government/admin/publications/48201"&gt;Chartered Status Design Competition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the report by Lord Lingfield on how the further education sector can best serve its users’ needs, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/professionalism-in-further-education-final-report-of-the-independent-review-panel"&gt;Professionalism in Further Education: final report of the Independent Review Panel&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;advice for further education colleges and training providers on 24+ Advanced Learning Loans, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.practitioners.slc.co.uk/further-education.aspx"&gt;24+ Advanced Learning Loans Student Loans Company Learning Provider Services&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://readingroom.skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/sfa/24plusall_updated_guide_and_faqs_may_2012.pdf"&gt;SFA loans FAQs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ours and our partners’ plans to ensure that young people and adults get the advice they need on learning and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-careers-service-the-right-advice-at-the-right-time"&gt;National Careers Service: the right advice at the right time&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our proposals for piloting community learning trusts, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;Community Learning Trust prospectus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans for engaging 16 to 24 year-olds in education, training and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/16-24-education-training-and-work-strategy-and-reforms"&gt;Building engagement, building futures: our strategy to maximise the participation of 16-24 year olds in education, training and work&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/21/contents/enacted" title="Education Act 2011"&gt;Education Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier for colleges to make their own decisions. It means that &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; colleges can now borrow money without needing permission from the government. Colleges can also change the way they govern themselves, and those rated ‘outstanding’ by Ofsted no longer have to face routine inspections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/"&gt;UK Commission for Employment &amp;amp; Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/the-national-careers-council"&gt;National Careers Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56741</id>
    <published>2012-12-16T23:07:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-16T23:07:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-national-careers-council"/>
    <title>The National Careers Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s vision for a better quality of information, advice and guidance on learning and work is set out in the document &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-careers-service-the-right-advice-at-the-right-time"&gt;The Right Advice at the Right Time&lt;/a&gt; , published in April 2012, the month the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121205150610/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/further-education-skills/national-careers-service-for-england"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt; was launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Council is chaired by Dr Deirdre Hughes, OBE, with 10 members and 3 associate experts. The Council has been tasked to produce an Annual Report to government in March 2013. The Council’s Secretariat is provided by BIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-councils-work"&gt;The Council’s work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council is taking forward three initial work strands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="access-quality-and-professionalism"&gt;Access, quality and professionalism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strand Leader: David Mc Nerney in association with Ruth Spellman, OBE, Rajay Naik and Steve Higginbotham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="connectivity-of-national-careers-service-to-business-and-the-wider-careers-market"&gt;Connectivity of National Careers Service to business and the wider careers market&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strand Leader: Jenny Rudge, OBE in association with Linda Taylor, OBE; Professor Tony Watts, OBE; Brian Lightman; and Nick Chambers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="intelligence-innovation-and-impact"&gt;Intelligence, innovation and impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strand Leader: Kieran Gordon in association with Chris Heaume, OBE; Simon Surtees; and Heather Jackson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="meetings"&gt;Meetings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural meeting of Council took place in London on 21 May 2012. This was followed by meetings on 12 June 2012 and 24 September 2012 with John Hayes, MP, then Minister for Further Education, Skills and Lifelong Learning (jointly with the Department for Education) and government policy-makers, to discuss and agree the proposed Council work strands for 2012-2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/ncc-statement-20-june-2012.doc"&gt;Statement by Dr Deirdre Hughes, OBE, Chair, on behalf of the National Careers Council, 20 June 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/national-careers-council-october-statement-october-2012.pdf"&gt;Statement by Dr Deirdre Hughes, OBE, Chair, on behalf of the National Careers Council, 3 October 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="evidence-to-lord-heseltine-review"&gt;Evidence to Lord Heseltine Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 30 August 2012 members of the NCC met with the Lord Heseltine Review team of how spending departments and other relevant public sector bodies interact with the private sector, and to assess their capacity to deliver pro-growth policies. The meeting covered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raising the work-readiness of school leavers and those acquiring tertiary qualifications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remedying skills deficiencies in the current workforce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;addressing the longstanding NEETs problem and encouraging apprenticeships and support for the lower skilled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A copy of the written evidence submitted to Lord Heseltine’s Review can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/ncc-summary-of-evidence-lord-heseltine-review.pdf"&gt;Summary of evidence relating to Education, Employment and Skills presented on 30 August 2012 to the Lord Heseltine Review benchmarking UK performance against a range of economic indicators&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ncc-workplan"&gt;NCC Workplan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Careers Council is currently auditing key policy themes and has identified seven major challenges that will inform its ongoing work. A workplan, formally presented to the minister on 2 July 2012, sets out key priorities and plans for 2012 to 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/n/12-997-national-careers-council-workplan.pdf"&gt;National Careers Council: Workplan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further update will be produced in September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="next-stage-plans"&gt;Next stage plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two Council meetings are scheduled to be held on 14 January 2013 and 18 April 2013. Dr Hughes will be meeting with interested parties to find ways of connecting organisations and individuals to feed into the Council’s work. The Council will develop a more detailed work plan for each of the three work strands and look at ways to involve others in its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to feed in your views, please submit them to the Council Secretariat: &lt;a href="mailto:robert.canniff@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;robert.canniff@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-careers-council---members-biographies"&gt;National Careers Council - members’ biographies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="dr-deirdre-hughes-obe---chair"&gt;Dr Deirdre Hughes OBE - Chair&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deirdre was awarded an OBE in the 2012 New Year Honours List for her services to career guidance. She is a Commissioner at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/"&gt;UK Commission for Employment &amp;amp; Skills&lt;/a&gt; (July 2011). She is also an Associate Fellow at the Institute for Employment Research (IER), Warwick University, an Associate at the Centre for Educational Sociology, Edinburgh University. Deirdre is a ‘Lead Consultant’ within the European Lifelong Guidance Policy Network on quality assurance and evidence, and active member of the International Centre for Career Development and Public Policy (ICCDP). She is also Director of DMH Associates based in Derbyshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="linda-jc-taylor-obe"&gt;Linda JC Taylor OBE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda’s career has been in the careers guidance sector, most recently as Chief Executive of Connexions South London. She is a Fellow of ICG a past member of the National Apprenticeship Group and Sec.General of the IAEVG. Linda was awarded the OBE in 2008 for public and voluntary services to young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="heather-jackson"&gt;Heather Jackson&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather Jackson has over 20 years’ experience of working closely with government on the development of career guidance for adults, including acting as External Policy Adviser to the Cross-government Review of IAG for Adults (2005-2007); as Head of Information, Advice and Guidance at the National Health Service University and involvement in the initial design and development of the current telephone and face-to-face services for adults. Heather currently chairs NAEGA (National Association of Guidance for Adults) and is a member of the CPA Executive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chris-heaume-obe"&gt;Chris Heaume OBE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1974 Chris has had a substantial career with young people in London as a youth worker, FE manager, Connexions CEO, Ofsted Inspector and Trustee of the Partnership for Young London, recognized in an OBE in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="david-mcnerney"&gt;David McNerney&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David McNerney is HR Director at Sellafield Ltd, which is responsible for safely delivering decommissioning, reprocessing and nuclear waste management activities on behalf of the Nuclear Decommissioning Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David has spent the last 27 years working in Human Resources, Change and Business Services roles, both in the UK and abroad. He has worked in a variety of industries, including manufacturing, telecoms, and utility management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rajay-naik"&gt;Rajay Naik&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajay Naik is Director of Government and External Affairs at The Open University. He is also Chairman of UK Programmes at the Big Lottery Fund, a Commissioner at the Department of Health and serving in his sixth year as a Governor at a major FE college. Rajay was formerly a member of the Browne Review into higher education funding, and is a former Chairman of the British Youth Council. He has served on the boards of the National Youth Agency, v, Learning and Skills Council and the Changemakers Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="professor-tony-watts-obe"&gt;Professor Tony Watts OBE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Watts is a Founding Fellow and Life President of the National Institute for Careers Education and Counselling, and Visiting Professor at the University of Derby and at Canterbury Christ Church University. A co-founder of CRAC, he has carried out many international studies of career guidance systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ruth-spellman-obe"&gt;Ruth Spellman OBE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WEA’s new Chief Executive Ruth Spellman has had a career marked by a commitment to lifelong learning. She was awarded an OBE in 2007 for services to workplace learning and an Honorary Doctorate from Cranfield in 2010. Ruth was formerly Chief Executive of the Chartered Management Institute (CMI), and has previously been CEO of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers and Investors in People (IIP) UK. She has also been HR Director of the NSPCC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="jenny-rudge-obe"&gt;Jenny Rudge OBE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Rudge is the Chief Executive of Careers South West Ltd.and has 36 years experience of working in the careers sector. She has previously served on the National Taskforce for Modern Apprenticeships and as an advisor to the DFES for the Every Child Matters initiative. Jenny was awarded an OBE for services to careers education and guidance in 2002.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="kieran-gordon"&gt;Kieran Gordon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kieran has 30 years experience of working in the careers guidance sector, including latterly as Chief Executive of Greater Merseyside Connexions (GMCP). Kieran was a member of the UK Taskforce on the Careers Profession and served on the National Careers Service Advisory Group, and served on the Presidential team of the Institute of Careers Guidance (ICG) for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="steve-higginbotham"&gt;Steve Higginbotham&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A career guidance professional - Chief Executive of igen (a provider of careers/IAG, training and employability services); Director and Immediate Past President of Institute of Career Guidance; Director of Careers England (and Chair of Adult Task Group); Director of Careers Yorkshire &amp;amp; the Humber (National Careers Service prime contractor); member of the Careers Profession Alliance (CPA) Executive Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="simon-surtees-ma-dipcg---associate-member"&gt;Simon Surtees MA DipCG - associate member&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon qualified as a Careers Adviser in 1981 and has worked across London throughout his career. He brings to the Council experience of Careers Guidance with individuals of all ages and extensive experience of managing and training Careers Advisers and Personal Advisers. He is also a Governor of St Marks Academy in Mitcham. He is currently a Project Manager with CfBT Include working with Training Providers in West and South London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="brian-lightman---associate-member"&gt;Brian Lightman - associate member&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Lightman taught modern languages in SE England and had two headships in S Wales before becoming General Secretary of the Association of School and College Leaders (ASCL) in September 2010. He served on the Board of Careers Wales Cardiff and the Vale of Glamorgan from 2004-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nick-chambers---associate-member"&gt;Nick Chambers - associate member&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Chambers is the director of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.educationandemployers.org/"&gt;Education and Employers Taskforce&lt;/a&gt;. The charity aims to make it easier for education and employers to work together to help young people. It undertakes research and runs &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.speakers4schools.org/"&gt;Speakers for Schools&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.inspiringthefuture.org/"&gt;Inspiring the Future&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56684</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair"/>
    <title>Making the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses say current employment laws are difficult to cope with and put them off taking on staff. This slows the growth of businesses and the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simpler, more flexible employment laws will make it easier for companies to hire and manage staff, while protecting basic workers’ rights. This should encourage employers to create new jobs, supporting enterprise and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair the government is: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/reviewing-employment-law" title="to make them more flexible for employers and employees"&gt;reviewing employment laws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/introducing-more-flexible-working-practices" title="introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers"&gt;introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/setting-and-enforcing-the-national-minimum-wage" title="setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates"&gt;setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates&lt;/a&gt;  to protect workers from exploitation and businesses from unfair competition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/encouraging-modern-workplaces-and-flexible-working" title="making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments"&gt;making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/providing-guidance-on-employment-law" title="providing better guidance on employment law"&gt;providing better guidance on employment law&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/enforcing-standards-in-employment-agencies-and-employment-businesses-and-recruitment-agencies" title="enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies"&gt;enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies&lt;/a&gt; to better protect workers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/researching-the-labour-market" title="researching the labour market"&gt;researching the labour market&lt;/a&gt; to produce data on employment relations, the labour market and equality at work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We agreed to review employment law in May 2010 as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition-agreement-may-2010_0.pdf" title="Coalition Agreement"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulations launched in April 2011 and includes a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/employment-related-law/" title="review of employment law"&gt;review of employment law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extended the time you need to be employed to be able to claim for unfair dismissal from 1 to 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-bill-policy-paper" title="Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill"&gt;Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill&lt;/a&gt; which will make changes to the employment tribunal system, including ensuring all employment tribunal claims go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acas.org.uk/index.aspx?articleid=1461" title="Acas"&gt;Acas&lt;/a&gt; and introducing a simpler process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removed the compulsory retirement age, making it easier for older people to carry on working&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;launched a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Regional-Mediation-Pilot-Schemes-up-and-running-67b90.aspx"&gt;pilot scheme&lt;/a&gt; encouraging the use of mediation to resolve disputes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reviewed how employment rights are enforced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-consulting"&gt;Who we are consulting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out consultations on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/r/11-511-resolving-workplace-disputes-consultation"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt; more quickly without having to go to an employment tribunal &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/6529"&gt;changing the rules on large-scale redundancies&lt;/a&gt;  so that employers can restructure more effectively while also carrying out good quality consultations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/e/12-1037-ending-the-employment-relationship-consultation.pdf" title="changing the rules on ending the employment relationship"&gt;changing the rules on ending the employment relationship&lt;/a&gt;, the use of settlement agreements and changes to the compensation limit in unfair dismissal cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/employment-tribunal-rules-review-by-mr-justice-underhill"&gt;changing employment tribunal rules&lt;/a&gt; to make them more flexible and effective and to get better value for the taxpayer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out an impact assessment on the benefits of &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/5450" title="resolving workplace disputes"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt;. We estimate these changes will save businesses £40 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56700</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:45:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:45:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-innovation-workshop"/>
    <title>Support for Innovation Workshop</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library, NE1 8AX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30th January 2013, 9.30am to 3.30pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying competitive and growing a business in today’s challenging trading conditions is tough.  However, a range of Government support and funding is available to help your business innovate and grow. Find out more at this free practical workshop for small and medium sized businesses with the appetite and potential to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus will be on the importance of innovation to future success and how government schemes can help you develop, protect and commercialise new ideas. Subjects include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-innovation"&gt;Importance of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Addison, innovation specialist and pioneer of Procter &amp;amp; Gamble’s open innovation programme, will describe how innovation is vital for growth. In particular, P&amp;amp;G’s approach to open innovation could be reused in your business for sourcing and commercialising new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="support-for-innovation"&gt;Support for Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering grants and other support for R&amp;amp;D through the Technology Strategy Board and the R&amp;amp;D Tax Credit scheme run by HMRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-your-innovation"&gt;Protecting Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering support from the Intellectual Property Office to protect your IP and how schemes like Patent Box can make it much more cost effective to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commercialising-your-innovation"&gt;Commercialising Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including support from the Design Council to enhance product value through design and how Growth Accelerator can support your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Register for the free workshop at &lt;a href="www.business-events.org.uk"&gt;www.business-events.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is being held at the Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library. The Centre is designed to support entrepreneurs, inventors and small businesses from that first spark of inspiration to successfully launching and developing a business. It is the first regional centre based on the British Library’s model and have been running since September 2011. Since the launch, over 2,000 entrepreneurs have used the Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre is a partnership between the British Library, Newcastle City Council, Newcastle Science City and Northumbria University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56688</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T16:14:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:14:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/data-strategy-board"/>
    <title>Data Strategy Board</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="latest-news"&gt;Latest news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 14 December 2012, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts announced a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://rnn.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;further investment in open data through an expansion of the Technology Strategy Board’s Innovation Voucher programme&lt;/a&gt;. This new development will make &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/data-strategy-board#faq-innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/a&gt; available to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; who want to use open data to help commercialise their ideas and develop new products and prototypes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vouchers will form part of the second round of the Technology Strategy Board’s Innovation Voucher programme and will compliment the three open data investments announced on 12 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2012 ministers Matthew Hancock and Francis Maude announced three new complementary investments in open data designed to increase the flow of open data and to support companies working to create innovative new products from the re-use of public data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the press notice &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;New funding to accelerate benefits of open data&lt;/a&gt;. There will be: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/data-strategy-board#dsb-breakthrough-fund"&gt;Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/data-strategy-board#open-data-immersion-programme"&gt;Open Data Immersion Programme&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;upgrades to the format in which &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/data-strategy-board#open-geographical-data-upgrades"&gt;Ordnance Survey data&lt;/a&gt; can be downloaded to make it easier, more accurate and more flexible for companies to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the measures announced are expected to be in place by early April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement demonstrates a real commitment from government to open up public data to stimulate economic growth, unlock new commercial opportunities for business and develop more transparent and efficient public services. Further details are available in the frequently asked questions below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Strategy Board (&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt;) held its inaugural meeting on 11 July 2012. The Board is chaired by Stephan Shakespeare. The purpose of this Board is to raise the UK economic competitiveness, increase accountability and improve public services through greater access to public data for people and businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remit of the board will look to maximise value of data from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/shareholderexecutive/structure/portfolio-unit/public-data-group"&gt;Public Data Group&lt;/a&gt; of Trading Funds and beyond. The membership of the board includes data users from outside the public sector, with representatives of commercial re-users and the Open Data community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="data-strategy-board-chairs-blog"&gt;Data Strategy Board Chair’s blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/blog/author/stephanshakespeare/"&gt;Access the &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; Chair’s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="purpose-of-the-data-strategy-board"&gt;Purpose of the Data Strategy Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt;’s remit is to create maximum value, for businesses and people across the UK, from data held by the Public Data Group Trading Funds (Ordnance Survey, Met Office, Land Registry, Companies House) and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the public sector the &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;steer the management of contracts for weather and geographic information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider how data from the Data Strategy Board might generate economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work to ensure that ministers have appropriate advice to enable:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delivery of Open Data from the Public Data Group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of data and services to the public sector UK general public, including services which contribute to the protection of life, property and UK national infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making access to data easier for all users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increasing public access to free data over time, subject to affordability and value for money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/growth/docs/terms-reference-data-strategy-board.pdf"&gt;Data Strategy Board Terms of Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="papers"&gt;Papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_52737"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36775/dsb-28-nov-2012-agenda.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-52737-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36775/dsb-28-nov-2012-agenda.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-52737-accessibility-help"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 28 November 2012: agenda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;40.5 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-52737-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20DSB%20meeting%2028%20November%202012%3A%20agenda%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27DSB%20meeting%2028%20November%202012%3A%20agenda%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 28 November 2012: agenda").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_52738"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36776/dsb-28-nov-2012-action-record.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-52738-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36776/dsb-28-nov-2012-action-record.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-52738-accessibility-help"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 28 November 2012: action record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;120 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-52738-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20DSB%20meeting%2028%20November%202012%3A%20action%20record%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27DSB%20meeting%2028%20November%202012%3A%20action%20record%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 28 November 2012: action record").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h4 id="older-papers"&gt;Older papers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/d/dsb-3-oct-2012-action%20record.doc"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 3 October 2012: action record&lt;/a&gt; (DOC, 87 Kb)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/d/dsb-3-oct-2012-agenda.doc"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; Meeting 3 October 2012: agenda&lt;/a&gt; (DOC, 37 Kb) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/d/dsb-11-july-2012-action-record.doc"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 11 July 2012: action record&lt;/a&gt; (DOC, 79 Kb)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/d/dsb-11-july-2012-agenda.doc"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; meeting 11 July 2012: agenda&lt;/a&gt; (DOC, 35 Kb)   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-shakespeare-review"&gt;The Shakespeare Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has announced that Stephan Shakespeare Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt;, will lead an independent review of public sector information. Further details of the review can be found in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Review-of-open-data-to-explore-growth-opportunities-68203.aspx"&gt;press notice&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/i/12-1233-independent-public-sector-information-review-draft-terms.pdf"&gt;draft terms of reference&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 143 Kb) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments on the terms of reference are welcome and can be sent to the review mailbox at: &lt;a href="mailto:datastrategyboard@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;datastrategyboard@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="useful-links"&gt;Useful links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/transparency"&gt;Cabinet Office: transparency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/about-us/what/pws/customer-group"&gt;Public Weather Service Customer Group&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/oswebsite/public-sector/mapping-agreement/index.html"&gt;Public Sector Mapping Agreement (PSMA) for England and Wales&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.data.gov.uk/"&gt;data.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/shareholderexecutive/structure/portfolio-unit/public-data-group"&gt;Public Data Group&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theodi.org/"&gt;Open Data Institute (ODI)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nesta.org.uk/"&gt;NESTA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can email the &lt;a href="mailto:datastrategyboard@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;datastrategyboard@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the debate on Twitter: #datastrategy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="faqs-on-the-three-new-complementary-investments"&gt;FAQs on the three new complementary investments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="dsb-breakthrough-fund"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; Breakthrough Fund&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What is the &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; Breakthrough Fund?
A. The fund will assist open data proposals where government departments, government agencies and local authorities have identified constraints on data release. It will help the government’s “presumption to publish” agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. Who is eligible?
A. Government departments, government agencies and local authorities are eligible to apply. In the case of local authorities, collaborative bids will be encouraged (especially from district councils) based on geographic, economic, community of interest, shared services or other local or regional partnership groupings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What will the fund cover?
A. The fund will cover a number of sub-themes of activity which could include funding for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IT/tool development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;standardising data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making data linkable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Q. What are the criteria for applications?
A. In order to qualify for funding organisations must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;demonstrate that they have not been able to identify appropriate funding through existing budgets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commit to making the data available for free under the Open Government License, to high quality, with appropriate frequent updates on an ongoing basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;show that there is a demand for the data to be released / standardised / linked and that there is a longer term economic, social or environmental benefit to making it more accessible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commit to ways to track the use of their data and the benefit which has been realised from its release&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the data available through the government’s Data.gov.uk website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="open-data-immersion-programme"&gt;Open Data Immersion programme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;including competition prizes &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What is the Open Data Immersion Programme?
A. The programme will comprise of a series of events and competitions, run by the Open Data Institute and NESTA (National Endowment for Science Technology &amp;amp; the Arts). It will involve a range of data owners – such as Trading Funds, Departments, agencies and local authorities - and data users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The events will be aligned to both specific sector challenges and industry themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. Who is eligible for the programme?
A. The programme will be targeted at small to medium enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) and start-ups. Key participants will be developers who can code the products and services, data owners/domain experts who understand and can help source the appropriate information and product/industry business leaders who have an explicit understanding of the real world industry challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What will participants get from the events?
A. Participants who are selected to partake in an Innovation Camp event will get the opportunity to work closely with data owners/domain experts to help develop their products, and also the chance to partner with other
&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;/start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning projects at each event will be eligible to take their concepts into early product development with pre-seed funding from the Technology Strategy Board (TSB) Innovation Vouchers or competition prizes run by NESTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ODI anticipates engaging the private sector to in some way match the commitment of the Data Strategy Board funding. This could be in the form of NESTA prizes, support and or resources to support the winning projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. Where can I find more information about the Open Data Immersion Programme?
A. More information on the programme will be published shortly on the Open Data Institute website at: www.theodi.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-geographical-data-upgrades"&gt;Open Geographical Data upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What are Open Geographical updates?
A. The Open Geographical updates include new product releases; release of OS VectorMap District Version 1, and OS Terrain 50. New styling is being released for Meridian2 and Strategi. These updates will increase the quality, accuracy and currency of a number of products, whilst the styling will make them easier to use and interpret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. Who is eligible?
A. The new products will be available to everybody through the &lt;a href="www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/oswebsite/products/os-opendata.html"&gt;OS OpenData website&lt;/a&gt; from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. Where can I find more information about the new products?
A. Further information is available on the &lt;a href="www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk"&gt;Ordnance Survey website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="faq-innovation-vouchers"&gt;FAQ Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.  How does this relate to the existing Innovation Vouchers programme?
A.  The Technology Strategy Board (TSB) will deliver the new vouchers as part of the existing Innovation Voucher programme.  The vouchers will also adopt the format and structure of the vouchers available to other sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.  How much is each voucher worth? 
A.   The vouchers will have a value of £5,000 each. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.  How can I apply for a voucher?
A.  Application for the vouchers will be online through the existing TSB Vouchers portal at: https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q. What are Innovation Vouchers?
A. The purpose of Innovation Vouchers is to help stimulate and promote innovation in targeted sectors where we want to encourage greater levels of innovation. Vouchers can be used to incentivise &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to engage with the knowledge base and other forms of innovation advice to help them to grow by developing new ideas and potential new commercial products. Start-ups and small and medium sized businesses and sole traders from across the UK can apply for an Innovation Voucher. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.  Who is eligible?
A.   Innovation Vouchers for Open Data Business Innovators and Inventors are aimed at &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and sole traders. The vouchers will help them access specialist and technical advice from knowledge suppliers to help develop new or improve existing data products that make use of open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.  Where can I find more information?
A.  Further details can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org"&gt;TSB website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="data-strategy-board-members"&gt;Data Strategy Board members&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="stephan-shakespeare-chair-dsb"&gt;Stephan Shakespeare: Chair, &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan Shakespeare is CEO and Co-founder of YouGov, the international market research agency. He has been a school-teacher, writer and campaigner, and founded PoliticsHome.com. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan is sits on the Public Policy External Advisory Board of the University of Cambridge, he is co-founder of Opigram, sat on the LSE’s Polis Advisory Board and is a former Justice of the Peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan studied English at Oxford. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: @StephanShaxper  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nick-baldwin-chair-public-weather-service-customer-group-pwscg"&gt;Nick Baldwin: Chair, Public Weather Service Customer Group (PWSCG)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Baldwin has been independent Chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/about-us/what/pws/customer-group"&gt;Public Weather Service Customer Group (PWSCG)&lt;/a&gt; since September 2007. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has a portfolio of advisory, consultancy and governance roles, working in the government, utility, housing and charity sectors. He is Chairman of the Office for Nuclear Regulation, Chairman of Sanctuary Housing Group and Chairman of Ambitious About Autism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously he worked in electricity, gas and water utilities, culminating in being the Chief Executive of Powergen plc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick is a Chartered Engineer, a Chartered Director, a Fellow of the Institution of Engineering &amp;amp; Technology (FIET) and a Fellow of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers (FIMechE). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="professor-sir-john-beddington-government-chief-scientific-adviser"&gt;Professor Sir John Beddington: Government Chief Scientific Adviser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir John Beddington was appointed as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/go-science/chief-scientific-adviser"&gt;Government Chief Scientific Adviser (GCSA)&lt;/a&gt; on 1 January 2008. Since being in post, the GCSA has led on providing scientific advice to government during the 2009 swine flu outbreak and the 2010 volcanic ash incident. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GCSA has also been responsible for increasing the scientific capacity across Whitehall by encouraging all major departments of state to recruit a Chief Scientific Adviser. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout 2008 and 2009 Sir John raised the concept of the ‘Perfect Storm’ of food, energy and water security in the context of climate change, gaining considerable media attention and raising this as a priority in the UK and internationally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to his appointment as GCSA, he was Professor of Applied Population Biology and headed the main departments of environmental science and technology at Imperial College. His main research interests are the application of biological and economic analysis to problems of Natural Resource Management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir John has previously been advisor to a number of UK government departments including the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, the Ministry of Defence and the Cabinet Office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has also advised several governments and international bodies including the Australian, New Zealand and US governments, the European Commission, the United Nations Environment Programme and Food and Agriculture Organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was, for 6 years, a member of the Natural Environment Research Council. In June 1997 he was awarded the Heidelberg Award for Environmental Excellence, in 2001 he became a Fellow of the Royal Society. In 2004 he was awarded the Companion of the Order of St Michael and St George by Her Majesty the Queen and in June 2010 was awarded a knighthood in the Queen’s Birthday Honours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: uksciencechief &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="michael-coughlin-executive-director-local-government-association"&gt;Michael Coughlin: Executive Director, Local Government Association&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael is Executive Director at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/"&gt;LGA&lt;/a&gt; having recently been Chief Executive at Reading Unitary Authority, previously serving as Chief Executive at Crawley Borough Council in West Sussex. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has over 30 years experience of working in local government, having worked in two Director positions at the Royal Borough of Windsor and Maidenhead and prior to that at Elmbridge Borough Council and Bexley London Borough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has included extensive work with Councillors of all political parties and at a national level with a variety of Government departments, Ministers and senior Civil Servants. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is educated to degree level with post-graduate qualifications in Management, Marketing and Leisure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for a number of organisational and service programmes, major regeneration and capital projects and behaviour change, innovation and community engagement. He is a judge for both the Municipal Journal and O2 Future Fund. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael has served on the South East England Councils, South East Strategic Leaders and Improvement and Efficiency South East’s Chief Executives’ Advisory Groups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was a Board member of Thames Valley Connexions and Reading UK Economic Development Company, is an alumni of the Leadership Centre for Local Government’s Leeds Castle programme, and a Fellow of the Royal Society for the Arts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael is married with a family of older youngsters. He is a league and team squash player and plays bass and guitar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: m__coughlin &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="john-dodds-director-of-innovation-at-the-department-for-business-innovation-and-skills-head-of-dsb-secretariat"&gt;John Dodds: Director of Innovation at the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, Head of &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; Secretariat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John has been the Director of Innovation at the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills since March 2011. John and his teams work to support Ministers in their objective that Britain should be one of the most innovative economies in the world – with innovation making a major contribution to growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2006 to 2011 John was Director of the Better Regulation Executive with the objective of reducing the impact of red tape on business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, John carried out a broad range of roles in HM Treasury including spells as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head of the Defence, Diplomacy and Intelligence Team (2002-2006), leading Treasury interests in defence spending and procurement &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Head of Information Services (1997-2002), leading the Treasury’s internal information strategy and with responsibility for delivery of IT, library and records management services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Head of the Budget Coordination Team (1994-1997), project managing the Chancellor of the Exchequer’s Budget for Ken Clarke and Gordon Brown and editor of the Budget ‘Red Book’ &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy Adviser in the European Community Division (1991-1994) playing a key role in the negotiation of the 1992 European Community financing settlement and the accession of Sweden, Finland and Austria to the European Union.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;John studied Mathematics at Christ’s College, Cambridge from 1979-1982 and has an MSc in Statistics from Manchester University where he won the M S Bartlett prize in 1983. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sir-ian-magee-cb-chair-geographic-information-customer-group"&gt;Sir Ian Magee CB: Chair, Geographic Information Customer Group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian Magee is Chair of the Geographic Information Customer Group. He is a Senior Fellow of the Institute for Government. He is co-author of ‘Read Before Burning’, the Institute’s report on arms-length bodies (July 2010); of ‘System Error’ the Institute’s report on government IT (March 2011); and of ‘System Upgrade?’ (June 2012), the Institute’s analysis of the progress government is making with its ICT strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2005, he was 2nd Permanent Secretary at the Department for Constitutional Affairs; and Head of Profession for Operational Delivery for the whole Civil Service. He has been a CEO of three different Executive Agencies. Ian was a member of the Capability Review team for the Cabinet Office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was a Senior Adviser to Booz and Company, international management consultants, and is an Advisory Board member of two companies. Ian is an Executive Coach to senior civil servants and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian conducted a review of criminality information for the Home Secretary, published in July 2008; and a review of the Legal Services Commission for the Justice Secretary, published in March 2010. Ian has a special interest in public sector leadership, and in the effective use of data to improve services to the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="heather-savory-chair-governments-open-data-user-group"&gt;Heather Savory: Chair, Government’s Open Data User Group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather is a successful executive with a solid commercial track-record and extensive board and senior management experience in entrepreneurial and high technology businesses, consulting and central government. She has strong expertise in all aspects of high growth business development and large-scale change environments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather is Chair of the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/chair-open-data-user-group-appointed"&gt;Open Data User Group (ODUG)&lt;/a&gt;; she also sits as a member of the Public Sector Transparency Board and on the Regulatory Board of the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors (RICS). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously Heather has worked at 3Dlabs as Vice President of Engineering and Operations, eComData as Managing Director and at the centre of UK Government spending two years in HM Treasury and three in the Department of Business, Innovation and Skills at the Better Regulation Executive (&lt;abbr title="Better Regulation Executive"&gt;BRE&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather graduated from Loughborough University of Technology with a 1st class BSc (Hons) in Electronic and Electrical Engineering and a Diploma in Industrial Studies; she also has an Executive MBA from London Business School. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: SaturnSA4 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="steve-thomas-managing-director-for-strategic-development-experian-plc"&gt;Steve Thomas: Managing Director for Strategic Development, Experian Plc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve has been a UK board member since joining Experian in April 2007. He leads Experian’s UK Industry Sector Development and Operations including Public Sector. He is also responsible for UK Strategy, Marketing and Communications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve joined Experian in April 2007 following 18 years at IBM, where he served on the UK board as Vice President of the Communications and Industrial sectors for UK, Ireland and South Africa. Whilst at IBM Steve led a number of multi-billion technology, software and consulting businesses in the UK &amp;amp; EMEA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve graduated from Loughborough University with a BSc (Joint Hons) in Mathematics &amp;amp; Sports Science. He also has gained an IBM Executive Development at Insead and an IBM Condensed MBA from Harvard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chris-yiu-head-of-digital-government-unit-the-policy-exchange"&gt;Chris Yiu: Head of Digital Government Unit, the Policy Exchange&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Yiu is Head of the Digital Government Unit at Policy Exchange, the UK’s leading think tank. He directs research on public policy for a world increasingly dominated by technology, data and the internet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris authored the Policy Exchange report ‘A right to data’, which called for all of the non-personal data collected or created to support the day-to-day business of government to be made open: easy to access and free at the point of delivery, without restriction on use or reuse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also authored ‘The big data opportunity’, which dealt with the opportunities and challenges presented by big data and analytics in the public sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris is serving on the Data Strategy Board as a member of the Coalition for a Public Interest Data Policy. This is an independent group interested in the development of public data policies that promote transparency, efficiency and innovation whilst consolidating fundamental rights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris has spent the past decade working at the heart of public policy and business strategy. In government he held a number of positions, including advising on tax and financial services policy at HM Treasury, and on economic and foreign policy at the Prime Minister’s Strategy Unit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In business he served a range of clients with McKinsey &amp;amp; Company, working across the technology, financial services, healthcare and consumer goods sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris was born and brought up in London. He holds a first class degree in economics and a master’s degree in economics and finance, both from the University of Cambridge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: @PXDigitalGov &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bill-roberts-ceo-swirrl-it-ltd"&gt;Bill Roberts: CEO, Swirrl IT Ltd&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Roberts is CEO and co-founder of Swirrl IT Ltd. Swirrl works with public sector organisations to help them share their data as ‘5-star’ linked open data. Recognising that the benefits of open data are only realised when the data is used is the guiding principle of Swirrl’s approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill spends much of his time engaging with re-users of public sector data - in central and local government, the third sector, academics and private sector companies. Bill hopes to bring this hands-on experience of the open data economy to bear on the issues the Data Strategy Board is tasked to address. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill has a PhD in Fluid Dynamics from the University of Edinburgh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: @billroberts &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="overview-of-the-board"&gt;Overview of the Board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt; is a Ministerial Advisory Board that advises &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ministers/david-willetts"&gt;David Willetts&lt;/a&gt;, Minister for Universities and Science, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/francis-maude-minister-cabinet-office"&gt;Francis Maude&lt;/a&gt;, Minister of Cabinet Office. It is led by an independent chair, and includes data users from outside the public sector, including representatives of commercial re-users and the Open Data community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Board also incorporates existing public sector customer groups, who will continue to provide sector expertise around the commissioning of weather services and geographic information for the public sector. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/about-us/what/pws/customer-group"&gt;Public Weather Service Customer Group&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/corporate/1878453"&gt;Geographic Information Group&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/open-data-user-group"&gt;Open Data User Group&lt;/a&gt; will become sub-committees of the &lt;abbr title="Data Strategy Board"&gt;DSB&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 to 3 public sector seats for the chair to appoint. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/55880</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:08:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:08:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up and grow a business </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people feel that starting a business is not for them, either because they’re worried about finding funding and making money or because they don’t think they have the skills or experience needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, research shows that existing small and medium enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) can be put off growing their business because of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of access to finance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not being able to recruit people and lacking the right skills in new and existing staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;day-to-day cash flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-the-uk-an-easier-place-to-do-business"&gt;Making the UK an easier place to do business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/enabling-businesses-to-get-finance"&gt;providing funding and programmes to make loans available to more small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a scheme with the Bank of England to enable banks and building societies to borrow from them at cheaper rates so that they can then lend to small to medium businesses (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) at lower interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new business bank that will provide more funding to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support"&gt;providing funding and programmes to encourage private sector investment in small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with private sector investors to provide government and private sector money to invest in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investing in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; with government and private sector money through the Start-Up Loan Scheme, the Business Finance Partnership and Business Angel Co-Investment Fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/encouraging-a-more-entrepreneurial-society"&gt;funding and managing initiatives to encourage young people and give them the skills to set up their own business&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recruiting young business owners to volunteer as enterprise champions who will go into schools and talk to young people about running their own business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with schools and colleges to promote schemes such as ‘Tenner’ which gives £10 to each student to start a business and ‘Enterprise Village’ which helps schools to set up businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support--2"&gt;providing support and advice to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve launched websites that provide information to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; on how to run and grow their business – Business in You, GrowthAccelerator, Mentorsme and Manufacturing Advisory Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of private sector businesses in the UK increased to 4.8 million at the start of 2012 – a record high. Barclays estimate there were just under 500,000 business start-ups in England and Wales in 2011; also a record number and 12,700 (2.6%) more than in 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period about 500,000 businesses closed. Businesses have told us that they need access to finance and less red tape in order to keep running. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve developed our policies to support start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; so that they can continue to grow and make a contribution to the economy and so that they get access to finance and support that hasn’t been previously available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work closely with businesses, financial institutions and other government departments to help make sure the environment is right for UK businesses to start up, grow and succeed. Our work covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;Better regulations to make doing business easier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax – working with HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs who are introducing a range of measures to help start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; including a National Insurance holiday for the first year of employing people, reduced Corporation Tax and a Seed Enterprise Investment Scheme &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment"&gt;Exporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth"&gt;Innovation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56434</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-tackles-red-tape-head-on-with-package-of-measures"/>
    <title>Government tackles red tape head on with package of measures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of the way that appeals are handled by regulators launched today is the first stage of a new wave of bureaucracy busting measures announced by the government, Business Minister Michael Fallon confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and other interested parties will have a chance to take part in a review of the effectiveness of appeals mechanisms operated by national and local regulators. The Focus on Enforcement Appeals Review will give those affected the opportunity to talk about their experiences of formal and informal appeals processes, and suggest how they could be made to work more effectively, providing a swifter route to resolution and better industry understanding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will also gather examples of approaches that have successfully helped businesses understand regulators’ decisions and meet their obligations more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have started a bonfire of excessive red tape, but I know that it is just as important that we look at the way that regulations are enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is room for far more effective enforcement which reduces the burden on business which stick to the rules.  Despite best efforts, sometimes things can go wrong – that has become clear from previous Focus on Enforcement Reviews. So I want to hear views on how we can improve the way appeals currently work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greater clarity and trust between regulators and businesses will lead to better enforcement of the law and higher standards across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest review follows a package of new measures announced at the Autumn Statement to tackle systemic problems with the way regulations are enforced and cut the unnecessary red tape and burdens that companies have to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a consultation on placing a legislative duty on non-economic regulators to have regard to growth and take into account the economic impacts of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new accounting system for regulators, so that in future regulators will have to publish impact assessments for prior consultation, scrutiny and challenge by industry, of the impacts of all changes in their activities that have a significant (positive and negative) financial impact on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consultation on an amended Regulators’ Compliance Code to ensure regulators are internally and geographically consistent, give consideration to earned recognition, and offer minimum service standards to those they regulate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government action to ensure regulators are transparent about the fees they charge and bear down on their costs and improve their efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also today, as part of the package the government announced plans to cut bureaucracy by widening the range of regulations included in the Primary Authority scheme. The plans would see the scheme covering age-related sales of gambling, the Housing Health and Safety Rating system for assessing potential hazards in dwellings, sun-bed tanning and Welsh regulations for single-use carrier bag charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships are reducing regulatory burdens for companies and allowing them to grow. It’s now time to extend the scope of the scheme to streamline the way regulators work with businesses, improve protections to the public and help local authorities to target their resources against rogue traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major business groups such as the CBI, British Retail Consortium and FSB are strongly in favour of Primary Authority and of its extension. The Trading Standards Institute and Chartered Institute of Environmental Health are also in favour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence arising from sector-specific Focus on Enforcement reviews has already indicated that businesses have concerns about how current appeals systems operate. These include confusing or multiple appeals mechanisms lack of transparency and in some cases resolution taking excessively long periods of time.   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The forthcoming review will invite evidence from all sectors of the economy and any regulatory regime. Appeals mechanisms for economic regulators are not included in the scope of this review. Interested parties can participate in the review of appeals at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year at Budget, the government announced a new approach to cutting red tape, looking at how rules are enforced, rather than the rules themselves. A series of Focus on Enforcement Reviews have shown that in addition to sector-specific issues, there are also systemic enforcement issues limiting industry that affect most if not all sectors. So, rather than tackling systemic issues case by case, the Government’s Autumn Statement package  aims to change the system, creating greater clarity and fairness for businesses while ensuring regulators focus their resources where they are needed most. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Primary Authority Scheme is run by the Better Regulation Delivery Office, an independent unit within the Business Innovation and Skills Department (BIS). See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are currently 602 businesses and 93 local authorities involved in Primary Authority partnerships, covering over 58,000 premises and over 1.57 million employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the scope of the scheme, or the list of regulations which can be covered by partnerships, can be achieved by secondary legislation. The consultation announced today runs until 24 January 2013 to allow feedback from stakeholders before secondary legislation is introduced into Parliament.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Housing Health and Safety Rating System (HHSRS) is a risk-based evaluation tool to help local authorities identify and protect against potential risks and hazards to health and safety from any deficiencies identified in dwellings. It was introduced under the Housing Act 2004 and applies to residential properties in England and Wales.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56633</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-online-business-support-offer-growth-and-improvement-service-my-new-business"/>
    <title>Assessment of the online business support offer: Growth and Improvement Service, My New Business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether online business support services provided by Business Link have performed effectively against the strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’.  That is to successfully assist businesses through a website rather than through higher cost services (for example face to face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study also makes an early assessment of the value of the services provided to new users, with a focus on cost effectiveness and effective referral to other appropriate business support services in the public, private and third sectors. The support services include the comprehensive start-up service provided by My New Business, and online tools provided by the Growth Improvement Service, enabling businesses to identify and solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56643</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-business-link-helpline"/>
    <title>Assessment of the Business Link helpline</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether the Business Link helpline is performing effectively against its strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’, in which more businesses are assisted online rather than through other higher cost provision (for example face-to-face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the research has assessed the value of the service being provided to callers and how far actual demand has matched expectations. The findings are being used to help inform plans for continual improvement of the service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is based on interviews with helpline staff, analysis of monitoring data, call case studies and a customer survey that consisted of 657 telephone interviews that were completed with customers of the helpline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
