<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Communities and Local Government</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T16:22:45+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57535</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T16:22:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T16:22:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-pop-up-shop-to-showcase-high-street-entrepeneurs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens pop-up shop to showcase high street entrepreneurs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s efforts to regenerate high streets and encourage entrepreneurs, the shop is being opened in time for final Christmas present buying this week by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk, with the support of national enterprise campaign StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To directly support enterprise and showcase Britain’s best new retailers, ministers have set up the pop-up store inside their Victoria-based office building to act as a blueprint for high streets across the country to emulate through schemes such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cutting the ribbon on the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5697/ribbon-cutting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles cutting the ribbon with Mark Prisk and Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the first ever Whitehall pop-up shop with ‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell. Every fortnight six new British start-up businesses will move into the shop, sharing costs and trialling their exciting ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop will be open to the public for at least a year and will offer affordable retail space to over 150 small start-up businesses. The department is not seeking any financial return from the shop, which is being supported by sponsors Intuit, John Lewis, SNR Denton and StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5698/shop-floor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The first 6 pop-up tenants are NANUKK, Milla &amp;amp; Arti, Arthur &amp;amp; Henry, London Mummy, Morrow’s Outfitters and The English Tee Shop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe pop-ups are a great way to get empty spaces used and could be easily replicated in other town centres across the country. Mr Prisk has written to the British Property Federation to urge landlords to get on board. He said that, starting in January, all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Town Team partners will receive support to facilitate new pop-ups in their empty high street premises, which could support thousands of new businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to rejuvenating the high street. A multi-million pound strategy is backing local partnerships such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams to breathe new life into their town centres. This includes a doubling of small business rate relief; mentoring from retail experts; and workshops to address town centre challenges. A guide to opening a pop-up will be published soon and StartUp Britain has published a tool kit today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is providing over £80 million of start-up loans for young entrepreneurs, which could create over 30,000 new businesses. Ministers are also changing planning restrictions so that landlords can alter how an empty shop is used for up to two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these steps will make it easier for start-ups to find other low-cost stores to set up in. Last year 450,000 people set up new businesses and almost two thirds of new start-ups say they would benefit from trading on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are absolutely determined to support the high street and we know pop-ups are a great way to bring empty shops back to life and get new businesses going, so we thought ‘why not open one right here in the department?’. It will also showcase how we can unleash more of our best and brightest young entrepreneurs onto the country’s high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The PopUp Britain model gives retail entrepreneurs an affordable opportunity to scale up their businesses and become a part of their own high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing record numbers of people setting up businesses and they are starting out small and online. They are the driving force of the economy. This initiative offers them a chance to physically test out new markets as well as get their products in front of consumers and big buyers in a way that has never been available to them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By actively encouraging local authorities to give start-ups access to empty shops across Britain, we hope it will help accelerate British enterprise as well as providing a vibrant addition to the local British shopping experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real appetite in our town centres to get them revitalised so they remain attractive places to visit. And it’s not just talk: there are many extremely capable and serious people with some superb ideas; but they need a bit of help to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up shops are a superb way for all sorts of entrepreneurs to test their ideas. So I’m delighted that this department is opening the first pop-up shop in Whitehall and I look forward to inviting all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Towns Teams here to see how they could replicate this model across the country in the new year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a brilliant idea and it is great to see the government actively supporting business in this way. For many aspiring and growing enterprises, having access to a retail unit where new propositions and ideas can be tested directly with customers can be the catalyst to increase sales. I hope other landlords follow this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the Bright Ideas Trust, where we invest in businesses started by young unemployed people, we see many business struggle to secure retail space as they grow out of their bedrooms and away from their kitchen tables.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=neKNqnTu6qY"&gt;Pop-up shop event video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="startup-britain"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startupbritain.co/"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/a&gt; is a national campaign by entrepreneurs for entrepreneurs, harnessing the expertise and passion of Britain’s leading businesspeople to celebrate, inspire and accelerate enterprise in the UK. The campaign was founded by eight entrepreneurs and was launched in March 2011 by the Prime Minister. It has successfully run pop-up stores in Richmond, Surrey, which opened in July and which have already helped 42 businesses get access to the high street. Four in five of the tenants said the experience had been good for their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-six-pop-up-britain-victoria-tenants"&gt;First six pop-up Britain Victoria tenants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established 6 months ago by 27-year-old Shrewsbury-based designer Sarah McLeod, silk scarf company &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nanukk.com/"&gt;NANUKK&lt;/a&gt; features beautiful pieces of Art printed onto silk fabrics. All the scarves are made in England. Sarah has been labelled as one to watch, after she was awarded the River Island Graduate Fashion Week Award in 2008. 
Sarah said: “It will be great to have a physical presence in the marketplace at last! So far I’ve only been online. People will love the feel of my silk scarves and I hope it will make them buy. I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millaandarti.co.uk/"&gt;Milla &amp;amp; Arti&lt;/a&gt; was set up by product design consultant Deborah Reyner 18 months ago. Her British-made homeware collection includes bespoke lavender hearts for weddings, patchwork kits, gift ties and ribbons, collars and bows. 
Deborah said: “This is a wonderful opportunity for Milla &amp;amp; Arti and to talk about my products which are made by the British seaside and get people interested in making and doing themselves. I haven’t been able to sleep for a week before this, I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brother and sister Mark and Clare Lissaman named their ethical organic cotton men’s shirt company after their grafting grandfathers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.arthurandhenry.com/"&gt;Arthur &amp;amp; Henry&lt;/a&gt; was developed after ethical consultant Clare noticed there were no ethical formal shirts on the market. “I was at the World Congress on Organic Cotton a few years back and realised that although all the men attending were passionate about organic cotton - none were actually wearing any as they were all suited up and couldn’t find proper smart shirts in organic cotton,” Clare, from Islington, said. “So we thought we’d make some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re thrilled and delighted to have this opportunity. For a newly established, ethical menswear brand, this is an amazing opportunity to meet customers face-to-face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single mum and former interior designer Esther Gibbs, from Chiswick, created &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmummy.com/"&gt;London Mummy&lt;/a&gt; after people kept asking her where she bought the cushions and accessories she had made herself. All her products are now either made in England – some by Esther herself - or by women’s collectives in China. Her handpicked selection includes retro bed linen, colourful crochet animals, quirky kids’ stationery, classic toys and games, funky lunchboxes, wall art and more. Esther also makes beautiful children’s fabrics, which she sells in store too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther said: “I sell online but I’ll sell much more in the shop. Once people understand what the shop is about and what it’s doing for small British businesses, it will be a great asset for the high street and small businesses. I’m delighted to be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sock entrepreneur Philip Morrow, 25, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.morrowsoutfitters.com/"&gt;Morrow’s Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; last year as a way to re-establish his great-grandfather’s former gentlemen’s outfitters shop that operated in Liverpool between 1912 and 1987. His range of Loughborough-made cotton socks come in over 40 designs and colours. 
Phillip said: “Pop-up shops make a great deal of sense for small online businesses such as mine. I’m over the moon about getting the opportunity to come into PopUp Britain in Victoria.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-time English teacher and designer Alia Qadir, 30, from Ealing, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theenglishteeshop.com/"&gt;The English Tee Shop&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to combine her passion for fashion and love of grammar! All her cotton is English-made and printed. She sells online and runs her business part-time from home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia said: “Until now I have relied on my online presence to sell my brand. But my T-shirts are made from a really good quality, soft jersey, and that doesn’t come across online. I’m really delighted about this new pop-up adventure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-town-team-tool-kit"&gt;New Town team tool kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the prototype shopping concept comes a newly-developed pop-up-specific tool kit for Town Teams to implement, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a national pop-up lease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a central website with information about the initiative for town teams and new businesses interested in applying for a slot at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.popupbritain.com"&gt;www.popupbritain.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to free pop-up payment equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a step-by-step guide for setting up a PopUp Britain shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PopUp Britain branding to make the shop recognisable to the consumer as a place where they can support British enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review, the department is running a number of high street Town Team Portas Pilots in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs. Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams in May, and 15 more in July, with three from London, bringing the total to 27. They each receive up to £100,000 of funding plus support from Government and retail expert Mary Portas. More detail can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"&gt;Improving high streets and town centres pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-teams"&gt;Town Teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 330 Town Team Partners support includes: an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management; special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and support from industry experts and trade bodies including an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice; regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas; and ‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work. All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919132719/www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;List of Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="statistics"&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key statistics and evidence on start-ups in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 saw a record high for start-ups: over 450,000 people set up a company
 and became their own boss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a StartUp Britain poll revealed 82% of start-ups found the pop-up experience was valuable for their business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the UK, there are 4.8 million private sector companies employing an estimated 23.9 million people with a turnover of £3,100 billion. Small and medium-sized enterprises also account for almost half of the net growth in jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to the latest figures from the British Retail Consortium, 11.3% of shop premises in UK town centres are now vacant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to research from StartUp Britain, 63% of businesses not already on the high street think their business would benefit from a high street presence and, of these, 88% believe funding is the biggest barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="additional-quotes"&gt;Additional quotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Johnson, Chairman of StartUp Britain, former Pizza Express boss and Chairman and part-owner of Patisserie Valerie and Giraffe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new high street name that will become synonymous with buying British and supporting small British enterprise is a fantastic idea. I’m sure PopUp Britain will be embraced by town planners and local government as a way to offer tangible support to their own high streets and start-up communities.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Russell, Chief Executive of WeArePopUp, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-ups are ideal incubators for the next generation of entrepreneurs. It’s very encouraging to see the Government opening a national showcase in a high-profile location such as Cardinal Place in Victoria. Pop-ups can change the fortunes of local communities and we look forward to this support encouraging more landlords to open up their empty shops and become part of the solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosie Cann, Director at Popupspace, a property consultancy that specialises in pop ups, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find space for lots of established retailers, but the challenges for new businesses wanting to open shops are much wider. What we have here is a unique offering to smaller start-ups looking for affordable space to sell, but also for business support and a high profile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Little, UK Managing Director of Intuit, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up tenants need to be able to accept card payments but it can take weeks to get set up, the equipment and transactions can be expensive and require long-term contracts. Intuit is proud to support PopUp Britain with Intuit Pay, giving start-up retailers a way to get set up in minutes to securely take card payments on their smart phone or tablet – with no commitment and no contracts. With Intuit Pay anyone can now accept card payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the shop are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269606220/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/17814</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/statutory-consultee-performance-and-award-of-costs"/>
    <title>Statutory consultee performance and award of costs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes to amend guidance in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/costs-awards-in-appeals-and-other-planning-proceedings-circular-03-2009"&gt;Circular 03/09: Costs Awards in Appeals and Other Planning Proceedings&lt;/a&gt; in relation to statutory consultees and their advice at appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also announced clarifications to the guidance in relation to local councils and their development plan, and in relation to ensuring evidence submitted at appeal is manifestly accurate and truthful. The government is also requiring the 5 main statutory bodies to report on, and be accountable for their performance on dealing with planning applications as part of their individual Improvement Plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of responses was published on 18 December 2012. The report above summarises the key issues raised and provides a revised addendum to circular 03/09.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57427</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:14:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:14:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"/>
    <title>Building regulations: access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilet and regulation 7, and is section 1 of 4, relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 1 provides an overview of the consultation package as a whole as well as proposals on a number of areas including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replacing the currently referenced standards in part A (structure) with the new British Standards based on Eurocodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligning the existing guidance in Approved Document C (site preparation and resistance to contaminants and moisture) with the most up-to-date radon maps to ensure the safety provisions are targeted appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarifying the guidance on access statements in Approved Document M (access to and use of buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalising the guidance supporting parts M, K and N (access, protection from falling, collision and impact and glazing respectively) to remove unnecessary costs on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making minor changes to the technical guidance in Approved Document B (fire safety) to resolve practical problems in the application of requirement B2 (internal fire spread (linings))&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the intention to take forward the repeal of the fire protection provisions in the Local Acts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the non-regulatory approach proposed in relation to domestic security and changing places toilets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="draft-approved-documents"&gt;Draft Approved Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published alongside this section of the consultation is a draft version of a new Approved Document K (protection from falling, collision and impact). Not only does this reflect the proposed changes resulting from the rationalisation of parts K, M and N, it also seeks consultees’ views on the proposed new style of Approved Documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new style has also been applied to a draft revised Approved Document regulation 7 which can be found in the main consultation document as annex I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-consultation-sections"&gt;Other consultation sections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57426</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:14:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:14:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"/>
    <title>Building regulations: electrical safety</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out detailed proposals on part P, and is section 3 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise. It includes proposals to reduce the cost associated with the provisions governing electrical safety in the home whilst not undermining safety benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57425</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:13:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:13:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"/>
    <title>Building regulations: the building control system</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on the building control system, and is section 4 of 4 relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 4 includes proposals on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving local authority building control processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving private sector approved inspector arrangements, including removing the warranty link rule&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extending the competent person self-certification schemes framework and introducing specialist third-party certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing ‘appointed persons’ to act as compliance co-ordinators on construction sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57422</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:12:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:12:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"/>
    <title>Building regulations: conservation of fuel and power</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on part L of the building regulations. It is section 2 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes proposals for tighter carbon dioxide emission standards for new homes and non-domestic buildings, to take the next step towards zero carbon standards, plus tighter performance standards for works to existing buildings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper also contains proposals to introduce, on a phased basis, requirements for additional energy efficiency improvements to be carried out when other specified works (eg extensions) are planned and Green Deal finance is available as an option to meet the up-front costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57041</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-planning-authorities-on-implementing-planning-requirements-of-the-eu-waste-framework-directive-2008-98-ec"/>
    <title>Guidance for local planning authorities on implementing planning requirements of the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC) (‘the Directive’) provides an overarching legislative framework for the management of waste across Europe. This guidance note provides advice on the measures required by local planning authorities to ensure compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is aimed primarily at waste planning authorities, but it highlights the main legal and policy provisions of relevance to all planning authorities, and the action we expect them to take to assist them in ensuring compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be read alongside the government’s planning policy for waste management, currently set out in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;Planning Policy Statement 10&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-a-companion-guide-to-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;companion guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57070</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-taking-work-incentives-into-account-guidance"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: taking work incentives into account: guidance</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system. Councils will design local Council Tax reduction schemes for working-age applicants that will also support the wider objectives of welfare reform. This guidance sets out the key considerations for councils when designing their local scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
