<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/54846</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/2011-skills-for-life-survey"/>
    <title>2011 skills for life survey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2011 skills for life survey provides a national profile of adult literacy, numeracy, and Information and Communication Technology (ICT) skills, and assesses the impact that different levels of skills had on people’s lives. BIS commissioned this follow-up survey in 2010 to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine changes in literacy and numeracy levels among the adult population of England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide a baseline of ICT skills among adults in England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the demographic, social and motivational factors related to people’s skills levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/16919</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T21:29:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T21:29:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/department-for-business-innovation-and-skills-a-guide-to-the-work-of-bis-sector-teams"/>
    <title>Department for Business, Innovation and Skills - a guide to the work of BIS sector teams</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="aerospace"&gt;Aerospace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Bourne (email: &lt;a href="mailto:roger.bourne@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;roger.bourne@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 1128) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="aviation-technology"&gt;Aviation technology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIS supports the aerospace and defence sector on a wide range of technology activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS ensures the international regulations and standards that are developed to minimise the impact of civil aviation are adequate, fair, contribute to the aviation industry’s sustainability and are not in conflict with the legitimate interests of UK aerospace industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This requires policy development, co-ordination of research activities, environmental model development, project environmental assessment and environmental forecasts and scenarios. Close co-operation takes place with the Department for Transport, which takes technical advice from us. We co-operate with the International Civil Aviation Organization, European Civil Aviation Conference expert panel on the Abatement of Nuisances Caused by Air Transport (ECAC/ANCAT), United Nations Economic Commission For Europe (UNECE), and the Intergovernmental Panel On Climate Change (IPCC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="aerospace-msc-bursary-scheme"&gt;Aerospace MSc Bursary Scheme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 9 July 2012 at the Farnborough Airshow, the Prime Minister announced funding for 500 Masters-level degree places in aerospace engineering over the next three years – from 2013 to 2014 onwards. The places will be jointly funded with industry, with government committing £3 million, and will help provide industry with the next generation of skilled engineers they need. The programme will be overseen by the Royal Academy of Engineering and Royal Aeronautical Society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the bursary scheme will be available soon on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raeng.org.uk"&gt;Royal Academy of Engineering&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://aerosociety.com"&gt;Royal Aeronautical Society&lt;/a&gt; websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="aerospace-business-leaders-and-aerospace-growth-partnership-groups"&gt;Aerospace Business Leaders and Aerospace Growth Partnership Groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Aerospace Business Leaders Group is the senior engagement forum to discuss issues of strategic importance affecting the sector. The Group is chaired by the Secretary of State for BIS and also attended by the Minister for Business and Enterprise and senior BIS officials. Industry is represented by a small group of the UK’s top aerospace business leaders. Having identified key strategic issues, such as barriers to growth and key competitiveness drivers, action will be taken forward through an Aerospace Growth Partnership group, chaired by the Minister for Business and Enterprise, with wider business representation across the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/r/12-954-reach-skies-strategic-vision-uk-aerospace.pdf"&gt;Reach for the skies: a strategic vision of aerospace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="repayable-launch-investment"&gt;Repayable launch investment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repayable launch investment is a risk-sharing government investment in the design and development of civil aerospace projects in the UK. The investment is repayable at a real rate of return, usually via levies on sales of the product. Repayable launch investment is permitted for the civil aerospace under the Civil Aviation Act 1982, which charges the Secretary of State with ‘organising, carrying out and encouraging measures for the designing, development and production of civil aircraft.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last 25 years the Government has invested £1.7 billion in repayable launch investment projects and during that period £2.7 billion has been received in income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="automotive"&gt;Automotive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contacts"&gt;Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specific job of BIS Automotive Unit is to help the UK Automotive Industry succeed. It does this by encouraging the spread of best practice in design and manufacture, supporting inward investment and influencing the design of regulations and tax policy so that they reflect the best interests of the sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="relationship-management-team"&gt;Relationship Management Team&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7215 1187&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for BIS’s relationship with the major vehicle manufacturers and suppliers based in the UK. The team also leads on the relationship with the UK construction equipment industry and coordinates the Unit’s activity on trade development and investment and on issues impacting on the components sector as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="automotive-policy--regulation-team"&gt;Automotive Policy &amp;amp; Regulation Team&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7215 1188&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team takes the lead on regulatory and policy issues affecting the automotive sector. One of its many roles is to ensure that industry’s concerns are taken fully into account by Government and the European Commission, dealing with issues such as vehicle emissions, Block Exemption and End of Life Vehicles. The team is responsible for BIS’s relationship with the two main automotive trade associations, the &lt;abbr title="Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders"&gt;SMMT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the RMI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="innovation-and-skills-team"&gt;Innovation and Skills Team&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team leads on strategic issues where innovation, technology and skills are central to the sustainable development of the automotive sector as a critical part of an integrated transport system. It is responsible for taking forward BIS’s objectives under the Powering Future Vehicles strategy and manages BIS’s relationship with &lt;abbr title="Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders"&gt;SMMT&lt;/abbr&gt; Foresight Vehicle , the Low Carbon Vehicle Partnership and the &lt;abbr title="Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders"&gt;SMMT&lt;/abbr&gt; Industry Forum. The I&amp;amp;S Team plays a leading role in the Technology Strategy Board’s Innovation Platforms and Knowledge Transfer Networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="analysis-team"&gt;Analysis Team&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7215 1114&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the sector is provided by the BR Business Analysis Unit. The Unit is responsible for analysing key trends in the automotive sector and their implications for the future growth of the industry in the UK. It works closely with trade associations and academic and other analysts as well as drawing on the assessments of UK firms themselves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="automotive-council-uk"&gt;Automotive Council UK&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.automotivecouncil.co.uk/"&gt;Automotive Council UK&lt;/a&gt; is chaired jointly by the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) and Industry Chair, Richard Parry-Jones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information on the work of the Automotive Council or its sub-groups please contact Automotive Council Secretary &lt;a href="mailto:bob.lonnon@bis.gsi.gov.uk?subject=automotive%20council"&gt;Bob Lonnon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/g/11-1478-growing-automotive-supply-chain.pdf"&gt;Growing the Automotive Supply Chain: The Road Forward&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/g/12-1010-growing-uk-automotive-supply-chain-2012-update.pdf"&gt;Growing the Automotive Supply Chain: 2012 update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chemicals"&gt;Chemicals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contacts-1"&gt;Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Turner (Email: &lt;a href="mailto:mark.turner@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;mark.turner@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 6465)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit is arranged in teams based on the key primary products and themes within the chemicals industry. Additionally, it should be noted that another Department (eg Defra) may have the overall policy lead even where there is a BIS interest noted below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodity, Consumer, Speciality and Fine Chemicals - including dyestuffs, pigments, crop protection, pharmaceutical ingredients; BIS discussions relating to the implementation of the EU Chemicals strategy (REACH)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemicals Sector Regulatory Forum; Plastics and Rubber Sector; BIS discussions relating to the implementation of the EU Biocides Directive &amp;amp; draft Regulation; Security of hazardous chemicals and misuse of chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemicals Regional, Cluster Strategy, Chemicals Innovation - including R&amp;amp;D, Technology Transfer, Materials Innovation, Speciality Chemicals Innovation, Chemistry Innovation Knowledge Transfer Network, Regional Chemical Initiatives .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemicals-industry-regulatory-forum"&gt;Chemicals Industry Regulatory Forum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This joint government/industry body is a response to the better regulation agenda.If you would like to know more, please contact group secretary &lt;a href="mailto:alastair.east@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Alastair East&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/c/chemicals-regulatory-forum-april-2012.pdf" title="Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 20 April 2012"&gt;Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 20 April 2012&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/c/chemicals-regulatory-forum-october-2011.pdf" title="Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 21 October 2011"&gt;Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 21 October 2011&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/c/chemicals-regulatory-forum-january-2012.pdf" title="Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 27 January 2012"&gt;Note of the Chemicals Regulatory Forum meeting - 27 January 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="construction"&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="construction-act-review"&gt;Construction Act Review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out measures as consequential changes necessary to the Scheme following the changes introduced at part 8 of the Local Democracy Economic Development and Construction Act 2009 (the 2009 Act) to amend the 1996 Act. The deadline for responses to this consultation was Friday 18 June 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the consultation and analysis of responses are below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/construction-contracts-regulations-1998-amendments?cat=open" title="Consultation on amendments to the Scheme for Construction Contracts (England and Wales) Regulations 1998"&gt;Consultation on amendments to the Scheme for Construction Contracts (England and Wales) Regulations 1998&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/s/11-1013-scheme-for-construction-contracts-consultation-responses.pdf" title="Analysis of responses to the consultation"&gt;Analysis of responses to the consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="constructionline"&gt;Constructionline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owned by BIS, Constructionline is a contributor to the Rethinking Construction initiative. It is the UK’s register of pre-qualified construction contractors and consultants. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.constructionline.co.uk/static/"&gt;Constructionline&lt;/a&gt; is designed to streamline pre-qualification procedures, to save valuable resources in the construction industry, rendering it more efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="green-construction-board"&gt;Green Construction Board&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grasping the opportunities for growth presented by a sustainable construction, infrastructure and property sector is the main priority for the Green Construction Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Board, co-chaired by Minister of State for Business, Rt Hon Michael Fallon MP and President and CEO of Skanska UK, Mike Putnam, is focused on taking a unified approach to the problems facing the industry, providing strategic leadership on key issues and identifying steps to promote the UK’s excellence in green construction. The Board will also work to promote the message that a ‘green’ construction sector can lead to business opportunities and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="purpose"&gt;Purpose&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as monitoring the delivery of this Action Plan, the Board is also updating and refreshing actions going forward and takes collective responsibility for leading the change to a low carbon economy. The Green Construction Board will look more widely at green property and construction issues, encompassing priority activities of the Strategy for Sustainable Construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_26101"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15370/strategy-for-sustainable-construction.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-26101-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15370/thumbnail_strategy-for-sustainable-construction.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15370/strategy-for-sustainable-construction.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-26101-accessibility-help"&gt;Strategy for sustainable construction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;1.89 MB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;64 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-26101-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Strategy%20for%20sustainable%20construction%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Strategy%20for%20sustainable%20construction%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Strategy for sustainable construction").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_26102"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15371/strategy-for-sustainable-construction-progress.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-26102-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15371/thumbnail_strategy-for-sustainable-construction-progress.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15371/strategy-for-sustainable-construction-progress.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-26102-accessibility-help"&gt;Strategy for sustainable construction - progress report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;3.14 MB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;71 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-26102-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Strategy%20for%20sustainable%20construction%20-%20progress%20report%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Strategy%20for%20sustainable%20construction%20-%20progress%20report%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Strategy for sustainable construction - progress report").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h4 id="membership"&gt;Membership&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The membership of the Green Construction Board represents both Government and senior representatives from industry and is jointly chaired by the Minister of State, Rt Hon Michael Fallon MP, who will act as the Government co-Chair together with Mike Putnam, President and CEO Skanska UK. DECC, Defra, DCLG, Cabinet Office and BIS are among the key Departments represented on the Group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Fallon, BIS &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mike Putnam, Skanska UK &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bill Bolsover CBE, Aggregate Industries &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunand Prasad, Penoyre &amp;amp; Prasad LLP &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robert Care, Arup Group &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark Oliver, H+H UK Limited &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark Clare, Barratt Developments  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lynne Sullivan, sustainableBYdesign LLP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Andrew Gould, Jones Lang LaSalle  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Wates, Wates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chris Hopkins,Ploughcroft Building Services  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Thornton, DEFRA  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bill Hughes, Legal &amp;amp; General Property &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geoffrey Spence, HMT – IUK &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Maskell, Philips Electronics UK  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;William Jordan , Cabinet Office - ERG &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chris Newsome, Anglian Water &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phil Wynn Owen, DECC &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Morrell, BIS &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Schofield, DCLG &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Sachdev, Sainsburys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="green-construction-board-working-groups"&gt;Green Construction Board Working Groups&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Green Construction Board has established 7 Working Groups to ensure the delivery of a comprehensive programme of activity. A “Sponsor” and a Chair have been appointed to lead each of these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Group No.&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Workstream&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sponsor&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Chair&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Routemap&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paul Morrell, Chief Construction Adviser&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paul Morrell, Chief Construction Adviser&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Buildings&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sunand Prasad, Partner, Penoyre &amp;amp; Prasad; Phil Wynn-Owen, Director General – Climate Change, DECC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paul King, CEO, UKGBC&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chris Newsome, Director of Asset Management, Anglian Water&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chris Newsome, Director of Asset Management, Anglian Water&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Knowledge &amp;amp; Skills&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lynne Sullivan, Partner, Sustainable by Design&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;George Martin, Professor &amp;amp; Business Affairs Director, Low Impact Building Centre (LIBC), Coventry University (until the end of the year)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Greening the Industry (to include Measurement)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bill Bolsover, Chairman, Aggregate Industries&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Robert Pearce, Head of Architecture &amp;amp; Specifications, M&amp;amp;S&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Valuation and Demand&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bill Hughes, Managing Director, L&amp;amp;G Property; Andrew Gould, Managing Director – England, Jones Lang LaSalle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Louise Ellison, Head of Sustainability, Quintain&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Promotion&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;James Wates, Deputy Chairman, Wates Group&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Colin Courtney, Director, Green Support, Skanska AB&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information, please contact: &lt;a href="mailto:green.board@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;green.board@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="low-carbon-construction"&gt;Low carbon construction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An innovation and growth team was establised in 2009 to review the construction industry to ensure it was ‘fit for purpose’ for delivering a low carbon future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review looked at the strengths of and opportunities for the UK construction industry in a low carbon economy and considered how the UK can be a world leader in this sector. This review was led by Paul Morrell, the Chief Construction Adviser, and was undertaken by a mix of industry experts and those with wider business experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/l/10-1266es-low-carbon-construction-igt-executive-summary" title="Executive summary"&gt;Low carbon construction innovation &amp;amp; growth team: executive summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/l/10-1266es-low-carbon-construction-igt-executive-summary" title="Final report"&gt;Low carbon construction innovation &amp;amp; growth team: final report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/BISCore/business-sectors/docs/l/11-976-low-carbon-construction-action-plan.pdf" title="Government response to the Low Carbon Construction Innovation &amp;amp; Growth Team report"&gt;Low carbon construction action plan: Government response to the Low Carbon Construction Innovation &amp;amp; Growth Team report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the Construction Innovation and Growth Team contact: &lt;a href="mailto:constructionigt@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;constructionigt@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="construction-statistics"&gt;Construction statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIS Construction Market Intelligence (CMI) has responsibility for the collection, analysis and publication of statistics on the construction sector. We provide regular statistical analyses of building materials and overseas trade, price and cost indices and key performance indicators for the construction industry. As well as statistical advice, we work closely with economists in BIS to assist in the assessment of the construction market and in the formulation of efficient policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills/series/building-materials-and-components-monthly-statistics-2012" title="Building materials and components: monthly statistics"&gt;Building materials and components: monthly statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills/series/construction-statistics" title="Construction statistics"&gt;Construction statistics&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cyber-security"&gt;Cyber security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/search/apachesolr_search/cyber%20security" title="Cyber security"&gt;cyber security policy&lt;/a&gt; is led by Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="electronics"&gt;Electronics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-1"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Begbie (Email: &lt;a href="mailto:mark.begbie:bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;mark.begbie:bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 1813)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="energy-intensive-industries"&gt;Energy-intensive industries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/energy-intensive-industries-compensation-for-carbon-leakage"&gt;Energy-intensive industries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="engineering"&gt;Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-2"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ivan Youd (Email: &lt;a href="mailto:ivan.youd@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;ivan.youd@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 8161) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="manufacturing-and-materials-including-composites"&gt;Manufacturing and materials (including composites)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contacts-2"&gt;Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manufacturing: Caroline Jackson (Email &lt;a href="mailto:caroline.jackson@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;caroline.jackson@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 0226&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Composites: Dominic James (Email: &lt;a href="mailto:dominic.james@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;dominic.james@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;, telephone: 020 7215 8432)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="advanced-manufacturing"&gt;Advanced manufacturing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2010 BIS launched its ‘Growth Review Framework for Advanced Manufacturing’. The Framework document was an invitation to provide comments and evidence to help identify the challenges and barriers to manufacturing growth, to feed into the Growth Review process. The document set out the Government’s ambitions for manufacturing, developed through consultation with industry. It was supported by in-depth economic analysis and a statistical annex in order to provide a substantial evidence base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/g/10-1297-growth-review-framework-for-advanced-manufacturing.pdf"&gt;Growth Review Framework for Advanced Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/m/10-1333-manufacturing-in-the-uk-an-economic-analysis-of-the-sector.pdf"&gt;Manufacturing in the UK: an economic analysis of the sector&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/m/10-1334-manufacturing-in-the-uk-supplementary-analysis.pdf"&gt;Manufacturing in the UK: supplementary analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="marine"&gt;Marine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-3"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Joyce &lt;a href="mailto:peter.joyce@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;email: peter.joyce@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; telephone: 020 7215 1165)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="marine-sector-strategy"&gt;Marine sector strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-marine-industries-a-strategy-for-growth" title="A strategy for growth for the UK Marine Industries"&gt;A strategy for growth for the UK Marine Industries&lt;/a&gt; draws on the thinking of business, government and universities. It is the first integrated UK strategy for the marine industries and establishes a foundation for ambitious but sustainable long-term growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="office-for-life-sciences"&gt;Office for Life Sciences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-life-sciences-strategy" title="Office for Life Sciences"&gt;Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt; policy here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="postal-services"&gt;Postal Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services" title="Postal Services"&gt;Postal Services&lt;/a&gt; policy is here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="retail"&gt;Retail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-4"&gt;Contact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Unit 
Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills 
1 Victoria Street 
London SW1H 0ET 
Email: retail@bis.gsi.gov.uk 
BIS Public Enquiries: 020 7215 5000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bis-retail-strategy"&gt;BIS Retail Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIS has developed a range of sector specific objectives which will be taken forward over the course of 2012 to 2013. These objectives have been developed to facilitate growth of the sector at a local, national, European and international level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/b/12-1197-bis-retail-strategy.pdf"&gt;BIS Retail Strategy&lt;/a&gt;  was developed with input from the British Retail Consortium, the Association of Convenience Stores and Gloucestershire First (the first Local Enterprise Partnership Retail Pathfinder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="retail-policy-forum"&gt;Retail Policy Forum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Retail Policy Forum (RPF - chaired by BIS’s Retail Unit) enables a representative cross-section of retailers, and their representative bodies, to talk to Government Departments and EU officials about regulations and other key policies affecting the sector at an early stage in the process. It aims to help both retailers and policy makers by minimising the burdens on retail, looking for alternatives to regulations (where appropriate) and making any regulations and enforcement as practical and sensible as possible. The RPF meets three times a year. When necessary, additional meetings are held to take an in-depth look at particular subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Retail Unit also manages a Virtual RPF of UK retailers, trade associations and others with a professional interest in retailing. Communications are mainly by email and members can join the RPF’s working groups. To apply for membership of the Virtual RPF please email the Retail Unit explaining your interest in the sector and supplying contact details, including job title, telephone number and postal address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="healthy-high-street"&gt;Healthy High Street?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/h/10-1224-healthy-high-street.pdf"&gt;Healthy High Street? A healthcheck for high streets and town centres&lt;/a&gt;  was published in November 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide is a simple to use health check to alert retailers and others to early signs of potential decline in their High Street – and to do so in good time for them to take preventative action. It then offers some useful first steps, including advice on working together with others to rejuvenate the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-portas-review"&gt;The Portas review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May 2011 the Prime Minister announced that he had asked Mary Portas, leading retail marketing consultant, to undertake a review of the English high street. The report was published in December 2011: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/p/11-1434-portas-review-future-of-high-streets.pdf"&gt;The Portas review: an independent review into the future of our high streets&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2120019.pdf"&gt;government’s formal response to the recommendations made by Mary Portas&lt;/a&gt; in her report was published by the Department for Communities and Local Government in March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="understanding-high-street-performance"&gt;Understanding high street performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIS has also published a report &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/u/11-1402-understanding-high-street-performance.pdf"&gt;Understanding high street performance&lt;/a&gt;, which explores the many factors impacting on the economic and social performance of town centres and High Streets. This study is intended to help inform government and local authority decision-making regarding town centres, high streets and local economic growth. It has also provided input to the Mary Portas review.  The executive summary is available separately: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/u/11-1433-understanding-high-street-performance-summary.pdf"&gt;Understanding high street performance: executive summary&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="services-professional-and-business"&gt;Services (professional and business)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_27100"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15695/uk-global-hub-professional-business-services.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27100-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15695/thumbnail_uk-global-hub-professional-business-services.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15695/uk-global-hub-professional-business-services.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27100-accessibility-help"&gt;The UK as a global hub of professional and  business services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;1.19 MB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;24 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-27100-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20The%20UK%20as%20a%20global%20hub%20of%20professional%20and%20%20business%20services%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27The%20UK%20as%20a%20global%20hub%20of%20professional%20and%20%20business%20services%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("The UK as a global hub of professional and  business services").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_27101"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15696/professional-business-services-2020-vision-for-growth.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27101-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15696/thumbnail_professional-business-services-2020-vision-for-growth.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15696/professional-business-services-2020-vision-for-growth.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-27101-accessibility-help"&gt;Professional and  Business Services: A 2020 Vision for Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;954 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;36 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-27101-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Professional%20and%20%20Business%20Services%3A%20A%202020%20Vision%20for%20Growth%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Professional%20and%20%20Business%20Services%3A%20A%202020%20Vision%20for%20Growth%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Professional and  Business Services: A 2020 Vision for Growth").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="contacts-for-other-sectors"&gt;Contacts for other sectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sector&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BIS contact&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Telephone&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Call Centres&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbc&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbc&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ceramics manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clothing &amp;amp; Textiles (including technical textiles) manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbc&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbc&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Footwear manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victoria Griffiths&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 6212&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Furniture&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victoria Griffiths&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 6212&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Giftware manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Glass packaging manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victoria Griffiths&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 6212&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Industrial Minerals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jewellery manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leather goods manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victoria Griffiths&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 6212&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paper, Pulp and Paper Products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ray Ward&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1560&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Print&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ray Ward&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1560&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sports equipment manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tobacco-based product manufacture&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phil Bennett&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;020 7215 1456&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="trade-association-forum"&gt;Trade Association Forum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIS works with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.taforum.org/"&gt;Trade Association Forum&lt;/a&gt; to develop and communicate best practice among trade associations. The Forum carries out benchmarking studies and other research projects. It disseminates the results of these, and broader best practice, through its seminars, workshops and other events, and via its website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information is available from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Stuart Bean
&lt;br&gt;Trade Association Forum
&lt;br&gt;Centre Point
&lt;br&gt;103 New Oxford Street 
&lt;br&gt;London WC1A 1DU
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7395 8283
Email: &lt;a href="mailto:stuart.bean@taforum.org.uk"&gt;stuart.bean@taforum.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bis-contacts"&gt;BIS Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information about BIS’s work with the Trade Association Forum, or about trade associations more generally, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Anthony Murphy 
&lt;br&gt;Director of Strategy, Services and Olympics 
&lt;br&gt;Business Relations 
&lt;br&gt;Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform 
&lt;br&gt;1 Victoria Street 
&lt;br&gt;London SW1H 0ET
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 020 7215 3752
Email: &lt;a href="Anthony.Murphy@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Anthony.Murphy@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/47081</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:54:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:54:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/processes-for-tackling-anti-competitive-activity"/>
    <title>Processes for tackling anti-competitive activity</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets provide the best means of ensuring that the economy’s resources are put to their best use by encouraging enterprise and efficiency, widening choice and contributing to our international competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, timely and effective enforcement is essential to identify any anti-competitive practices or structures that may develop and lead to a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/business_leaflets/general/oft911.pdf"&gt;loss of competition in markets&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/speeches/spe0304.pdf"&gt;abuse of market power&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-competition-authorities"&gt;Current competition authorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills sets the overall policy framework for competition, it is regulated by the UK’s independent competition authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 main competition bodies are responsible for investigating and enforcing decisions on competition matters in the UK market:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/"&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) is the principal competition authority whose responsibility is to enforce competition and make markets work well for the benefit of consumers. The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; derives most of its powers from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2002/40/contents"&gt;Enterprise Act 2002&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1998/41/contents"&gt;Competition Act 1998&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; investigates mergers and anti-competitive practices in markets and also enforces consumer law – see “&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/shared_oft/business_leaflets/competition_law/oft442.pdf"&gt;Modernisation – Understanding Competition Law&lt;/a&gt;”. Large mergers with a European dimension may be covered by the European Community Merger Regulation (ECMR). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Commission&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;) conducts in-depth inquiries into mergers, markets and the regulation of certain industries such as utilities and communications. However, the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; only undertakes its inquiries where they have been referred to it by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;, one of the sectoral regulators [Link to section below] or in exceptional circumstances the Secretary of State.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.catribunal.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Appeal Tribunal&lt;/a&gt; (CAT) is a specialist judicial body whose function is to hear and rule on appeals of decisions made by the competition authorities. The CAT has a cross-disciplinary expertise in law, economics, business, competition and economic regulatory issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/index_en.html"&gt;European Commission&lt;/a&gt; (Directorate General for Competition) has exclusive powers to act on certain large mergers with a European dimension. It also has powers to investigate anti-competitive practices when trade between members of the European Community, or in some cases the European Economic Area (EEA), is affected. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="sectoral-regulators"&gt;Sectoral regulators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of Sectoral Regulators have a specific role in promoting or facilitating competition within their sectors. Some also have the power to apply the Competition Act 1998 concurrently with the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The regulators with such ‘concurrent powers’ are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofgem.gov.uk/Pages/OfgemHome.aspx"&gt;Ofgem&lt;/a&gt; - in the energy markets &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/"&gt;Ofwat&lt;/a&gt; - in the water industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/"&gt;Ofcom&lt;/a&gt; - in the communications sector &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk/"&gt;ORR&lt;/a&gt; - for railway services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.caa.co.uk/"&gt;CAA&lt;/a&gt; - in relation to air traffic services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.niaur.gov.uk/"&gt;Utility Regulator&lt;/a&gt; - for gas and electricity in Northern Ireland &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.monitor-nhsft.gov.uk/monitors-new-role"&gt;Monitor&lt;/a&gt; - for NHS Foundation Trusts. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="oft-market-studies-and-cc-market-investigations"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; market studies and &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; market investigations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Office of Fair Trading (&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;) market studies are detailed investigations of markets that are not operating well for consumers but where neither consumer regulation enforcement by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; nor competition enforcement through a referral to the Competition Commission (&lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;) is likely to resolve the issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where those studies make recommendations to government. the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) co-ordinates government responses and ensures that they take account not only of competition and consumer interests but wider public policy objectives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Market studies will usually be performed under section 5 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/Acts/acts2002/ukpga_20020040_en_1"&gt;Enterprise Act 2002&lt;/a&gt; in order to identify whether perceived problems should be addressed through the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s other functions. There is a range of possible outcomes of a study including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving the market a clean bill of health (ie a decision that intervention is not appropriate on the evidence available) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publishing information to help consumers &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging firms to take voluntary action &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging a consumer code of practice &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making recommendations to the Government or regulators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investigation or enforcement action against companies or individuals suspected of breaching consumer law or competition law &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a market investigation reference to the Competition Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; conducts in-depth inquiries into markets – market investigations – undertaken in response to a reference made by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; or sectoral regulator and, in certain limited circumstances, by the Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills.
The market studies and market investigations where BIS has played an active role are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;medicines distribution &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pharmaceutical price regulation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sale and rent back &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment Protection Insurance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supply of airport services in the UK by BAA &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rolling stock leasing (ROSCOs) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;property searches &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commercial use of public information (CUPI) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supply of groceries in the UK &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To find information on these and other market studies, go to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://collections.europarchive.org/tna/20090703093314/http:/www.berr.gov.uk/whatwedo/businesslaw/competition/market-studies/page17610.html"&gt;National Archives market studies pages&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mergers"&gt;Mergers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper framework for control of mergers is important to ensure that competition is not damaged when businesses come together. UK mergers are considered by the competition authorities under the Enterprise Act 2002. Public interest considerations are specified in the Act as being national security, media plurality and stability of the UK financial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, mergers will be considered by the UK competition authorities if the annual UK turnover of the enterprise being taken over exceeds £70 million, or the merger creates a 25% share or more in a market for goods or services in the UK or a substantial part of it. There is no statutory requirement to pre-notify mergers to the UK competition authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investigation-by-the-oft"&gt;Investigation by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; investigates mergers in the first instance and, with the exception of public interest cases, decides whether or not they should be referred to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; for further investigation. The test is whether the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; believes a merger has resulted or may be expected to result in a substantial lessening of competition.
In making decisions, the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; will either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;refer to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; for further investigation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear the merger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear it subject to undertakings in lieu of a reference to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details of mergers investigated by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investigation-by-the-cc"&gt;Investigation by the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a merger is referred to the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt;, it has to determine whether it has resulted in a substantial lessening of competition and to take the action it considers reasonable and practicable to address any adverse effects arising from the merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; reports are published. Details of mergers investigated by the &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/"&gt;Competition Commission&lt;/a&gt; website. Companies can also obtain &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/mergers/"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; and informal advice from the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; on its merger procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="mergers-between-water-and-sewerage-companies"&gt;Mergers between water and sewerage companies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special regime exists for mergers between water and sewerage companies. These are considered under sections 32-35 of the Water Industry Act 1991, as amended by the Enterprise Act and the Water Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-community-merger-regulation"&gt;European Community Merger Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large mergers with a European dimension that breach certain jurisdictional thresholds of the European Community Merger Regulation (ECMR) – Council Regulation No. 139/2004 – fall to the European Commission for investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking mergers involving enterprises with an aggregate worldwide turnover of more than Euro 5bn (around £4bn) and where the aggregate Community-wide turnover of each of at least two of the enterprises concerned is more than Euro 250m (around £200m) will be investigated by the European Commission taking into account the views of Member States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, those mergers where more than two-thirds of the Community-wide turnover of each enterprise concerned falls within one and the same Member State, are not caught by the EC Merger Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; will normally advise the EC on competition issues it sees relevant to cases being considered under the EC Merger Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on individual cases under the ECMR can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/index_en.html"&gt;Commission’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public interest cases under the EC Merger Regulation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State may also intervene on public interest grounds in mergers being considered under the EC Merger Regulation, where the public interest consideration in question is also recognised in the EC Merger Regulation. In such cases the European Commission will continue to consider the competition issues whilst the UK authorities consider public interest aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-processes-and-competition-authorities-from-april-2014"&gt;New processes and competition authorities from April 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s 2011 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/competition-regime-for-growth"&gt;consultation on competition reform&lt;/a&gt; confirmed that many aspects of the UK’s competition regime are world class but it also highlighted some significant challenges for the current system and made a number of proposals to enhance the regime’s performance. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012, set out the reforms that will come into effect from April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms – currently being considered by Parliament in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill – will bring together the best of the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Competition Commission"&gt;CC&lt;/abbr&gt; into a single Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to become a world-leading competition authority, advocating competition both at home and abroad. It will have a greater role in ensuring competition in regulated sectors is being addressed, through enhanced cooperation and information sharing between itself and the sector regulators. It will make better use of public resources, and business will benefit from having a single agency to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-markets-and-mergers-regimes"&gt;The Markets and Mergers regimes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the CMA is set up, we shall maintain the separation of decision making between the two-phases of market and merger investigations [see page 94 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;]. Currently the two phases of an investigation are carried out by separate organisations: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phase 1, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/OFTwork/;jsessionid=8200B8DBE569E41858F3F97E2DFC0CAF"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which can undertake an initial study into a merger or market to see if there is a competition issue to be addressed. If so, it can refer the case to:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/our-work"&gt;Competition Commission&lt;/a&gt;, Phase 2, which will carry out a deeper study to get to the nub of the problem and impose remedies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The separation of Phase 1 and Phase 2 decision-making on regulatory appeals will also be maintained and provided for in legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMA will have powers, additionally, to conduct investigations into practices that impact on more than one market [see page 30 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;], such as extended warranties and other secondary point of sale practices, without the need to make multiple market investigation references. These powers will enable the CMA to take a more targeted approach to tackling recurring sources of consumer complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMA will have discretion to stop a proposed merger [see page 42 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] where there are concerns the merger may be anti-competitive, and to consider with the companies involved whether the merger should be allowed to proceed. Legislation will clarify that the Authority can reverse mergers that have already taken place where this is deemed appropriate after investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government also proposes to improve remedies by enabling the CMA to require parties to appoint an independent third party [see page 48 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] to monitor, arbitrate, and/or implement remedies; and by giving the CMA the power to require parties to publish certain non-price information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="streamlining-and-strengthening-the-competition-tools"&gt;Streamlining and strengthening the competition tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minor change will give the Secretary of State the power to request the CMA to investigate public interest issues [see page 30of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;] alongside competition issues in a market investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to ensure greater certainty and to reduce the burden to business, the Government proposes introducing or reducing statutory time limits at all stages of market investigations. This will be supported by information gathering powers at all stages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory time limits will also be introduced at all stages of the mergers process [see page 44of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="anti-trust-and-cartels"&gt;Anti-trust and cartels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system for enforcing the legal prohibitions in anti-trust (abuse of market dominance and other anti-competitive agreements) and cartel cases (eg agreement between companies to fix prices) contained in the Competition Act 1998 (‘antitrust’) is being strengthened. Proposals include statutory change to bolster separation between investigation and decision making and new powers for the CMA to improve the efficiency of investigations and transparency of the decision making process [see page 54of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/g/12-512-growth-and-competition-regime-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government’s response (PDF, 591 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is work currently carried out by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Appeals against decisions by the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; (and the CMA once the reforms have been fully introduced) can be made to the Competition Appeal Tribunal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sectoral-regulation-and-concurrency"&gt;Sectoral Regulation and ‘concurrency’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sectoral regulators already have the power to refer cases to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; but rarely use them. We want to encourage the CMA to be a more proactive central resource for these regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectoral regulators have ‘concurrent competition powers’, ie: they have a choice between using their own sectoral powers and making use of the 1998 Competition Act to refer issues to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt;. We want to strengthen the primacy of the Competition Act by requiring sectoral regulators with concurrent powers to consider that route first; and also to give the CMA the power to take Competition Act cases from the sectoral regulators where it is better placed to proceed with the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="competition-complaints"&gt;Competition complaints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe a company or group of companies are acting anti-competitively, then you may wish to consider making a complaint to the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; via its special hotline and email address for complaints under the Competition Act:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition Act Enquiry Line: 08457 22 44 99
Email enquiries: &lt;a href="mailto:enquiries.competitionact@oft.gov.uk"&gt;enquiries.competitionact@oft.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a detailed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/advice_and_resources/resource_base/legal/competition-act-1998/complaints"&gt;how to complain section&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;abbr title="Office of Fair Trading"&gt;OFT&lt;/abbr&gt; website. This gives examples of behaviour which may indicate that a company is breaching the Competition Act. It also gives information on what to do in order to complain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17101</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:35:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:35:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/energy-intensive-industries-compensation-for-carbon-leakage"/>
    <title>Energy-intensive industries: compensation for carbon leakage </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview-of-the-compensation-scheme-for-energy-intensive-industries"&gt;Overview of the compensation scheme for energy-intensive industries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policies aimed at reducing carbon emissions are going to impact upon the bills faced by industrial consumers. This will have the greatest effect on those industries that use the most electricity, leading to a risk that investment in the UK is lost – carbon leakage. The government intends to compensate those businesses most at risk of carbon leakage, to help offset these increased costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his Autumn Statement on the 29 November 2011 the Chancellor announced that the government intends to implement measures to reduce the impact of policy on the costs of electricity for the most electricity-intensive industries, beginning in 2013 and worth around £250 million over the Spending Review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this the government has committed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compensate key electricity-intensive businesses to help offset the indirect cost of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/consult_carbon_price_support.htm"&gt;Carbon Price Floor&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/clima/policies/ets/index_en.htm"&gt;EU Emissions Trading System&lt;/a&gt;, subject to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/europe/state-aid"&gt;state aid guidelines&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase the level of relief from the climate change levy on electricity for Climate Change Agreement participants from 65 to 90%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To support this, in March 2012 BIS and the Department for Energy and Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="Department for Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt;) launched Compensation for the indirect costs of the Carbon Price Floor and EU Emissions Trading Scheme (ETS) - call for evidence. This asked companies and trade bodies to engage actively and share information and data on their electricity-intensity, in order to help government target compensation effectively. It closed on 4 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, and separate to the call for evidence, the government has also committed to explore options for reducing the impact of electricity costs on electricity-intensive industries as a result of electricity market reform policies where this has a significant impact on their competitiveness, and subject to value for money and state aid considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2012 BIS and &lt;abbr title="Department for Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt; launched a consultation on a proposal setting out the eligibility and design of the scheme to compensate energy intensive industries for the indirect costs of EU ETS and the Carbon Price Floor. See the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/energy-intensive-industries-compensation-scheme"&gt;Energy intensive industry compensation consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact"&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a question about the package, or the call for evidence, or would like to register your interest please contact us: &lt;a href="mailto:energyintensiveindustries@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;energyintensiveindustries@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="questions-and-answers"&gt;Questions and answers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-long-is-the-process-of-designing-the-compensation-scheme-going-to-take-before-a-firm-announcement-can-be-made"&gt;How long is the process of designing the compensation scheme going to take before a firm announcement can be made?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect to make an announcement in March 2013, although compensation may be made later than this. This is because any compensation to companies is subject to state aid considerations which can take up to two years. The government is engaging with the Commission early and regularly, aiming to shorten the state aid timescale as much as is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="when-will-this-package-be-delivered"&gt;When will this package be delivered?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s intention is that this package will start to be implemented in 2013, subject to state aid clearance. Eligibility for Indirect Compensation for indirect EU Emissions Trading System costs will be based on EU guidance, which was issued in May 2012. Compensation for indirect Carbon Price Floor costs is also state aid, and is therefore subject to Commission approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reduced rate of the climate change levy, for those sectors who have signed Climate Change Agreements, from 35 to 10 per cent on electricity. This will only take effect from 1 April 2013, subject to legislation in the Finance Bill 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="does-the-package-remove-the-incentive-for-these-companies-to-become-more-energy-efficient-in-the-future"&gt;Does the package remove the incentive for these companies to become more energy efficient in the future?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy will continue to be a major cost for energy intensive companies, incentivising them to become more efficient. These industries will continue to have a vital role to play in the UK economy. They need to adapt to lower carbon means of production where possible, but it is equally important that they remain competitive and that the UK remains an attractive location for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-effects-does-this-package-have-on-carbon-emissions"&gt;What effects does this package have on carbon emissions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon emissions from electricity (power generation) are constrained by the EU ETS cap. This package will compensate for the increase in the indirect costs associated with the carbon price floor and the EU ETS, but will not affect the environmental integrity of the cap. Sectors who will receive an increased CCL rebate will be bound by the targets of their CCA agreements which encourage energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-about-electricity-market-reform-emr"&gt;What about Electricity Market Reform (&lt;abbr title="Electricity Market Reform"&gt;EMR&lt;/abbr&gt;)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also committed to explore options for reducing the impact of electricity costs on electricity-intensive industries as a result of electricity market reform policies, where this has a significant impact on their competitiveness. This is also subject to value for money and state aid consideration. For more information on &lt;abbr title="Electricity Market Reform"&gt;EMR&lt;/abbr&gt;, visit the &lt;abbr title="Electricity Market Reform"&gt;EMR&lt;/abbr&gt; page on the &lt;abbr title="Department for Energy and Climate Change"&gt;DECC&lt;/abbr&gt; web site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="documentation"&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of documents and reports that enable a greater understanding of the role of energy intensive industries as we transition to a green economy and the impact that energy and climate change policy has on them. This page will be regularly updated with documentation relevant to energy intensive industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fiscal measures in support of energy intensive industries were announced at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/autumn_statement.pdf"&gt;Autumn Statement, November 2011&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/v/vince-cable-chris-huhne-7-dec-2011.pdf"&gt;Joint Vince Cable/Chris Huhne Letter Outlining the Measures in the Energy Intensive Industry Package – December 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An international comparison of energy and climate change policies impacting energy intensive industries in selected countries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/meeting_energy/aes/impacts/impacts.aspx"&gt;Estimated impacts of energy and climate change policies on energy prices and bills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="energy-intensive-industry-sub-group-of-the-green-economy-council"&gt;Energy Intensive Industry Sub-Group of the Green Economy Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Energy Intensive Industries Group was created by the Green Economy Council. Its original purpose was to bring together evidence on how Energy Intensive Industries are affected by energy and climate change policies and was tasked with coming forward with ideas for policy proposals. This led to the development of the Energy Intensive Industries package announced by the Chancellor in his 2011 autumn statement. Going forward the role of the group remains to support the work of the Council by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advising on issues for energy intensive industries around green and climate change policies, including, issues around competitiveness, business opportunities and challenges, so that the Government’s strategic approach properly reflects short, medium and long term needs of businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussing and, where appropriate, identifying action for energy intensive industries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acting as a mechanism for energy intensive industries to bring forward issues relating to the green economy which affect business, including views on what further Government policies are needed to ensure the development of the green economy and to facilitate green growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting the development of the Energy Intensive Industries Package by informing the proposal for carbon price and EU Emissions Trading Scheme compensation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reporting at regular intervals to the Green Economy Council on the work of the group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="membership"&gt;Membership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Group has a membership drawn from Government and the Council. Current industry members of the sub-group are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Green Economy Council – EII sub Group&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Organisation&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Stephen Mayne&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CBI&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philip Pearson&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TUC&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rob Sneddon&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Community Union&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jeremy Nicholson&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Energy Intensive Users Group&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gareth Stace&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EEF&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Diana Montgomery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Construction Products Association&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nick Sturgeon&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chemicals Industry Association&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tim Morris&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tata Steel&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Steven Schofield&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Shell&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Martin Casey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cemex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;John Sandford&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wienerberger&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tony Smith&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pilkington UK&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Andrew Mackenzie&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ineos&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-of-the-meetings"&gt;Notes of the meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="september-2012"&gt;11 September 2012&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members discussed the upcoming consultation on compensation for the indirect costs of EU ETS and the carbon price floor. Members heard that the state aid pre-notification for the compensation measures would be sent to the Commission by the end of September. There was an update on work on an exemption from the costs of &lt;abbr title="Electricity Market Reform"&gt;EMR&lt;/abbr&gt; feed-in-tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members discussed the possible implications of the proposal to simplify or scrap the Carbon Reduction Commitment (&lt;abbr title="Carbon Reduction Commitment"&gt;CRC&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an update on the progress of the upcoming energy efficiency strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="july-2012"&gt;3 July 2012&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members agreed the terms of reference and membership of the Energy Intensive Industry Sub-group of the Green Economy Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an update on the Green Investment Bank and members heard an update on the proposals for compensation for the indirect costs of the carbon price floor and EU ETS. Government will consult on the EII package in late summer. Members also heard an update on the process of providing and exemption from &lt;abbr title="Electricity Market Reform"&gt;EMR&lt;/abbr&gt; FITS for EIIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS outlined the timeframe for publishing the ‘An international comparison of energy and climate change policies impacting energy intensive industries in selected countries’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members discussed the ongoing Climate Change Agreement target negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TUC and EIUG presented their report on the value of EIIs to the UK supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="energy-intensive-industry-package--october-2012-consultation-update-consultation"&gt;Energy intensive industry package – October 2012 consultation update: consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have developed a proposal setting out the eligibility and design of the scheme to compensate energy intensive industries for the indirect costs of EU ETS and the Carbon Price Floor. We are now consulting on these proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document and response forms are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/energy-intensive-industries-compensation-scheme"&gt;Energy intensive industries compensation scheme consultation page&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will close on 21 December 2012, to allow ample time for interested parties to comment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please email &lt;a href="energyintensiveindustries@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;energyintensiveindustries@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; if you have any questions about the energy intensive industry package or you would like to attend the discussion event in October. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/17440</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"/>
    <title>State Aid</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="what-is-state-aid"&gt;What is State Aid?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid refers to forms of assistance from a public body, or publicly-funded body, given to selected undertakings (any entity which puts goods or services on the given market), which has the potential to distort competition and affect trade between member states of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission monitors and controls State Aid in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;.  Member States are obliged to notify and seek approval from the Commission before granting State Aid. This gives the Commission the opportunity to approve or refuse to approve the proposed measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission is obliged to order the recovery of any aid from the beneficiaries that has not been properly notified to and approved by the Commission and that is later found to be in breach of the rules. This involves repayment with interest to the public authorities that granted the aid, which could be devastating to firms awarded the aid. Money must be clawed back even if this means that the company concerned goes bankrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a helpful introductory guide to get up to speed on State Aid, please consult our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/10-951-state-aid-beginners-guide.pdf"&gt;beginners guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more detailed guidance, you may find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-1040-state-aid-guide"&gt;State Aid guide for practitioners&lt;/a&gt; useful, also the Treasury published &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http:/www.bis.gov.uk/files/file32879.pdf"&gt;Risk Based Guide to State Aid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="why-have-state-aid-rules"&gt;Why have State Aid rules?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid rules aim to ensure fair competition and a single common market. Giving favoured treatment to some businesses would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;harm their business competitors and risk distorting the normal competitive market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hinder the long-term competitiveness of the Community by propping up inefficient, aid dependent companies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow those Member States with the deepest pockets to favour their own industries.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is why the European Community founding Treaty generally forbids State Aid, with certain exemptions. The State Aid rules contribute to the effective functioning of the Single Market and European Union economic reform in two key ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they prevent State Aid that would seriously distort competition - thereby helping to achieve a fair market for businesses in all Member States.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they allow State Aid that promotes economic development and other legitimate policy objectives, where this benefit outweighs any distortion of competition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The European Commission guide, &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Competition Policy and the Consumer, contains a section on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/state_aid/overview/index_en.html"&gt;State Aid&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-864-state-aid-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; guide may answer some questions you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-can-bis-do-for-public-authorities"&gt;What can BIS do for Public Authorities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) State Aid Branch aims to advise public authorities on the State Aid rules (except agriculture, transport and banking which are covered by Department for Environment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/a&gt;, Department for Transport &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;DfT&lt;/a&gt; and Her Majesty’s Treasury &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/"&gt;HMT&lt;/a&gt; respectively, and develop the UK’s State Aid policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our key message is seek advice early. State Aid rules can be complex and getting it wrong can mean you have to recover aid from businesses. You should seek advice at an early stage. This will help you to avoid problems later on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advisers can help you to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;design aid to avoid or minimise the element of State Aid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoid giving illegal State Aid and the penalties for this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;select and use the most suitable available vehicles for State Aid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;handle notifications and procedures for getting State Aid approval &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please complete the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/s/10-1295-state-aid-assessment-form.doc"&gt;State aid assessment form&lt;/a&gt; if you are planning to fund a project and contact us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/10-951-state-aid-beginners-guide.pdf"&gt;State Aid Beginners Guide&lt;/a&gt; and then our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-864-state-aid-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/a&gt; useful references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS will of course help you as much as possible but ultimate responsibility for aid lies with the aid giver. Aid givers must become familiar with the rules and organise themselves to deal with the notification process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-can-private-organisations-get-advice"&gt;Where can private organisations get advice?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a private sector organisation and have a State Aid query you should seek independent legal advice. Any concerns you may have about public funding that you are receiving or being offered should be directed to the public authority providing that funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/a&gt;(Defra) advises on State Aid rules for agriculture, fisheries and aquaculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/a&gt;(DfT) advises on State Aid rules for transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;  (DCLG) can advise on State Aid schemes for land and property regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devolved Administrations: The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Home"&gt;Scottish Government&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/"&gt;Welsh Assembly Government&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.detini.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Enterprise, Trade &amp;amp; Investment in Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; can provide initial advice and liaise with BIS, Defra, DfT and DCLG on your behalf if necessary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/12-747-state-aid-frequently-asked-questions.pdf"&gt;State Aid frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/i/12-746-introduction-general-block-exemption-regulation.pdf"&gt;Introduction to the General Block Exemption regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-1040-state-aid-guide.pdf"&gt;The State Aid Guide: guidance for state aid practitioners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/10-951-state-aid-beginners-guide.pdf"&gt;State Aid: A beginners guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file32879.pdf"&gt;Taking account of state aid issues in policy making&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/state_aid/studies_reports/vademecum_on_rules_09_2008_en.pdf"&gt;Vademecum Community on State Aid Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file49310.pdf"&gt;Universities and Research Organisations on the &lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt; state aid framework for R&amp;amp;D&amp;amp;I: guidance note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file53292.pdf"&gt;How the state aid rules impact upon funding for the delivery of public services of general economic internet (&lt;abbr title="Service of General Economic Interest"&gt;SGEI&lt;/abbr&gt;): general notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file52860.pdf"&gt;The Financial Transparency (&lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt; Directive) Regulations 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="rules-regulations-and-procedures"&gt;Rules, regulations and procedures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission monitors and controls State Aid in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; by requiring Member States to notify the Commission in advance of proposed State Aid in order to ensure compliance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few exceptions to the notification requirement, namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your measure falls within the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/europe/state-aid/de-minimis-aid-regulations"&gt;De Minimis regulation&lt;/a&gt; i.e. you are giving less than 200,000 Euros over three fiscal years &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measures which are covered under a pre-existing and approved scheme &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measures falling within the General Block Exemption regulation &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If none of the above conditions are satisfied, you will need to obtain approval, contacting the State Aid Unit in the first instance. The following sections cover the various regulations and procedures in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="do-i-need-to-notify-my-aid-project"&gt;Do I need to notify my aid project?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_28348"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16292/flow-chart.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-28348-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16292/thumbnail_flow-chart.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16292/flow-chart.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-28348-accessibility-help"&gt;State aid process flow chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;72.9 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;1 page&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-28348-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20State%20aid%20process%20flow%20chart%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27State%20aid%20process%20flow%20chart%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("State aid process flow chart").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents-1"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/state-aid/10-1154-state-aid-notification-process-flowchart.pdf"&gt;State aid notification process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notification"&gt;Notification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notification is not necessarily a quick or easy process. It is often easier to design aid measures to comply with a block exemption regulation etc so that notification is not required. State Aid approval cannot be taken for granted - you should factor in a degree of uncertainty – the Commission may block, delay or request modifications to proposed schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to predict exactly how long approval will take but as a guide, straightforward cases where there is a good fit with the rules can be expected to be resolved within 6-9 months. More complex cases will take longer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that State Aid Branch will provide advice on process and on developing content of notifications but you are ultimately responsible for drafting the notification and making the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-involved"&gt;What is involved?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a policy is designed and the need for notification has been identified, the pre-notification (essentially a draft notification) is developed and submitted by the applicant public authority’s policy lead. This is signed off by the State Aid Branch and validated by the UK representative. The pre-notification will then be submitted via SANI to the Commission, and the pre-notification period begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, the Commission will respond with a request for further information and / or to arrange a discussion. There can be several rounds of questions and answers and refinement of the notification and scheme over a period of some months until the Commission is satisfied that it can be approved. They will then invite the applicant to submit final notification via SANI, and final approval should normally be given within two months of final notification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-you-can-help-us"&gt;How you can help us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think State Aid EARLY. Take time and ensure sufficient resource is made available to understand state aid implications and risks of developing policy options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest time in understanding the relevant frameworks and guidelines and how your scheme fits with their requirements. Robust justification will be required where an aid measure departs from these. If you are uncertain about whether your scheme meets the rules, contact the State Aid Branch for further advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be honest with us about difficulties and areas of uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing evidence instead of assertions will enable your scheme to proceed more efficiently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="de-minimis-aid-regulations"&gt;De Minimis aid regulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De minimis aid is used to describe small amounts of State Aid that do not require European Commission approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission considers that public funding which complies with the de minimis regulation has a negligible impact on trade and competition, and does not require notification and approval. The total de minimis aid which can be given to a single recipient is €200,000 over a 3 year fiscal period. This can be given for most purposes, including operating aid, and is not project-related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that all funding under the €200,000 ceiling should be counted as de minimis.  It is strongly recommended to give even small amounts as aid under a specific approved scheme, or a block exemption, if possible, and to keep the de minimis cover as a back-up for when there are no other options. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The maximum de minimis funding any single recipient can receive is €200,000 (cash grant equivalent) over a 3-year fiscal period. The sterling equivalent is calculated using the Commission exchange rate applicable on the written date of offer of the de minimis funding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This ceiling takes into account all public assistance given as de minimis funding over the previous 3 fiscal years and which can take various forms (grants, loans, subsidised contracts, etc). Aid given under an approved scheme does not have to be cumulated with de minimis aid. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a few things you should keep in mind when considering de minimis aid: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;De minimis aid cannot be given for export related activities (except attendance at trade fairs), agriculture and fisheries or aid favouring domestic over imported products.  If you wish to give aid for agricultural activities, separate de minimis regulation applies; you may wish to contact DEFRA for this. If the aid you wish to give does not fall under an existing approval you need to obtain approval, contacting the State Aid Unit in the first instance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;De minimis aid does not affect the level of State Aid that a recipient can receive under any other schemes approved by the Commission, i.e. it is cumulated only with other de minimis aid. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="administration"&gt;Administration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using the de minimis regulation, public authorities must take the time to read and understand the regulation and to satisfy themselves that they are in compliance. The key requirements and processes are as follows: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When granting de minimis aid you must ensure that the new award does not breach the €200,000 ceiling over a 3-year fiscal period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must ask the enterprise concerned about any aid received during the previous 3 fiscal years and determine how much of this was de minimis aid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must also inform the recipient explicitly that it is de minimis aid you are giving them, for their future reference. The offer letter should include the value of the award in Euros and the following paragraph: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation 1998/2006 (de minimis aid regulation), this is a de minimis aid. There is a ceiling of €200,000 for all de minimis aid provided to any one firm over a 3-year period. Any de minimis aid awarded to you under this offer letter will be relevant if you wish to apply, or have applied, for any other de minimis aid. For the purposes of the de minimis regulation, you must retain this letter for 3 years from the date on this letter and produce it on any request by the UK public authorities or the European Commission. (You may need to keep this letter for longer than three years for other purposes.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should read our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/10-951-state-aid-beginners-guide.pdf"&gt;Beginner’s Guide&lt;/a&gt;  and our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-864-state-aid-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; and speak to the State Aid Unit if you have any further questions about de minimis aid. You may also find it useful to read the full text of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2006/l_379/l_37920061228en00050010.pdf"&gt;the regulation&lt;/a&gt; on the European Commission’s Competition website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-block-exemption-regulation"&gt;General Block Exemption Regulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The General Block Exemption Regulation (&lt;abbr title="General Block Exemptions"&gt;GBER&lt;/abbr&gt;) consolidates into one text and harmonises the rules that were previously existing in five separate Regulations. The European Commission adopted the General Block Exemption Regulation on the 29th August 2008, reducing the administrative burden for the public sector, the beneficiaries and the Commission. The &lt;abbr title="General Block Exemptions"&gt;GBER&lt;/abbr&gt; covers a range of pre approved State Aid areas that do not require individual approval from the European Commission in advance. Aid granted under cover of the Regulation only has to be notified within twenty days of the aid being granted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Regulation authorises aid in favour of SMEs, research, innovation, regional development, training, employment of disabled and disadvantaged workers, risk capital and environmental protection. The Regulation also introduces aid measures promoting female entrepreneurship, such as aid for young innovative businesses, aid for newly created small businesses in assisted regions, and measures tackling problems like difficulties in access to finance faced by female entrepreneurs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a section covering the &lt;abbr title="General Block Exemptions"&gt;GBER&lt;/abbr&gt; in detail in our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-1040-state-aid-guide"&gt;practitioner’s guide&lt;/a&gt; and you can find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32008R0800:en:NOT"&gt;full text on the Commission website&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any more questions or need further information on this or any other State Aid issue, contact the State Aid Unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="administration-and-notification-of-general-block-exemption-aid-measures"&gt;Administration and notification of General Block Exemption Aid measures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are required to send the Commission a summary information sheet about the aid measure via the State Aid Notification Interactive (SANI) within 20 working days following implementation of the measure. A copy of the information sheet may be found at annex III of the regulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The General Block Exemption Regulation contains detailed guidelines and conditions particularly as regards Definitions, Eligible Costs, Maximum Aid amounts and Scope (i.e. sectors or areas that can or cannot be supported). Aid administrators are responsible for ensuring compliance with all of the conditions of the general block exemption regulation and we strongly recommend that you take the time to read and understand the regulation before using it. Please note that these requirements include retention and provision of accurate and timely information on the usage of the scheme as required, in particular for the annual return and monitoring exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please seek the advice of State Aid Branch if you have any doubts about the compliance of your scheme with the State Aid rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="using-sani"&gt;Using SANI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be registered on SANI please contact the State Aid Branch. For help using SANI please consult the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://webgate.ec.europa.eu/competition/sani/help/"&gt;SANI manual&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that you will need to provide a web site link to the scheme. This should provide full details of the scheme including the criteria for qualifying for aid, eligible costs, scope etc. By doing so, you will fulfil the requirement that Member State have to publish on a web site full details of the scheme. The link to the web site must be given on the SANI submission otherwise the summary information sheet cannot be submitted. Please be aware that the Commission frequently check the web sites provided in summary information forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once completed, please send the electronic summary information sheet via SANI to State Aid Branch who will send it to the Commission for submission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="state-aid-regulations-and-frameworks"&gt;State Aid regulations and frameworks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure whether your State Aid project fits under a pre-existing scheme, you should search for a matching scheme using the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/elojade/isef/index.cfm?clear=1&amp;amp;policy_area_id=3"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Commission State Aid case search tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All State Aid rules and regulations and further guidance on these may be found on the Commission’s website. The key measures are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="horizontal-measures"&gt;Horizontal measures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="de-minimis-and-block-exemption-regulations"&gt;De Minimis and Block Exemption Regulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2006/l_379/l_37920061228en00050010.pdf"&gt;De Minimis Aid Regulation 1998/2006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2003/l_124/l_12420030520en00360041.pdf"&gt;SME Definition from January 2005&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:214:0003:0047:EN:PDF"&gt;General Block Exemption Regulation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/08/482&amp;amp;format=HTML&amp;amp;aged=0&amp;amp;language=EN&amp;amp;guiLanguage=en"&gt;General Block Exemption Regulation – frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environmental-aid"&gt;Environmental aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2008:082:0001:0033:EN:PDF"&gt;State aid for Environmental Protection Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-aid-and-uk-assisted-areas"&gt;Regional aid and UK assisted areas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid, provided as Regional Aid, can be used to promote the economic development of certain disadvantaged areas within the European Union. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the basis of Article 87(3)a and Article 87(3)c of the Treaty, State Aid granted to promote the economic development of certain disadvantaged areas within the European Union is considered compatible with the common market by the European Commission. This kind of State Aid is referred to as Regional Aid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional aid for business consists of aid for investment, or in certain limited circumstances operating aid, targeted on specific regions to redress regional disparities. Increased levels of regional investment aid may be granted to SMEs located within the disadvantaged areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="current-assisted-areas-map"&gt;Current assisted areas map&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assisted Areas are those locations where regional aid may be granted under &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; legislation. The current &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/a/11-769-assisted-areas-2007-2013.pdf"&gt;Assisted Areas Map&lt;/a&gt;  came into effect on 13 February 2007, and remains in force until 31 December 2013. The map was reviewed in response to the European Commission’s revised &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2006:054:0013:0044:EN:PDF"&gt;Regional Aid Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. The review concluded with the publication of the current map in October 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="forthcoming-assisted-areas-map"&gt;Forthcoming assisted areas map&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014-2020 UK Assisted Areas map is due to come into effect in January 2014. BIS will be working with the Devolved Administrations to consult on the new map in 2013. The map will be developed in accordance with the European Commission’s revised Regional Aid Guidelines for 2014-2020, a draft of which is due to be published in December 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2006/c_054/c_05420060304en00130044.pdf"&gt;guidelines on national regional aid for 2007-2013&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/comm/competition/state_aid/regional_aid/regional_aid.html"&gt;further information on regional aid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="rescue-and-restructuring-aid"&gt;Rescue and restructuring aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2004/c_244/c_24420041001en00020017.pdf"&gt;Guidelines on State Aid for Rescuing and Restructuring Firms in difficulty&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="research-and-development-and-innovation-rdi"&gt;Research and Development and Innovation (R&amp;amp;D&amp;amp;I)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2006/c_323/c_32320061230en00010026.pdf"&gt;Community Framework for State Aid For Research and Development and Innovation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="risk-capital"&gt;Risk Capital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2006/c_194/c_19420060818en00020021.pdf"&gt;Guidelines on State Aid to promote Risk Capital Investments in SMEs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="vertical-measures"&gt;Vertical measures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sector-specific-rules"&gt;Sector specific rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sector-specific legislation can be found on the following Commission link: 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/comm/competition/state_aid/legislation/specific_rules.html"&gt;Sector specific rules&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;audiovisual production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;broadcasting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electricity (stranded costs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;postal services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shipbuilding steel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-measures"&gt;Other measures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_312/l_31220051129en00470048.pdf"&gt;amendment to transparency directive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2009:235:0007:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;State aid and broadband guidelines&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/state_aid/legislation/sgei.html"&gt;State aid - Services of General Economic Interest (&lt;abbr title="Service of General Economic Interest"&gt;SGEI&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="complaints-about-state-aid"&gt;Complaints about state aid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="complaints-by-uk-industry-about-alleged-unfair-aid"&gt;Complaints by UK industry about alleged unfair aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a UK company believes that a competitor is receiving illegal aid then they should complain directly to the Commission on the Complaints Form. The Commission is obliged under the Procedural Regulation to act on any evidence of potential illegal aid and will therefore take complaints seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="member-state-or-interested-party-complaints"&gt;Member state or interested party complaints&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any Member State or interested party can challenge a Commission decision in the European Court of Justice. (Article 230 of the &lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt; Treaty).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Member States have an automatic right to bring such cases to the Court, or to intervene in a case before the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other interested parties, such as companies contesting a Commission decision to approve aid for a competitor, need to show they have a legitimate interest or standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Court has precedent as to when a third party can intervene and any company wishing to challenge a Commission decision could do so directly or if they wish could seek their own legal advice as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To challenge a decision successfully means proving that the Commission infringed an essential procedural requirement or misused its powers in the way it reached a decision. It is not enough merely to disagree with a decision. One has to show that had the Commission followed its own obligation and procedures properly - including properly considering the relevant facts - it could not have reached the decision it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A challenge to a decision has to be made within two months of Member States or interested parties being notified of the decision. Anyone wishing to challenge a decision can do so by contacting the Commission directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commission-or-another-member-state-complaint-against-a-member-state"&gt;Commission or another Member State complaint against a Member State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission or another Member State may also bring a claim to the European Court of Justice that a Member State has failed to fulfil its obligations or to comply properly with a Commission decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 108(2) allows the Commission or a Member State to refer directly to the ECJ if at the end of the Commission’s investigation, its decision is not being complied with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="complaints-referred-by-national-courts"&gt;Complaints referred by national courts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Justice also considers cases referred to it by national courts under Article 234. Member States may submit written observations and may appear at the hearing even if they did not submit written observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 108(2) allows the Commission or a Member State  to refer directly to the ECJ if at the end of the Commission’s investigation, its decision is not being complied with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission and the Court have the power to fine Member States for not complying with decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commission-complaints-about-uk-aid"&gt;Commission complaints about UK aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission may also receive a complaint, or itself raise a concern about a proposed UK State Aid payment or scheme that it may have heard about through the media. The Commission would then ask the UK for a detailed explanation within a set time. The Commission would be legally within its powers to open an Article 108(2) formal investigation procedure, backed by an injunction to halt any current aid payments, if it was not satisfied with the UK response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid Branch can advise on the best way to handle Commission complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to fully satisfy the Commission’s enquiries, so that it can put a convincing case to the complainant that no further action need be taken. The complainant may otherwise pursue the matter in the national courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consequences-and-penalties"&gt;Consequences and penalties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission monitors and controls State Aid in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; by requiring Member States to notify the Commission in advance of proposed State Aid. This gives the Commission the opportunity to approve or refuse to approve the proposed State Aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Procedure Regulation (659/99) defines unlawful aid as unnotified aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the present procedural rules, the Commission is under the obligation to order the recovery from the beneficiaries of any unlawful aid that is found to be incompatible with the Common Market. This includes repayment with interest to the public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="application-of-law"&gt;Application of law&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obligation under Article 108(3) of the Treaty to notify proposed State Aid or changes to existing approved State Aid is directly enforceable in Member States’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only the European Court of Justice has competence to review the legality of the Commission’s decisions and actions in controlling State Aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National courts uphold the rights of persons in the event of a breach by national authorities of the ban on putting State Aid into effect without Commission approval. The courts must take steps on the question of the validity of decisions and recovery of unlawful aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission and the Court have the power to fine Member States for not complying with decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="state-aid-and-annual-reporting"&gt;State aid and annual reporting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-european-commission-ec-requires-each-member-state-to-provide-information-about-state-aid-spend"&gt;The European Commission (&lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt;) requires each Member State to provide information about State Aid spend.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notified-and-approved-state-aid"&gt;Notified and Approved State Aid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission (&lt;abbr title="European Commission"&gt;EC&lt;/abbr&gt;) requires each Member State to provide a yearly report on State Aid paid out under approved State Aid schemes and individually approved State Aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid Branch will ask aid administrators once a year to provide details of State Aid paid under approved State Aid schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-block-exemptions-gber"&gt;General Block Exemptions (&lt;abbr title="General Block Exemptions"&gt;GBER&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the conditions of the general block exemption regulation is to provide an annual report on block exemption schemes. Please make sure that you follow the conditions laid out in the &lt;abbr title="General Block Exemptions"&gt;GBER&lt;/abbr&gt;; you must provide a webpage outlining the scheme and make sure that it stays updated for the duration of the scheme. Most schemes have a brief overview with a linked PDF with the full detail required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid Branch is responsible for compiling the annual report on the UK’s State Aid schemes for the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid Branch will ask aid administrators once a year around spring to provide details of State Aid paid under the general block exemption regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission can take legal action against the UK if we do not comply with the condition to provide annual reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reports-to-the-world-trade-organisation-wto-on-state-aid"&gt;Reports to the World Trade Organisation (&lt;abbr title="World Trade Organisation"&gt;WTO&lt;/abbr&gt;) on State Aid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State Aid Branch also must provide a detailed report every two years around February to the &lt;abbr title="World Trade Organisation"&gt;WTO&lt;/abbr&gt; on State Aid paid out. Again State Aid Branch will request information from aid administrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="service-of-general-economic-interest-sgei"&gt;Service of General Economic Interest (&lt;abbr title="Service of General Economic Interest"&gt;SGEI&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending under the &lt;abbr title="Service of General Economic Interest"&gt;SGEI&lt;/abbr&gt; block exemption regulation is subject to separate periodic reporting (every 3 years).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/45373</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:53:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:53:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/maritime-anti-piracy-documentation-service"/>
    <title>Maritime anti-piracy documentation service </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Export Control Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) has launched a paid-for commercial service to provide documents in connection with maritime anti-piracy trade control requirements. This service is designed to meet the documentation requirements of a number of port states in the Indian Ocean. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documentation service is specifically for UK Private Security Companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) who are registered to hold either the Open General Trade Control Licence (&lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt;) Maritime Anti Piracy or related original Standard Individual Export Licences (&lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licences"&gt;SIELs&lt;/abbr&gt;) for exporting military and paramilitary equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The [&lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (Maritime Anti-Piracy)] was published in light of the efforts to combat piracy and security threats, as highlighted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/london-conference-somalia/"&gt;London Conference on Somalia held on 23 February 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its publication, UK &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; have advised that they are facing problems getting their controlled equipment into Mauritius. The Mauritian government is requesting a ‘certificate’ to the effect that the PSC has all the necessary UK government licences, and they are not accepting an electronic record (our licences are issued electronically via SPIRE). &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; think it quite possible that other governments will follow suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide includes further details about the certificates, the fee structure and how to apply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="certificates"&gt;Certificates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; has designed a set of certificates that should satisfy both the overseas documentation requirements of overseas governments and also resolve the issue for UK industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The certificates are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an approval certificate for use of the &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (maritime anti-piracy) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a maritime anti-piracy certificate &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each set would be produced in hard copy and sealed and signed. This will be done as a commercial service for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; by the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; and at a cost based on full economic cost recovery basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="approval-certificate-for-use-of-the-open-general-trade-control-licence-maritime-anti-piracy-licence"&gt;Approval certificate for use of the Open General Trade Control Licence (Maritime Anti-Piracy Licence)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approval certificate will replace the current email notification that &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; sends to notify a PSC that they can use the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/open-general-trade-control-licences"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (Maritime Anti-Piracy)&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; allows, subject to certain conditions and the provision and approval of certain information, the transfer of common military and paramilitary equipment used in maritime security operations for protection against acts of piracy. The new approval certificate can be mailed to you as with the current &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; approval - free of charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about Open General Licences: an overview and also about Open General Trade Control Licences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you require additional formal documentation to satisfy the port state authorities, it can also be provided in hard copy, sealed and signed, but at a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-maritime-anti-piracy-certificate"&gt;The Maritime Anti-Piracy Certificate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hard-copy, sealed and signed document that pulls together and verifies the following documents, also in hard copy form, and all sealed and signed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open General Trade Control Licence (Maritime Anti-Piracy Certificate)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the relevant Standard Individual Export Licence (&lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt;) issued by the UK’s strategic export licensing authority, &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;. This includes a list of weapons with serial numbers that are being transferred and used in accordance with the &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (Maritime Anti-Piracy). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: serial numbers may be added to an extant &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; at any time via an email amendment request to your &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; Licensing Officer. This is also a chargeable service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often the case that, when a &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; application is made for the export of weapons from the UK, a complete list of the serial numbers is not available at that time, 3 or 4 weapons being bought and shipped to a PSC at a later time when the PSC has a new anti-piracy contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provision has been made, therefore, to accept &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; amendment requests from the exporter, by email, for the addition of serial numbers to the &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt;. This can be done as many times as required. A hard copy &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt;, sealed and signed will be produced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt; will normally send documents by post to a UK address. However, we can make arrangements to leave your documents at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;, 1 Victoria Street Reception Desk for collection by a courier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: the hard copy &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; would normally be provided by the weapons dealer associated with the PSC and may be used by a PSC, subject to agreement with the weapons dealer, as part of the overall documentation package referred to above. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fee-structure-and-how-to-request-the-maritime-anti-piracy-commercial-service"&gt;Fee structure and how to request the Maritime Anti-Piracy Commercial Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The various activities and fees for the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s service are set out below  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="payment"&gt;Payment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of each service is shown below:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fee&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; Registration + hard copy + &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (MAP) Approval Certificate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£119 + VAT&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; Amendment to add armouries + hard copy + &lt;abbr title="Open General Trade Control Licence"&gt;OGTCL&lt;/abbr&gt; (MAP) Approval Certificate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£59 + VAT&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; hard copy + seal/sign*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£20 + VAT&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Subsequent &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; amendments to add serial numbers + hard copy + sign/seal (see note below)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£59 + VAT&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Post &amp;amp; Packing and Delivery by Royal Mail to UK address&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£20 + VAT&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: this hard copy, sealed and signed &lt;abbr title="Standard Individual Export Licence"&gt;SIEL&lt;/abbr&gt; documentation, when it includes a list of weapons complete with serial numbers, may also be useful for arms traders wishing to demonstrate that the export has been approved by the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using a Purchase Order for payment, please ensure that it is sent with the order form to the &lt;abbr title="Export Control Organisation"&gt;ECO&lt;/abbr&gt;. Your documents will not be dispatched until payment is received. If you are not using a Purchase Order, you may pay by cheque, payable to ‘&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please complete the attached approval certificate application form with details of your requirements, together with associated payment, to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Maritime Anti-Piracy Unit
&lt;br&gt;Export Control Organisation
&lt;br&gt;Department of Business, Innovation and Skills
&lt;br&gt;1 Victoria Street
&lt;br&gt;Orchard 3
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1H 0ET
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fax: 020 7215 0531		
E-mail: &lt;a href="mailto:eco.antipiracy@bis.gis.gov.uk"&gt;eco.antipiracy@bis.gis.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are unable to accept payment by credit, debit or charge card. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/17786</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:47:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:47:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/repi-transport"/>
    <title>REPI Transport</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="transport"&gt;Transport&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="j1---travel-to-work"&gt;J1 - Travel to Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_28685"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16487/J1_REPI.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28685-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16487/J1_REPI.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28685-accessibility-help"&gt;Table J(1) - Main mode of transport to work by region of workplace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;26 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-28685-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Table%20J%281%29%20-%20Main%20mode%20of%20transport%20to%20work%20by%20region%20of%20workplace%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Table%20J%281%29%20-%20Main%20mode%20of%20transport%20to%20work%20by%20region%20of%20workplace%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Table J(1) - Main mode of transport to work by region of workplace").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Table J(1) - Main mode of transport to work by region of workplace (XLS, 26 Kb)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Updated: May 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Labour Force Survey, Office for National Statistics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="j2---average-traffic-speed"&gt;J2 - Average Traffic Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_28686"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16488/J2_REPI.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28686-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16488/J2_REPI.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28686-accessibility-help"&gt;Table J(2) - Average traffic speed on major English roads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;37 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-28686-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Table%20J%282%29%20-%20Average%20traffic%20speed%20on%20major%20English%20roads%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Table%20J%282%29%20-%20Average%20traffic%20speed%20on%20major%20English%20roads%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Table J(2) - Average traffic speed on major English roads").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Table J(2) - Average traffic speed on major English roads (XLS, 37 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Updated: May 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Transport Statistics, Department for Transport&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="j3---motor-vehicle-flows"&gt;J3 - Motor Vehicle Flows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_28687"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16489/Table_J3_-_Average_Daily_Motor_Vehicle_Flows_0712.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28687-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16489/Table_J3_-_Average_Daily_Motor_Vehicle_Flows_0712.xls" aria-describedby="attachment-28687-accessibility-help"&gt;Table J(3) - Average daily motor vehicle flows, all roads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;25 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-28687-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Table%20J%283%29%20-%20Average%20daily%20motor%20vehicle%20flows%2C%20all%20roads%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Table%20J%283%29%20-%20Average%20daily%20motor%20vehicle%20flows%2C%20all%20roads%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Table J(3) - Average daily motor vehicle flows, all roads").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;Table J(3) - Average daily motor vehicle flows, all roads (XLS, 25 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Updated: July 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Transport Statistics, Department for Transport&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/3161</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:01:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:01:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england"/>
    <title>Boosting private sector employment in England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain parts of the country have been dependent on the public sector for employment. To help these areas grow their private sectors - and create more jobs - the government has established a regional growth fund (RGF) of £2.4 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have up to £1 billion of funding to allocate under the RGF to stimulate economic growth and encourage private sector investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund/how-to-apply" title="apply for funding"&gt;apply for funding&lt;/a&gt; from now until 13 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund will support private sector projects and public/private partnerships that have the potential for long-term economic growth and the creation of sustainable jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="who-can-apply-for-funding"&gt;Who can apply for funding?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private or public-private organisations in England can apply for funding. It can be used for capital investment, research and development or training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations must apply for a minimum of £1 million funding. Funding can be a grant, loan or loan guarantee. We will assess projects on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value for money for taxpayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ability to create jobs in the private sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;project management expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Projects must fit the European Union’s rules on state aid - we need to ensure any funding does not give a company unfair competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011, we allocated £1.4 billion of the RGF in 2 rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round 1, April 2011: £450 million was allocated to 50 bids, attracting £2.5 billion in private sector investment. The projects will create or safeguard over 27,000 direct jobs, with around 100,000 more in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round 2, October 2011: £950 million was invested in 126 bids, attracting nearly £6 billion of private investment. Around 200,000 jobs will be created or protected: around 37,000 direct jobs, with more than 164,000 in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the &lt;a href="government/admin/detailed-guides/16467"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/16774</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:46:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/audit-accounting-and-reporting-guidance-for-uk-companies"/>
    <title>Audit, accounting and reporting: guidance for UK companies</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that the UK economy has efficient and effective capital markets and there is confidence in the corporate framework through greater transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing for reliable and informative reporting contributes to this commitment. It includes the implementation of international accounting standards and international standards on auditing and requires an ongoing dialogue with UK stakeholders and EU or international regulators on measures to encourage market stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="audit-exemptions-and-change-of-accounting-framework"&gt;Audit exemptions and change of accounting framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 September 2012 government made regulations to allow more companies to make a commercial decision about whether or not to have a statutory audit.&lt;br&gt;
Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2301/contents/made"&gt;The Companies and Limited Liability Partnerships (Accounts and Audit Exemptions and Change of Accounting Framework) Regulations 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We has also published its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/12-874-audit-exemptions-and-accounting-framework-response.pdf"&gt;response to the consultation on audit exemptions and change of accounting framework&lt;/a&gt;, which sets out its conclusions on the proposed changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, to be eligible for an audit exemption in the UK, small companies must be less than a certain size in terms of balance sheet and turnover. The new regulations align mandatory audit thresholds with accounting thresholds, meaning Small to Medium Enterprises (&lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be able to obtain an exemption if they meet two out of three criteria relating to balance sheet total, turnover and number of employees. This change will allow 36,000 more companies to choose not to have an audit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations also exempt most subsidiary companies from mandatory audit, as long as their parent undertaking guarantees their liabilities. A further 83,000 subsidiary companies could benefit. Companies House has now made forms available for subsidiaries to use when filing the parent guarantee that has been put in place by their parent undertaking. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/forms/generalForms/AA06_statement_of_guarantee_by_a_parent_undertaking_of_a_subsidiary_company.pdf"&gt;form AA06&lt;/a&gt; for companies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/forms/generalForms/LL_AA06_statement_of_guarantee_by_a_parent_undertaking_of_a_subsidiary_limited_liability_partnership.pdf"&gt;form LL AA06&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;abbr title="Limited liability partnerships"&gt;LLPs&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, another 67,000 dormant subsidiaries will no longer need to prepare and file annual accounts, provided they are subject to a similar guarantee, which they have filed using the same forms. Guidance on the new subsidiaries exemptions is also available from Companies House as part of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;its general &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/about/gbhtml/gp2.shtml"&gt;guidance to companies (see Chapter 8 - Dormant Company Accounts and Chapter 11: Audit Exemption for Subsidiaries)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/about/gbhtml/gpllp2.shtml"&gt;guidance to &lt;abbr title="Limited liability partnerships"&gt;LLPs&lt;/abbr&gt; (see Chapter 11 - Dormant LLP Accounts and Chapter 12: Audit Exemption for Subsidiaries)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following consultation by the Financial Reporting Council (&lt;abbr title="Financial Reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;) on changes to UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles (&lt;abbr title="UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles"&gt;UK GAAP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the government has also decided to allow companies that prepare their accounts under International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) to move to &lt;abbr title="UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles"&gt;UK GAAP&lt;/abbr&gt; and take advantage of reduced disclosures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new regulations remove EU gold-plating and ensure UK &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; are not at a disadvantage compared to their European competitors. These changes are part of the government’s wider drive to reduce unnecessary burdens and make the UK one of the best places in the world to start, finance and grow a business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fourth-and-seventh-company-law-directives-company-reporting"&gt;Fourth and seventh company law directives: company reporting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Council Directives 78/660/EEC (4th Directive) and 83/349/EEC (7th Directive) require member states to establish a legal framework for producing annual accounts and consolidated accounts, for limited companies. These Directives also include reporting requirements in respect of corporate governance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4th and 7th Directives also set the thresholds which determine whether a company is large, medium or small for reporting and audit purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information is available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/company/board/index_en.htm"&gt;European Commission website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-of-accounts-other-than-by-reference-to-uk-gaap-or-ifrs"&gt;Preparation of accounts other than by reference to &lt;abbr title="UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles"&gt;UK GAAP&lt;/abbr&gt; or &lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A letter requesting views on whether there are any circumstances when the use of non-UK and &lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt; accountancy framework for UK incorporated companies would be sensible. Responses should be sent to &lt;a href="mailto:Margaret.Sutherland@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Margaret.Sutherland@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-partnerships-accounts-regulations-2008-si-2008569-technical-defect-in-definition-of-qualifying-partnership"&gt;The Partnerships (Accounts) regulations 2008 (SI 2008/569): technical defect in definition of ‘qualifying partnership’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is currently considering responses to the letter dated 13 April 2010 and draft regulations sent to interested parties on the technical defect in the definition of ‘Qualifying Partnership’ in The Partnership (Accounts) Regulations 2008 (SI 2008/569). The period for comment on this closed on 6 July 2010. Though earlier commencement dates have previously been considered, it is now likely that any new regulations will apply to financial years beginning on or after 1 October 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-standards-accounting"&gt;International standards (accounting)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European law requires listed companies to use International Accounting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) from 1 January 2005 when preparing their consolidated accounts. The relevant law is Regulation (EC) No. 1606/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 19 July 2002 on the application of International Accounting Standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Accounting Standards Board (&lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards Board"&gt;IASB&lt;/abbr&gt;) is responsible for writing accounting standards to be used by all listed groups. The standards are also called International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the terms are often used interchangeably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before standards as written by the &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards Board"&gt;IASB&lt;/abbr&gt; can be used by European companies they are required to be adopted for use in the European Union. The Accounting Regulatory Committee (&lt;abbr title="Accounting Regulatory Committee"&gt;ARC&lt;/abbr&gt;) is composed of representatives from Member States and chaired by the Commission. The function of the Committee is a regulatory one and consists of providing an opinion on Commission proposals to adopt (endorse) an international accounting standard or an interpretation as envisaged under Article 3 of the &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation. The Committee has been set up by the Commission in accordance with the requirements contained in Article 6 of the &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, the use of &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; has been extended so that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publicly traded companies in the UK are also permitted to use &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; in their individual accounts from the same date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other companies and limited liability partnerships in the UK are permitted to use &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; in both their individual and consolidated accounts from the same date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information can be found in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/files/file46791.pdf"&gt;‘Guidance for UK companies on accounting and reporting: requirements under the Companies Act 2006 and the application of the &lt;abbr title="International Accounting Standards"&gt;IAS&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="audit-directive"&gt;Audit directive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="directive-200643ec-on-statutory-audits-of-annual-and-consolidated-accounts"&gt;Directive 2006/43/EC on Statutory Audits of Annual and Consolidated Accounts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous government held two public consultations on the implementation of the Audit Directive on 5 March 2007 and 19 July 2007 (including draft regulations). On 17 December 2007 it published a summary of the comments on the Draft Regulations and the government’s conclusions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU Audit Directive is implemented in relation to companies through Parts 16 and 42 of the Companies Act 2006, as amended by the Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors Regulations (&lt;abbr title="Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors Regulations"&gt;SATCAR&lt;/abbr&gt;) and other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/company-and-partnership-law/company-law/regulations-statutory-instruments"&gt;related regulations&lt;/a&gt;. Most aspects of this amended regulatory framework are applicable to company reporting periods beginning on or after 6 April 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other regulations implementing the Audit Directive have been made by other government and regulatory bodies, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HM Treasury, which has implemented parts of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1519/contents/made"&gt;Audit Directive for Building Societies&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1140/contents/made"&gt;Friendly Societies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/1950/contents/made"&gt;Lloyds syndicates&lt;/a&gt;. The Regulations have commenced for reporting periods beginning on or after 29 June 2008&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Financial Services Authority, which has implemented certain requirements on listed companies, through the listing rules. The amended rules have commenced for reporting periods beginning on or after 29 June 2008&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Professional Oversight Board of the Financial Reporting Council (&lt;abbr title="Professional Oversight Board"&gt;POB&lt;/abbr&gt;) has made regulations, which commenced on 6 April 2008 as part of the implementation of the Companies Act - these &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Home.aspx"&gt;regulations on transparency reports, the register of auditors and examination requirements&lt;/a&gt; also implement parts of the Audit Directive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information about the Directive is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/auditing/directives/index_en.htm"&gt;European Commission website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on the implementation of Articles 45, 46 and 47 of the Audit Directive, see the section below on Relations with third countries. This includes information on recent Commission Decisions issued under Articles 46 and 47 of the Audit Directive, and on publication of draft regulations for comment by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="disclosure-of-non-audit-services-provided-to-large-companies-by-their-auditors"&gt;Disclosure of non-audit services provided to large companies by their auditors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has now replaced Schedule 2 to the Companies (Disclosure of Auditor Remuneration and Liability Limitation Agreements) Regulations 2008 to provide a new classification of non-audit services to large companies, intended to improve insight into the potential questions around the auditor’s independence and link more clearly to the classification of non-audit services under Article 49 of the Audit Directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are in line with recent changes to the Auditing Practices Board’s (&lt;abbr title="Auditing Practices Board"&gt;APB&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) Ethical Standards for Auditors which set out the principles to be followed by auditors in order to maintain their independence. The &lt;abbr title="Auditing Practices Board"&gt;APB&lt;/abbr&gt; completed a review of the Ethical Standards on 17 December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/company-and-partnership-law/company-law/regulations-statutory-instruments"&gt;Companies Act 2006 Regulations and Commencement Orders page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft regulations below were published for comment for a period beginning on Thursday 7 April 2011 and ending on Thursday 30 June 2011. &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has published a report of the comments made on the draft regulations explaining the changes that have been made in response to comments received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/11-1268-explanatory-text-companies-disclosure-regulations.pdf"&gt;Explanatory Text - Companies (Disclosure of Auditor Remuneration and Liability Limitation Agreements) (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 84 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/c/11-818-companies-disclosure-auditor-agreements-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;Draft Companies (Disclosure of Auditor Remuneration and Liability Limitation Agreements) (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 54 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="relations-with-third-countries"&gt;Relations with third countries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="third-country-auditors"&gt;Third-country auditors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Audit Directive requires the registration and regulation of auditors that audit the accounts of companies from outside the &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;, which issue securities on regulated markets in the &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; (‘third country auditors’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 19 January 2011, the European Commission issued a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:015:00112:0016:EN:PDF"&gt;Decision (2011/30/EU)&lt;/a&gt; on the equivalence of certain third country public oversight, quality assurance and, investigation and penalty system for auditors and audit entities and a transitional period for audit activities of certain third country auditors and audit entities in the EU. Further details are available on the Commission website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has now made regulations to implement the Commission Decision by amending the Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors Regulations 2007 (SI 2007/3494) and Part 42 of, and Schedule 10 to, the Companies Act 2006 via regulations under section 2(2) of the European Communities Act 1972. The Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors (Amendment) Regulations 2011 (SI 2011/1856) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/company-and-partnership-law/company-law/regulations-statutory-instruments"&gt;Companies Act 2006 Regulations and Commencement Orders page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; issued draft regulations implementing the Decision, in relation to third country auditors registered or domiciled outside the &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;, for comment for a period beginning on Thursday 7 April 2011 and ending on Thursday 19 May 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draft Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors (Amendment) Regulations 2011](http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/11-807-explanatory-text-draft-statutory-third-country-auditors.pdf) (PDF, 53 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/11-806-statutory-third-country-auditors-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;Draft Statutory Auditors and Third Country Auditors (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 64 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final regulations also implement the Decision for Statutory Auditors in respect of any audits which they conduct of UK-traded non-&lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; companies. As a result, statutory auditors will continue to be exempted from the requirements of the Disclosure and Transparency Rules implementing Article 45 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/DTR/4/1"&gt;Audit Directive (DTR 4.1.7(R))&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Commission Decision has replaced &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:202:0070:0073:EN:PDF"&gt;Decision (2008/627/EC)&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed the introduction of provisions on the registration and regulation of third-country auditors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The registration and regulation of third country auditors in the UK is the responsibility of the Professional Oversight Board of the Financial Reporting Council. Further information is available on the &lt;abbr title="Professional Oversight Board"&gt;POB&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transfer-of-audit-working-papers"&gt;Transfer of audit working papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Audit Directive also introduced provisions to control the transfer of auditors’ working papers to the audit authorities of countries outside the &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt;. The Directive allows transfers of papers to those third countries whose audit regulatory authorities are approved as “adequate” by the European Commission, where those authorities have entered into working arrangements with &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 February 2010 the European Commission issued the first determination of adequacy under the Directive, by issuing a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:035:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;Decision (2010/64/EU) (‘the first Decision’)&lt;/a&gt; in favour of the audit authorities of Canada, Japan and Switzerland. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:240:0006:0009:EN:PDF"&gt;second Decision (2010/485/EU)&lt;/a&gt; was issued on 1 September 2010. &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has made regulations to implement the Commission Decisions by amending Part 42 of the Companies Act 2006 via regulations under section 2(2) of the European Communities Act 1972. The Companies Act 2006 (Transfer of Audit Working Papers to Third Countries) Regulations 2010 (SI 2010/2537) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/company-and-partnership-law/company-law/regulations-statutory-instruments"&gt;the Companies Act 2006 Regulations and Commencement Orders page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This follows the publication of draft regulations to implement the first Decision for comment for a period of consultation which ended on Friday 28 May 2010. &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; has published a report of the comments made on the draft regulations explaining the changes that have been made in response to comments received, as well as to implement the second Decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/10-1231-explanatory-text-transfer-of-audit-working-papers-regulations.pdf"&gt;Explanatory text - The Companies Act 2006 (Transfer of Audit Working Papers to Third Countries) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 59 Kb) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/10-887-draft-for-consultation-audit-working-papers-to-third-countries-regulations.pdf"&gt;Consultation Draft - The Companies Act 2006 (Transfer of Audit Working Papers to Third Countries) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="audit-offence"&gt;Audit offence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 507 of the Companies Act 2006 created new offences relating to reports on company audits. It is possible that behaviour by auditors that could involve committing one of these offences could also be pursued by the auditors’ regulatory authorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has issued guidance under section 508 to help regulatory and prosecuting authorities to determining how they should carry out their functions in these circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/10-574-guidance-offences-in-connection-with-auditors-report-section-507"&gt;Companies Act 2006, section 508. Guidance for regulatory and prosecuting authorities in England, Wales and Northern Ireland: offences in connection with auditors’ reports (section 507)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance refers to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/audit-and-auditors.pdf"&gt;Background note: audit and auditors&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 29 Kb)  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/8477</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:30:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:30:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"/>
    <title>Providing better information and protection for consumers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government believes that consumers who are well-informed about their rights and what they’re buying are more confident and more likely to spend money. We also think that consumers who feel properly protected by the law are more likely to spend money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to give consumers more confidence - and legal back-up - to deal with bad service or shoddy goods. We also want to encourage consumers to spend money, as this will help the economy grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-bill-of-rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to simplify and clarify consumer law with a new bill (Act of Parliament). This will contain a clear list of rights for consumers, along with new measures to protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-bill-of-rights" title="Consumer bill of rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/a&gt; will also contain remedies for when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform"&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘consumer landscape’ is the network of organisations that help consumers - Citizens Advice, for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘competition landscape’ is the network of organisations that deal with competition issues and anti-competitive activities in business – the Office of Fair Trading, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning to reorganise both the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="consumer and competition landscapes"&gt;consumer and competition landscapes&lt;/a&gt; between now and 2014, to make them both simpler to understand and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-201183eu"&gt;Implementing the Consumer Rights Directive 2011/83/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-2011-83-eu" title="Consumer Rights Directive."&gt;Consumer Rights Directive (CRD)&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; measure. All &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CRD gives consumers additional rights when buying in the UK and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. We’re aiming to make the CRD part of UK law by June 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="misleading-and-aggressive-selling"&gt;Misleading and aggressive selling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/misleading-and-aggressive-selling" title="Misleading and aggressive selling."&gt;improving the rights of people who have been misled into buying something&lt;/a&gt;, or who have been pressured into buying something. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="personal-data"&gt;Personal data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re helping consumers make better buying decisions by giving them improved access to the personal data companies hold about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/midata" title="Midata"&gt;midata project.&lt;/a&gt;. We’re working with business, consumer and privacy groups. The project is led by an independent data expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midata project runs on a voluntary basis, but we’ll pass a law to make industry cooperation compulsory if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-buying"&gt;Community buying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers can combine their buying power to buy goods and services together. This can get them better deals. The government is supporting community buying in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by providing clear advice to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/community-buying" title="Community groups"&gt;community groups&lt;/a&gt; who want to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by running the ‘Buy better together challenge’, which has a £60,000 fund to be shared amongst innovative collective purchasing projects - the challenge was won by Smarterbuys, an organisation that helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so they can buy essential goods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="who-can-i-contact-for-help-and-advice"&gt;Who can I contact for help and advice?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t help with individual problems – but here are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/consumer-protection-rights" title="Help and advice"&gt;some people who can.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/" title="Trading Standards."&gt;Trading Standards&lt;/a&gt; have worked on mainly local cases and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://oft.gov.uk/" title="Office of Fair Trading."&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/a&gt; (OFT) worked on some national ones. A National Audit Office (NAO) report was critical of this split and the ‘enforcement gap’ it caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews."&gt;Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews&lt;/a&gt; were published in spring 2012. They recommended a number of changes including transferring the main responsibility for consumer advice to the Citizens Advice service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consulted in June 2011 with proposals for reforming consumer institutions – the ‘consumer landscape’. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/empowering-and-protecting-consumers?cat=closedwithresponse" title="Empowering and Protecting Consumers: Consultation"&gt;Empowering and protecting consumers&lt;/a&gt; had 184 responses and closed in September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted in summer 2012 about whether we should have an ‘order-making power’ for midata. This power would give us the legal authority to make businesses release personal data to their customers. Following the consultation, we announced that we would legislate if companies didn’t release customers’ data voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital.pdf" title="proposals to update and simplify consumer law"&gt;proposals to update and simplify consumer law.&lt;/a&gt;  How would they affect consumers and businesses? That consultation closed on 5 October 2012. We’ll publish the results in spring 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital" title="Goods, services, digital content"&gt;Consultation on the supply of goods, services and digital content (July 2012)&lt;/a&gt; here and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-961-supply-of-digital-content-impact.pdf" title="Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content."&gt;Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1008-consultation-ban-above-cost-payment-surcharges" title="Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges."&gt;Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 15 October with the government response due in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-999-consultation-implementation-of-consumer-rights-directive.pdf" title="Consumer rights consultation"&gt;implementation of the Consumer Rights Directive&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 1 November. The government response is due in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-543-enhancing-consumer-confidence-effective-enforcement-consultation.pdf" title="Consumer law enforcement powers"&gt;Simplifying consumer law enforcement powers.&lt;/a&gt; The government response is expected in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re consulting on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending" title="Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law."&gt;Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;. This opened on 2 November and closes on 31 December with government response due early in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to know your views on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending"&gt;Give your views about extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked with a number of partners to produce our ‘Guide for community buying groups’. All of the organisations below contributed or checked material for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action with Communities in Rural England (ACRE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allen Valleys Oil Buying Co-operative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brighter Living Partnership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citizens Advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oxfordshire Rural Community Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The R Shop Bulk Buying Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solar 100 Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sustain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up2Us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also worked with the Law Commission and the Scottish Law Commission, who both did studies on misleading and aggressive selling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
