<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Transport</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57030</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-local-roads"/>
    <title>Cash boost for local roads</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils can plan how to spend their share of a £215 million fund for local road maintenance after funding allocations were published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £215 million is part of a £333 million fund announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend the life of roads in England.  This funding is in addition to the £3 billion the government is already providing for councils in England between 2011 and 2015 for highways maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This maintenance funding could be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges or repairing damage to highway infrastructure caused by severe weather events, such as the recent flooding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extra money will support economic growth and development by helping local authorities to get the best out of their local road networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding can be spent on measures to bring smoother, safer and more reliable journeys to the travelling public whether they are commuting to work or taking the children to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help local residents see where this money has been spent it will be a condition of the funding that local authorities commit to publishing a short statement on their websites at the end of each financial year setting out what and where this additional funding has been spent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities are also encouraged to look at the information published by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep"&gt;Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme&lt;/a&gt; which is leading the way by bringing together the public and private sectors to develop good practice and reduce costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne announced in the Autumn Statement on 5 December additional funding of £333 million for highways maintenance for both the motorway and trunk road and local road network. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£215 million additional capital funding will be provided to local highway authorities, including London, to help renew and repair the network in England. £140 million will come in 2013 to 2014, with the remaining £75 million following in 2014 to 2015. The funds will be distributed on the basis of the department’s existing highways maintenance capital funding formula. A &lt;a href="/government/publications/local-transport-capital-block-funding"&gt;full list of the allocations by region and local authority&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be eligible for this additional funding and to promote greater transparency and accountability, the department will require local highway authorities to publish a brief note on their website by the end of each financial year (end of April 2014 and end of April 2015) on where (in terms of location) and how this additional funding was spent on highways maintenance. This is so local communities are able to see how this extra funding has been spent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme (HMEP) is a sector-led programme designed to maximise returns from highways investment and deliver efficient and effective services.  HMEP provides practical guidance on highway maintenance efficiencies for local authorities, supplier organisations and representative bodies in the form of toolkits, case studies and good practice.  The most recent of these, launched on 29 November, are the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/standard-spec.php"&gt;standard specification&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/asset-management.php"&gt;asset management toolkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/57028</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-18-december-2012"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 18 December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the last Transport Council of the Cypriot Presidency (the Presidency) taking place in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be asked to reach a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the Council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. I was very concerned when we first received the proposal from the Commission. The Commission’s impact assessment was inadequate and failed to make the required links between the costs and benefits of new requirements. It was also incomplete as it did not accurately assess costs in all member states. Our initial analysis was that it would cost over £1 billion pounds to implement while having an insignificant positive impact on road safety in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position we adopted during the negotiation of the draft periodic roadworthiness regulation at Council working group meetings has been to resist additional burdens where insignificant road safety benefit was identified. With the support of the UK and other member states in resisting excessive burdens, the Presidency has proposed moving from a regulation to a directive and has made substantial changes to the text that radically simplifies the implementation of the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has been positive and has resulted in a substantially improved and less expensive proposal and as such I hope the Presidency will be able to achieve a general approach on the dossier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency will provide a progress report on 2 other proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing the ‘connecting Europe’ facility. The UK abstained from the partial general approach agreed on this dossier at the June Transport Council. While we were broadly supportive of the text of the regulation we could not formally support agreement to the draft regulations in advance of an agreement on the overall Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;) negotiations as this could prejudge the overall &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The UK supports the thrust of the proposal in introducing a clearer, stable governance arrangement for the programme but has concerns that some of the European Parliament’s proposed amendments, such as the introduction of funding for applications to use the navigation systems, could have significant financial implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will adopt conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The UK welcomed this timely communication from the Commission and has been actively engaged in the drafting of Council conclusions. We support the broad aims of the communication – liberalisation of aviation and fair competition – and we are pushing to ensure that the Council’s conclusions reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will also adopt a proposal for a Council decision on the signature, on behalf of the EU, and provisional application of the Euro-Mediterranean aviation agreement between the EU and its member states, on the one part, and the State of Israel, on the other. The UK supports the signature and implementation of this agreement which forms a part of the EU’s external aviation policy to negotiate comprehensive air services agreements with neighbouring countries. This agreement will supersede the current bilateral agreements between individual member states and Israel. It aims at gradual market opening, promoting regulatory (e.g. safety) harmonisation and the promotion of open and fair competition between air carriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This agreement will integrate the Israeli aviation market into the European single market accompanied by convergence with EU aviation regulations. It will enhance opportunities for EU airlines and investors in Israel, provide consumer benefits as a result of increased competition and better access, and help to strengthen the economic links between the EU and Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the Commission will provide information on the cleaner power for transport package and aviation emissions trading scheme (&lt;abbr title="emissions trading scheme"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57054</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-highways-and-rail-schemes-amendments-to-planning-act-2008-definitions"/>
    <title>Nationally significant highways and rail schemes: amendments to Planning Act 2008 definitions</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is on proposals to amend the definitions of ‘nationally significant’ rail and highways projects set out in the Planning Act 2008. The aim of this is to speed up the completion of projects and reduce the costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57524</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"/>
    <title>Port marine safety code</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The port marine safety code establishes a national standard for every aspect of port marine safety and aims to enhance safety for those who use or work in ports, their ships, passengers and the environment. The code applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56774</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-ec-392-2009"/>
    <title>Consultation on the implementation of EU Regulation (EC) 392/2009</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the UK’s draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation gives effect, within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention to create parity for the passenger shipping industry and help ensure that UK citizens have access to the same levels of compensation when travelling between two different &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states. Furthermore, it increases the limits of liabilities for death or personal injuries to passengers being carried by sea; requires carriers to have compulsory insurance, and provides claimants with the right of taking direct action against the insurers. The intended effect is to provide an enhanced framework of compensation in the event of death or personal injury to a passenger, or the loss or damage to luggage when travelling on a sea journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation also brings into scope certain domestic passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56725</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"/>
    <title>Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation guidance for suppliers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of it comes from sustainable renewable sources. Guidance has been in place to assist suppliers with compliance since the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; was first introduced. Obligated suppliers are consulted each year on revisions to the guidance. These have taken into account the latest European and domestic legislative developments and experience in operating the obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"&gt;Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56290</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/industry-launches-new-rail-technical-strategy"/>
    <title>Industry launches new rail technical strategy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail industry leaders have outlined a 30 year vision for the railway through a new edition of the ‘Rail technical strategy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Rail technical strategy’ describes how technology can help the railway increase capacity, improve reliability, cut carbon emissions and reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy has been developed by the Technical Strategy Leadership Group – a cross-industry expert body with representatives from across the rail industry – and endorsed by the Rail Delivery Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.futurerailway.org"&gt;Read the Rail technical strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Transport  Simon Burns MP welcomed the strategy saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the industry picking up the baton to develop this Rail technical strategy. Technology has a vital role to play in improving the railway’s performance, cutting its costs along with carbon emissions and delivering a better travelling experience for passengers. By setting in place a 30 year vision, the railway is demonstrating that it has a bright and exciting future, and the potential to support our economy and society for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57003</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"/>
    <title>Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport asked Ecofys to produce a report on the current animal fat (tallow) market to assess whether there has been any impact from allowing double counting of biodiesel produced from category 1 tallow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to explain the issue, the risks, and the available data relating to the tallow market to enable the department to set out its approach to monitoring impacts and also seek stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"&gt;Consultation about the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation suppliers’ guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56448</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T17:28:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:28:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/revisions-to-the-levels-of-funding-required-by-goods-and-public-service-vehicle-licence-holders"/>
    <title>Revisions to the levels of funding required by goods and public service vehicle licence holders</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has given notice of revisions to the levels of funding required by holders of goods and public service vehicle operators’ licences operating for hire or reward. This is a requirement of EU Regulation 1071/2009 which affects holders of standard national and standard international licences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Traffic Commissioners retain their discretion to set the financial standing levels for restricted licence holders (not covered by the regulation) and they propose to maintain the current rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revised figures are set out below and are based on the euro exchange rate on the first working day in October 2012 – as prescribed by EU Regulation 1071/2009. The new rates will come into force on 1 January 2013 and will remain in place until the 31 December 2013 (previous rates are in brackets). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Minimum financial level requirement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standard national and standard international licences&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a. first vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,200 (£7,700)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b. each additional vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,000, ( £4,200)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Restricted licences&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a. first vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,100 ( £3,100)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b. each additional vehicle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,700 ( £1,700)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="note-to-editors"&gt;Note to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The financial limits set by EU Regulation 1071/2009 are 9000 euros for the first vehicle and 5000 euros for each subsequent vehicle. For member states not participating in monetary union, the regulation requires the equivalent in their currencies to be revised every year, using the euro exchange rate published in the Official Journal of the European Union on the first working day of October in the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
