<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/65301</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sweet-deal-for-growth-in-birmingham"/>
    <title>Sweet deal for growth in Birmingham</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A raft of initiatives to boost economic growth in Birmingham will be on the agenda today as Business Minister Michael Fallon visits the city to champion government support for the area’s economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will be putting the seal of approval to a new deal to cut red tape for Mondelez International, owner of the Cadbury’s brand which will reduce duplication and costs whilst maintaining high safety standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal, known as a primary authority partnership, means Birmingham City Council will provide advice to all of Mondelez International’s UK sites on regulations including food safety and hygiene and has already lead to Mondelez International cutting £250,000 in packaging costs alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Fallon will then visit Quality Plated Products (QPP), a manufacturing company in Great Barr who have been awarded a loan of £245,000 from the government’s Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative. The company uses a unique technology to supply metal plated plastic to the automotive industry. Thanks to the government support it will be increasing capacity, creating an additional 11 jobs and starting a new apprenticeship scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Birmingham has long been an engine of the country’s economy, and my tour around the city has shown that’s certainly the case today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is doing all it can to support the West Midlands; whether that’s direct support through our Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative to companies like QPP, rolling out ultra fast broadband, or helping household names like Cadbury by reducing the amount of red tape they have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By taking clear and decisive action and giving direct help to companies and regions they can realise their growth potential and compete in the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister’s tour will also see him visiting Aero Engine Controls, a leading aerospace and defence manufacturing company. This is part of a series visits today by Business Ministers to discuss how business and government can work more effectively together to tackle barriers to growth, boost exports and grow high value jobs in the UK. The Minister will also meet members of the Greater Birmingham and Solihull Local Enterprise Partnership to discuss their ‘Strategy for Growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships can be formed to cover key aspects of environmental health, trading standards and fire safety services, including health and safety, fair trading, food standards and product safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are now more than 600 businesses and 97 local authorities operating one or more of the 2,016 primary authority partnerships. The scheme covers more than 58,500 premises. 37% of businesses involved are SMEs. It was introduced in 2009 and is administered by the Better Regulation Delivery Office (BRDO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative is a national fund of up to £125m to create more competitive supply chains, sustain or create new employment opportunities, and create better synergies and sustained collaborative relationships throughout supply chains that participate in this initiative. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx"&gt;http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s industrial strategy is about looking to the future, presenting a long-term, whole of government approach to supporting British business, giving them the confidence they need to invest, hire staff and grow. Long-term strategies are being developed in partnership with industry in key sectors including aerospace, nuclear, and the information economy - the aerospace strategy will be published in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/65413</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T09:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training"/>
    <title>Improving the quality of further education and skills training</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Introducing a new FE funding system, improving teacher training and apprenticeships
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The further education (&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt;) system – the colleges and training providers that teach vocational qualifications and skills – needs to guarantee students high quality teaching and courses to help students into jobs or university and create the skilled workforce employers need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve quality and efficiency in &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; and skills training, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing a new funding system based on student loans: it’s for people aged 24+, studying at levels 3 and 4, or for advanced and higher apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freeing colleges from central government control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; teacher training more professional&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing better careers advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a new traineeships programme to support young people, aged 16 to 24, to develop skills for employment, including apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for funding post-16 learning in England is shared between the Department for Education (16-18 year olds) and the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (19 year olds and over).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, an independent review of further education, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.education.gov.uk/publications/eOrderingDownload/The%20Wolf%20Report.pdf"&gt;the Review of Vocational Education&lt;/a&gt; made a number of recommendations including that we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move to ‘per-student’ funding instead of ‘per-qualification’ funding, to make institutions more accountable to learners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the quality of apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government then carried out a public consultation to invite opinions on these recommendations &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/new-challenges-new-chances-next-steps-in-implementing-the-further-education-reform-programme"&gt;New challenges, new chances: next steps in implementing the further education reform programme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the responses to the consultation, the government published its plans, in December 2011, for the &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; sector in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-investment-statement-for-2011-to-2014-new-challenges-new-chances" title="New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan"&gt;New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will shortly publish an update on ‘New challenges, new chances’. This will explain the progress we have made in reforming the further education and skills system. We have already published a number of reports and plans on aspects of the system, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-for-sustainable-growth-strategy-document"&gt;Skills for sustainable growth&lt;/a&gt;, which sets out the national skills strategy for England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/11-1380-further-education-skills-system-reform-plan.pdf"&gt;Our plan for further education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/s/12-p172-skills-funding-statement-2012-2015.pdf"&gt;Skills funding statement 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;, which contains our budget for skills and the numbers of learners it will support for the next 2 years, set out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our strategy for investing £550 million in college facilities in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/12-1340-further-education-college-capital-investment-strategy-plan.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; college capital investment strategy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jason Holt’s independent report on apprenticeships and small businesses, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/making-apprenticeships-more-accessible-to-small-and-medium-sized-enterprises-a-review-by-jason-holt"&gt;Making apprenticeships more accessible to small and medium-sized enterprises: a review by Jason Holt&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doug Richard’s independent report for the government on the future of apprenticeships, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-richard-review-of-apprenticeships"&gt;The Richard review of apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans to set up chartered status for the further education sector, to help institutions celebrate their success and reputation, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/chartered-status-for-the-further-education-sector-proposals-to-create-a-chartered-status-scheme-for-further-education-institutions-consultation"&gt;Chartered status for the further education sector&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/chartered-status-for-further-education-institutions-design-competition"&gt;Chartered status design competition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the report by Lord Lingfield on how the further education sector can best serve its users’ needs, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/professionalism-in-further-education-final-report-of-the-independent-review-panel"&gt;Professionalism in further education: final report of the Independent Review Panel&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;advice for further education colleges and training providers on 24+ Advanced Learning Loans, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.practitioners.slc.co.uk/further-education.aspx"&gt;24+ Advanced Learning Loans Student Loans Company learning provider services&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://readingroom.skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/sfa/24plusall_updated_guide_and_faqs_may_2012.pdf"&gt;Skills Funding Agency loans - FAQs for further education providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ours and our partners’ plans to ensure that young people and adults get the advice they need on learning and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-careers-service-the-right-advice-at-the-right-time"&gt;National Careers Service: the right advice at the right time&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our proposals for piloting community learning trusts, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;Community Learning Trust prospectus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans for engaging 16 to 24 year-olds in education, training and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/16-24-education-training-and-work-strategy-and-reforms"&gt;Building engagement, building futures: our strategy to maximise the participation of 16-24 year olds in education, training and work&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/21/contents/enacted" title="Education Act 2011"&gt;Education Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier for colleges to make their own decisions. It means that &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; colleges can now borrow money without needing permission from the government. Colleges can also change the way they govern themselves, and those rated ‘outstanding’ by Ofsted no longer have to face routine inspections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/"&gt;UK Commission for Employment &amp;amp; Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/the-national-careers-council"&gt;National Careers Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/64318</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T14:25:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:25:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair"/>
    <title>Making the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is changing employment laws to encourage companies to hire staff while protecting employee rights. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses say current employment laws are difficult to cope with and put them off taking on staff. This slows the growth of businesses and the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simpler, more flexible employment laws will make it easier for companies to hire and manage staff, while protecting basic workers’ rights. This should encourage employers to create new jobs, supporting enterprise and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair the government is: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/reviewing-employment-law" title="to make them more flexible for employers and employees"&gt;reviewing employment laws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/introducing-more-flexible-working-practices" title="introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers"&gt;introducing more flexible working practices for parents and older workers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/setting-and-enforcing-the-national-minimum-wage" title="setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates"&gt;setting and enforcing National Minimum Wage rates&lt;/a&gt;  to protect workers from exploitation and businesses from unfair competition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/encouraging-modern-workplaces-and-flexible-working" title="making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments"&gt;making it easier for businesses to employ people and for employees to balance work and family commitments&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/providing-guidance-on-employment-law" title="providing better guidance on employment law"&gt;providing better guidance on employment law&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/enforcing-standards-in-employment-agencies-and-employment-businesses-and-recruitment-agencies" title="enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies"&gt;enforcing standards in employment agencies and employment businesses and recruitment agencies&lt;/a&gt; to better protect workers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/supporting-pages/researching-the-labour-market" title="researching the labour market"&gt;researching the labour market&lt;/a&gt; to produce data on employment relations, the labour market and equality at work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We agreed to review employment law in May 2010 as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition-agreement-may-2010_0.pdf" title="Coalition Agreement"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulations launched in April 2011 and includes a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/employment-related-law/" title="review of employment law"&gt;review of employment law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extended the time you need to be employed to be able to claim for unfair dismissal from 1 to 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-bill-policy-paper" title="Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill"&gt;Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill&lt;/a&gt; which will make changes to the employment tribunal system, including ensuring all employment tribunal claims go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acas.org.uk/index.aspx?articleid=1461" title="Acas"&gt;Acas&lt;/a&gt; and introducing a simpler process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removed the compulsory retirement age, making it easier for older people to carry on working&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;launched a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Regional-Mediation-Pilot-Schemes-up-and-running-67b90.aspx"&gt;pilot scheme&lt;/a&gt; encouraging the use of mediation to resolve disputes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reviewed how employment rights are enforced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-consulting"&gt;Who we are consulting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out consultations on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/r/11-511-resolving-workplace-disputes-consultation"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt; more quickly without having to go to an employment tribunal &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules" title="Collective Redundancies: Consultation on changes to the rules"&gt;changing the rules on large-scale redundancies&lt;/a&gt;  so that employers can restructure more effectively while also carrying out good quality consultations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/e/12-1037-ending-the-employment-relationship-consultation.pdf" title="changing the rules on ending the employment relationship"&gt;changing the rules on ending the employment relationship&lt;/a&gt;, the use of settlement agreements and changes to the compensation limit in unfair dismissal cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/employment-tribunal-rules-review-by-mr-justice-underhill"&gt;changing employment tribunal rules&lt;/a&gt; to make them more flexible and effective and to get better value for the taxpayer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve carried out an impact assessment on the benefits of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/r/11-1381-resolving-workplace-disputes-final-impact-assessment"&gt;resolving workplace disputes&lt;/a&gt;. We estimate these changes will save businesses £40 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64952</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T13:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T13:15:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-viscount-younger-of-leckie-appointed-as-business-minister"/>
    <title>The Viscount Younger of Leckie appointed as Business Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Lord Younger appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger was appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills, by the Prime Minister today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger will be responsible for all of the  Department for Business Innovation and Skills business in the House of Lords, in particular steering the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill through its final stages in the Lords. He will also have responsibility for the Intellectual Property portfolio. Lord Younger was previously a Government Whip in the House of Lords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Lord Younger said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have been asked by the Prime Minister to do this important job; the business department is central to the Government’s drive for balanced and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I look forward to making a real contribution to supporting business to generate new private sector employment and boost our international competiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to entering the House of Lords Lord Younger had a 25 year career in the human resources industry and financial services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Full list of Lord Younger’s Ministerial responsibilities will be published shortly. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/64300</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"/>
    <title>Countering weapons proliferation </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Securing global safety by preventing countries and terrorists access to the materials needed for weapons of mass destruction.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of weapons of mass destruction (&lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;) poses a threat to the UK and the international community. Indiscriminate trade in conventional arms and the use of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (&lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt;) weapons and ballistic missiles raises serious humanitarian and security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working around the world to champion and implement UK policies as set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the spread of &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; weapons and ballistic missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works with international partners and through organisations such as the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, G8, NATO and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce terrorists’ ability to create, obtain or use &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; materials and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the FCO’s tools to combat these threats is our Counter-Proliferation Programme. In the financial year 2012 to 13, the value of the programme is £3 million. This funding is used to support projects around the world which increase political will or technical capacity to reduce the threat of weapons proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-counter-proliferation-strategy"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in March 2012. The strategy’s main aims are to deny terrorists the materials and expertise to make and use &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;; to stop countries such as Iran and North Korea from obtaining &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt; or advanced conventional weapons; and to build up the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/About/"&gt;International Atomic Energy Agency (&lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; and other organisations and treaties that help us meet our goals through the international community and which help to protect global security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemical-weapons"&gt;Chemical weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the destruction of remaining chemical weapons stocks and works to encourage full national implementation of the Chemical Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;) by all countries. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/the-chemical-weapons-convention"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention&lt;/a&gt; bans the development, production, stockpiling and use of chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biological-weapons"&gt;Biological weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has signed up to the global implementation of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/04FBBDD6315AC720C1257180004B1B2F?OpenDocument"&gt;Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of the convention is to help prevent states acquiring or keeping biological and toxin weapons, and prevent them ever being used by states or terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt; doesn’t have a verification system like that of the &lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Participating countries are required to submit relevant data and declarations, or confidence-building measures, to the United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs. This increases openness and gives participating countries confidence that others are complying with the convention. The UK’s confidence building measures are published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/CEC2E2D361ADFEE7C12572BC0032F058?OpenDocument"&gt;Implementation Support Unit website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-weapons"&gt;Nuclear weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;. The UK is one of 189 states that have signed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The treaty aims to stop the spread of nuclear weapons and ultimately eliminate them. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; has three equally important ‘pillars’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to work towards non-proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to champion nuclear disarmament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nuclear-security"&gt;Nuclear security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK will continue work to strengthen international nuclear security by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the security of fissile materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing the number of sites containing nuclear and radiological material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing the acquisition of proliferation-relevant information and expertise by terrorists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through the successful development of the UK’s Global Threat Reduction Programme we are reducing the threats posed by nuclear and radiological materials and expertise in vulnerable locations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting the full implementation of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sc8076.doc.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Resolution 1540&lt;/a&gt;, which requires all states to refrain from supporting non-government agents from developing, acquiring, manufacturing, possessing, transporting, transferring or using nuclear, chemical or biological weapons and their delivery systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK also supports and contributes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nti.org/treaties-and-regimes/global-partnership-against-spread-weapons-and-materials-mass-destruction-10-plus-10-over-10-program/"&gt;Global Partnership Against the Spread of Weapons and Materials of Mass Destruction&lt;/a&gt;, agreed at the G8 Summit at Kananaskis, Canada in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-programmes"&gt;State programmes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the international legal framework, conventions and treaties, some countries have active programmes to develop and produce &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Of particular concern is Iran’s nuclear programme; the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s nuclear programme and willingness to provide weapons to other countries; and Syria’s possession of chemical and biological weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works through various international organisations to seek peaceful means to reduce the threat from these programmes and the networks that support them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arms-trade-treaty"&gt;Arms Trade Treaty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a legitimate arms trade, there is also an urgent need for more effective and coherent international regulation of that trade. The UK is working to achieve an international arms trade treaty to provide clearer and more effective control of the illegal arms trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; conference in July 2012 was unable to adopt an Arms Trade Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, the UK will continue to play a leading role in future negotiations to help to secure one. An &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to reduce the flow of weapons from legitimate trade to the illicit market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; process towards an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; and submissions from states (including the UK’s views on an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/first/63/documentation.shtml"&gt;United Nations General Assembly website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="export-licensing"&gt;Export licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has joined other governments around the world to pursue &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/3849543/eu-arms-export"&gt;collective implementation of export controls&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the proliferation of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The 4 main export control regimes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.australiagroup.net/en/index.html"&gt;Australia Group&lt;/a&gt; - designed to harmonise export control measures aimed at curtailing the unhindered proliferation of chemical weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mtcr.info/english/index.html"&gt;Missile Technology Control Regime&lt;/a&gt; - an informal and voluntary association of countries that share the goal of non-proliferation of unmanned delivery systems of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/Leng/default.htm"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt; - responsible for making sure nuclear export controls work in practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt; - established to promote transparency and greater responsiblity in transfers of conventional arms and dual-use goods and technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read further details about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s regulatory authority responsible for assessing and issuing strategic export licences to UK exporters is the Export Control Organisation (ECO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS). Read more about the UK’s policies and procedures for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2"&gt;controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;) was born out of fear that the Cold War era would lead to a nuclear arms race and is still the basis of the international nuclear non-proliferation regime. All states are now party to it apart from India, Israel, Pakistan and South Sudan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; provides for a Review Conference every 5 years, both to review developments over the previous 5 years and to look ahead to the future. At the last &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;Review Conference in 2010&lt;/a&gt; a series of action plans were agreed to enhance implementation of the treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/"&gt;The International Atomic Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt; was set up as the world’s ‘Atoms for Peace’ organisation in 1957 within the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; family, and supports the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The agency is at the centre of international efforts to address Iran’s nuclear dossier and to ensure the benefits of safe and secure peaceful nuclear energy are accessible to everyone, not just to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thenuclearsecuritysummit.org/eng_main/main.jsp"&gt;Seoul Nuclear Security Summit&lt;/a&gt; assembled 53 countries, the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; and Interpol, to continue work to secure vulnerable nuclear material around the world within 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 December 2008 in the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly, 133 States voted in favour of a draft resolution ‘Towards an Arms Trade Treaty’. There was a clear majority view that, working together, the international community can shape an Arms Trade Treaty into an effective legally binding mechanism to regulate the international trade in arms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our detailed guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-embargoes-and-restrictions"&gt;sanctions, embargoes and restrictions.&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/current-arms-embargoes-and-other-restrictions"&gt;Current arms embargoes and other restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the Common Foreign and Security Policy (&lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; applies restrictive measures in pursuit of the specific &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; objectives set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/treaties/index.htm"&gt;Treaty on European Union.&lt;/a&gt; (see particularly Article 11)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; External Action website&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of restrictive measures adopted in the framework of the &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; that are currently in force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/sc/committees/list_compend.shtml"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Sanctions Committees website&lt;/a&gt; contains links to the latest versions of all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council targeted sanctions lists. The individuals and entities included in these lists are subject to the relevant measures imposed by the Security Council, and all member states are obliged to implement these measures. Each separate list is maintained by the relevant Security Council Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64302</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/building-materials-and-components-statistics-december-2012"/>
    <title>Building materials and components statistics: December 2012</title>
    <category>Statistical data set</category>
    <summary>Statistics and analysis on the construction sector
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presents information on selected building materials, including monthly data on price indices, bricks, cement and concrete blocks. It also presents quarterly data on sand and gravel, slate, concrete roofing tiles, ready-mixed concrete and imports and exports of construction products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69439"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/thumbnail_13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48973/13-313a-construction-building-materials-bulletin-december-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/313A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;481 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;40 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69440"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48974/13-313a-data-construction-building-materials-tables-december-2012.xls" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48974/13-313a-data-construction-building-materials-tables-december-2012.xls"&gt;Building materials and components: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/313A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Excel Spreadsheet&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;687 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69441"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/thumbnail_13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48975/13-p125a-construction-building-materials-commentary-december-2012.pdf"&gt;Building materials and components commentary: December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
        &lt;span class="references"&gt;Ref: &lt;span class="unique_reference"&gt;BIS/13/P125A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;102 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;11 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64919</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-workforce-management-november-2012"/>
    <title>BIS workforce management: November 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Management information on staff numbers and paybill costs in BIS, its agencies and executive non-departmental public bodies</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For workforce numbers, both payroll and non-payroll (contingent labour, including consultants) information is provided, split between full-time equivalents (FTE) and headcount, with payroll staff numbers mapped to standard Civil Service grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For costs, payroll paybill information is broken down into its component parts ie salaries, allowances, employers pensions contributions etc. For non-payroll costs, these are split between costs for consultancy and those of other non-payroll workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covers November of the financial year 2012 to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/64915</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T14:27:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-workforce-management-april-2012-to-october-2012"/>
    <title>BIS workforce management: April 2012 to November 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Management information on staff numbers and paybill costs in BIS, its agencies and executive non-departmental public bodies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For workforce numbers, both payroll and non-payroll (contingent labour, including consultants) information is provided, split between full-time equivalents (FTE) and headcount, with payroll staff numbers mapped to standard Civil Service grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For costs, payroll paybill information is broken down into its component parts i.e. salaries, allowances, employers pensions contributions etc. For non-payroll costs, these are split between costs for consultancy and those of other non-payroll workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covers April to November of the financial year 2012 to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64247</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-geraint-jones-appointed-as-reviewer-for-the-office-for-fair-access"/>
    <title>Press Release: Geraint Jones appointed as reviewer for the Office For Fair Access</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, announced today that he is appointing Geraint Jones as the statutory reviewer for OFFA. Should a university or college object to a provisional decision by the Director of Fair Access, the reviewer can be asked to assess the case impartially. He may recommend that there are grounds for the Director to reconsider his decision.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geraint Jones QC was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge before going to the Bar in 1976. He took silk in 2001 and is now recognised as a leading commercial and Chancery practitioner with extensive experience of judicial review work. He has an undoubted reputation for fearless independence and impartiality in upholding the rule of law. He sits as a Recorder and as a part-time Judge of the Tax Tribunal. He is also an arbitrator at the International Court of Arbitration for Sport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that Geraint Jones will be the reviewer for OFFA, his skills and experience, if called upon, will be of great value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The position of statutory reviewer for OFFA has been in place since OFFA was established in 2004. So far there has been no need to call upon the services of the statutory reviewer. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the ‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB), published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
