<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/driving-standards-agency</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/driving-standards-agency.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Driving Standards Agency</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64184</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-driving-tests-at-halfords"/>
    <title>Green light for driving tests at Halfords</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans to offer practical driving tests from branches of Halfords have been given the go ahead by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving tests will be available from the Halfords store in Wellingborough from Tuesday 5 February. Other branches of Halfords across the country are expected to start offering tests in coming months. All tests will be conducted by Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) examiners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move is part of an initiative to offer a more local service for driving test candidates. As well as using conventional test centres, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working with public and private sector partners to provide driving tests in areas that don’t have a local test centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very pleased to be working with Halfords to provide a more local service for driving test candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great example of working with private sector partners to provide an important local service that is convenient as well as being cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfords Commercial Director, Paul McClenaghan, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Halfords is already a local destination for motorists, who come to us for a diverse range of automotive products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re always seeking new ways in which to enhance our offer, so working with the Driving Standards Agency is a natural fit for the business and extends the help we are able to provide to motorists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is currently consulting on proposals to improve the way all motoring services are delivered. The &lt;a href="/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy" title="Motoring Services Strategy"&gt;Motoring Services Strategy&lt;/a&gt; consultation outlines long term proposals to put customers firmly at the heart of the way motoring services are delivered, so that they best serve the consumer while getting the best possible deal for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56606</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-monitoring-in-dsa-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Equality monitoring in DSA 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An analysis of staff diversity in DSA, for staff in post between 1 April 2011 and 31 March 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An analysis of staff diversity, for staff in post between 1 April 2011 and 31 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis looks at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;staff in post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cessations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grievances and discipline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness absence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;performance marking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recruitment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It considers whether there were significant differences with respect to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;race&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pay band&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;age&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sexual orientation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;religion and belief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/64057</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T17:16:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T17:16:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/drink-drive-rehabilitation-scheme-ddrs-course-approval-and-quality-assurance-model"/>
    <title>Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (DDRS): course approval and quality assurance model</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>A breakdown of the application for Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (DDRS) courses and how the courses will be quality assured.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The breakdown of the application for approval for DDR includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="initial-approval"&gt;1. Initial approval&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.1 An applicant seeking approval to deliver a Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (DDRS) course must provide the required evidence to demonstrate how they meet the specified criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.2 The initial approval decision will be made by a desk-based analysis of ‘self certified’ evidence provided by the applicant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3 The provider of the approved course will thereafter be required to periodically provide the Driving Standards Agency (DSA) with data to enable ongoing, risk-based, quality management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="course-content"&gt;Course content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants must be able to provide evidence that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.1 The course content and learning materials clearly link to the desired outcome of the current DSA DDRS Syllabus (published by the Secretary of State for Transport) and ultimately the DSA National Driving Standard (Category B)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.2 The course content links to the theoretical and professional models and adult learning principles which underpin the Syllabus 
.
1.3.3 The course they intend to deliver is capable of providing an appropriate, client-centred, response to the learning needs of offenders:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;taking into consideration different learning styles and varying levels of ability&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;regardless of their gender, race, sexual orientation, religion or belief and with particular reference to those groups within the category B driving population defined as ‘vulnerable’ (young persons (17-18 years ), the elderly  and those with a recognised learning or physical disability)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="course-delivery-arrangements"&gt;Course delivery arrangements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants must be able to provide evidence that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.4 The course, including the delivery and administration arrangements, aligns with the DDRS course guidance published by DSA on behalf of the Secretary of State for Transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.5 They employ, or have access to, sufficient suitably qualified trainers to deliver the proposed course consistently to an appropriate standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NB It is not a formal requirement that every member of staff should be able to evidence the full range of competences required to deliver DDRS. For example, individuals may be employed to deliver specific elements of the syllabus e.g. information about crash statistics. In these circumstances applicants must explain how they intend to deploy individual staff to ensure the full requirements of the syllabus will be delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.6   They have in place resources, including access to premises which comply with relevant health and safety regulations, are conducive to learning and provide appropriate levels of confidentiality for all those taking part, sufficient to meet demand in all the specified areas covered by their application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.7  They have in place plans for the deployment of staff sufficient to ensure the security of all staff involved in delivery and to meet demand in all specified geographical areas covered by their application&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.8   A recognised method of course and trainer evaluation (such as the Kirkpatrick four level training evaluation model ) will be operated in order to confirm, as a minimum, that Reaction (level 1) and Transfer of Learning (level 2) have taken place, demonstrating that each offender has gained a basic level of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.9. Processes are in place to ensure all staff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;understand their duty of care, and the limits of their competence, in relation to individuals who request further assistance or who present evidence of harmful or dependent drinking and who may benefit from medical support&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;know how to provide guidance to individuals who request further assistance &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="course-administration-arrangements"&gt;Course administration arrangements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.10 Applicants must provide evidence processes in place to capture and respond to customer complaints&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.11 Applicants must provide evidence that they have suitable processes and procedures in place to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;record the number of referred offenders from court&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record the number of referred offenders transferred from and to another DDRS course provider&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify the percentage of referred offenders who begin the course&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify the number of referred offenders who successfully complete the course&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify the reasons referred offenders give for leaving the course before completion &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record complaints received and disposal of complaints&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record and report a summary of course and trainer evaluation findings and related actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensure that all such records are kept accurately and in compliance with the relevant legislation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;assurance that data collected via these processes will be retained in accordance with the requirements of Data Protection legislation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="appropriate-persons"&gt;Appropriate persons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants must provide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.12 Details of the legal status of the organisation making the application&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.13 Details of the key management personnel in the organisation making the application, sufficient to allow the DSA to satisfy itself that there are no other matters which might disqualify them from being appropriate persons to be responsible for an approved DDR course&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.3.14 Details of at least one senior manager who is resident in the UK and who will be the main point of contact, on a day to day basis, for the management of the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.4 DSA will not, normally, require a centre inspection to take place prior to, or as part of, the initial approval process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.5 The case officer responsible for the desk-based analysis of evidence will present their recommendation regarding approval to the appropriate person responsible for approval at the DSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.6 DSA may, on behalf of the Secretary of State, decide to refuse approval of a course, or to grant approval subject to conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.7 Where the appropriate person responsible for approval at DSA feels unable to reach a judgement based on the recommendation, for example, due to uncertainty as to whether the evidence provided meets the approval criteria requirement, they may call on the services of an appropriate expert. However, in the majority of cases any such issues would normally be resolved in the initial review of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.8 DSA must give a decision in writing on each application for approval, on behalf of the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="initial-centre-inspection-and-follow-up"&gt;2. Initial centre inspection and follow-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1 DSA will, normally, undertake an initial centre inspection, within 12 months of a provider being approved to deliver DDRS courses. The cost of this inspection will be covered by the application (for approval) fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.2 DSA will prioritise its programme of centre inspections based on the information available to it. For example, where DSA has not seen evidence demonstrating previous competence in delivery of DDRS or related courses, the provider is likely to be inspected before an organisation which has demonstrated previous competence in delivery of a DDRS or related course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.3 Where a provider has previously demonstrated competence in the delivery of DDRS courses, the inspection may be omitted; so long DSA is confident that no aspect of the provision has changed substantially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.4 During a centre inspection, the case officer will confirm the information given in the provider’s application and seek to give developmental feedback. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.5 DSA will agree a date for the centre inspection with the provider, and give them an outline of what they wish to see during that inspection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.6  A case officer undertaking a centre inspection will produce a report of their findings within 10 working days. That report will be sent to the provider for their information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.7 The report of a centre inspection will include an indication of whether the provision is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compliant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not compliant (subject to areas for development)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2.8 The content of centre inspection reports will be confidential to the provider concerned and DSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.9 Where a case officer reports that provision is ‘Not compliant’ they will inform the provider of the developmental requirements which must be made to resolve any issues, and a date by which those changes must be made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.10 Compliance with any development requirement should be evidenced in written or electronic form within the specified timescale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="quality-assurance"&gt;3 Quality assurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further quality assurance processes, including scheduled and unannounced quality assurance audit inspections, and reporting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.1 DSA may undertake further quality assurance processes, including requiring the provider to produce additional information or making additional audit inspections, either to the administration centre or to course delivery locations, during the provider’s period of approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.2 Further requirements to provide information or to conduct additional centre inspections will be evidence lead, informed by the initial centre inspections, follow-up and other relevant factors, for example complaints received by DSA, inconsistencies in numerical or financial reporting, changes to the organisational structure, changes to training delivery or a change of ownership in total or in part. It is the responsibility of the provider of the approved course to produce the required information to allay any concerns that might arise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.3 The schedule for quality assurance visits (including scheduled and unannounced quality assurance audit inspections, either to the administration centre and/or to course delivery locations) will be determined by DSA on risk-based criteria. However, each provider should expect to receive at least one quality assurance inspection during their period of approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.4 DSA will normally agree an appropriate date for a centre or course delivery inspection, with the provider and give them an outline of what they wish to see during that inspection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.5 The duration of any centre or course delivery inspection will be the minimum time required to allow the case officer to have confidence in their conclusions, and for the provider to make available any information that they believe is relevant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.6 Where DSA has reason to believe that some aspect of a course is being delivered or managed inappropriately, it reserves the right to make unannounced inspections (either to the administration centre and/or to course delivery locations).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.7 Centre or course delivery inspections may cover any aspect of provision, but DSA will be evidence led. DSA will not, normally, require the provider to produce additional documentation beyond the agreed reporting requirements, unless there is clear reason to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.8 The report of a quality assurance inspection will include indication of whether the provision is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;outstanding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;satisfactory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inadequate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;3.9 Where a case officer reports that provision is ‘Inadequate’ they will inform the provider of the changes which must be made to resolve any issues, and a date by which those changes must be made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.10 Failure to make required changes by the agreed date following an ‘Inadequate’ classification may result in DSA issuing a 28 day notification of being minded to suspend or withdraw approval to deliver DDRS courses, dependent on the severity of findings underpinning the classification, and any non-compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.11 Compliance with any requirement to change should be evidenced in written or electronic form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.12 Where a case officer reports that provision is ‘Satisfactory’ they will inform the provider of developments and actions recommended for improving the provision and outcomes of the course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.13 Whether as part of a centre or course inspection or through other information or investigation DSA is satisfied that there is serious misconduct on the part of the course provider, or a person acting on behalf, or under the direction of the course provider, approval will be withdrawn without delay. Under these circumstances, DSA on behalf of the Secretary of State, will indicate the reason for the withdrawal of approval and, if appropriate, the nature of any serious misconduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69047"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48932/dsa-ddrs-course-approval-evidence-requirement.rtf" aria-describedby="attachment-69047-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48932/dsa-ddrs-course-approval-evidence-requirement.rtf" aria-describedby="attachment-69047-accessibility-help"&gt;DDRS course approval evidence requirement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rich Text Format"&gt;RTF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;217 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69047-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20DDRS%20course%20approval%20evidence%20requirement%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27DDRS%20course%20approval%20evidence%20requirement%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("DDRS course approval evidence requirement").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h3 id="grade-4-outstanding"&gt;Grade 4: Outstanding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service that delivers well above minimum requirements for users&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="grade-3-good"&gt;Grade 3: Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service that consistently delivers above minimum requirements for users&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="grade-2-satisfactory"&gt;Grade 2: Satisfactory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service that delivers only minimum requirements for users&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="grade-1-inadequate"&gt;Grade 1: Inadequate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service that does not deliver minimum requirements for users&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/64034</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T17:15:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T17:15:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/drink-drive-rehabilitation-scheme-ddrs-application-for-course-approval"/>
    <title>Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (DDRS): application for course approval </title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>DDRS aims to provide an educational opportunity for convicted drink-drivers to discourage reoffending and reduce road casualties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) was introduced to provide an educational opportunity for convicted drink-drivers. Organisations wishing to seek approval for &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; courses should apply to the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) who will make the approvals decision on behalf of the Secretary of State. Information on how to do this is provided here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We strongly recommend that organisations read the Statutory Guidance for Approved Course Providers, The &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course syllabus and the other relevant documentation before they attempt to compile an application for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations should be familiar with the legal requirements imposed on providers of approved courses, by the legislation relating to the &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1988/53/contents" title="Road Traffic Offenders Act 1988"&gt;Road Traffic Offenders Act 1988&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2939/contents/made" title="The Rehabilitation Courses (Relevant Drink Offences) Regulations 2012"&gt;The Rehabilitation Courses (Relevant Drink Offences) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Statutory Guidance for Approved Course Providers &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The application for course approval requires organisations to explain what arrangements they will operate in order to meet the approvals criteria and how the operation of those arrangements will be evidenced (ie recorded). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have fully completed all sections before sending it to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, as insufficient information will delay your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will be unable to consider an application until the application fee is paid in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="applicant-and-areas"&gt;Applicant and areas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 1 of the application form concerns the organisation applying for &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval and where, should approval be granted, they intend to deliver their approved course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that, if course approval is granted, it will be granted to the legal entity whose details have been entered here. If this legal entity ceases to exist, eg a sole trader becomes a limited company or an approved organisation is merged with or acquired by another organisation, then the initial course approval will no longer be valid. The approval cannot be transferred, sold or otherwise passed from one legal entity to another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the nature or identity of the legal entity is unclear from the details provided, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will seek clarification and no approval will be granted until such clarification is received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ddrs-specified-geographic-areas"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; specified geographic areas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; courses are offered in 22 specified geographic areas in England and Scotland only. Wales will implement its own provision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each provider will need to indicate the specified areas for which they seek course approval. You can download a map and list of the different areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69038"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48927/dsa-ddrs-specified-geographic-areas.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-69038-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48927/thumbnail_dsa-ddrs-specified-geographic-areas.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48927/dsa-ddrs-specified-geographic-areas.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-69038-accessibility-help"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; specified geographic areas and court list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;2.73 MB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;8 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69038-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20DDRS%20specified%20geographic%20areas%20and%20court%20list%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27DDRS%20specified%20geographic%20areas%20and%20court%20list%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; specified geographic areas and court list").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that a prospective course provider will be required to supply evidence demonstrating that they could deliver sufficient course provision to meet demand within those specified geographical area(s). Course approval may be suspended or withdrawn if it appears they are unable to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each applicant will be able to apply for approval to provide a course in as many of the specified geographical areas as they wish, provided they can satisfy the approval criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course approval is granted within specific geographical area(s). If a provider wishes to deliver courses in a different geographical area they will have to send a new course application and pay the relevant fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="course-content-and-delivery"&gt;Course content and delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 2 of the application form requests information relating to the content and delivery of the course the prospective provider wishes to be approved. This includes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;outlines of course plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how the course fits with the &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; syllabus and statutory guidance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adjustments that the provider will make to the course to allow full learning and participation for those with specific learning needs or disabilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those whose first language is not English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition a prospective provider should supply information on course and trainer evaluation processes. The provider is also required to submit with the course approval application, examples of the learning materials which will be provided to course participants. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; courses must be approved by the Secretary of State (SoS) and comply with the &lt;a href="/drink-drive-rehabilitation-syllabus" title="Drink-drive rehabilitation syllabus"&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course and the course provider must meet certain criteria in order for the Secretary of State to approve the course, these requirements must be maintained throughout the approval period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These criteria are detailed in the guides: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt;): guidance for course providers’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt;): course approval evidence requirement’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69039"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48928/dsa-ddrs-course-approval-evidence-requirement.rtf" aria-describedby="attachment-69039-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48928/dsa-ddrs-course-approval-evidence-requirement.rtf" aria-describedby="attachment-69039-accessibility-help"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval evidence requirement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rich Text Format"&gt;RTF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;217 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69039-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20DDRS%20course%20approval%20evidence%20requirement%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27DDRS%20course%20approval%20evidence%20requirement%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("&lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval evidence requirement").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="facilities-and-trainers"&gt;Facilities and trainers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 3 of the application form focuses on the facilities and trainers the prospective course provider intends to use when delivering the approved course. Information required includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;details of each trainer the prospective provider intends to utilise for course delivery, including relevant experience and qualifications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the addresses of any confirmed premises at which training will be delivered must also be provided (on a separate sheet, or a separate file if the application is submitted electronically)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;details of how staff will be deployed across the specified geographic area(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providers must demonstrate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how they will ensure the security of their staff and the safety of participants attending the course&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that they have considered how they could deliver sufficient course provision to meet demand within the specified geographical area(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="administrative-arrangements"&gt;Administrative arrangements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 4 of the application form is composed of a number of statements, which the prospective provider is asked to confirm by placing a tick in each box. If the statement is not true, the box should be left blank and no tick inserted. If it is found that incorrect information has been given, course approval may be suspended or withdrawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-approvals-and-accreditations"&gt;Other approvals and accreditations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 5 of the application form allows prospective providers an opportunity to supply any details of relevant external approvals or accreditations (such as ISO accreditation) which they wish to bring to the attention of &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; in order to support the course approval application. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="payment-methods"&gt;Payment methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 6 of the application form asks the prospective provider to indicate their preferred method of payment for the application fee, from a choice of cheque, credit/debit card or BACS transfer. If a cheque payment is the preferred method, this should be included with the application form itself; for either of the other options, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will contact the applicant to arrange payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fees"&gt;Fees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a statutory fee of £1,000 for each application for &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval which can be paid by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheque&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;credit or debit card&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BACS transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheques should be sent with the application form. For credit or debit card payment or BACS transfer, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will contact the applicant by telephone to arrange payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course providers will be required to submit to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; a quarterly return indicating the number of offenders who have successfully completed the approved &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A statutory fee of £7 for each offender who completes a &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course during this period will be payable to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Fees are payable to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; no later than 14 days after the close of the reporting period. Payments can be made via cheque, credit/debit card or by BACS transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="course-fees"&gt;Course fees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; aims to reduce drink-drive reoffending. To keep fees affordable to the majority of offenders a maximum course fee of £250 has been set by regulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course providers are free to create a structure of course fees to suit their business models subject to the statutory maximum. Providers are encouraged to keep the structure as clear as possible to avoid confusion for the court(s) and offenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory course guidance requires that each offender must pay the course fees in full before they complete a course, even if they are paying by instalments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-to-apply-for-approval"&gt;How to apply for approval&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, download the application form, fill it in and send it to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_69037"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48926/dsa-ddrs-course-application-form.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-69037-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/48926/dsa-ddrs-course-application-form.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-69037-accessibility-help"&gt;Application for &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;57 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-69037-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Application%20for%20DDRS%20course%20approval%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Application%20for%20DDRS%20course%20approval%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;customer.services@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Application for &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course approval").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;A completed &lt;abbr title="Drink Drive Rehabilitation Scheme"&gt;DDRS&lt;/abbr&gt; course application should contain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all the required information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting information to show compliance with the requirements for approval under the relevant legislation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the relevant fee to enable the application to be processed &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="processing-your-application"&gt;Processing your application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will send an acknowledgement email to confirm receipt of your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application will be processed within 30 days of receipt and the provider will be notified by email of the decision as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;course approval&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;course approval subject to additional conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;course approval refused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If any additional information is required pre-approval, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will contact the designated primary contact, detailing what is required and the date it is required by. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; does not receive the additional information requested within the timescale given, this may prevent &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; from completing the approval process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prospective providers also need to be aware that if &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; cannot complete the approval process within the 30 working day period, due to it being incomplete or invalid, then all documentation will be returned to the centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these circumstances, as approval has not been granted, there is no provision for a refund of the approval fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="granting-course-approval"&gt;Granting course approval&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will grant course approval to any prospective provider that demonstrates that it is able to deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an appropriate course &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using appropriate staff and facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;within the defined specified geographic area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the necessary administrative infrastructure and processes to meet the approval criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="appeal-against-dsas-decision"&gt;Appeal against &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s decision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that if course approval is refused or approval is given subject to additional conditions, the provider has the right to appeal against the decision to the First-tier Tribunal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information regarding appeal arrangements to the First-tier Tribunal will be provided by &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contact &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; if you need any further guidance or clarification on anything in this document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:ddradmin@dsa.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;ddradmin@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 0115 936 6241&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Post Test Operations
&lt;br&gt;Driving Standards Agency
&lt;br&gt;4th Floor, The Axis Building
&lt;br&gt;112 Upper Parliament Street
&lt;br&gt;Nottingham
&lt;br&gt;NG1 6LP
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/59988</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:21:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-06-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 06/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Despatch is the ezine for road safety professionals from the Driving Standards Agency (DSA). You can download issue 06/2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving motoring services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new online service being rolled out to approved driving instructors (&lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADIs&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;booking tests from mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to improve &lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADI&lt;/abbr&gt; check tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better rehabilitation for drink drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; launching an &lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADI&lt;/abbr&gt; theory test DVD-ROM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56299</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:50:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/improving-motoring-services"/>
    <title>Improving motoring services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Consultation to suggest improvements about how motoring services are delivered.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Road users, businesses and other stakeholders were today invited to suggest improvements to the way motoring services such as driving tests and vehicle licensing are delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is putting customers firmly at the heart of the way motoring services are delivered so that they best serve the consumer while getting the best possible deal for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, the Department for Transport is outlining broad reform proposals for the 4 motoring services agencies: Driving Standards Agency (DSA); Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA); Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (VOSA) and the Vehicle Certification Agency (VCA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you drive, run a business or pay taxes you will be a customer of ours and I hope you will have your say about how we can improve the services we offer you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much progress has already been achieved and it is now much easier to use digital services to get driving licences, and sort out vehicle tax. We have also already announced that we are bringing the driving test closer to customers by exploring a range of different locations, such as colleges and retail premises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But there is more that can be done and this consultation is about the government listening to its customers before agreeing the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s 4 agencies are already engaged in programmes of reform to deliver long term financial stability and efficiency, and better services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation sets out a longer term view of the future of these reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Position the agencies at the forefront of digital services, ensuring that those who find access to digital services difficult are supported to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support economic growth and vehicle manufacturing by reforming the Vehicle Certification Agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring the driving test closer to the customer by exploring opportunities to improve convenience to customers. This includes assessing options for the delivery of the practical test. We are keen to explore all options that maintain the integrity of the test and high quality standards whoever is the provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transform &lt;abbr title="heaviy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt;, bus and coach testing by expanding joint ventures and collaboration with private sector providers, and reducing the number of government owned test stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliver better customer services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider rationalising the number of bodies and agencies involved in delivering services - delivering services as simply as possible, increasing flexibility and innovation, improving efficiency and reducing costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 7 March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation is the department’s response to the government’s broader vision for public services as set out in the civil service reform plan, the Open Public Services white paper and the government digital strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/55873</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:48:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy"/>
    <title>Motoring services strategy</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Seeking views on reforms which will put customers and businesses closer to the heart of the 4 motoring services agencies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on reforms which will put customers and businesses closer to the heart of the 4 motoring services agencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/dvla/"&gt;Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/driving-standards-agency"&gt;Driving Standards Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/vca/"&gt;Vehicle Certification Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/vosa/"&gt;Vehicle and Operator Services Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It outlines 6 major drivers which will accomplish this vision. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maximising digital services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reforming the Vehicle Certification Agency to support economic growth and vehicle manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing the driving test closer to the customer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transforming heavy goods vehicle, bus and coach testing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delivering better customer services through dialogue with our customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;defining our organisations to provide better services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/17306</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:42:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T11:42:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dsa-opening-hours-christmas-and-new-year--2"/>
    <title>DSA opening hours: Christmas and New Year</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Driving Standards Agency (DSA) will close at times over Christmas and New Year, but its online services will be available as normal.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s online services will be available throughout Christmas and the New Year. You’ll be able to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/driving/learning-to-drive" title="Book and manage your theory or practical driving test"&gt;book and manage your theory or practical driving test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/dsa-online-business-service" title="Use the DSA online business service"&gt;use the &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; online business service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/driving/teaching-people-to-drive" title="Use instructor services"&gt;use instructor services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="driving-test-centres-and-customer-service-centre"&gt;Driving test centres and customer service centre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will be operating a normal service up to and including Friday 21 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Driving test centres&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Customer service centre&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;England and Wales: closed - Scotland: most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tuesday 25 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 26 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tuesday 1 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Scotland: closed - England and Wales: most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="last-date-to-change-or-cancel-a-driving-test"&gt;Last date to change or cancel a driving test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must give at least 3 clear working days’ notice to change your test date or cancel it, or you’ll have to pay again. Sundays and public holidays don’t count as working days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tables show the last dates you can change or cancel your test. The date will depend on where you live, and whether you’re doing it online or by phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="england-and-wales"&gt;England and Wales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Test date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel online&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel by phone&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 22 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 30 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 3 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 4 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 5 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 6 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 7 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="scotland"&gt;Scotland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Test date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel online&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel by phone&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 22 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 30 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 3 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 4 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 5 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 6 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 7 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/17200</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T16:11:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/relocation-of-falkirk-driving-test-centre-to-grangemouth"/>
    <title>Relocation of Falkirk driving test centre to Grangemouth</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This initial screening was carried out to find out the impact of relocating the driving test centre at Falkirk to Grangemouth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has closed the driving test centre at Falkirk and opened a new one in Grangemouth. This is to improve facilities for driving examiners and candidates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new test centre opened on 9 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; considers that driving test candidates and staff won’t have any significant or detrimental impact on their journeys to the centre, or on its driving test routes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new centre is easily accessible via the network of main roads in the area. It’s located 4.2 miles away from the original centre. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/17145</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T13:23:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T13:23:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/approving-drink-drive-rehabilitation-courses"/>
    <title>Approving drink-drive rehabilitation courses</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation is about updating how drink-drive rehabilitation scheme courses are provided so more people take training.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation is about updating the arrangements for providing training courses under the drink-drive rehabilitation scheme, including how they’re funded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals build on the government policy in the ‘Strategic framework for road safety’ by providing improved education for convicted drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is that these proposals will: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create better quality courses which will encourage more offenders to take training and reduce the likelihood of them reoffending&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure that courses are available in every part of the country&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure that courses are of the same standard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow the Driving Standards Agency to take action against trainers not providing courses as they should&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="decisions"&gt;Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new scheme will make sure that courses are available in every part of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;monitor course providers to make sure that courses are all of the same standard – we’ll charge fees to cover our costs for doing this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take action against course providers who are not up to standard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give course providers the right to appeal if their application is refused or if we remove their course approval&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give existing course providers enough time to move over to the new scheme, if that’s what they want to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;let course providers use first or second class post for sending out notices to offenders, as long as they get a receipt of posting and keep it for their records&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Training providers can decide the cost of the course, but it can’t cost more than £250.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="important-dates"&gt;Important dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;What’s happening&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Invitations to apply issued&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 January 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Closing date for receipt of applications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8 February 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New courses start&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24 June 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Approval of existing courses runs out&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18 August 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
