<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60074</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family"/>
    <title>UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sattar Beheshti, a young Iranian citizen, died in detention in early November. Mr Beheshti’s only crime appears to have been using the internet to advocate the defence of human rights. Commenting on reports that Iranian security forces disrupted a family ceremony mourning his death, a  Foreign Office Spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are dismayed by the Iranian security forces’ harassment of the family of blogger Sattar Beheshti during the mourning ceremony on 13th December to mark his death. Mr Beheshti died in suspicious circumstances while in custody. This is not the first time the family of a victim of the regime has received such treatment, which is completely unacceptable. Iran must respect the family’s right to mourn their loss in peace, as well as make serious attempts to bring those responsible for Mr Beheshti’s death to justice. The impunity enjoyed by agents of the state must end. We reiterate our condolences to Mr Beheshti’s family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60061</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/commonwealth-reform-package-endorsed-by-commonwealth-heads-of-government"/>
    <title>Commonwealth reform package endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A landmark Commonwealth Charter and a package of reforms to modernise and sharpen the impact of the Commonwealth have been endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings to a close discussion on Commonwealth reform which began at the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Perth, Australia, in October 2011, and included consideration of the Eminent Persons Group report A Commonwealth of the People: Time for Urgent Action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreed proposals include a new Commonwealth Charter setting out the core values and aspirations of the Commonwealth and its members, and commitments to strengthen the Secretariat’s work on election observation and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Commonwealth, the Rt. Hon. Hugo Swire MP, commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Commonwealth Heads of Government have agreed a new Commonwealth Charter and endorsed a package of reforms to strengthen the Commonwealth. This marks an important milestone in Commonwealth modernisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Commonwealth Ministers devoted a great deal of effort to achieve this result. This reflects our belief that the Commonwealth can make a strong, positive contribution on a range of global issues and nurturing democratic standards worldwide.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms, now adopted, show vision and a genuine desire by all members to increase the Commonwealth’s impact and relevance. All parts of the Commonwealth family must now work together to implement these reforms, to ensure that the organisation is as strong and effective as it can be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ability to protect core democratic values is central to the Commonwealth’s credibility. I hope that the Charter becomes a useful tool to promote these values throughout the Commonwealth. We look forward to events in the coming months to officially launch the Charter, and will play our part in raising its profile in the UK.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/news/34580/252051/191212epgcharter.htm"&gt;Commonwealth Secretariat press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-take-steps-to-strengthen-the-commonwealth?id=816829782&amp;amp;view=News"&gt;Ministerial statement, Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/59945</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice"/>
    <title>Christmas Holiday Travel Advice</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you do get into problems while abroad then we are here to help, but you can avoid a lot of difficulties in the first place by following these basic tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/staying-safe/travel-insurance/" title="Travel insurance"&gt;take out comprehensive travel insurance&lt;/a&gt; - make sure it covers you for any activities you are likely to undertake such as extreme or water sports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nathnac.org/" title="NaTHNaC"&gt;The National Travel Health Network and Centre’s website&lt;/a&gt;T or contact your GP’s surgery as early as possible before you travel to find out if you need any vaccinations or other medication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for certain countries your passport must be valid for six months after the date you travel - check the entry requirements section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take enough money for your trip and some back-up funds in a mix of cash and cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-pack-explore-a-new-guide-for-travellers" title="Plan. Pack. Explore. – a new guide for travellers"&gt;download our Plan. Pack. Explore. app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="winter-sports"&gt;Winter sports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New research reveals that a third of people taking their first winter sports holiday risk serious injury because they are not sufficiently in shape when they hit the slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research also reveals that two out of five winter sports enthusiasts have injured themselves at least once, highlighting the importance of getting in shape and warming up properly before skiing or snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/get-fit-for-ski" title="Get Fit For Ski"&gt;Find out more about our Get Fit For Ski campaign.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visiting-friends-or-family-abroad"&gt;Visiting friends or family abroad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You still need to take the same preparations as if you were going on holiday. Our research shows that nearly half of young people did not take out insurance the last time they stayed with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56575</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the single market more effective</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the EU expanded to include more states, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate acheived by other EU states. However, the European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at a rate as low as just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the EU and other dynamic markets, such as South Korea, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the EU as a whole. To achieve higher growth and increased employment, all member states and the EU institutions will need to take action. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which encourages all member states to reinforce financial stability, create jobs and improve competitiveness, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong single market creates jobs and benefits all member states. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234 billion, went to the EU. The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other EU prime ministers, urged the EU to improve the single market, concentrating on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update EU single market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting EU consumers in cyberspace. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;.  Member States must implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013. E-invoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-invoicing within the EU could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;EU-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; which came into force on 1 July 2011 is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for EU exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act (2011)&lt;/a&gt; sets out twelve ways to boost growth and improve confidence in European business. In October 2012 the European Commission proposed a second set of actions, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smact/docs/single-market-act2_en.pdf"&gt;Single Market Act II&lt;/a&gt;, to further develop the single market’s economic opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act II (2012)&lt;/a&gt; describes the EU’s goals of improving the digital economy, including e-commerce and electronic invoicing, and creating more efficient transport and energy networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/u/11-760-uk-response-single-market-act"&gt;response to The Single Market Act&lt;/a&gt; in February 2011 looks at how the UK will work with other member states on reforms that will create the most jobs and economic growth at the lowest cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a study, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/e/11-517-economic-consequences-of-completing-single-market"&gt;The economic consequences for the UK and the EU of completing the single market&lt;/a&gt;, in February 2011. This paper considers the benefits of the single market and the negative effects of the UK opting out of future European trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; published a study in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/feeds/~/media/568CC723188C40DFBB02E868353B40B9.ashx"&gt;The UK and the single market: trade and investment analytical papers topic 4 of 18&lt;/a&gt;, that examines the importance of the EU for British exporters and investors. The analysis found that businesses have benefited from the opportunities provided by the single market. Such benefits include: better connected and cheaper networks; mutual recognition of standards; and easier access to cheap and competitive inputs for British manufacturers. In addition greater competition within the single market has fostered innovation. For consumers, the single market has created more choice and lowered prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/59931</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories: Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chaired the first meeting of the Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council in London from 4-5 December. This Council brings together the political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers. It provides a forum for the exchange of views on political and constitutional issues and has a mandate to lead work to review and implement the strategy and commitments in the June 2012 White Paper The Overseas Territories: Security Success and Sustainability and to promote the security and good governance of the Territories and their sustainable economic and social development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council agreed a communiqué which identified priority issues and set out a comprehensive action plan for joint work. A copy of this communiqué has been laid in the Library of the House. The communiqué reflects the commitment of the governments of the Overseas Territories and the UK to work together to support economic growth and jobs; to protect the environment and create green growth; to harness effectively the support of the EU, the Commonwealth and other international organisations; and to deliver better government, better education and stronger, healthier and safer communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with our commitment in the White Paper we will report to Parliament on progress in implementing the commitments in the communiqué by territory governments and UK Departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual Joint Ministerial Council succeeds the Overseas Territories Consultative Council set up in 1999. It was attended this year by political leaders and representatives of the following Territories: Anguilla; Bermuda; the British Virgin Islands; the Cayman Islands; the Falkland Islands; Gibraltar; Montserrat; Pitcairn; St Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha; and the Turks and Caicos Islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 December the Prime Minister welcomed Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Overseas Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council" title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council-communique" title=" Joint Ministerial Council communique"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council communiqué&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60060</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-national-strategy-on-the-protection-of-civilians-in-armed-conflict"/>
    <title>UK National Strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2010 the United Kingdom launched a national strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict (PoC). The strategy, a collaboration between the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Department for International Development and the Ministry of Defence, sets out what the Government is doing to keep the Protection of Civilians at the forefront of our work on political, security and humanitarian fronts. The strategy covers the period 2010-2013, and provides for annual progress reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 2012 report summarises the UK’s work in four policy areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political engagement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protection by peace support operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanitarian action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State capacity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/59902</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T19:18:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK condemns the decision by the Jerusalem District Planning Board to give approval for a plan to build 1,500 housing units in the East Jerusalem neighbourhood of Ramat Shlomo, and is extremely concerned by reports that the Board is considering giving the approval to a further 5000 housing units in East Jerusalem this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on yesterday’s announcement the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Israeli settlements are illegal under international law, and I condemn this decision. It is deeply disappointing that despite the international community repeatedly raising our concerns, Israel continues to press ahead with plans to expand them.  Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties.  This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.  If implemented, it would make a negotiated two-state solution, with Jerusalem as a shared capital, very difficult to achieve.  We  urge Israel to reverse this decision and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity”
.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57510</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:04:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:04:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth Land </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen visited the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office for the second time today, as the last official engagement of her Diamond Jubilee year. Her Majesty’s previous visit was in 1982 to mark the department’s bicentenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of the building, Foreign Secretary William Hague announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory had been named ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’ in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a mark of this country’s gratitude to The Queen for Her service, we are naming a part of the British Antarctic Territory in her honour as ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fitting tribute at the end of Her Majesty’s Diamond Jubilee year, and I am very proud to be able to announce it as she visits the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Territory is a unique and important member of the network of fourteen UK Overseas Territories. To be able to recognise the UK’s commitment to Antarctica with a permanent association with Her Majesty is a great honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area now to be known as Queen Elizabeth Land, which was previously unnamed, is around 169,000 square miles (437,000 sq km), making up just under a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory. This is almost twice the size of the UK, which stands at 94,000 square miles (244,000 sq km).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land is bounded on the North side by the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves, to the North East by Coats Land, on the East by Dronning Maud Land and extending on the West side to a line between the South Pole and Rutford Ice Stream, east of Constellation Inlet.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen has been on the throne for 60 of the 104 years since the UK claimed territory in Antarctica in 1908. This includes the entire time it has been known as the British Antarctic Territory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Queen Elizabeth Land" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5726/QEL-Antarctica-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Antarctic Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt;) extends from 20⁰ to 80⁰ West. It was claimed by the UK in 1908 and was the first official claim in Antarctica. It was designated officially as a separate Overseas Territory in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All claims to territory within Antarctica are held in abeyance under Article IV of the Antarctic Treaty, 1959, which neither confirms nor denies competing claims, but prevents new claims being made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name Queen Elizabeth Land will now be used on all British maps. Because of the unique status of Antarctica, which is covered by an international Treaty that suspends territorial sovereignty, it is for other countries to decide whether or not they will officially recognise this name.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place naming in &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaken on the basis that a currently unnamed area requires a name for scientific or logistical purposes. This approach is fully in line with the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions on names are made by the Commissioner of the British Antarctic Territory, who is based in London. The Commissioner takes advice on new names from the Antarctic Place Names Committee, which meets twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has no permanent population. British presence is maintained via three research stations operated by the British Antarctic Survey. The Territory itself is self-financing, investing modest receipts from stamp sales and the income tax from overwintering British scientists in environmental projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is not the first time that land in Antarctica has been named after The Queen. Princess Elizabeth Land in East Antarctica, which was discovered in 1931 by the Australian Sir Douglas Mawson, was named by him after Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth (now Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II). And in 2006, an unnamed mountain range in the Antarctic Peninsula was named The Princess Royal Range, in recognition of Her Royal Highness’s work to support environmental and heritage protection work in Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Foreign Secretary's speech"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s speech&lt;/a&gt; welcoming Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on supporting the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories" title="Supporting the Overseas Territories"&gt;Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57035</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-foreign-offices-human-rights-work-in-2011"/>
    <title>The Foreign Office's Human Rights work in 2011</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government welcomes the attentive scrutiny of its human rights work during 2011 carried out by the Foreign Affairs Committee. The Government agrees with the FAC’s assessment that the UK has a strong record in upholding human rights across the world. We welcome the FAC’s comment that our Annual Report on Human Rights and Democracy for 2011 provides ample evidence of our work in promoting higher standards of human rights abroad, sometimes in difficult circumstances. We were pleased that the FAC recognise the considerable effort that went into the production of the FCO’s Annual Human Rights Report for 2011. We have taken steps to strengthen our human rights reporting over the last two years in response to direction from Ministers and feedback from the FAC and others. We will continue to ensure that our reporting is targeted to meet the needs of Parliament and our national and international readership.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Command Paper sets out the Government’s response to the Foreign Affairs Committee’s report of 17 October 2012 into the Foreign and Commonwealth Office’s Human Rights Work in 2011. The Committee’s recommendations are set out in bold. Unless otherwise indicated, references are to paragraphs in the Foreign Affairs Committee Report (HC116).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/57435</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office"/>
    <title>Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary announced that an area in the British Antarctic Territory has been named Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are all delighted to welcome you to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office for the final event of your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In a year in which millions of British people have been able to see you and cheer you, we are truly honoured here in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to have you here with us and to take our part in closing this magnificent period of celebration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is an opportunity for everyone here to show how proud they are to serve in your Majesty’s Diplomatic Service and in the Home Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And there are over 10,000 British and locally-engaged staff in our Embassies and High Commissions abroad who will be equally inspired by your visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You embody a life of service to our country, and a lifetime of diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have made over 260 official visits to 116 different countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Promoting reconciliation, as you did on your visit to West Germany in 1965, and to Japan in 1975;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving encouragement to nations after profound change, such as your visit to Russia in 1994 and to South Africa in 1995;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helping to heal the wounds of history and to make peace irreversible, as I saw myself during your truly historic State Visit to Ireland last year;
And all the time steadfastly uniting the Commonwealth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are deeply grateful to you, and to the 11 members of the Royal Family who have travelled to 29 countries and territories for your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, I am conscious that I am your twenty-second Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your wisdom and experience are an inspiration to all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are striving for excellence in all that we do in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our goal is to be the best Diplomatic Service in the world: helping British people overseas, supporting our economy, keeping our country secure, and upholding freedom and human rights at all times. We do this with your example always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we are renaming in your honour the newly-restored old Home Office Library, which now houses our historians and the Knowledge and Information Management team, which will be called the Diamond Jubilee Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I am delighted to announce that as a mark of our country’s gratitude to you, an area of the Antarctic 437,000 square kilometres in size, nearly twice the size of the United Kingdom and more than a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory, will be given a name for the very first time. From today, in your honour, it will be forever known as Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are proud to serve a Queen who has achieved so much for our nation and who embodies the ideals of public service that we cherish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we thank you for your visit; for this proud and happy occasion that we will all remember for the rest of our lives, and which will be recorded for our successors in the plaque you are unveiling today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank everyone here and all the staff of Foreign and Commonwealth Office, all over the world for all their hard work on behalf of our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And now your Majesty to commemorate your visit today I invite you to unveil the plaque marking your Diamond Jubilee Year.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5731/Queen_s-visit--final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title="Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
