<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60215</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens"/>
    <title>Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the United Nations vote on the human right situation in Iran, the Foreign Secretary has released a video. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic freedoms of ordinary Iranians are being denied. Many citizens live in constant fear of arbitrary arrest, false imprisonment and, in some cases, death. There is undeniable evidence of abuse: the recent death in custody of blogger Sattar Beheshti is one tragic example. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also spoke about Nasrin Sotoudeh, who recently ended a 49-day hunger strike in protest against the harassment of her family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have sacrificed your own freedom, family life and health in order to help others. I want you to know that we are following your case closely. And that I echo the many calls upon Iran for your immediate release. Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regime hopes to silence those who call for basic human rights in Iran. I want to make clear that the promotion and protection of human rights is at the heart of UK foreign policy. And we are committed to supporting and protecting those who defend human rights and work tirelessly to advance personal freedoms, often at great personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OHQkieCYSZg"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/ukiniran/punishing-a-human-rights-defender-nasrin-sotoudehs" title="Nasrin Sotoudehs story"&gt;Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family" title="UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60204</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria"/>
    <title>UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria  </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the publication of a new UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today the UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria published its latest report on the human rights situation in Syria. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. The Commission concludes that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commission has received credible accounts of Government soldiers executing captives. Incidents of direct targeting of civilians by aerial bombardment, including “barrel bombs,” rocket attacks and machine gun fire have risen significantly over recent months. There is testimony of systematic patterns of torture in detention centres, including of children. This report is a stark reminder of the horrific situation in Syria. I call upon all sides to put an end to the violence and pursue a process of genuine political transition which reflects the will of the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work undertaken by the UN Commission of inquiry, in difficult circumstances, is vital to ensure that human rights violations and abuses committed by all parties are documented. We will continue to do all we can to support their work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Countries/SY/ColSyriaDecember2012.pdf" title="UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Countries/MENARegion/Pages/SYIndex.aspx" title="UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60181</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-court-of-human-rights-decision-on-chagossian-case"/>
    <title>European Court of Human Rights’ decision on Chagossian Case</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case concerns complaints made by the Chagos Islanders arising from the evacuation of the British Indian Ocean Territory between 1967 and 1973.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the end of this legal process, which has taken many years. We have made clear our regret for the wrongs done to the Chagossian people over forty years ago. Nevertheless, it was right for the Government to defend itself against this action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that this litigation is concluded, the Government will take stock of our policy towards the resettlement of the British Indian Ocean Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;), as we have always said we would. There are fundamental difficulties with resettlement in &lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;, but we will be as positive as possible in our engagement with Chagossian groups and all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Human Rights decision on application 35622/04: Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.echr.coe.int/ECHR/Homepage_EN" title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/60218</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change"/>
    <title>Taking international action to mitigate climate change</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the global average temperature rises more than 2°C above pre-industrial levels, significant negative impacts of climate change will be more likely and the cost of managing them will rise sharply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution led to an increase in greenhouse gas emissions caused by human activity. The Earth’s surface has consequently warmed by about 0.8°C since around 1900, with much of this warming occurring in the past 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have a 50% chance of keeping climate change to within 2°C of pre-industrial levels, global greenhouse gas emissions need to peak before 2020 and then decline steeply. The UK can’t make this happen on its own - the government has to work at an international level to make sure all countries do what is needed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/encouraging-the-eu-to-demonstrate-leadership-on-climate-change"&gt;encouraging the EU to demonstrate leadership on climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/negotiating-internationally-for-a-comprehensive-global-climate-change-agreement"&gt;negotiating for a comprehensive global climate change agreement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/What-we-do/Key-Issues/Climate-and-environment"&gt;reducing the impact of climate change in developing countries and the overseas territories&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/international-climate-fund-icf"&gt;providing £2.9 billion through the International Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; to help developing countries mitigate and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/reducing-emissions-from-deforestation-and-forest-degradation-redd"&gt;financially supporting developing countries through REDD+&lt;/a&gt; to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/leading-the-diplomatic-effort-to-mitigate-climate-change"&gt;leading the diplomatic effort to mitigate climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;building an evidence base to understand and predict climate change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; that climate change is happening and mainly due to increasing greenhouse gases emitted as a result of human activity, the UN negotiated a treaty at its Conference on Environment and Development in 1992. This treaty is known as the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/2860.php"&gt;United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; and the UK is one of the 195 parties to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties to the convention meet annually at the Conference of the Parties (&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-on-the-human-environment-stockholm--foundation-of-the-un-environment-programme"&gt;1972: Conference on the Human Environment, Stockholm – foundation of the UN Environment Programme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first big global environment conference to co-ordinate international policy. Of the UN’s 132 member states, 114 participated. At the conference the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unep.org/Documents.Multilingual/Default.asp?documentid=97&amp;amp;articleid=1503"&gt;26 Principles&lt;/a&gt;  were agreed, to inspire and guide the world on the preservation and enhancement of the human environment. The conference also agreed the founding of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unep.org/Documents.Multilingual/Default.asp?DocumentID=43"&gt;UN Environment Programme (UNEP)&lt;/a&gt;,  an international institution to co-ordinate the environmental activities of the UN. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="earth-summit-rio-de-janeiro--agreement-of-the-un-framework-convention-on-climate-change"&gt;1992: Earth Summit, Rio de Janeiro – agreement of the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also known as the UN Conference on Environment and Development, this saw 172 UN member states meet to agree further measures to halt environmental degradation and pollution 20 years after the Stockholm conference. The parties reached a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/geninfo/bp/enviro.html"&gt;number of agreements&lt;/a&gt;  and founded new mechanisms for taking international discussions forward. They also agreed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/2860.php"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under the auspices of which international negotiations on climate change continue today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-3-cop-3-kyoto--agreement-of-the-kyoto-protocol"&gt;1997: Conference of the Parties 3 (&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 3), Kyoto – agreement of the Kyoto Protocol&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/kyoto_dec_1997/meeting/6378.php"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 3&lt;/a&gt;  took place in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997. The parties agreed the Kyoto Protocol, which set legally binding targets for developed countries to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions for the first time. The protocol came into force on 16 February 2005. In addition to setting targets for emissions reduction, the Kyoto Protocol also allows for ‘flexible mechanisms’ such as emissions trading, which lets countries with emissions reduction targets purchase greenhouse gas emissions reductions credits from other countries. This effectively allows emissions reductions to take place wherever it is most cost effective for them to occur.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/negotiating-internationally-for-a-comprehensive-global-climate-change-agreement"&gt;Further information on how global negotiations to mitigate climate change have progressed to date.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60122</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T11:37:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:37:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/change-of-her-majesty-s-ambassador-to-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Change of Her Majesty’s Ambassador to South Sudan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will succeed Dr Alastair McPhail OBE, who will be transferring to another Diplomatic Service appointment. Mr Hughes will take up his appointment in March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hughes began his diplomatic career in 1982 as Desk Officer for Australia. He has served overseas in Africa, Europe, South Asia and Latin America. He will move to South Sudan after four years in Sierra Leone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment as Her Majesty’s Ambassador to the Republic of South Sudan, Mr Hughes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I will be very sorry to leave Sierra Leone, but am naturally very pleased to have this opportunity to represent the United Kingdom in the UN’s newest member state. I look forward to building on the work of the team that helped South Sudan in transition and in its very early days of independence. I hope to put the wide and strong range of relationships they developed to good use to strengthen political, economic and security cooperation between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full name:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ian Noel Hughes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Married to:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tereasa June née Tinguely&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Children:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Three&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009 – Present&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;British High Commissioner, Freetown and Her Majesty’s Ambassador, Monrovia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005 – 2009&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Her Majesty’s Ambassador, Guatemala City&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2003 – 2005&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Deputy High Commissioner, Mumbai&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2000 – 2003&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Deputy Head of Mission, Mexico City&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1997 – 2000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Deputy Head, Near East and North Africa Department&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1993 – 1997&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;New Delhi, First Secretary Press and Public Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1991 – 1993&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Press Officer, News Department&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990 – 1991&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Middle East Department, Iraq (Multilateral) Desk Officer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1988 – 1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Berne, First Secretary Political&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1985 – 1988&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tegucigalpa, Deputy Head of Mission&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1982 – 1985&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Australia Desk Officer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60102</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T10:30:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T10:30:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0MNVdzOKLbM&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s Christmas message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2012 has been a remarkable year. Britain and the Commonwealth have celebrated the Diamond Jubilee of Her Majesty The Queen who today visited the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, her last engagement of this jubilee year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK also welcomed the world during the Olympic and Paralympic Games, the legacy of which will live on for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year has been a celebration of Britain’s diversity, innovation and creativity. 2013 presents us with many challenges but we’ll continue to work towards making the world safer, fairer, and more prosperous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to our presidency of the G8 and the ambitious agenda the Prime Minister has set for us and our partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And at this time of year we remember especially all those who will be spending this festive season in places of conflict. The suffering of the Syrian people and the prolonged misery that they have faced has saddened us all. The UK will continue to search for a peaceful solution. I’d like to thank all those who’ve worked so hard to protect others around the world including our servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wish you and your families wherever you are in the world a Merry Christmas and a peaceful and Happy New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60065</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ncpprp-bonus-data-for-the-reporting-year-2011-12"/>
    <title>NCPPRP (bonus) data for the reporting year 2011/12</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-consolidated performance related pay for the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office and FCO Services for performance year 2011/2012&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60184</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/government-procurement-card-data"/>
    <title>Government procurement card data</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details of the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office’s (FCO’s) information on government procurement cards are attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60198</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy"/>
    <title>The FCO Digital Strategy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy covers the work of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office. It covers the implications of
digital for our overall diplomatic work, as well as for our services to the British public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
