<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56611</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-welcomes-new-counter-terrorism-centre-in-uae"/>
    <title>UK welcomes new counter terrorism centre in UAE</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the broad experience and expertise of the 30 Global Counter-Terrorism Forum (GCTF) founding member nations, the Centre will lead global research on the drivers of terrorism, deliver training to address these, and identify practical, operational initiatives to reduce the threat from terrorism. It was launched at the third ministerial meeting of the GCTF in the United Arab Emirates (UAE), which was attended by representatives from all member nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tunisia, where he is on an official visit, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s launch in Abu Dhabi of the Centre of Excellence for Countering Violent Extremism (CVE) is an important milestone in the global fight against terrorism. In particular I welcome the leadership that His Excellency Foreign Minister Abdullah bin Zayed has shown and the Emirati commitment to host the Centre and make it a reality. The UK will continue to give it our full support. We have nominated an expert to serve as a Member of the International Steering Board and are seconding a Director of Training &amp;amp; Capacity-Building into the Centre’s senior management team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to do our utmost to tackle the root causes of terrorism by ensuring a collaborative international approach to the common threat of terrorism. The Global Counter Terrorism Forum offers us an excellent platform from which to address this constantly changing challenge, drawing on the expertise and experience of its members”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thegctf.org/web/guest/about" title="Global Counter-Terrorism Forum"&gt;Global Counter-Terrorism Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56578</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:58:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:58:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/change-of-her-majesty-s-ambassador-to-turkey"/>
    <title>Change of Her Majesty’s Ambassador to Turkey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will succeed Mr David Reddaway CMG MBE. Mr Moore will take up his appointment in January 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Moore was Director for Europe, Latin America and Globalisation until November 2012. He joined the FCO in 1987 and has worked in London on the Middle East and security policy before becoming Director of Programmes and Change. A Turkish speaker, he has served overseas in Vietnam, Turkey, Pakistan and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment as Her Majesty’s Ambassador to the Republic of Turkey, Mr Moore has said “I am delighted to be returning to Turkey where I served early in my diplomatic career. I look forward to working with this close NATO ally, EU candidate and increasingly important political and trading partner, to build an even stronger relationship of trust and friendship between Britain and Turkey in the years ahead.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Full name:&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Richard Peter Moore&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Married to:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Margaret Patricia Isabel Moore (k.a. Maggie)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Children:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;One son, one daughter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010-present&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director Europe, Latin America and Globalisation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008-2010&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director Programmes and Change&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Stanford Executive Programme&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005-2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Deputy Director Middle East&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001-2005&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kuala Lumpur, Counsellor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1998-2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Section Head, Security Policy Group&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995-1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Islamabad, First Secretary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1992-1995&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Desk Officer, Iran&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1991-1992&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Istanbul, Consul (Political and Press)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ankara, Second Secretary (Political)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1988&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hanoi, Third Secretary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1987&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Joined Her Majesty’s Diplomatic Service&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56674</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/science-and-innovation-network-annual-report-2011-12"/>
    <title>Science and Innovation Network: Annual Report 2011 - 12</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report shows the scope of the work carried out by the Science and Innovation Network, a joint &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;-&lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; network operating in around 28 countries and territories around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt; officers are scientifically literate staff in &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; posts who work to benefit the UK through influencing the science and innovation policies of governments, businesses and academia, informing UK policy, and promoting ‘best with best’ collaboration between the UK and other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report, launched by &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; Permanent Secretary, Martin Donnelly, and &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; Chief Scientific Advisor, David Clary, at the &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; on 12 December 2012, gives an overview of the &lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt; and highlights some of its achievements over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt;’s 90+ staff are managed by a team based in &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;’s International Knowledge and Innovation Unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56422</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T16:31:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:31:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-confirms-settlement-of-al-saadi-case"/>
    <title>Government confirms settlement of Al Saadi case</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Libyan national Sami Al Sa’adi and his family members brought a civil claim against Her Majesty’s Government and named defendants relating to alleged rendition to Libya in 2004 and subsequent mistreatment in detention there.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to this claim, a Government spokesperson said today: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can confirm that the Government and the other defendants have reached a settlement with the claimants. There has been no admission of liability and no finding by any court of liability.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56662</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change"/>
    <title>Taking international action to mitigate climate change</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the global average temperature rises more than 2°C above pre-industrial levels, significant negative impacts of climate change will be more likely and the cost of managing them will rise sharply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution led to an increase in greenhouse gas emissions caused by human activity. The Earth’s surface has consequently warmed by about 0.8°C since around 1900, with much of this warming occurring in the past 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have a 50% chance of keeping climate change to within 2°C of pre-industrial levels, global greenhouse gas emissions need to peak before 2020 and then decline steeply. The UK can’t make this happen on its own – the government has to work at an international level to make sure all countries do what is needed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/encouraging-the-eu-to-demonstrate-leadership-on-climate-change"&gt;encouraging the EU to demonstrate leadership on climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/international/negotiations/negotiations.aspx"&gt;negotiating for a comprehensive global climate change agreement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/What-we-do/Key-Issues/Climate-and-environment"&gt;reducing the impact of climate change in developing countries and the overseas territories&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing £2.9 billion through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/international-climate-fund-icf"&gt;International Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; to help developing countries mitigate and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financially supporting developing countries through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/reducing-emissions-from-deforestation-and-forest-degradation-redd"&gt;REDD+&lt;/a&gt; to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/leading-the-diplomatic-effort-to-mitigate-climate-change"&gt;leading the diplomatic effort to mitigate climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;evidence base to understand and predict climate change&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; that climate change is happening and mainly due to increasing greenhouse gases emitted as a result of human activity, the UN negotiated a treaty at its Conference on Environment and Development in 1992. This treaty is known as the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/2860.php"&gt;United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; and the UK is one of the 195 parties to it. Parties to the convention meet annually at the Conference of the Parties (&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-18-doha-2012"&gt;Conference of the Parties 18, Doha 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18 agreed to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;close 2 of the 3 parallel negotiating tracks so that future negotiations will all focus on the new agreement in 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a work plan for negotiation of a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/items/6240.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-17-durban-2011"&gt;Conference of the Parties 17, Durban 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17 agreed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/bodies/body/6645.php"&gt;Durban Platform for Enhanced Action&lt;/a&gt;, which aims to negotiate a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015 and increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide in 2012 a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establish a board for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/durban_nov_2011/session/6294.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-16-cancun-2010"&gt;Conference of the Parties 16, Cancun 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16 agreed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an overall 2°C target to limit temperature rise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to use the UN system to assess different countries’ actions against climate change &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on a system of measurement, reporting and verification to gauge how countries are meeting their promises to reduce greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to establish the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; and help developing countries access low carbon technology and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to halt, slow, and reverse the destruction of trees through the development of international rules and a monitoring system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/cancun_nov_2010/session/6254.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/essential_background/items/6031.php"&gt;Further information on earlier Conferences of Parties to the &lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56249</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:00:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice"/>
    <title>Iranian investigation into death of detained blogger is missed opportunity for justice</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marking the 40th day anniversary of the death of Sattar Beheshti, Foreign Officer Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is now forty days since the blogger Sattar Beheshti died in custody in Iran. I would like to use this occasion to extend my condolences to his family. That the Iranian authorities instigated an investigation into Sattar’s tragic death should have been a positive step. However, once again the authorities have failed to deliver justice. Neither Sattar’s family who have reportedly faced harassment and threats from the security services, nor Sattar’s countrymen and women have been given credible answers about the events that led to his death. Instead, the state-controlled media and the parliament have dismissed his death as a heart attack brought on by a fear of arrest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sattar was right to be afraid of the security forces and what could happen to him in jail. The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention. We are deeply disappointed that having taken the initiative to investigate,  Iran has been unwilling to hold those responsible to account. The sacking of the head of Cyber Police will not stop the security and detention forces from operating with impunity. Systemic change is needed to bring about a more transparent and accountable system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous statement on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reports-that-an-iranian-blogger-has-died-in-detention" title="Reports that an Iranian blogger has died in detention"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt on twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO" title="@AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/55819</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:04:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:04:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Establishing stability in Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in Afghanistan for one overriding reason - to protect our national security by helping the Afghans take control of their own. We are helping Afghanistan develop the ability to maintain its own security and prevent the return of international terrorists, such as al Qaeda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, Afghanistan is supported by a range of international partners to develop its security, governance, infrastructure, economy and ability to provide essential services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is a top UK foreign policy priority and it is our defence main effort. We are one of more than 60 countries helping the Afghan Government establish the conditions to be able to protect its citizens, provide for their basic needs and determine the country’s future, eventually without significant help from the international community. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinafghanistan.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Embassy in the capital Kabul&lt;/a&gt; provides a focus for the UK’s work in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="military-support"&gt;Military support&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s military activities in Afghanistan are conducted under a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/1974%282011%29"&gt;UN Mandate&lt;/a&gt; as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/"&gt;International Security Assistance Force (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. We are the second largest contributor to this coalition of 50 nations and the majority of our armed forces in Afghanistan operate in the southern province of Helmand. &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; conducts operations alongside the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;), mainly the Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training the Afghan Army and Police so that they are capable of independent operations and can protect the population and provide a basic civilian policing service, will be crucial to ensure Afghanistan’s long-term stability and prevent terrorists from finding a safe haven there. As well as carrying out combat operations, &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; provides training, mentoring, advice and support to the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-transfer-of-responsibility-for-security-to-afghanistan-by-2014"&gt;The transfer of responsibility for security to Afghanistan by 2014&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shared aim of President Karzai and the members of the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; is that the transfer of responsibility for security to the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; is completed across the whole country by the end of 2014, when the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; mission is due to end.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature and size of the UK’s presence in Afghanistan is changing. President Karzai and &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to this process of change - known as ‘Transition’ - whereby full responsibility for security and governance is taken on by the Afghans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transition has already started in large areas of Afghanistan, including Helmand Province. Over three-quarters of Afghanistan’s population now live in these areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, established in 2002, is made up of the Afghan National Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;), the Afghan Air Force (AAF) and the Afghan National Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;). These groups are mentored and trained by &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces and other specialists from the international community, for example British Police Officers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; are growing in size and capability. By 2013 we expect them to be approximately 352,000 strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; now leads 80% of conventional operations and carries out 90% of its training. As its capability grows it is increasingly taking responsibility for more specialist tasks such as dealing with Improvised Explosive Devices (roadside bombs) and route clearance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015 &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; will start a new, and smaller, non-combat mission in Afghanistan based on training, assisting and advising the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;. This will take place alongside international community activities that will continue to support Afghanistan’s development in other areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK support for Afghanistan’s long-term development beyond 2014 was confirmed in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-enduring-strategic-partnership-document-between-the-uk-and-afghanistan"&gt;Enduring Strategic Partnership&lt;/a&gt; agreement signed by the Prime Minister and President Karzai of Afghanistan in January 2012. It reaffirmed both countries’ commitment to a continuing partnership and friendship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the agreements made at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/official_texts_87595.htm"&gt;Chicago Summit&lt;/a&gt; in May 2012 the UK will contribute £70 million per year from 2015 to 2017 for the development of the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our Armed Forces will be involved in supporting the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; through a new Afghan National Army Officer Academy in Kabul. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="economic-and-social-projects"&gt;Economic and social projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are helping Afghanistan to become a more viable state that can increasingly meet its population’s needs from its own resources. This work includes support for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://projects.dfid.gov.uk/project.aspx?Project=201023"&gt;economic and social development&lt;/a&gt; and helping the Afghan Government implement its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-ministry-of-counter-narcotics-national-drug-control-strategy"&gt;National Drug Control Strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK agreed to maintain our development assistance of £178 million a year until 2017 at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Tokyo-Conference-on-Afghanistan-8-July-2012/"&gt;Tokyo Conference&lt;/a&gt; in July 2012. This support will help the Afghan Government to reduce extreme poverty, create jobs and achieve long-term economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s development assistance is led by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Where-we-work/Asia-South/Afghanistan/"&gt;Department for International Development&lt;/a&gt;. It concentrates on 3 main areas to increase stability and reduce poverty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving security and political stability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stimulating the economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping the Afghan Government deliver basic services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.stabilisationunit.gov.uk/"&gt;Stabilisation Unit&lt;/a&gt; is working with the Afghan Government and its people in these 3 main areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan’s development into a more viable state is a long-term task that will continue to face many challenges. Our efforts are not designed to create a perfect Afghanistan but one that is able to maintain its own security and prevent the return of international terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-provincial-reconstruction-team"&gt;The Provincial Reconstruction Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.helmandprt.com/"&gt;Provincial Reconstruction Team (&lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Team"&gt;PRT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; is a UK-led, multinational effort of the UK, US and Danish governments. It works with &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Regional Command South West, helping the Afghan Government establish improved governance and development across Helmand Province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As agreed by President Karzai and the international community, all &lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Teams"&gt;PRTs&lt;/abbr&gt; across Afghanistan will close by the end of 2014, in keeping with developing Afghan sovereignty and transition.  This includes Helmand.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the remainder of its presence in Helmand, the &lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Team"&gt;PRT&lt;/abbr&gt; will focus on supporting the Government of Afghanistan reach inclusive political settlements backed by good governance, strong rule of law and sustainable development in line with the Government of Afghanistan’s national ministry strategies, standards and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is in Afghanistan because the country had become a base for terrorists that threatened our country and the rest of the world. The Taliban government gave al Qaeda safe haven in Afghanistan and this allowed terrorists to plan and carry out attacks around the world, most notably the 9/11 atrocities in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taliban were given the opportunity to help bring the leaders of al Qaeda to account. When they refused to do so, action was taken by members of the international community to remove them from control of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The al Qaeda training camps and Taliban regime that provided them safe haven were dismantled in the months after 9/11. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="political-settlement"&gt;Political settlement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stability of Afghanistan will not be achieved by security activities alone and we are supporting Afghan efforts to achieve a political settlement that will secure peace and stability. The Prime Minister, Foreign Secretary and others are actively involved in trilateral talks with their Afghan and Pakistani counterparts. Everyone is committed to this and we have all called on the Taliban to break from al Qaeda and participate in a peace process. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:SpeechPresenter/55967</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-to-contribute-funds-to-courts-in-sierra-leone-and-cambodia--2"/>
    <title>UK to contribute funds to Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on UK contributions to the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in a written ministerial statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce that in order to strengthen international justice and help secure accountability for some of the most horrific crimes against humanity in the last 50 years, the UK will make a voluntary contribution of £1,000,000 to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and a voluntary contribution of £600,000 to the international component of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s contribution will help ensure the Special Court for Sierra Leone is able to complete its work, and leave a lasting legacy for the people of Sierra Leone. On 30 May, the Court sentenced Charles Taylor, a former President of Liberia, to 50 years in jail for aiding and abetting war crimes. Taylor is the first former Head of State to be convicted by an international tribunal and the Court is currently hearing his appeal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia is delivering long awaited justice for millions of Cambodians through the trials of the most senior and responsible surviving members of the Pol Pot regime. The scale of the crimes committed and the number of victims makes it one of the most significant tribunals of its kind since Nuremberg. The Government’s contribution will help to prevent the collapse of the Court which has faced a significant shortfall in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International justice is central to foreign policy. It is essential for securing the rights of individuals and states, and for securing peace and reconciliation. Through the International Criminal Court, and the separate international tribunals, we are working to make clear that those responsible for the worst crimes will be held to account and that political leaders will not enjoy impunity. Our support to these institutions is an important element in our strategy to reduce conflict, promote stability and strengthen the rules based international system. In order to give Parliament a full accounting of this work we will, from this point forward, also provide an annual statement at the start of the financial year detailing our progress on this important issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
