<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Ministry of Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-02T17:44:29+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/61054</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T17:44:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T17:44:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/mod-police-committee-terms-of-reference"/>
    <title>MOD Police Committee - Terms of reference</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>Appointments to the Ministry of Defence Police Committee are approved by the Secretary of State for Defence. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Committee’s main role is to provide independent scrutiny and assurance to the Secretary of State that the Ministry of Defence Police is delivering policing services in accordance with the Ministry of Defence Police Act 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to perform this role the Committee is required to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide scrutiny and guidance to ensure that police powers and authority are impartially and lawfully exercised by the Chief Constable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirm that &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt; is meeting the standards required of a police force&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Validate that &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s exercise of its authority is responsible, proportionate and impartial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Validate that &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s use of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt; is appropriate in relation to the exercising of policing powers and authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide scrutiny and guidance on any other matter in relation to the use of policing powers which fall within the responsibility of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s targets and performance and the Ministry of Defence Police and Guarding Agency’s corporate and business plans as far as required to the exercise the above functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider all complaints made against all members of the Chief Officer ranks of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt;. This may be delegated to a sub-panel of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Police Committee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Undertake all responsibilities required of the Conduct and Appeal Regulations (Statutory Instruments)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submit an annual report to the Secretary of State for Defence on the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence Police"&gt;MDP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s discharge of policing powers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publish the operating costs and expenses of the Police Committee each year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61035</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T14:50:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/army-olympic-gold-medalist-awarded-mbe"/>
    <title>Army Olympic gold medalist awarded MBE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Captain Heather Stanning has been awarded an MBE by Her Majesty The Queen in the New Year Honours for her achievements at the 2012 Olympics.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Stanning, of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24677.aspx" title="32 Regiment website"&gt;32 Regiment Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, and her rowing partner, Helen Glover, were &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympic-gold-for-armys-heather-stanning" title="Read more at GOV.UK"&gt;the first British Olympians to win gold medals in the 2012 Olympic Games&lt;/a&gt;, and the first female pairing to win Olympic gold medals in a women’s rowing event at the Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about her award, Capt Stanning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud and honoured to be awarded an &lt;abbr title="Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;. After an amazing year this really is the perfect end. I can’t thank the public, the Army and my family enough for all the support they have given to me in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now I am looking forward to 2013 and my planned deployment to Afghanistan, which I know will be as challenging and rewarding as everything I achieved in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capt Stanning was commissioned from Sandhurst in 2008 before joining 32 Regiment Royal Artillery. Two years ago she was released from Army duties to allow her attempt to row into Olympic history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair had a number of successes leading up to the Olympics, notably winning all three World Cup regattas prior to the London Games. This level of form and confidence was carried into the Olympics, and through months of hard work, intense training and determination, the pair won Olympic gold in the Women’s coxless pairs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capt Stanning has now returned her unit in the Army and is due to deploy to Afghanistan in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56526</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T10:31:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T10:31:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"/>
    <title>Countering weapons proliferation </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Securing global safety by preventing countries and terrorists access to the materials needed for weapons of mass destruction.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of weapons of mass destruction (&lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;) poses a threat to the UK and the international community. Indiscriminate trade in conventional arms and the use of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (&lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt;) weapons and ballistic missiles raises serious humanitarian and security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working around the world to champion and implement UK policies as set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the spread of &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; weapons and ballistic missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works with international partners and through organisations such as the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, G8, NATO and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce terrorists’ ability to create, obtain or use &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; materials and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the FCO’s tools to combat these threats is our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/a&gt;. In the financial year 2012 to 13, the value of the programme is £3 million. This funding is used to support projects around the world which increase political will or technical capacity to reduce the threat of weapons proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-counter-proliferation-strategy"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in March 2012. The strategy’s main aims are to deny terrorists the materials and expertise to make and use &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;; to stop countries such as Iran and North Korea from obtaining &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt; or advanced conventional weapons; and to build up the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/About/"&gt;International Atomic Energy Agency (&lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; and other organisations and treaties that help us meet our goals through the international community and which help to protect global security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemical-weapons"&gt;Chemical weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the destruction of remaining chemical weapons stocks and works to encourage full national implementation of the Chemical Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;) by all countries. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/the-chemical-weapons-convention"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention&lt;/a&gt; bans the development, production, stockpiling and use of chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biological-weapons"&gt;Biological weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has signed up to the global implementation of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/04FBBDD6315AC720C1257180004B1B2F?OpenDocument"&gt;Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of the convention is to help prevent states acquiring or keeping biological and toxin weapons, and prevent them ever being used by states or terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt; doesn’t have a verification system like that of the &lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Participating countries are required to submit relevant data and declarations, or confidence-building measures, to the United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs. This increases openness and gives participating countries confidence that others are complying with the convention. The UK’s confidence building measures are published on the the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/CEC2E2D361ADFEE7C12572BC0032F058?OpenDocument"&gt;Implementation Support Unit website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-weapons"&gt;Nuclear weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;. The UK is one of 189 states that have signed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The treaty aims to stop the spread of nuclear weapons and ultimately eliminate them. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; has three equally important ‘pillars’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to work towards non-proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to champion nuclear disarmament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nuclear-security"&gt;Nuclear security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK will continue work to strengthen international nuclear security including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;securing fissile material in Kazakhstan, in a joint project with the US &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to build a central store for spent radioactive sources in Ukraine  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to create new jobs for 3,000 former weapons scientists in Russia and other former Soviet Union countries  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;assisting many other countries through our collaboration with the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; on its Nuclear Security Fund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will continue to offer funding and expertise for physical nuclear security upgrades and help support the strongest possible security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are supporting the full implementation of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/N04/328/43/PDF/N0432843.pdf?OpenElement"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Resolution 1540&lt;/a&gt;, which requires all states to refrain from supporting non-government agents from developing, acquiring, manufacturing, possessing, transporting, transferring or using nuclear, chemical or biological weapons and their delivery systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-programmes"&gt;State programmes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the international legal framework, conventions and treaties, some countries have active programmes to develop and produce &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Of particular concern is Iran’s nuclear programme; the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s nuclear programme and willingness to provide weapons to other countries; and Syria’s possession of chemical and biological weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works through various international organisations to seek peaceful means to reduce the threat from these programmes and the networks that support them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arms-trade-treaty"&gt;Arms Trade Treaty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a legitimate arms trade, there is also an urgent need for more effective and coherent international regulation of that trade. The UK is working to achieve an international arms trade treaty to provide clearer and more effective control of the illegal arms trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; conference in July 2012 was unable to adopt an Arms Trade Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, the UK will continue to play a leading role in future negotiations to help to secure one. An &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to reduce the flow of weapons from legitimate trade to the illicit market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; process towards an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; and submissions from states (including the UK’s views on an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/first/63/documentation.shtml"&gt;United Nations General Assembly website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="export-licensing"&gt;Export licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has joined other governments around the world to pursue &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/3849543/eu-arms-export"&gt;collective implementation of export controls&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the proliferation of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The 4 main export control regimes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mtcr.info/english/index.html"&gt;Missile Technology Control Regime&lt;/a&gt;, which controls the proliferation of missile systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/Leng/default.htm"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt;, which controls the supply of nuclear related technologies and materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.australiagroup.net/en/index.html"&gt;Australia Group&lt;/a&gt;, which seeks to ensure that exports do not contribute to the development of chemical or biological weapons &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt;, which promotes greater responsibility in transfers of conventional arms and dual-use goods and technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read further details about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s regulatory authority responsible for assessing and issuing strategic export licences to UK exporters is the Export Control Organisation (ECO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS). Read more about the UK’s policies and procedures for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2"&gt;controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;) was borne out of fear that the Cold War era would lead to a nuclear arms race and is still the basis of the international nuclear non-proliferation regime. All states are now party to it apart from India, Israel, Pakistan and South Sudan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; provides for a Review Conference every 5 years, both to review developments over the previous 5 years and to look ahead to the future. At the last &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;Review Conference in 2010&lt;/a&gt; a series of action plans were agreed to enhance implementation of the treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/"&gt;The International Atomic Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt; was set up as the world’s ‘Atoms for Peace’ organisation in 1957 within the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; family, and supports the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The agency is at the centre of international efforts to address Iran’s nuclear dossier and to ensure the benefits of safe and secure peaceful nuclear energy are accessible to everyone, not just to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thenuclearsecuritysummit.org/eng_main/main.jsp"&gt;Seoul Nuclear Security Summit&lt;/a&gt; assembled 53 countries, the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; and Interpol, to continue work to secure vulnerable nuclear material around the world within 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 December 2008 in the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly, 133 States voted in favour of a draft resolution ‘Towards an Arms Trade Treaty’. There was a clear majority view that, working together, the international community can shape an Arms Trade Treaty into an effective legally binding mechanism to regulate the international trade in arms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our detailed guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-embargoes-and-restrictions"&gt;Sanctions, embargoes and restrictions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/current-arms-embargoes-and-other-restrictions"&gt;Current arms embargoes and other restrictions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the Common Foreign and Security Policy (&lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; applies restrictive measures in pursuit of the specific &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; objectives set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/treaties/index.htm"&gt;Treaty on European Union&lt;/a&gt; (see particularly Article 11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; External Action website&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of restrictive measures adopted in the framework of the &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; that are currently in force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/sc/committees/list_compend.shtml"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Sanctions Committees website&lt;/a&gt; contains links to the latest versions of all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council targeted sanctions lists. The individuals and entities included in these lists are subject to the relevant measures imposed by the Security Council, and all member states are obliged to implement these measures. Each separate list is maintained by the relevant Security Council Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/60995</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T12:45:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/gurkha-pension-and-redundancy-calculators"/>
    <title>Gurkha pension and redundancy calculators</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Find out what benefits you are entitled to under the Gurkha pension and redundancy schemes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="gurkha-pension-calculator-gpc"&gt;Gurkha pension calculator (&lt;abbr title="Gurkha pension calculator"&gt;GPC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gurkha pension calculator below gives a forecast of benefits for members of Armed Forces Pension Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Armed Forces Pension Scheme"&gt;AFPS&lt;/abbr&gt;) 75 or &lt;abbr title="Armed Forces Pension Scheme"&gt;AFPS&lt;/abbr&gt; 05 who transferred as part of the serving Gurkha Offer To Transfer (&lt;abbr title="Gurkha Offer To Transfer"&gt;GOTT&lt;/abbr&gt;). All officers, and those soldiers who joined as part of the 1993 intake and earlier, were given a service credit. This calculator will adjust the pensionable service to take into account any service credit received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="gurkha-redundancy-calculator"&gt;Gurkha redundancy calculator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to be used in conjunction with DSPS(A)’s letter (reference DSPS(A) 4.5.23 dated 15 April 2011). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gurkha soldiers and Late Entry officers selected for redundancy are entitled to receive a lump sum in compensation for shortening their career as well as other terminal and retirement benefits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the entitlement of Gurkha Late Entry officers, who joined the Army before 1 July 1997, and Gurkhas soldiers, who joined the Army before 1 October 1993, to redundancy compensation is affected by the terms and conditions of the &lt;abbr title="Gurkha Offer To Transfer"&gt;GOTT&lt;/abbr&gt;, which means that the Armed Forces Redundancy Calculator (&lt;abbr title="Armed Forces Redundancy Calculator"&gt;AFRC&lt;/abbr&gt;) will not produce an accurate forecast. In these cases, Gurkhas must use the Gurkha pension calculator (&lt;abbr title="Gurkha pension calculator"&gt;GPC&lt;/abbr&gt;) to produce a forecast of the parts of their redundancy package which the &lt;abbr title="Armed Forces Redundancy Calculator"&gt;AFRC&lt;/abbr&gt; cannot calculate correctly and then, in some cases, apply a manual workaround.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/16543</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/armys-airborne-engineers-build-french-connection"/>
    <title>Army's airborne engineers build French connection</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An exercise has seen British airborne engineers build a bridge over a large man-made lake and train with their French counterparts.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/role/834.aspx" title="23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)"&gt;23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)&lt;/a&gt; has been working in the harsh climate and unforgiving landscape of Northumbria with French troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/genie/17e-regiment-du-genie-parachutiste" title="17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste"&gt;17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (17e RGP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper tested troops in a humanitarian relief operation in a country facing famine and struggling to recover from damage caused by a tsunami, with government control undermined by insurgents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After deploying from their base at Woodbridge in Suffolk, the exercise started in earnest with the use of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/equipment/705.aspx" title="Air Portable Ferry Bridge"&gt;Air Portable Ferry Bridge&lt;/a&gt; (APFB) equipment to move vehicles and personnel across the two-mile-wide (3.2km) expanse of Kielder Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APFB specialist equipment is designed to be parachuted or moved by helicopter and set up either as a conventional bridge or a self-propelled ferry to cross wider obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sappers preparing the bridge" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1134/16x-2012-115-0114.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sappers preparing the bridge to go over Kielder Water during Exercise Eagle Sapper [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sappers then moved to Otterburn, where they were challenged to build water supply points capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day, cross rivers using bridging equipment and improvised materials, demolish obstacles, and construct defensive positions which were then attacked by enemy forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training was intended to test the unit in their role providing combat engineering support to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/12409.aspx" title="16 Air Assault Brigade"&gt;16 Air Assault Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, which is ready to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice for operations ranging from disaster relief to war-fighting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jason Hones, Commanding Officer of 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper has seen our soldiers working for up to 22-hours-a-day on demanding tasks that test both their combat engineering and infantry skills in very harsh terrain and weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1135/16x-2012-115-0631.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The sappers and their French counterparts built a water supply point capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges  [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that we test the mettle of the soldier we are going to send on operations in arduous and unknown conditions so that we know he can cope with anything that is thrown at him. If a soldier can survive in Northumbria in winter he can survive anywhere in the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The French troops joined the exercise as part of the developing partnership between 16 Air Assault Brigade and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/brigades/11e-brigade-parachutiste" title="11e Brigade Parachutiste"&gt;11e Brigade Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (11e BP), which have been tasked to develop a Combined Joint Expeditionary Force for contingency operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lt Col Hones said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really lucky to have soldiers from our French partner regiment with us, having recently sent troops over to train in France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1136/16x-2012-115-0667.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A water supply point constructed during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working together on this exercise is developing our integration at the section level, to learn how we each operate and our particular strengths and weaknesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will take this to the next level up in the coming months, working towards the aim of being able to work seamlessly together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Matthieu Le Puloc’h commanded the ten-strong 17e RGP contingent, who lived and worked with their British counterparts throughout the two-week exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is our first joint training and our presence is about learning how 23 Engineer Regiment works so that, if we do go on operations together, we know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defends his position" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1137/16x-2012-115-0804.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defending his position during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are a lot of similarities in our basic role as airborne engineers, but our equipment and working practices are different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Otterburn is a cold and hard environment but we have quickly adapted to it and the exercise has been a great experience to broaden the minds of our soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Steve McCann said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s been a tough exercise in difficult conditions that has been made more challenging by working with our French counterparts. Their kit is slightly different and the language barrier makes everything go a little bit slower, but we’re showing them how we work and it’s rewarding to complete engineering tasks together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/17217</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/military-urge-generous-public-not-to-swamp-postal-system-at-christmas"/>
    <title>Military urge generous public not to swamp postal system at Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Service personnel are urging members of the public to avoid sending unsolicited Christmas gifts and packages to operational theatres.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Christmas post deadline of 3 December approaches for Armed Forces personnel serving overseas, servicemen and women are urging members of the public not to send unsolicited gifts and packages to operational theatres such as Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these kind sentiments are appreciated, such generosity has often resulted in delaying important mail from family and friends reaching their destination at this special time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceFor/ServiceCommunity/BFPO/BritishForcesPostOffice.htm" title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;British Forces Post Office&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) is overwhelmed by the generosity of the public who send individuals, and groups, in operational theatres boxes of treats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although well-intentioned, the message is very clear: if people wish to show their support for those serving in Afghanistan, there are far more effective ways of doing so such as donations to Service charities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; spokesperson Lieutenant Colonel Brett Duxbury said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with every year, the Christmas post period is by far our busiest. Just this week we dispatched more than 10,500 bags of mail to operational theatres, which will arrive in time for Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unsolicited mail can seriously impact on our ability to deliver post from loved ones to personnel serving on operations at Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not underestimate the impact that mail from friends and family can have on morale and it is for that reason we make it our priority each year to ensure it arrives on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parcels are coming in thick and fast to the military’s premier transport hub of &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, via the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, and have been loaded onto aircraft ready for dispatch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Service personnel are working hard to ensure that this mail is delivered alongside other vital supplies such as helicopters, armoured vehicles and lifesaving equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Danny Smith, from No 1 Air Mobility Wing at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last two days over 23 tonnes of mail has arrived at Brize Norton from the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, which has been loaded onto aircraft and is now en route to various operational theatres including Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a challenging but important task ensuring it is all dispatched quickly. Having served in Afghanistan at Christmas last year, I understand how much value our boys and girls place on receiving post from people closest to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1242/Mail1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas mail for the troops, sorted, bagged and packaged, awaits final transportation to Afghanistan in the air cargo hangar at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The volume of mail arriving at Camp Bastion for onward distribution to other locations in Afghanistan can cause other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The onward delivery of goodwill parcels to forward operating bases necessitates additional resupply flights and convoys, which places Service personnel at additional risk in what is already a difficult and dangerous operating environment. Every time an additional convoy is laid on, more troops are put at risk of enemy attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of items included in many welfare parcels are either already readily available in theatre or are simply not appropriate for the Afghan environment. Not only does this mean that the items go to waste, but time and resources have to be diverted from crucial operations to organise their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government is dedicated to the care and welfare of the men and women of our Armed Forces, particularly those deployed on operations. This is reflected in the Deployed Welfare Package, a key part of which is the safe and timely delivery of free personal mail from family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past this mechanism has been used by the general public to show their support and resulted in huge volumes of unsolicited goodwill parcels being sent, which have overwhelmed the in-theatre postal and logistics capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst unsolicited mail is well-intentioned, mail sent by families and friends is the most important to deployed personnel and is our absolute priority. Moreover, unsolicited mail strains the logistics supply and prevents mail from families getting through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason the MOD will be repeating its unsolicited mail campaign. Rather than sending their own letter or parcel, I would encourage people to make a donation to one of Britain’s excellent Service charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They might also consider &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;‘uk4u Thanks!’&lt;/a&gt; - a charity that provides Christmas gifts to deployed Service personnel. Once again I would like to say thank you to the British public, on behalf of the MOD and Armed Forces, for their incredible support of our serving personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1243/Mail2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mail for troops in places such as Afghanistan awaiting loading onto aircraft at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the charity uk4u Thanks! will, for the ninth year, deliver a Christmas Box of practical gifts and treats to every soldier, sailor and airman deployed overseas - in Afghanistan and elsewhere - and to those in hospital and recovery centres in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its parcels are delivered via the supply chain, meaning there is no impact on the mail network. Although the charity benefits from corporate sponsorship, it also needs donations from the public to continue its work bringing Christmas cheer to thousands of personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD provides a comprehensive Deployed Welfare Package which includes a free mail service for families and friends, 30 minutes of telephone calls a week and internet access, there are still areas where life in an operational theatre can be improved over and above that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and in order to enable members of the public to make a contribution to the welfare of personnel in an appropriate way, the MOD Operations Welfare Fund was established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priority for spending from the fund is set by commanders in theatre for those items which have the most impact on enhancing the morale of their personnel, and any money donated to this fund enables commanding officers on the ground to bid for items which their men and women have asked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of items purchased through the fund are Wii handsets, portable DVD players, games and table tennis tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make a donation can send a cheque to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations Welfare Fund, J1 Operation HERRICK, PJHQ, Sandy Lane, Northwood, Middlesex HA6 3HP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recommended Christmas posting date for personnel on Her Majesty’s ships is Friday 30 November 2012, and for Operation HERRICK and Operation KIPION is Monday 3 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/61033</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-year-honours-for-service-personnel-and-defence-civilians"/>
    <title>New Year Honours for Service personnel and Defence civilians</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>120 UK Service personnel have been granted state honours by Her Majesty The Queen in the annual New Year Honours list.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;42 civilians have also been honoured either for work in the Ministry of Defence or in other aspects of UK Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 162 Defence personnel named in the New Year Honours list for 2013 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="royal-navy-awards"&gt;Royal Navy Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew David Hugh MATHEWS &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Charles Anthony JOHNSTONE-BURT &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Robert LISTER &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Boyce CHARLIER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Matthew Edward PORTER &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew BETTON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nicholas Geoffrey DUNN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Nicholas John GRACE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Timothy Mark HULME &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surgeon Commander Anthony Wayne LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore Richard William MASON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore James Mark SLAWSON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1(Abovewater Warfare Weapons) Paul Michael Stewart BARKER Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nigel David BOND &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Christopher Paul CANNING &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Damian Andrew Giles EXWORTHY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Terence GILLARD Royal Naval Reserve (Sea Cadet Corps)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Abovewater Warfare Tactical) James Edward HALL Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Thomas Maxwell Philip HENDERSON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Rodney Leslie LESTER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Brian MEADOWS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Annette Eileen PENFOLD Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 David John ROACH Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Air Engineering Technician) David Alun ROWLANDS &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Simon TOTTLE Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="appointments-to-the-civil-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;Appointments to the Civil Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commander"&gt;As Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore William Michael WALWORTH &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Fleet Auxiliary  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting Commander Simon Roscoe COTTAM Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="army-awards"&gt;Army Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-1"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander-1"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant General James Jeffrey Corfield BUCKNALL &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions-1"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Shaun Alex BURLEY &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Ian Martin COPELAND late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Gregory Stephen SMITH QVRM &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; DL late The Royal Green Jackets Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-1"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders-1"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Gareth Paul COLLETT late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Peter Andrew FOX late Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Edward Oliver FORSTER–KNIGHT &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Adjutant General’s Corps (Royal Military Police&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier John Craig LAWRENCE &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late The Royal Gurkha Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers-1"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Barry William BENNETT &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Ian Miles COMERFORD Corps of Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robert James HEALEY Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Garry HEARN late Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Peter Michael LITTLE The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Nicholas Charles Tristram MILLEN late The Royal Dragoon Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Timothy Marc Piers MOUNTFORD Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robin Charles SMITH The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Roger John Nathaniel STEWART late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Simon Philip STOCKLEY Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Neil UNSWORTH The Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Murray Courtenay WHITESIDE &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Army Air Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members-1"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Christopher Charles ATTRILL The Royal Irish Regiment Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kenneth Harry BAKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Joanna Jane BRAIN Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bombardier Alexander Robert BUCHANAN Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Robert James COLLINS The Parachute Regiment &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Jonathan DEANS Adjutant General’s Corps (Educational and Training Services Branch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Leigh James DRUMMOND The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Paul John EDWARDS The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Alastair Neil FIELD The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Darren John FISHER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal (Acting Sergeant) Terry John FITZGERALD Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James FLETCHER Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 James Alexander FORD Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch) Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Christopher James FULLER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Frederick William GREENHOW Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Rowena Charlotte GRIFFITHS Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Charles Edward Digby GRIST The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Barry HEAP Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Cameron Arthur HILL The Royal Logistic Corps Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Steven Robin HOOK The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Leslie John HUNT Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Christian Glyndwr LAMB The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Guy William John LOCK Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Matthew John Frederick MIDDLEDITCH QGM The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Stephen John MORGAN Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Stuart Andrew NASH Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Andrew James PARKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Bombardier Benjamin James PARKINSON Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Hemchandra &lt;abbr title="Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland"&gt;RAI&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; Adjutant General’s Corps (Gurkha Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Fabian Andrew David Lechmere ROBERTS &lt;abbr title="Member of the Royal Victorian Order"&gt;MVO&lt;/abbr&gt; Irish Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Brian Mackenzie ROSS The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Robert SADLER Royal Mercian and Lancastrian Yeomanry Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James SANGER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mathew Timothy James SHORT Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martyn Jonathan THOMPSON Royal Army Veterinary Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mark Lloyd WELHAM The Royal Welsh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Nicholas Simon WILSON The Yorkshire Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kevin YOUNG Royal Regiment of Artillery Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-1"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major (Local Lieutenant Colonel) Stephen Wyatt BARTLETT &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; The Rifles Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Simon Michael John BELL &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; late The Cheshire Regiment Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Philip Guy DAVIS Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaplain to the Forces 3rd Class Reverend Louis KINSEY &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Army Chaplains’ Department Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Sonja McCOY Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="royal-air-force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-2"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander-2"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Timothy Michael ANDERSON &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Distinguished Service Order"&gt;DSO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Andrew Douglas PULFORD &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions-2"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Raymond Jackson PENTLAND&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Julian Alexander YOUNG &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-2"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders-2"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Nigel Philip BEET &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Margaret Elaine WEST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Domonic Anthony STAMP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers-2"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick Alexander BOUNDY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick John DENNIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Christopher John FISHER &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Volunteer Reserve (Training)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain James Cameron McGregor JOHNSTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Michael Dawson LAVENDER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Justine Elizabeth MORTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stephen Michael Robert WARD &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members-2"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Timothy Alexander BARLOW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician David Jeremy BRIGGS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Benjamin John CLARK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Benjamin David CROSSLEY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Glynis Mary DEAN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Kevin John Patrick FOXWELL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Phillip Leslie JONES&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Tal Thomas Adam LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Martin Alan PURVIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Simon Edward READE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Derek Charles SMITH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician Barry John STRINGER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Paul WHEABLE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer David John WOODHEAD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Dale Edward Spencer WOOLMAN-LANE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-2"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Maureen KENDALL Royal Auxiliary Air Force&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="civilians-in-defence"&gt;Civilians in defence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="knight-bachelor-kt"&gt;Knight Bachelor (&lt;abbr title="Knight Bachelor"&gt;Kt&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Hew Francis Anthony Strachan
For services to the Ministry of Defence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="commanders-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-cbe"&gt;Commanders of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Michael Thomas COCHRANE
For services to Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="officers-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-obe"&gt;Officers of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Anthea DOLMAN GAIR
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Diana DONOVAN
For voluntary service to The Gurkha Welfare Trust&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James HEPBURN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher HURRAN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vincent MIFSUD, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For services to Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Charles PENLINGTON
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cynthia Kit Man SHAW
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Sylvia Nina QUAYLE, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="members-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-mbe"&gt;Members of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Ann Elizabeth CABLE
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Andrew CAMBRIDGE
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Gail CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Stamford James CARTWRIGHT, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to the West Midland Reserve Forces &amp;amp; Cadets Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horace MacDonald CROSS
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Barrie DAVIES
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm DYER
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy JOBSON
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Graham John LAWRENCE
Ministry of Defence, Andover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Albert MABEY
For voluntary service to the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel John Robert MacKENZIE, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel MAIN
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Rachel McLAUGHLIN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Rossiter NEWSOME, JP
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher PAGE
Ministry of Defence, Yeovil&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken PAYNE
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry PITCHFORTH
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Mary Elizabeth PLUME
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David REES
For services to Defence Capability &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William John SCOTT
For voluntary service in the Air Training Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Hannah SEAKINS
Ministry of Defence, Hitchin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John UNDERHILL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-british-empire-medal-bem"&gt;The British Empire Medal (&lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Arnold BURCHELL
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Janet Stewart CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the British Red Cross Society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Paulin CLINTON
For services to Veterans Aid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian CLOUGH
Ministry of Defence, Mid Glamorgan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Ellis GRINNALL
Ministry of Defence, Monmouthshire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Carole Jean HILLMAN
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter William SKELLON
For voluntary service to the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Jean SLATER
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Alan Ronald TAPP
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60903</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T19:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T19:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/general-normal-schwarzkopf-tribute"/>
    <title>General Norman Schwarzkopf tribute </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Chief of the Defence Staff has paid tribute to the retired US General Norman Schwarzkopf, who died yesterday, 27 December 2012, aged 78.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Schwarzkopf was commander of coalition forces in the first Gulf War from 1990-91.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, &lt;a href="/government/people/david-richards" title="General Sir David Richards"&gt;General Sir David Richards&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General Norman Schwarzkopf’s command in the Gulf was an example of the finest qualities of American leadership: decisive, inclusive and measured. At the head of a coalition of forces from around the world, including many from the region, he played a pivotal role in the liberation of Kuwait. The operation was not only a UN act but marked the transition from a Cold War doctrine of dissuasion and balance to a new world where force could be used for good. As its first practitioner General Schwarzkopf accomplished what so few can: he shaped his times. He was the first of what are now many US generals to lead British forces in this kind of conflict, rather than in Cold War stasis of the previous decades. For that, and his inspirational command in war, he will be remembered on this side of the Atlantic with respect. The Anglo-American alliance has gone from strength to strength since his time, but it started with him. My thoughts are with his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/16790</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-illustrious-visits-malta"/>
    <title>HMS Illustrious visits Malta</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Illustrious has arrived at the Mediterranean island of Malta for a five-day visit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 1,500 sailors and marines lined the deck of the Portsmouth-based helicopter carrier as she entered the port of Valletta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an onboard reception for the Earl and Countess of Wessex, the ship will be holding an affiliation event for representatives from the Maltese cities of Senglea, Vittoriosa and L’Isla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helicopter carrier is twinned with the three cities due to a previous HMS Illustrious which was bombed during the Second World War and underwent extensive repair at the Grand Harbour in Malta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martin Connell, Commanding Officer of HMS Illustrious, said it was a proud moment for him to be sailing HMS Illustrious into Valletta. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very much aware of not just the history of this ship but also the previous Illustrious and what the people of Malta did to help save her in 1941.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1157/IL120467045.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious as she enters the port of Valletta [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gov.mt/" title="Government of Malta"&gt;Maltese Government&lt;/a&gt; also allowed the Grand Harbour in Valletta to be used for berthing by HMS Cumberland and HMS York following their evacuation of British nationals from Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time in Grand Harbour, sailors and marines from HMS Illustrious will be helping out with a variety of worthy causes including a clean-up of outdoor spaces in collaboration with the Nature Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the week &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;HMS Illustrious&lt;/a&gt; will be joined by the Royal Navy fleet flagship, HMS Bulwark, and Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship Mounts Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Illustrious is part of the Cougar 12 deployment - a three-month work-up of the Royal Navy’s Response Force Task Group (RFTG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1158/IL120467008.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deployment is a test of the RFTG’s capability should it be called into action at short notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The force is designed to respond to rapidly unfolding world events - the last time being Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of Cougar 12, the ships have been working with Royal Marines commando units and the Fleet Air Arm to put their amphibious capability to the test - the power to transfer marines from ships onto the beaches of hostile nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as exercising the 3,000 British sailors, marines and airmen, the task force has worked alongside French and Albanian forces to ensure the nations could co-operate on a military level in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-news"&gt;Related News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/BritishAndAlbanianNaviesWorkTogetherInTheAdriatic.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;British and Albanian navies work together in the Adriatic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/HmsIllustriousTrainsWithFrenchNavy.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious trains with French Navy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/EquipmentAndLogistics/HmsIllustriousReturnsToPortsmouthAfterUpgrade.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious returns to Portsmouth after upgrade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
