<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Ministry of Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T19:30:54+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/57008</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:30:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/british-forces-overseas-falkland-islands-and-ascension-island"/>
    <title>British forces overseas: Falkland Islands and Ascension Island</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="falkland-islands-a-short-guide"&gt;Falkland Islands: a short guide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces are based in the Falklands to demonstrate the government’s continued commitment to the security of UK overseas territories in the South Atlantic. They include air defence assets, maritime patrol capability and infantry forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also regular naval deployments to the region and temporary deployments for routine exercises. The exact force levels are kept under constant review and are structured and maintained at a level consistent with this policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="recent-history-of-the-falklands"&gt;Recent history of the Falklands&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2 April 1982, few people in the UK knew where the Falkland Islands were. This changed dramatically when Argentina - claiming sovereignty - invaded the islands. At the time there were fewer than 80 Royal Marines based here and they were quickly overwhelmed, as were the local Defence Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Task Force set sail from the UK, immediately while the UN tried to find a diplomatic solution to the problem. On 25 April South Georgia was taken back, but the re-taking of the Falkland Islands was to take longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 2 May 1982 the Argentine cruiser General Belgrano was sunk. Two days later HMS Sheffield was sunk followed by the loss of HMS Ardent, Antelope and Coventry as well as the container ship Atlantic Conveyor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, that same month, on the 21 May, British forces came ashore at San Carlos, on East Falkland and joined in battle with the Argentine occupying force. In the Battle for Darwin and Goose Green, the Argentine force was defeated and the British commenced a ‘yomp’ (a long-distance march carrying full kit) across the island, now in a bitter winter, towards Stanley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 8 June there was one of the saddest days of the conflict when the Fleet Auxiliaries, RFA Sir Galahad and RFA Sir Tristram, were bombed at Fitzroy. One week later, on 14th June the Argentine force surrendered after bitter and protracted fighting on Mount Longdon, Wireless Ridge and Tumbledown, the mountains around Stanley. Three Falkland Island civilians, 254 British service personnel and 655 Argentine servicemen lost their lives during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after the conflict in 1982, work was started on the building of Mount Pleasant Airfield (&lt;abbr title="Mount Pleasant Airfield"&gt;MPA&lt;/abbr&gt;), 35 miles from Stanley. Construction was a joint venture for the Laing-Mowlem ARC consortium and of an extraordinary nature, in that a road was built from Stanley to Mount Pleasant. An airfield capable of supporting fighters, helicopters and transport aircraft was constructed and also a complex capable of providing for all needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the construction of &lt;abbr title="Mount Pleasant Airfield"&gt;MPA&lt;/abbr&gt;, many service and civilian personnel have been detached to the Falkland Islands and the stories of island life that they have returned with are as varied as each individuals personal expectations and experiences. The weather plays a significant part in the factors affecting the quality of life here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="falkland-islands-climate"&gt;Falkland Islands climate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main characteristic of the weather is that it can change very rapidly between being mild and pleasant, to being cold and severe. It is said that all 4 seasons can be experienced in any one day of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geographically, Stanley, the capital, lies on the same latitude south as Stamford in Lincolnshire does north, while its longitude is as far west as Goose Bay in Canada, which accounts for a 3-hour time lag in the Austral summer and a 5-hour time lag in the Austral winter. Generally winter begins in June and lasts until mid October, usually bringing snow and sub-zero temperatures. But the most distinguishing climatic factor is the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature changes due to wind-chill can happen quickly and you need to be prepared and equipped. A sunny day can rapidly become a sub-zero blizzard. The Austral summer, from October to April, brings similar temperatures to the UK summer. Overall, the wind tends to be less strong in the winter than in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="travelling-to-the-falklands"&gt;Travelling to the Falklands&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight time to the Falklands is approximately 18 hours, with a short stopover at Ascension Island. All individuals and families regardless of whether you are military or civilian fly to the Falklands from &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time difference between UK and the Falkland Islands is minus 5 hours GMT in winter (Falklands) and minus 3 hours GMT in summer (Falklands). The UK is ahead of the Falkland Islands. There is also a local time change (late August to late October and late January to late March) and the time difference during these periods is 4 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ascension-island-a-short-guide"&gt;Ascension Island: a short guide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First discovered in 1501 by Juan Da Nova, Ascension was called Conception before being re-named in 1503 by Alphonse D’Alberquerque. A stopping off point for ships, Ascension was not continually inhabited until 1815 when Napoleon Bonaparte was imprisoned on St Helena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British occupied Ascension to prevent the French from using the Island as an escape route. The Victoria Marines worked hard to make the Island habitable, introducing a variety of plants and animals. Buildings, which still stand today, were erected up the Mountain and in the Garrison, now called Georgetown. Although almost indefensible, forts were built but British sovereignty was never challenged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the 19th century Ascension had gone into decline. In 1899 The Easter Telegraph Company (now called Cable and Wireless) found a new use for this speck of land. They laid telegraphy cable on the seabed, and soon Ascension became the centre of communications in the South Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later NASA found another use for the Island and tested the moon buggy on the lava flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="georgetown"&gt;Georgetown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally called Garrison by the Victoria Marines, Georgetown houses most of the Islands Public Buildings. The Church of St Mary the Virgin can be seen within the Islands racetrack. The comer stone was laid in 1843 and it was finally consecrated by the first Bishop of St Helena in 1861. Fort Hayes can be clearly seen on the coastline. Built in about 1860 it is now used by the Heritage Society as a museum. The museum also boasts a splendid picture gallery as well as a large and varied number of artefacts from the Islands history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="green-mountain"&gt;Green Mountain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tallest peak on the Island, Green Mountain is often shrouded in mist. It was recognised as having the greatest potential for vegetation and the Marines had a farm up there. In Victoria times and well into the 20th century this provided all the fresh produce for the Island including milk and vegetables. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, with the advent of the Airbridge from the UK, the farm is considerably smaller than it was. The herd of cows has been reduced to a handful of cattle, which have become wild. There are a number of pigs remaining and a small quantity of fresh vegetables make their way to the shop periodically. Still standing are several of the buildings including the Red Lion, which despite its name was never a pub in the UK sense. It was originally built to house farm workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dew Pond is the highest point of the Island and can be found surrounded by bamboo at the summit of Green Mountain. It was dug out in 1875 to act as an emergency water supply, although in practice it would never have been sufficient to provide water for the Island. The path to the top is often muddy and a rope is provided to help both ascent and descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sisters-peak"&gt;Sisters Peak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sisters Peak is one of the most recently active volcanic peaks (500-700 years ago) of the island and dominates the skyline. A path was cut to the top in 1972 it was opened as the Hannay-Pass up Sisters. It was the position for the first letter box (see things to do). The lava flows down the other side of the peaks can be clearly seen and there are fumarole caves to be explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="two-boats-village"&gt;Two Boats Village&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two Boats was built to house the BBC workers when the South Atlantic Relay Station was opened at English Bay. It is so named after the 2 long boats, which were up¬ended into the ground to act as shelters from the sun at the bottom of Green Mountain, when the water was carried down the coast. Two such boats can still be seen on the way to Dampier’s Drip from a stile at the top of Two Boats Village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="comfortless-cove"&gt;Comfortless Cove&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beautiful cove and one of the only two places where swimming is safe when the sea is calm. A rope has been pulled across the entrance to the cove making it even safer. Ideal for snorkelling when the sea is calm you can see a variety of fish, including Blackfish, which are the dustbins of the sea. Throw in any food substance and it will be enveloped by a Blackfish pushing and fighting to get their share. Inedible and not useful for bait they are perhaps one of the most common sights in the sea especially around the pierhead and are completely harmless to the swimmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comfortless Cove was originally called Comfort Cove. It was where the ships carrying yellow fever docked. Islanders would bring the stricken sailors food and water across the rocks whilst preventing an epidemic amongst their own community. There are several small cemeteries around the coastline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most visited is above the cover and is well signposted. It is called Bonetta Cemetery after the ship HMS Bonetta who brought its fever victims ashore in 1838. Such desolation led to the change of name. At a later date. The first transatlantic telegraph cables were brought ashore at this point. Some of the original cables can still be seen today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="boatswain-bird-island"&gt;Boatswain Bird Island&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boatswain Bird Island is inhabited by seabirds and landing by the public is forbidden. Boat trips and divers anchor off its shores and dolphins play around the boats although they tend to shy away from swimmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boatswain Bird Island can be seen from many vantage points around the Island; the top of Weatherpost or White Horse or simply by walking along from Hannay’s beach next to where the blow hole spews water into a fountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1923 the English Bay Company began mining guano deposits. The remains of this mining and the old log railway tracks can be seen on the surface of Boatswain Bird Island and around English Bay itself. Even after the English Bay Company stopped commercial operations the guano off Boatswain Island was collected to fertilise the farm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is the boatswain bird itself with its beautiful long tail that remains fairly aloof unlike the fairy terns, who in their eager curiosity fly low over your heads to see what you are doing. The Ascension frigate bird can be seen circling the skies looking for prey. The distinctive red pouches of the male are rarely seen. The boobies are a sight to behold when there is a fry around the Pierhead as they dive straight into the water to catch their share. Other birds include petrels, brown and black noddies and the wideawake or sooty tern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="falkland-islands-service-personnel-accommodation"&gt;Falkland Islands service personnel accommodation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="single-and-unaccompanied-service-personnel-accommodation"&gt;Single and unaccompanied service personnel accommodation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each room has a minimum of a single bed, wardrobe with internal shelving, desk, and sink unit with mirror. Each room is centrally heated and bedding in the form of duvet and feather pillows is provided. Sheets, pillowcases and covers are also provided. The only thing that individuals may find useful to bring is an extra coat hook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="service-family-accommodation"&gt;Service family accommodation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the guide to family accommodation on the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_53579"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36989/20121108-Pre_Arrivals_Pack-U.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-53579-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36989/thumbnail_20121108-Pre_Arrivals_Pack-U.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36989/20121108-Pre_Arrivals_Pack-U.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-53579-accessibility-help"&gt;Families pre-arrival pack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;722 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-53579-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Families%20pre-arrival%20pack%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Families%20pre-arrival%20pack%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Families pre-arrival pack").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="falkland-islands-amenities"&gt;Falkland Islands amenities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="withdrawing-money-and-making-payments"&gt;Withdrawing money and making payments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no ATM facilities on the Falkland Islands. Military Personnel can cash cheques with the Public Cashier and are allowed to cash four per month totalling no more than their take home pay. Cheques can also be cashed in the Officers’ and Sergeants’ Messes and at 12 Facility Reception, supported by a cheque guarantee card. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the British Forces Post Office is able to cash GIRO cheques free of charge. Civil Servants can also cash cheques with the public cashier up to £50 without a cheque guarantee Card (&lt;abbr title="cheque guarantee card"&gt;CGC&lt;/abbr&gt;) or up to their &lt;abbr title="cheque guarantee card"&gt;CGC&lt;/abbr&gt; limit. All other Civilian personnel must provide a valid &lt;abbr title="cheque guarantee card"&gt;CGC&lt;/abbr&gt; to cash any cheques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are strongly advised to bring extra cheque books with you into theatre as these are the most convenient method for withdrawing money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a branch of the Standard Chartered Bank in Stanley, there is no bank at the Military Personnel Centre (&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, this bank provides a cash advance service against credit and debit cards up to a maximum of £500 per day for a small fee. You will be required to show your passport as proof of i.d.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only facility at the Mount Pleasant Complex where Credit and Debit Cards are accepted is in the Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes (&lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt;) shops. Cashback is available against debit cards in the &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; Shops as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the larger shops in Stanley accept credit/debit cards. A handful of companies accept UK cheques but surcharges are often applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="shopping"&gt;Shopping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="mpc-shops"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; shops&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Families Ration Stores and &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; Bulk Store Shop for accompanied personnel. There are 2 small &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; Service Shops within the main accommodation complex. These cater for both accompanied and unaccompanied personnel, although prices are a little higher than in the UK. They sell sandwiches, confectionary, cold drinks, tinned and frozen food, greetings cards, magazines, jewellery and gifts, some single bedding, electrical goods (hairdryers, shavers etc), towels and toiletries. A selection of over-the-counter remedies for colds and headaches is sold here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="internet-shopping"&gt;Internet shopping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clothes and certain products are extremely limited and it is recommended to shop by Internet. It is advisable to register with a catalogue before leaving the UK, but do check that they deliver to &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; addresses. UK postal codes are also available and can be used in conjunction with the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; address. ZZ99 3WZ indicates that the address is overseas. For more information please see Mail below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="stanley-shopping"&gt;Stanley shopping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a growing number of small shops in Stanley, and it is improving all the time. These comprise mainly of gift shops, small supermarkets, by UK standards, and two DIY stores. Although attractive items go quickly, though the shops rarely run out of basics. There is not a chemist or traditional green grocer, though pharmacy items and fruit and vegetables are available from most supermarkets. There is no optician. Some prices are 30-40% higher than UK, but other items are cheaper than UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="fic-shopping-complex"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Company"&gt;FIC&lt;/abbr&gt; shopping complex&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shopping complex is some distance from the married quarters. It houses a Cable &amp;amp; Wireless shop, a ‘RightLines’ which is part of the &lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Company"&gt;FIC&lt;/abbr&gt; and a cafe. The ‘Right lines’ shop sells a wide range of products including a range of groceries, clothing, stationary, electrical items, watch batteries, fishing tackle, cosmetics and perfumes and FI souvenirs. If you cannot find what you are looking for in the shop, the shop assistant is always willing to bring goods in from the West Store in Stanley for the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bimble-box"&gt;Bimble Box&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bimble Box Shop sells Falkland Islands souvenirs, which includes logo sweaters, polo and rugby shirts, plaques and some sportswear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-service-institute-fund-sif"&gt;The Service Institute Fund (&lt;abbr title="Service Institute Fund"&gt;SIF&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Service Institute Fund"&gt;SIF&lt;/abbr&gt; hires out TV, videos, DVDs, games consoles, vehicles, fishing tackle and video and digital cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="churches-and-church-services"&gt;Churches and church services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are regular services in St Cuthbert’s Church, which is situated in the centre of the Mount Pleasant Domestic Complex. The Church is interdenominational and is served by &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; chaplains from either the Church of England, or the Church of Scotland and Free Churches who hold seperate services. A Catholic Priest from Stanley takes Mass and hears confessions weekly. In Stanley there are 3 churches: Christchurch Cathedral, St Mary’s Roman Catholic Church and the Tabernacle Free Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hairdressing"&gt;Hairdressing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sodexho-run unisex hairdressing salon is in the main accommodation complex. There are two hairdressers at present that offer a range of facilities. There are also 2 hairdressers based in Stanley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laundry"&gt;Laundry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Falkland Islands Laundry Facility or FILF as it is commonly known provides laundry and dry cleaning facilities free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="mail"&gt;Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mail normally arrives twice a week on the airbridge, and is delivered within 4-7 days of posting from UK. Inland first class postage rates apply, but there is no air parcel service for packets over 2 kg in weight. Sea mail can take up to 3 months to arrive. ‘Blueys’ (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Form 674) are Airmail Letter Forms available from UK Post Offices, &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; post office and &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; library which are sent free of charge to and from Falklands. If mail travels by sea, this can cause problems with internet shopping as it may arrive too late for you to be able to return the product under its guarantee. Unfortunately, some companies do not understand &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="telephone-facilities"&gt;Telephone facilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civilian telephone link with the UK is good, however it is expensive. Unaccompanied personnel who qualify for a welfare package are entitled to one 30 minute phone card a week and there are various public telephones within the accommodation complex where these cards can be used. If you are not entitled to the card or just wish to speak for longer, phone cards can be bought on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For residents of the Married Quarters you have the option of installing a private Cable and Wireless telephone line to make UK calls or use the Internet. Many families prefer this option as it gives flexibility in making and receiving calls. Calls to UK can be over £1/minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cable and Wireless bill calls monthly. For friends and family to phone the Falkland’s cheaply they can buy a phone card from the Post Office that slashes the cost per minute considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internet is by dial-up connection, with costs varying between 2p and 6p depending on the time of day that you connect. You can also connect via a broadband connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the dialling code to the UK is 0044 plus area code less the 0 plus phone number, eg 0044 1234 567890&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to call the Falkland Islands from the UK the code is 005 007 then the extension number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if making a compassionate call to the Falkland’s they should be directed through the compassionate cell to ensure a swift response&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="paying-bills-accompanied-staff-only"&gt;Paying bills (accompanied staff only)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can pay your different bills in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;families shop - the invoice is sent to the serving persons work via internal mail and this is paid at the cashier  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mess bill: collect from the mess after email informs that they are ready then pay at service funds cashier  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bulk store: invoice is sent to the serving persons work via internal mail and paid directly at the bulk store  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stanley Growers: staff at the families shop will give this to you and you can pay by cheque in the deposit box in the families store or you can pay them directly in Stanley  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cable &amp;amp; Wireless: comes via external Falkland mail and you can pay Cable &amp;amp; Wireless in Stanley or at the Cable and Wireless shop in the &lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Company"&gt;FIC&lt;/abbr&gt; shopping complex  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fuel - bills are delivered via internal mail and payable at the service funds cashier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="accompanied-staff-family-facilities"&gt;Accompanied staff: family facilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bringing-children-into-theatre"&gt;Bringing children into Theatre&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependant children can be brought into theatre as duty passengers if they are at university or 18 years and under. If your children are at boarding school they can come down for the school holidays three times a year. If your children are at University, they can come down once a year, this can be when you like but it is presumed that this will be for the summer holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your children are not at boarding school, they can be indulged down. A child under 16 must be accompanied by a nominated adult. A 16 to 17yr old can travel on their own, but can not escort a child under 16. Applications to bring children down are on local forms managed by the International University Sports Federation (&lt;abbr title="International University Sports Federation"&gt;FISU&lt;/abbr&gt;) administrative office and the JABC. Do check you have received a booking reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="schools-and-childcare-facilities"&gt;Schools and childcare facilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="primary-school"&gt;Primary school&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small primary school is established at Mount Pleasant, which has a head teacher and 2 class teachers. The school is part of Service Children’s Education, which is a government agency, which has schools worldwide, supporting the children of service personnel and entitled attached civilians. Children start school in the September after their fourth birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The holidays are in line with the UK but there is usually a four-week break in December and another four-week break in August. Children stay at school during lunchtime and eat a packed lunch. Children are transported to and from school by a school bus. The School has its own sweatshirt, which can be purchased from the school. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="secondary-school"&gt;Secondary school&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a secondary school in Stanley, which provides education for up to 16-year-olds studying GCSEs. A boarding house is provided for all children from outside Stanley and because of the distance from Mount Pleasant, children from the Station have to board, Monday to Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="childcare-for-working-parents"&gt;Childcare for working parents&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you are living in Stanley, where limited childcare facilities in the form of childminders are available, or have children of secondary school age who will therefore be boarding in Stanley, no pre- or post- school facilities are available for working parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="babies"&gt;Babies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Falkland Islands are a fantastic place to bring babies and young children. There is a lot to see and do and plenty of wide-open spaces, clean beaches, and wildlife. The Islands are a safe environment; with little crime, and even the weather isn’t as bad as many people are led to believe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of availability, you can get almost anything here. It requires shopping around and there is rarely any choice of brand or colour. So, if you like to use a specific brand of something, it is often not available and would be best brought with you or purchased over the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internet shopping can be extremely useful for baby gear. For instance the Boots web site sells most items available in its stores but they do charge a delivery fee for British Forces Post Office (&lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) orders of any value. Nappies, formula, baby food, clothing, over-the-counter medicine, lotions and potions, etc can all be sent down here. The only snag is that any parcels weighing over 2 kg will be sent on the monthly ship which can take around 8 -10 weeks. It pays to plan ahead a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;disposable nappies are available from various places in Stanley &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;related items: wipes, nappy bags, cotton wool, Sudocreme, baby shampoo and soap are all available in Stanley and generally at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;formula: available in various places in Stanley and can be ordered through websites like Boots and be sent down on the ship  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UHT cow’s milk: is readily available through the families shop, in the &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; and at Rightlines at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sterilisation: Milton, etc is available readily in Stanley  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;equipment: bottles, teats, beakers, etc are available in Stanley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These goods will be more expensive than in the UK and specific brands and sizes may not be available. If you use a specific brand it is best to bring any spares you might need with you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reusable or terry nappies are not available to buy, but some people choose to bring them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very limited selection of jars, tins and dried baby food are available in Stanley. The selection varies according to supply. In general it is necessary to make up purees etc, for young babies at home. The houses at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; all have large chest freezers and a wide selection of frozen fruit and vegetables are readily available alongside the fresh produce in the families shop at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="baby-clothing"&gt;Baby clothing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variable selection of baby and toddler clothing is available in a few shops in Stanley. Alternatively, Internet shopping is very popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather in the Falklands can be very windy and fairly cold. An all-in-one snowsuit or similar warm and waterproof outdoor clothing is extremely useful and although sometimes available in Stanley, choice is very limited&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Health Visitor attends &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; every other month and has a foot-measuring device. Shoes are not easily available in Stanley (although a limited selection is sometimes available along with trainers and Wellingtons). In general children’s shoes are purchased by mail order from the UK, or sent down by friendly relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a swimming pool at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; for the use of families. Swim nappies and costumes are occasionally available in certain shops in Stanley. The sun can be very strong all year round, and hats and sun screen are vital. (A limited selection can be purchased in Stanley)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="health-facilities-for-babies"&gt;Health facilities for babies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="health-visitor"&gt;Health Visitor&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Health Visitor in Stanley who visits &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; every other month and holds a weekly baby clinic in Stanley Hospital, which anyone can attend. Immunisations are arranged through the Health Visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="medicine"&gt;Medicine&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Med Centre at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; holds stocks of infant paracetamol, infant ibruprofen, as well as other prescription medicines for children. If your child requires a specific prescription, it is worth speaking to the Med Centre in advance of your posting. Calpol and other non- prescription medicine are also available in Stanley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="teething"&gt;Teething&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teething gel is available in Stanley and occasionally at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;, as are baby toothbrushes and toothpaste. Again, there is little or no choice over brands and the price is more than in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sunscreen"&gt;Sunscreen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunscreen of Factor 25 is normally available from the Med Centre at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; in limited supply and in Stanley. However, baby sunscreen in the UK is often of Factor 45 or higher and this is not always available - it is absolutely vital in the summer and necessary on many days in the winter too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="emergency-treatment"&gt;Emergency treatment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cases needing medical treatment beyond that available at the unit Medical Centre are transferred to the hospital in Stanley or returned to the UK or South America for specialized care. All emergencies are dealt with in the first instance by the Medical Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="baby-clinics"&gt;Baby clinics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The health visitor from Stanley visits &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; on a bi-monthly basis. Clinics are held in the Medical Centre and they usually also visit the playgroup&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="baby-equipment"&gt;Baby equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="cots-highchairs-and-stair-gates"&gt;Cots, highchairs and stair gates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all available from Barrack Stores at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;. However, they should be requested in advance of your arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="car-seats"&gt;Car seats&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a legal requirement that children are suitably restrained in vehicles. Again, car seats are not readily available in Stanley and are very expensive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pushchairs-and-carry-packs"&gt;Pushchairs and carry-packs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; and Stanley have pavements suitable for pushchairs. Elsewhere, this is not the case and many people find a back-pack carrier extremely useful. Again these are not available in the Falklands, but could be purchased tax-free through mail order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toys"&gt;Toys&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A selection of toys is available in several shops in Stanley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those coming with small babies need to be well prepared. Issued cots are on the whole ancient and rickety. Although baby items are available in Stanley, they are expensive and the availability is erratic. Consequently, experience suggests that you bring down as much as you can in terms of nappies, toiletries, dried baby food and clothes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="childrens-activities"&gt;Children’s activities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="scouting-groups"&gt;Scouting groups&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meet as one group in the community centre on Wednesday evening at 1830 - 2000hrs. Girls and boys up to the age of 12 can take part in a wide variety of activities under the supervision of trained leaders. Helpers are always welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="swimming-pools"&gt;Swimming pools&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; pool is open to children (for further details, see the sports facilities section) and pupils of the Mount Pleasant School as according to the timetable. A copy of this will be available upon your arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="family-shopping"&gt;Family shopping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="family-ration-shop"&gt;Family ration shop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shop stocks the same range of foodstuffs as the messes, plus an extra 60 items from a non-core range. They also stock a range of food and drinks imported from Chile by Stanley Growers, who run the local garden centre. Fresh bread is available and normally must be ordered the day before. This shop is the main source of supplies for most families. It is not available to unaccompanied personnel. The &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; has problems shipping so patience and a realistic expectation are essential. Prices are generally higher than in the UK due to freight charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some items are only available in ‘Catering Packs’. Stanley Growers is a small outlet that supplements the fruit and vegetables that are flown in on the ‘Airbridge’. Most items are available most of the time, but not in large quantities. The day after the airbridge lands is the day to go shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-naafi-bulk-issue-store"&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; bulk issue store&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to purchase items in bulk (eg boxes of wine, dozens of toilet rolls) then you can buy directly from the &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt; bulk store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="groceries"&gt;Groceries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good basic range of foodstuffs is available from the rations shop and &lt;abbr title="Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes"&gt;NAAFI&lt;/abbr&gt;. Items bought in Stanley can supplement this. Specialist ingredients are sometimes not available so it is best to bring a supply. Special types of baby food and baby milk are limited and not always readily available. On the whole, however, it is possible to get most foodstuffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only shops available except for those at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; are found in Stanley. These comprise mainly of gift shops, small supermarkets and a DIY store. Clothes are extremely limited and it is recommended to shop by internet. It is advisable to register with a catalogue before leaving the UK, but do check that they deliver to &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pets"&gt;Pets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel are not encouraged to bring dogs to the Falkland Islands because of Hydatic disease caused by a sheep parasite. The disease can be transmitted to humans via the eggs of tapeworm carried by dogs on their coats or saliva and personnel are therefore strongly advised not to stroke island dogs. Cats must wear a collar and be neutered. Approval can be given to bring a pet to the Falklands providing the animal has resided in the UK since birth, or for 6 months or prior to embarking for the Islands. If this is the case, no quarantine restrictions apply, except for 2 weeks ‘house quarantine’ on arrival. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if your pet has travelled from a country other than the UK, it will have to undergo 6 months quarantine in the UK before embarking for the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for service animals, all animals must travel to the Falkland Islands by sea. To arrange transportation by ship, permission must be sought from the captain before sailing. The pet owner must provide the necessary documentation, cage, bedding and food for the duration of the voyage. The captain will appoint a volunteer to look after the pet for the voyage they will expect to be thanked financially for their efforts. This ship will not accept any liability. More details are available from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

DHL  
&lt;br&gt;Global Forwarding  
&lt;br&gt;Bldg 36  
&lt;br&gt;Sea Mounting Centre  
&lt;br&gt;Marchwood  
&lt;br&gt;Hants  
&lt;br&gt;SO40 4ZG  
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 02380 663455&lt;br&gt;
Fax: 02380 666021  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department of Agriculture  
&lt;br&gt;Stanley  
&lt;br&gt;PO Box 153  
&lt;br&gt;Falkland Islands  
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telephone: +500 27366&lt;br&gt;
Fax: +500 27352  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more than 2 pets will be allowed in any SFA. Pets permitted in SFA on the strict condition that they are controlled and do not become a nuisance to other SFA occupants. In this context; ‘nuisance’ may signify excessive noise, damage, aggression etc. In the event of complaints about pets, owners will be warned and advised to keep the animal under control. Should the problem persist, permission to keep the animal may be withdrawn, in which case the owner will be responsible for making whatever arrangements are necessary to remove the animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="jobs-for-the-family"&gt;Jobs for the family&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few employment opportunities at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Most of these vacancies are advertised locally and through the families officer or Command Sec. Only rarely are posts available in Stanley, but they require a commute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, contact Command Secretariat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-to-bring-to-the-falklands"&gt;What to bring to the Falklands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is recommended that you contact the person you are replacing before travelling to ensure that you do not bring duplicate items that are already in your accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In winter (Jun-Sep) it can be difficult to get outside. If you do venture out, the weather is inclement and changes quickly and dramatically. Inside, the long concrete linking corridors are cold but the bars, accommodation and working areas are very warm. The following lists apply to all military and civilian personnel unless otherwise stated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="packing-list-all-ranks"&gt;Packing list: all ranks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tough outdoor wear with hoods. Recommend that Gore-Tex etc are brought from UK either before departure or by mail order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s recommended that you bring the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fleece  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gore-Tex/waterproof jacket  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;warm trousers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sturdy shoes &amp;amp; walking boots  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;jumpers/sweatshirts  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;waterproof boots  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;waterproof trousers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;jeans/leggings  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dressing gown/slippers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tights (supply not good but improving)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gloves/hats/scarves  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;normal indoor clothing  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flip-flops for the showers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;walking socks  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;smart outfit of trousers, shirts and tie or dress/skirt and blouse  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extra socks and thermal underwear  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sports kit and swimwear  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some summer clothing (can be very warm and possible Authorised Absence in Ascension)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make-up, hair products and specialist medicinal needs  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sunglasses and suntan lotion (high protection factor)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sleeping bags (good quality/warm) – needed for all helicopter trips (service personnel and UK Based Civil Servants get these issued)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ladies - evening wear for mess functions and Stanley Balls  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CS95s and civilian dress &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of the Falkland Islands climate and the limited baggage allowance, CS95 boots, parkas, combat jackets/smocks, foul weather jacket/trousers may be worn with civilian dress. This concession is an exception to the normal Service rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="officers"&gt;Officers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All officers should bring a jacket/tie, lounge suit, mess kit. In addition, officers of the rank Cdr, Lt Col, Wg Cdr and above – their service parade dress with gloves and medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="wos--sgts"&gt;WOs &amp;amp; Sgts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All senior non-commissioned officers (&lt;abbr title="senior non-commissioned officers"&gt;SNCOs&lt;/abbr&gt;) should bring with them a jacket or pullover/cardigan, long sleeved shirt and tie as well as some smart slacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="electronic-equipment"&gt;Electronic equipment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A range of electrical and entertainment equipment is available in theatre. However, this is on a ‘first come, first served’ basis locally, so it is advisable to bring anything specific, such as cameras, with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transporting-personal-effects-to-the-falkland-islands"&gt;Transporting personal effects to the Falkland Islands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to bring additional personal effects into theatre, you can arrange for this to be carried out by the Defence Transports Movements Agency (&lt;abbr title="Defence Transports Movements Agency"&gt;DTMA&lt;/abbr&gt;). For military personnel, contact your Central Admin Point Of Contact for the &lt;abbr title="Defence Transports Movements Agency"&gt;DTMA&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet which will explain your entitlements and give you additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a civilian, you need to write to the &lt;abbr title="Defence Transports Movements Agency"&gt;DTMA&lt;/abbr&gt; and request a copy of the &lt;abbr title="Defence Transports Movements Agency"&gt;DTMA&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet. The address is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;abbr title="Defence Transports Movements Agency"&gt;DTMA&lt;/abbr&gt; HQ DLO  
&lt;br&gt;Monxton Road  
&lt;br&gt;Andover  
&lt;br&gt;Hants  
&lt;br&gt;SP11 8HJ  
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="getting-around-the-falkland-islands"&gt;Getting around the Falkland Islands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; covers a large area and with no public transport and few pavements, the distance from family quarters to such places as the families ration shop or Medical centre make travel on foot impractical.
&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; is 35 miles from Stanley, the Island’s capital and the journey normally takes about an hour, but considerably longer in bad weather. It is therefore essential for families to have their own transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; roads are properly surfaced, off base they are not metalled, rough and invariably badly marked with potholes. Consequently, a Land Rover or other 4 wheel-drive vehicle is the most suitable form of transport. There are a number of methods of acquiring a 4 wheel-drive vehicle. You may be able to buy from your predecessor. If this is not possible, it is advisable to ask someone already at &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; to look out for any vehicles up for sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative is to buy in the UK and ship down. Personnel who intend to ship a vehicle to the Falkland Islands should note that unleaded petrol is not available, only diesel. A guide for indulging vehicles to the Falkland Islands can be sent to you on request from the families Officer. A local driving licence is required by all posted to the Falklands for longer than 12 months; this can be purchased from the local police. No test is necessary, only third party, fire and theft insurance is available through the Falkland Islands Company (&lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Company"&gt;FIC&lt;/abbr&gt;) in Stanley or at “Rightlines”. Road tax is payable as well as a registration and transfer of ownership fee of £30.00. Fuel can be purchased either in Stanley but is mostly obtained on a repayment basis through service sources at the MT Pumps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sections allow their vehicles to be lent out to non accompanied personnel when they are not being used for operational reasons so if you are down for six months this is always an option. There is also a good free bus service for military and civilian staff run between Stanley and &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; at the weekend and during special occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="driving-in-the-falkland-islands"&gt;Driving in the Falkland Islands&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving is a necessary way to visit many parts of the Falkland Islands. However, you should be aware that there are certain dangers that can make driving extremely dangerous. For example, the road surfacing may change suddenly from metalled tarmac to loose shale and shingle. This means that sudden braking and steering may cause the vehicle to loose traction and skid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most roads are raised with deep drainage channels at either side to allow rapid water dispersion. There are few crash barriers or road markings. Such dangers are the reason for the strictly enforced 40mph speed limit on rural roads. Due to this speeding fines are incredibly expensive when compared to the fines enforced in the UK and can easily run into hundreds of pounds. If you are caught speeding in theatre, the Royal Falkland Islands Police will endorse your UK driving licence, if you do not have a Falkland Islands counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To obtain a Falkland Islands licence, you must go to the Police Station in Stanley with a photograph and £5.00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These plus other factors such as rapidly changing weather, freely roaming animals and the isolated nature of many routes can be challenging even for experienced drivers. On arrival ensure that you attend the driving brief which will provide advice and tips aimed to help you to drive safely in the Falklands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="heliops"&gt;Heliops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrants for R&amp;amp;R may be used to obtain trips to outer islands and remote locations. Further, groups may get together to make a ‘helibid’ to these locations. It is better to read the rules once you have arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="falkland-islands-government-air-service-figas"&gt;Falkland Islands Government Air Service (&lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Government Air Service"&gt;FIGAS&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Falkland Islands Government Air Service"&gt;FIGAS&lt;/abbr&gt; operates Islander passenger aircraft that provide internal air services throughout the Falklands. This can cost depending on how it is arranged so please speak to the Mount Pleasant Travel staff and the W &amp;amp; R clerk when you arrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="things-to-do-on-ascension-island"&gt;Things to do on Ascension Island&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ascension-island-wildlife"&gt;Ascension Island wildlife&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the most famous of the Ascension wildlife is the Green Turtle or Chelonia Mydas which swims from Brazil to the Islands sandy beaches to lay its eggs every November to May. During its 1000 mile journey the turtle fasts. Mating off shore the female clambers up the beach to dig her hole and lay up to 120 eggs at one time. The turtle visits the beach up to 10 times over a 17-day period. When these hatch the young make their way instinctively to the sea where a variety of predators means that few will survive. The Turtles once provided fresh meat for the sailors and a good source of income for the Island. Today they are a protected species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only indigenous inhabitants of the Island are the land crabs and the seabirds. The land crabs are most prolific around the foot of Green Mountain and the old NASA site. They are purple and orange and despite living on the land return to the seashore to lay their eggs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea birds have all but left the Island. Ships inadvertently introduced rats and mice. In a bid to exterminate them the cat was introduced. They found the birds much easier prey and drove them onto the hard to reach cliffs and shacks off the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donkeys and sheep introduced by the early farmers for labour and food have since been allowed to roam free causing an unusual traffic hazard, particularly after rain when they stand in the road to drink from the puddles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="watch-the-green-turtles-laying-and-hatching"&gt;Watch the green turtles laying and hatching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Season runs from December to June. Turtles can be found in many locations, but Long Beach, next to Georgetown, is probably the best location. They almost always lay their eggs at night when it is dark, however, please do your watch before 11pm, so if a turtle is disturbed, she will have a chance to try again. Don’t use a torch, approach from the rear and don’t take any photographs until she is well into the egg laying phase or returning to the sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the hatchlings emerge, they wait until it is dark and the sand has cooled, before trying to reach the sea. If they try to cross the beach in daylight, the birds often get them before they reach the water. I would recommend booking with the Conservation group for a turtle talk and watch. These happen on Monday and Thursday evenings at 9pm and costs £5 per person. They show you a video then take you down to Long Beach where they will try and find a turtle laying their eggs and some babies, depending on the time of year. The Conservation office on the main road through Georgetown and is open from 10am-noon Monday to Saturday and at other times on a request basis, Extension 6359.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="walk-up-green-mountain-and-get-a-stamp-in-your-passport"&gt;Walk up Green Mountain and get a stamp in your passport&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ascension Island offers an infinite variety of landscapes. From the dense lush vegetation on Green Mountain, to the spectacular volcanic landscapes found elsewhere. There are many good walks on the island, some easy, some severe, often with splendid views. Many of the walks are known as “letterbox” walks” with rubber stamps to validate your achievement in a map book. The book can be purchased from the Tourist Information Office in the Obsidian Hotel. Some routes are hazardous and expert advice should be sought before attempting any of them. For safety reasons, we recommend a minimum of 3 people to do a walk together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular walks is at the top of Green Mountain. You can drive up there and park just before the Red Lion (sorry it’s not a pub!) From the Red Lion follow the track up past the old pig farm and on to the cow sheds. Take the path sign posted to the Dew Pond. The path is well marked, but sometimes can be overgrown and is very often muddy. The top section gets very steep and there is a boardwalk and rope for you to help get to the top - not as difficult as it sounds. You can do this with children. The pond was built in the 1870s and an anchor chain just past the pond marks the highest point (2817ft) on the island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="visit-the-blow-hole-at-hannays-beach"&gt;Visit the blow hole at Hannays Beach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a short drive from Two Boats down Watson’s Way towards the North East Bay, when the road forks right. Park past the Ariane tracking station, then walk away from the station down to the beach where you will find the blow hole. Don’t forget your camera! There are lots of rock pools here which are full of fish - a great place to visit with children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="take-a-dip-at-comfortless-cove-or-english-bay"&gt;Take a dip at Comfortless Cove or English Bay&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Comfortless Cove turn off at One Boat and take a drive down to Pyramid Point Road. Follow the track to the left before the ‘golf ball’ then walk down to the beach. Enjoy a swim and relax on the beach, but before you leave pay a visit to the Bonetta Cemetery at the back of the cove. The Cemetery dates from 1838. It is where victims of yellow fever from among crews of ships patrolling the coast of West Africa were laid to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to English Bay turn right off Pyramid Point Road, onto English Bay Road. Go past the BBC Atlantic Relay Station, take the left turn just before the power station and follow the road down to the main beach. There is a good barbecue and covered area should you want some shade down on the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both beaches are excellent for snorkelling as there is a great variety of marine life to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NB: These are the only two beaches where you can swim and even then, do not swim if there is any swell running. Over the years several people have been killed by swells lifting them and dumping them on the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="take-a-walk-through-the-wideawake-sooty-tern-colony"&gt;Take a walk through the Wideawake (Sooty) Tern colony&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is seasonal and will depend on when the terns are nesting on Wideawake fairs at the back of the airfield. Please get advice from the conservation people in Georgetown if you want to go there on your own otherwise you take trips out on a Wednesday at 1000 hrs (for 2 hours) with the conservation office. Cost is £5 per person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="visit-st-marys-church-georgetown"&gt;Visit St Mary’s church Georgetown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built by the Royal Marines in 1843, St. Mary’s Church contains many interesting memorial stones and gives a real taste of Ascension Island history. It also contains stained-glass windows in memory of those men who lost their lives in the Falklands. St. Mary’s is open 24 hours a day and the door is only closed to keep out the donkeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="take-a-drive-up-the-nasa-road-to-the-devils-ashpit"&gt;Take a drive up the NASA road to The Devils Ashpit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you drive up the road watch out for the yellow and purple land crabs, which live in burrows on the side of the road. They like to live quite high up on land, only returning to the seashore to breed and lay their eggs on the beaches near the high water marks. At the end of the road you will see the old NASA control building. This area is the starting point for several walks on the east of the island. If you are equipped to do some walking, the Weather Post and Devil’s Cauldron are worth the effort from this point as they give the best views of Boatswain Bird Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="go-big-game-fishing"&gt;Go big game fishing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fishing is a very popular pastime at Ascension, both as a hobby and to supplement the diet and many people fish either from the shore or boats. The waters around the island host a wide variety of fish. Offshore can be found such species as Tuna, Wahoo, Marlin, Sailfish, Dorado and shark. Inshore Grouper, Bullseye and Congor Eel can be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several skippered boats (with fishing gear included) available for hire at reasonable rates. Contact numbers for local fisherman can be obtained from the reception at the Obsidian Hotel. Should you want to purchase fishing equipment, there is a shop situated in the Exiles building who specialise in fishing rods and all the necessary equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE - Fishing from the rocks around Ascension can be dangerous due to tidal surges and unpredictability of the sea state. Before attempting ANY form of fishing on Ascension, you should be wise to seek the advice of an experienced fisherman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="visit-the-museum"&gt;Visit the museum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fort Hayes Museum and Photo Gallery us run by the Ascension Island Heritage Society, and is well worth a visit. It is packed with information, photographs, historical facts and hands on things for the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the road to the side of the Saints Club, heading towards the pier, the museum is sign posted to the left. Follow down the hill and the main museum building is on the left. On the right is Fort Hayes itself and part of the museum is under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The museum is only open on a Saturday, from 11am to 1pm hrs and it is free to visit. Tours on request can be organised, but a small donation is usually accepted for special openings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="visit-a-fumerole"&gt;Visit a fumerole&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fumeroles are formed when large air pockets appear in red hot lava as a volcano erupts. When the lava cools a fumerole or cave evolves. There are many fumeroles and caves around the island to explore. A good one to visit with kids is the fumerole behind Command Hill, as it is easy to find and fairly easy walking to get to it. The reception at the Obsidian Hotel holds a folder that is full of fumeroles to visit and maps how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="go-diving-experienced-divers-only"&gt;Go diving (experienced divers only)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diving conditions are usually excellent with clear warm water and a wide variety of marine life. Sea conditions are particularly variable from November to May. Large swells can build up which can make diving impossible. There are no rescue or hypabaric facilities on the island, so safety is paramount, with divers having to take full responsibility for their actions. Conservative dive profiles, safety stops and voluntary depth limits make sense when the nearest recompression chamber is at least 8 hours flight away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base dive club is happy for divers from &lt;abbr title="Mount Pleasant Airfield"&gt;MPA&lt;/abbr&gt; to join them providing they are BSAC qualified and have a current diving medical. The club dive 2/3 times each month (usually on a Sunday). The cost is £10 per dive or £25 for a 6 month membership with the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gym"&gt;Gym&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gym at Travellers Hill is well equipped with squash court, cycling machines and weight training equipment. Various sports happen on a regular basis and anyone can join in - extra bodies always welcome! The PTI holds some equipment such as snorkels and masks (for both adults and kids) for the R&amp;amp;R visitors, which can be used during your stay. The PTI is usually in the gym office between 9-10:30am on the day after a flight arrives to issue these items, or you can contact him at other times on extension 3318.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tennis"&gt;Tennis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tennis courts in Georgetown, Travellers Hill, Two Boats Village and the American base. All these courts are free to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="swimming-pools-1"&gt;Swimming pools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Georgetown there is a small saltwater swimming pool that is open all day, but there is no lifeguard. Head towards the pier and as you reach the bottom of the hill turn right. About 150 metres on your right you will find the pool. It is free to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Two Boats Village there is a fresh water swimming pool situated behind the Two Boats Club that is free to use. There is no lifeguard and entry is gained via a keypad on the gate. The entry code is 231.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pool at Travellers Hill is for the more serious swimmer. There are sun loungers round the pool and there is a lifeguard. Access is limited - time can vary so check once you are in Ascension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="golf"&gt;Golf&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Golf is a very popular game in Ascension. The 18-hole golf course at One Boat (about half way between Georgetown and Two Boats) offers a unique environment to play golf. The “greens” are called “browns” and are made of crushed compacted lava smoothed flat with diesel oil and around the edges of the fairways large boulders of volcanic rock can be found. It is a very challenging course and it is recommended that you play with a local who is familiar with the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The golf course is open 7 days a week. The cost is £2.50* for a 9-hole game and £5.00*for a full round. There is a friendly match played every Thursday afternoon, which anyone can join in. *Prices are subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE - You must provide your own golf clubs or try the gym at Travellers Hill who may have spare clubs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sports-activities-and-facilities-in-the-falkland-islands"&gt;Sports activities and facilities in the Falkland Islands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Longdon Gymnasium has a fully equipped CV training area, a weight training area with fixed machines and free weights, a large games hall and 4 squash courts. Sporting activities on offer vary according to the instructors in Theatre but the range can include anything from aerobics and spinning to windsurfing lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tumbledown Gymnasium is a large sports hall used for lessons and indoor sports but also includes a golf simulator (small charge applicable) and a climbing wall. There is also Laser Quest available here at the weekends for adults and children (age dependent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; also has a 33-metre heated swimming pool, a sauna and a sun-shower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gull Island Pond is a shallow lake located at East Cove between &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; and Mare Harbour and is home to the Water Sports Centre equipped to cater for the canoeing, kayaking, dinghy sailing and windsurfing (at various levels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPS has its own joint Service Adventurous Training Centre located at Hillside in Stanley where Service personnel can undertake either AT or FD courses participating in activities such as mountain walking, climbing/abseiling, mountain biking and canoeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are partial to golf, a course is available at the &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; and also in Stanley. Please note that the golf courses are not as you would expect to find in the UK. There are no greens as such, just rough areas. At Stanley golf course you will find a unique hazard of a mine field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other activities available include mountain biking, go-karting, paint balling, surfing and fishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="personnel-insurance"&gt;Personnel insurance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes to the MoD policy on civilian use of sport facilities that includes dependants place conditions on civilians using the sports facilities at Mount Pleasant Complex (&lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt;). Although civilians are allowed access to the sports facilities, there is a requirement that individuals using these facilities must have their own 3rd party liability and personal accident insurance. A corporate 3rd party liability insurance to cover all civilians has been obtained by BFSAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there still remains the issue of personal accident insurance, which should be obtained before using the sports facilities. If individuals continue to use the facilities without personal accident insurance, they do so at their own risk. If you have any queries or questions regarding this policy, please contact J8 Policy and Personnel on your arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the policy of &lt;abbr title="Military Personnel Centre"&gt;MPC&lt;/abbr&gt; to allow dependants to use all the PEd facilities when available and on the understanding that military personnel and training matters take priority. Dependants under the age of 16 can only use the gymnasium when supervised by a suitable qualified adult and taking part in organised sports session; they may not use any of the CV or weight training equipment. Dependants under the age of 14 must be accompanied by an adult when using the swimming pool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56795</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:38:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:38:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/commercial-sale-of-type-22-frigates"/>
    <title>Commercial sale of Type 22 Frigates</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is the Disposal Services Authority (&lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) intention to invite expressions of interest in tendering for the Type 22 Frigates (HMS Chatham, HMS Campbeltown, HMS Cumberland and HMS Cornwall) for the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further Use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sinking for an Artificial reef&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this stage the &lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; does not require interested parties to specify which Vessel/s they wish to bid for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the &lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; intention to award at least one vessel to a UK Ship Recycler; this is in part to secure detailed knowledge of the UK’s capacity to recycle vessels. Any decision to award to a UK Ship Recycling company will be made in accordance with transparent and objective evaluation criteria which will be issued at the Invitation to Tender stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All interested parties should note that only Bidders that have completed and passed a Pre-Qualification Questionnaire (&lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be sent an Invitation to Tender (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt;) for the vessels and allowed access to view the vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vessels are moored at Portsmouth and will be sold from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; are planning on hosting viewings 25th February - 15th March 2013. Monday - Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously requested all bidders intending to undertake inspection of the vessels will be required to wear the correct PPE clothing i.e. steel toecap boots, high vis jackets (overalls optional). Please be assured that if you do not have steel toecap boots on arrival you will be refused access to the vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only Bidders that have received a copy of the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt; will be allowed access to inspect the vessels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bidders should not book travel until they have received a copy of the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Tender"&gt;ITT&lt;/abbr&gt; and understood the requirements.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the &lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt; can be down loaded from the bottom of this page or you can e-mail the &lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Commercial section requesting a copy at &lt;a href="mailto:deslcsls-dsa-comrcl-3b@mod.uk" title="email to request a copy: deslcsls-dsa-comrcl-3b@mod.uk"&gt;deslcsls-dsa-comrcl-3b@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closing date for returning the &lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt; to the &lt;abbr title="Disposal Services Authority"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and expression of interest is 17.00 GMT Wednesday 23rd January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hms-cumberland"&gt;HMS CUMBERLAND&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS CUMBERLAND" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5685/cumberland_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Cumberland&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;formally a Warship Frigate F85 was built at Yarrow Shipbuilders, Glasgow UK in 1988 and is now lying at   HMNB Portsmouth. The vessel ceased service on the 23rd September 2011 and is due to be tendered early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All interested parties should beware that only companies that have successfully completed a Pre Qualification Questionnaire (&lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be sent an invitation to tender for this vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More detailed information is available on &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/hms-cumberland-specifications?cachebust=1355755641&amp;amp;preview=56852" title="HMS CUMBERLAND"&gt;HMS CUMBERLAND&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hms-campbeltown"&gt;HMS CAMPBELTOWN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS CAMBELTOWN" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5689/campbeltown_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS CAMBELTOWN&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;formally a Warship Frigate F86 was built at Cammell Laird ship yard Birkenhead UK in 1987 and is now lying at HMNB Portsmouth.  The vessel ceased service on the 7th July 2011 and is due to be tendered early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All interested parties should beware that only companies that have successfully completed a Pre Qualification Questionnaire (&lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be sent an invitation to tender for this vessel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More detailed information is available on &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/hms-campbeltown-specifications?cachebust=1355754338&amp;amp;preview=56856" title="HMS CAMPBELTOWN"&gt;HMS CAMPBELTOWN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hms-chatham"&gt;HMS CHATHAM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS CHATHAM" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5690/chatham_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS CHATHAM&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;formally a Warship Frigate F87 was built at Swan Hunters Shipbuilders in Wallsend UK in 1989, and is now lying at HMNB Portsmouth.  The vessel ceased service on the 20th October 2011 and is due to be tendered early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All interested parties should beware that only companies that have successfully completed a Pre Qualification Questionnaire (&lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be sent an invitation to tender for this vessel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More detailed information is available on &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/hms-chatham-specifications?cachebust=1355754829&amp;amp;preview=56864" title="HMS CHATHAM"&gt;HMS CHATHAM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hms-cornwall"&gt;HMS CORNWALL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS CORNWALL" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5691/cornwall_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS CORWALL&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;formally a Warship, Frigate F99 was built  at Yarrow Shipbuilders, Glasgow UK in 1988 and is now lying at HMNB Portsmouth. The vessel ceased service on the 20th October 2011 and is due to be tendered early 2013.
All interested parties should beware that only companies that have successfully completed a Pre Qualification Questionnaire (&lt;abbr title="Pre-Qualification Questionnaire"&gt;PQQ&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be sent an invitation to tender for this vessel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More detailed information is available on &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/publications/hms-cornwall-specifications?cachebust=1355755350&amp;amp;preview=56870" title="HMS CORNWALL"&gt;HMS CORNWALL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_53206"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36910/PQQ_for_potential_purchasers_of_Government_Vessels_v1_5_clean.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-53206-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/assets/pub-cover-f3684e2880956dff7bb138bfb0c2bebf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36910/PQQ_for_potential_purchasers_of_Government_Vessels_v1_5_clean.doc" aria-describedby="attachment-53206-accessibility-help"&gt;Pre-Qualification Questionnaire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;MS Word Document&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;252 KB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-53206-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Pre-Qualification%20Questionnaire%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Pre-Qualification%20Questionnaire%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Pre-Qualification Questionnaire").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56853</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:05:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:05:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/female-officer-cadet-wins-sandhursts-sword-of-honour"/>
    <title>Female Officer Cadet wins Sandhurst's Sword of Honour</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The top accolade from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/training_education/training/17057.aspx" title="Royal Military Academy Sandhurst"&gt;Royal Military Academy Sandhurst&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Officer Cadet Sarah Hunter-Choat, who received the award during her commissioning at the Sovereign’s Parade on Friday 14 December.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted Sword of Honour is presented to the best overall Officer Cadet out of 200 in the senior term and is personally chosen by the Academy’s Commandant, Major General Timothy Evans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 200 cadets have their performance rigorously monitored throughout the year. Then, going into the final phase of their training, the 3 top candidates, termed ‘blade runners’, are carefully scrutinised then brought before the Commandant for a final interview. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat received the Sword of Honour from Defence Secretary Philip Hammond, who represented Her Majesty The Queen at the Sovereign’s Parade. It has been 6 years since a female officer won, when Angela Laycock was commissioned into the Royal Engineers in December 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat’s success follows in her parents’ footsteps. Her father Brigadier Tony Hunter-Choat had a long, distinguished military career, starting out in the French Foreign Legion before commissioning into the British Army, while her mother is a former RAF officer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56977</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-to-auction-off-radio-spectrum"/>
    <title>MOD to auction off radio spectrum</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radio spectrum refers to the radio waves over which all wireless communication takes place, including radio, television, radar, satellite, mobile voice and data. Under plans announced today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to auction around 200 Megahertz (&lt;abbr title="Megahertz"&gt;MHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) of its spectrum usage rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes as market demand for extra spectrum is mounting, fuelled by the sharp rise in the use of spectrum-hungry devices such as smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale will give private operators the chance to buy more spectrum to support the introduction of fourth-generation mobile services to people in cities, towns and villages across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively the spectrum could be used by fixed-line operators to provide wireless access to broadband services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum being sold by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is all below 15 Gigahertz (&lt;abbr title="Gigahertz"&gt;GHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is regarded as the most useful and valuable part of the radio spectrum because of its wide range of applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of all spectrum below 15GHz is held by the public sector and is used for a broad range of services including defence, emergency services, transport and science. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; holds around three-quarters of all publicly-held spectrum and one-third of all spectrum below 15GHz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome this opportunity to free up much-needed spectrum. We hope that the sale will help drive the roll-out of new generation networks and universal access to broadband, both of which are vital to the UK’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale follows the announcement made in the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/spend_index.htm" title="Spending Review"&gt;2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; that at least 500MHz of public spectrum below 5GHz will be released by 2020 for new mobile communications uses. The spectrum to be sold off is being cleared of military users to contribute towards this target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are expected to start at the end of 2013, with the auction completed by the summer of 2014. Ahead of this, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to produce an Industry Brochure in early spring 2013 and to host an Industry Day in early summer 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56828</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T16:30:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:30:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-brize-norton-counting-down-to-christmas"/>
    <title>RAF Brize Norton counting down to Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we take a closer look at how &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;RAF Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt; in Oxfordshire prepares for the festive season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-boss"&gt;The boss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAF Brize Norton is the largest station in the RAF and has approximately 6,000 Service personnel and 1,400 MOD civil servants and contractors. It is the home of the Air Mobility Squadrons and the ‘gateway to operations’ as the main airport used for deploying UK troops worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The station never sleeps and supports operations around the world 24/7, 365-days-a-year. Station Commander Group Captain Steve Lushington and his family will be serving Christmas dinner to the junior ranks on the big day. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the festive season gets into full swing, for personnel at RAF Brize Norton work continues as normal. The support to operations is paramount; even during the festive period personnel are still required to be on duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pilots and engineers on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/216squadron.cfm" title="216 Squadron"&gt;216 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/99squadron.cfm" title="99 Squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; maintain their high readiness state, personnel continue to control from the tower, operations staff continue to plan missions and taskings, all supporting tri-Service personnel across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Captain Steve Lushington" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5706/Brize1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Group Captain Steve Lushington, Station Commander at RAF Brize Norton [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/c17aglobemaster.cfm" title="C-17 Globemaster"&gt;C-17 Globemaster&lt;/a&gt; is a huge, heavy-lift transport aircraft operated by 99 Squadron. It can carry troops and all types of cargo around the world, including transporting &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/merlin.cfm" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/chinook.cfm" title="Chinook"&gt;Chinook&lt;/a&gt; helicopters direct to the front line in Afghanistan to provide support to ground troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stuart Lindsell is the Officer Commanding 99 Squadron and has volunteered to cover Christmas duties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The squadron is 300-plus-strong and moves an immense amount of personal mail and parcels from families and loved ones. It’s rewarding for us to know that we are helping to play a part in connecting Service families who are separated over the Christmas period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s very much ‘business as usual’ for 99 Squadron; we have crews covering aeromed standby, a crew based in the Middle East ready for normal tasking. The squadron engineers stand ready to generate an aircraft at short notice should an aeromed mission be called and they will also be manning the engineer control desks as normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best way to look at it is hopefully Christmas Day itself will be quiet, but Christmas Eve, Boxing Day and to that extent the New Year period are no different to any other time of year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festive season can bring wintry conditions and, a couple of years ago, when the UK was gripped by sub-zero temperatures and heavy snowfalls, in the thick of it were 99 Squadron who battled to get troops home for Christmas. Wing Commander Lindsell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Snow and ice are certainly not ideal flying conditions to say the least but as a station we are better off than we were when the wintry conditions of 2010 hit. We did manage to get everyone home but it was certainly a challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="snow-and-ice-operations"&gt;Snow and ice operations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Corporal John Oliver" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5707/Brize3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Corporal John Oliver from the Airfield Support Mechanical Transport section [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal John Oliver will also be on standby during Christmas and works at the Complete Equipment Schedule Store at Airfield Support Mechanical Transport that, amongst other things, makes sure vehicles are in working order. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve spent the last 2 months preparing and bringing online all the snow and ice prevention vehicles as they are not used during the summer months; we inflate their tyres, fill the vehicle up with whatever fluid it needs, test it and carry out daily inspections to make sure they are ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it was horrendous snow the main vehicle we would use is the airfield snow clearing vehicle or the compact jet sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicles are equipped to plough snow, break up compact ice and blow snow, broken ice or other debris to the side. Corporal Oliver continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is to make sure we have a serviceable fleet of vehicles to meet the minimum required to clear the airfield. It’s a priority to clear the runway and certain bays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Getting the airfield cleared is very important for the ‘airbridge’, especially for those personnel that want to get home in the last couple of days before Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="air-movements-squadron"&gt;Air Movements Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5708/Brize4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson getting into the festive spirit at a check-in desk in the air terminal [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal Emma Hopkinson works on the passenger check-in desk in the air terminal for the Air Movements Squadron. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s like a civilian airport. The difference is, if I went for a job in a civilian airport I would only just be either a check-in girl, departures, or elsewhere in the building, whereas here at Brize we have to multi-task and do everything - one minute I could be behind the check-in desk, then I could be on the check-through or departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We see the whole process through and make sure that nobody is left behind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked what it’s like checking in troops knowing they will be away for Christmas, Corporal Hopkinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is no different at Christmas, the process is still the same, it’s the personalities and how people are with you, and how you are with them - I try and be a bit more jolly! I’ve done Iraq, Afghanistan and Ascension Island at Christmas, so I know what it’s like being away at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Hopkinson will be on shift during the Christmas period but sets aside a day in the new year to have a ‘Christmas Day’ with her family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I remember one year my mum bought a second turkey and it stayed in the freezer until February! I go to college and have met a lot of people and they are surprised I’m working Christmas Eve and Christmas Day - they ask ‘are you open?’ and I say yes! it’s a 24/7 camp, and it’s the same for New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="christmas-presence"&gt;Christmas ‘presence’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5709/Brize5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as 'Kev the Rev', will be working over the New Year period [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like the station itself, the chapel is open 24/7, and for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/chaplains/" title="RAF Chaplains"&gt;RAF chaplains&lt;/a&gt; the run-up to Christmas is always busy. Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as ‘Kev the Rev’, will be working over the New Year period, but last year was on duty over Christmas. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because our senior chaplain was away on ops, I joined other officers on station and helped serve Christmas lunch in the Junior Ranks Mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a great experience, my wife was with me and some personnel brought family along. There was that family feel, the military family; everyone was in very good spirits as the portions of potatoes were getting bigger and bigger!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We often think about the people who are deployed at home or overseas, but it’s harder for the families left behind. Service people will make the most of it, no matter what, and I’m sure they get an extra mince pie or an extra bit of turkey and will make the most of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s the families left behind and the kids that don’t have their mum or dad with them on Christmas Day that find it hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best gift at Christmas is ‘presence’. For those who have had loved ones away last year, they will know that having loved ones around is the best gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If not ‘presence’, instantaneous communication such as emails and Skype is great; however, people underestimate e-blueys and handwritten letters - they have that personal touch which means so much to people and always makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/56837</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories"/>
    <title>Supporting the Overseas Territories</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a broad responsibility to support the Overseas Territories and to ensure their security and good governance. Britain and territory governments share significant challenges: building more diverse and resilient economies; cutting public sector deficits; regulating finance businesses effectively; and protecting biodiversity and natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-overseas-territories-programme-fund"&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund supports the work of government to maintain the security, stability and prosperity of the Overseas Territories. This fund supports the economic, security, environmental and governance strategies in the government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/publications/overseas-territories-white-paper-0612/ot-wp-0612"&gt;white paper on the Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Where-we-work/Overseas-Territories/"&gt;Department for International Development (&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; provides budgetary support for Montserrat, Pitcairn and St Helena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Documents/publications1/op/ovseas-terr-dept-2011.pdf"&gt;Department for International Development’s Operational Plan 2011-2015&lt;/a&gt; explains how money is allocated to the territories and how expenditure is monitored for effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-and-climate-fund-darwin-plus"&gt;Environment and climate fund: Darwin Plus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government launched &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2012/10/17/2-million-a-year-overseas-territories-fund/"&gt;Darwin Plus: Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;, an environment and climate fund for the UK’s Overseas Territories, in October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fund consists of contributions from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;), and &lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;. The fund will disburse around £2 million per year dedicated to a range of environment and climate-related projects to improve long-term natural resource management in the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance and application forms for the fund are available on &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://darwin.defra.gov.uk/news/2012-10/darwin-plus/%20%E2%80%9CDarwin%20Initiative%E2%80%9D"&gt;Darwin Initiative website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="protecting-the-overseas-territories"&gt;Protecting the Overseas Territories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the UK’s main military tasks is to provide security to the nation and its overseas territories. The Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a security policy in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/1AD4AFE6-4946-4BAC-A3A6-7AFBF9AA25BF/0/overseas_territories.pdf"&gt;Overseas Territories: the Ministry of Defence’s contribution&lt;/a&gt;, which explains how the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; will protect the Overseas Territories from 2012 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-the-public-sectors"&gt;Supporting the public sectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have set up the Jubilee Programme to share experience between public servants in the territories and the UK by giving territory officials opportunities to train and work with colleagues in the UK, and vice versa, encouraging long-term partnerships between the territories and public bodies in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories are very diverse, with thousands of small islands, vast areas of ocean, but also, in Antarctica, land 6 times the size of the United Kingdom. They include one of the world’s richest communities, in Bermuda; the most remote community, in Tristan da Cunha and one of the smallest, with only 54 people living on Pitcairn Island. The total population of the territories is roughly a quarter of a million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 14 British Overseas Territories and most have a permanent resident population. The exceptions are the British Indian Ocean Territory and the British Antarctic Territory, and South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands. The latter two have research stations. The Sovereign Base Areas on Cyprus have a resident population of Cypriot nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14 Overseas Territories are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/anguilla/"&gt;Anguilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/bermuda/"&gt;Bermuda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/british-indian-ocean-territory/"&gt;British Indian Ocean Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinbvi.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The British Virgin Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukincayman.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Cayman Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/falkland-islands/"&gt;The Falkland Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/europe/gibraltar/"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinmontserrat.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;Montserrat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/pitcairn-islands/"&gt;The Pitcairn, Henderson, Ducie &amp;amp; Oeno Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/st-helena/"&gt;Saint Helena&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/ascension-Island/"&gt;Ascension&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/tristan-da-cunha/"&gt;Tristan da Cunha (including Gough Island Dependency)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/south-georgia-south-sandwich/"&gt;South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas, Akrotiri and Dhekelia (on Cyprus)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://turksandcaicosislands.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Turks &amp;amp; Caicos Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can email enquiries about &lt;a href="enquiry.gibraltar@fco.gov.uk"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For enquiries about the Sovereign Base Areas, visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56779</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T11:14:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:14:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-portland-sets-sail-after-27-million-refit"/>
    <title>HMS Portland sets sail after £27 million refit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With more than 260,000 man-hours invested in the almost year-long project, the 133-metre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Portland" title="HMS Portland"&gt;HMS Portland&lt;/a&gt; has returned to sea bristling with the latest high-tech equipment, maintaining its role at the cutting-edge of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 19 major system and capability upgrades have been undertaken on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates" title="Type 23 frigates"&gt;Type 23 frigate&lt;/a&gt;, including the installation of new anti-submarine warfare sonar, full upgrade of the ship’s computer systems, an overhaul of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Weapons-Systems/Seawolf" title="Seawolf"&gt;Seawolf&lt;/a&gt; missile system, replacement of guns, refurbishment of the galley and upgrades of accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship sailed underneath the famous Forth Bridges having had a total exterior makeover too, with 15,000 litres of paint having been applied to her hull and superstructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Sarah West, Commanding Officer of HMS Portland, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very much looking forward to getting this fantastic ship back to sea to put her through her paces. In tandem with the MOD and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, the crew has spent many long months working hard to return HMS Portland to fighting form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Portland " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5675/NE120458002g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Portland sails from Rosyth following her refit [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Arthur, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ship is equipped for the many future challenges which greet the modern fleet and we are ready to be with her every step of the way. It is an exciting moment returning a warship to sea after refit - we know that HMS Portland is in great shape for regaining full operational readiness early next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has benefited from close partnership between Babcock, the MOD, ship personnel and the team under the Surface Ship Support Alliance, resulting in the refit programme being delivered on time and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babcock project manager Russell Glancy said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have successfully met the challenges of this project, and applied our experience from previous Type 23 refits, along with strong partnering, to ensure delivery of this upgrade and maintenance programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Portland will undertake a further 3 months of sea trials and training before returning to the fleet as a fully operational ship, prepared at any time to take on duties worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3,500-tonne Type 23 frigates, of which there are 13 in the fleet, are flexible and adaptable ships which protect the UK’s interests both in home waters and further afield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical deployments will include anything from the fleet ready escort, which is the UK’s high readiness ship, to counter-narcotics, piracy and terrorism patrols and the ship can provide humanitarian intervention and security when required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56799</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/court-martial-results-from-the-military-court-centres"/>
    <title>Court Martial Results from the Military Court Centres</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In line with the Government’s Transparency and Open Data initiative, the Military Court Service has agreed to provide Court Martial results in respect of the Military Court Centres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56824</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/notice-of-proposed-new-byelaws"/>
    <title>Notice of proposed new Byelaws</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice of proposal for the introduction of new byelaws in respect of the Ministry of Defence site known as RAF Croughton.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56866</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-focus-magazine-266"/>
    <title>Defence Focus magazine 266</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Focus magazine issue 266 - December 2012 - January 2013&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
