<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Ministry of Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T19:05:41+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56446</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:05:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:05:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-engineering-and-science-group"/>
    <title>Defence Engineering and Science Group</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK needs modern, battle-winning forces to defend the UK’s interests and to contribute to strengthening international peace and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; civil service exists to enable, equip and support the three armed services in the delivery of defence capability. As a part of this, the Defence Engineering and Science Group (&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt;) is a community of 13,000 professional engineers and scientists working within &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; civil service to equip and support the UK Armed Forces with state-of-the-art technology. We are the force behind the forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desg-graduate-scheme"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scheme is probably the very best graduate development scheme for engineers and scientists in the UK. It could prepare you for a career that meets your aspirations, if you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;possess strong problem-solving skills and enjoy the thought of working at the cutting edge of technology  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have the potential to lead people and work effectively in teams  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have genuine interest in developing yourself to your full personal and professional potential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme recruits and develops graduate engineers and scientists. There are also opportunities for students, sixth formers and those about to enter sixth form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting an education in engineering and science can be expensive and deciding on a career path at the end can be confusing without prior experience. Our sixth form and undergraduate student opportunities offer financial help, personal development opportunities and the experience you need to make decisions about your future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming no previous working experience, we will invest heavily in you. Over and above your salary, there will be considerable investment in your professional development. We aim to take you through to chartered status in your profession within just 4 years of starting the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-the-scheme-works"&gt;How the scheme works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prestigious &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme has been an industry leader for almost 30 years, launching hundreds of graduates into satisfying careers in engineering or science. The scheme is accredited by a number of professional institutions including IMeche, IET, RINA, IoP, IMarEST and RAeS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is tailored to individual development needs to ensure that you have the best possible preparation for your first professional post and your subsequent career in &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Civil Service. The scheme will last for a maximum of 2 years (reduced for graduates with previous experience) and includes a range of in-house work placements, industry secondments and formal training courses. There is no age limit for entry to the graduate scheme, but, it is designed for those with little or no work experience in engineering and science and may not benefit those with significant previous experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most graduates are based in Bristol, Bath, London, Waddington, Clyde or Plymouth. Work placements during the graduate scheme, however, can be located anywhere in the UK or overseas. At the end of the graduate scheme, most graduates take up permanent appointments in the above areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On entry to the scheme, you will be assigned to a Specialist Stream or Engineering System Anchor, taking into account your degree discipline and preferences wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/engineering-system-anchors"&gt;Engineering System Anchors document&lt;/a&gt; for more details and a guide to the ESAs that you can work in with a given degree - other choices may be possible. Contact us for further advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detailed information about the scheme, please see the Grad Fact Sheet in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/mod-desg-graduate-trainee"&gt;&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="accreditations"&gt;Accreditations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chartered engineers and scientists are an important asset to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and as a result the scheme has developed in accordance with the needs of many professional institutions. This has allowed for formal development plans to be applied to the scheme with the aim of our graduates achieving Charted status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is currently accredited by the following institutes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Institution of Engineering &amp;amp; Technology  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institution of Mechanical Engineers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Royal Institution of Naval Architects  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institute of Physics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Aeronautical Society  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institution of Civil Engineers  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institute of Marine Engineering, Science and Technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="eligibility-for-the-scheme"&gt;Eligibility for the scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply to the graduate scheme you must :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be British or have dual-nationality of which one is British&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have completed or be in your final year of an approved engineering or science degree (or others listed below)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have obtained, or expect to obtain a minimum 2:2 honours degree in one of the disciplines below&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the moment we will consider degrees in the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical/Electronic Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanical Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General Engineering/Engineering Science  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naval Architecture/Ship Science  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marine Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systems Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automotive Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avionics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aeronautical/Aerospace Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer Systems Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telecommunications Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information Technology/Information Systems  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer Science  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control Systems Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechatronics  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We may also consider accredited degrees in similar subjects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All degrees must be accredited by a professional institution licensed by the UK Engineering or Science councils or RICS. Contact us if you are not sure if your degree is being sought this season. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; helpline: 030 679 84320
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply"&gt;How to apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: We are now open for applications to the &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that all applications are completed online via an independent authority. When campaigns are running all application forms can be found online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full details of the &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Application and Assessment Centre process is on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/mod-desg-graduate-trainee"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Trainee Scheme guidance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-vacancies-for-desg-graduate-trainees"&gt;Current vacancies for &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; graduate trainees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://jobs.civilservice.gov.uk/company/nghr/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTI4MTgyNCZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xMjA2Jm93bmVyPTUwNTAwMDAmb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfbmdoci5uZ2hyX2RlcHQ9MTY2MjU0JnZhY19uZ2hyLm5naHJfdG93bj0xNjk3MzkmcmVxc2lnPTEzNTAwNDMxMTktODJhYmIyM2FmNWU5NTBmZjVlYmM1ZDcxYWZjOGJjNzQ2ZDY3ZGFhNA=="&gt;Bath, Bristol (75 vacancies) Job Ref: 1281824&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANT: Please note that &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme opportunities can be available nationwide at a number of sites throughout the UK, including London, Plymouth, Clyde (Scotland) Bath and Bristol and Waddington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-details"&gt;Contact details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions regarding your eligibility for the &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Trainee Scheme or other queries please contact the People Services Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; People Services Centre    
&lt;br&gt;Phone: 0800 345 7772  
&lt;br&gt;8am to 5pm, Monday to Friday  
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:peopleservices@pppa.mod.uk" title="Email: peopleservices@pppa.mod.uk"&gt;peopleservices@pppa.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-technical-undergraduate-scheme"&gt;Defence Technical Undergraduate Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that following a review, we are unlikely to be opening for DTUS applications this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DTUS is our premier undergraduate sponsorship programme for those who want a head-start into a &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; career. Whilst the adventure opportunities have a military flavour - you will go on to join the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Civil Service Graduate Scheme as a civilian engineer or scientist. Following a review, we will not be opening for DTUS applications this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="details-of-the-scheme"&gt;Details of the scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Technical Undergraduate Scheme is our premier undergraduate sponsorship programme for those students who want a head-start into a &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; career and offers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bursary of £4,000 pa while you study&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leadership and team-working development alongside the British Armed Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paid summer employment within &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; establishments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an accredited graduate scheme and exciting career opportunities on graduation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We offer sponsorship through DTUS to a limited number of students commencing or part way through an approved science or engineering degree at Aston, Birmingham, Loughborough, Newcastle, Northumbria or Southampton universities (arrangements also exist for Oxford and Cambridge). By providing a support unit at each of these universities, DTUS is designed to develop your leadership and team working skills and give you a deeper appreciation of the Armed Forces and the military environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme offers work placements in your summer holidays, excellent opportunities to participate in military and adventurous training and a generous academic bursary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eligibility-for-the-scheme-1"&gt;Eligibility for the scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply to DTUS you must be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;British or have dual-nationality of which one is British  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;studying for an approved science or engineering degree at one of the following Universities: Aston, Birmingham, Loughborough, Southampton, Newcastle, Northumbria, Oxford, or Cambridge  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in year 1 of a 3-year degree course or years 1 and 2 of a 4-year degree course and on track to achieve a 2:2 degree or better  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enthusiastic to pursue the unique development opportunities afforded by DTUS and to accept the additional obligations that exist within a military environment  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;available during the summer holidays to take up work placements in a variety of locations in the UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Degrees that we approve for the scheme are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naval Architecture  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ship Science  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marine Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronic Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electrical Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control Systems  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanical Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control Systems  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanical Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aeronautical Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aerospace Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avionics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systems Engineering  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telecommunications Engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All degrees must be accredited by a professional institution licensed by the UK Engineering or Science Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further details, see the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dtus-fact-sheet"&gt;DTUS fact sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desg-sponsorship-scheme"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Sponsorship Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Sponsorship Scheme is an excellent opportunity to explore the exciting variety of career possibilities within the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The aim of the scheme is to help you explore the exciting variety of career possibilities within the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; whilst gaining valuable work experience during your summer vacations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will get :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bursary of £1,500 a year while you study.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paid summer employment within &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; establishments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more detailed information please download the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/sponsorship-fact-sheet"&gt;Sponsorship Scheme fact sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="welbeck-the-defence-sixth-form-college"&gt;Welbeck: the Defence sixth form college&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welbeck DSFC has become one of the UK’s top sixth form colleges with an outstanding academic reputation. If you wish to apply to Welbeck you could eventually join the &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme through the Welbeck route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welbeck teaches a science and technology based A-level curriculum designed to prepare students for a technical degree at a leading UK university. It provides a head start in training for a career with the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; civil service or the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civil service Welbexians are expected to transfer to the Defence Technical Undergraduate Scheme (DTUS) to study for an approved degree and will receive an annual bursary plus paid summer placements. Following graduation you will join the prestigious &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Defence Engineering and Science Graduate Scheme (&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eligibility-to-apply-for-welbeck"&gt;Eligibility to apply for Welbeck&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To join Welbeck as a Ministry of Defence Civil Service candidate you must be a British citizen or hold dual nationality, once of which must be British.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Civil Service welcomes applications from disabled candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimum entry requirements are an ‘A’ grade at GCSE (or equivalent) in Mathematics (the higher or credit level syllabus) and a ‘B’ in grade dual award science/single science equivalent, as well as a ‘C’ grade in English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candidates must also score at least 40 points (38 in Scotland) for their best 7 subjects on the basis of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="academic-scoring-system"&gt;Academic scoring system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;GCSE Grades&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Points&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;SCE Standard Grades&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your school or college must supply a reference showing that you are expected to achieve the minimum entry requirements. Candidates must also be capable of taking mathematics and preferably physics and two other subjects for the first year of their sixth form, as well as an ICT course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuition is paid for by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Parents or guardians are required to make a contribution towards the cost of their child’s maintenance, which covers board, lodging and the value of clothing and services provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of contribution is determined on the basis of the parents’ or guardians’ residual or disposable income after allowance is made for other children, mortgage payments and other amounts normally acceped by the Inland Revenue. No other boarding school offers such a comprehensive and high-quality education as such low cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply-1"&gt;How to apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online applications for a September 2013 entry to Welbeck DSFC are now open with a planned closing date of 31 January 2013. Vacancies can be found on the Civil Service jobs webiste &lt;a rel="external" href="https://jobs.civilservice.gov.uk/company/nghr/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTI5OTI1MiZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xMjQyJm93bmVyPTUwNTAwMDAmb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfbmdoci5uZ2hyX2RlcHQ9MTY2MjU0JnZhY19uZ2hyLm5naHJfZ3JhZGU9MTY2NTk3JnZhY19uZ2hyLm5naHJfcmVnaW9uPTE2NjQ1MyZ2YWNfbmdoci5uZ2hyX3Rvd249MTcwMTk2JnJlcXNpZz0xMzU1NDE4MzMyLTVlOTAzOTZmMzllZTk3MzY0YjAwMjE2YjU4MWU5YTc5ODk4MjFlNTc=" title="Welbeck 2013 Entry, - Ref: 1299252"&gt;Welbeck 2013 Entry, - Ref: 1299252&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-desg-works"&gt;How &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is made up of a number of organisations, agencies and trading funds. The &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme recruits on behalf of Defence Equipment and Support (&lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment and Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt;), the organisation that equips and supports the UK’s armed forces for current and future operations. It acquires and supports through-life, including disposal, equipment and services ranging from ships, aircraft, vehicles and weapons, to electronic systems and information services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment and Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt; also satisfies ongoing requirements including food, clothing, medical supplies, maintenance and temporary accommodation, as well as operating HM naval bases and joint supply chain for land, sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment and Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt; works closely with industry through partnering agreements and private finance initiatives in accordance with the Defence Industrial Strategy (DIS) to deliver effective solutions for defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formed from the merger of the Defence Procurement Agency (DPA) and the Defence Logistics Organisation (DLO), with headquarters in Bristol, &lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment and Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt; has around 29,000 people based at sites across the UK and abroad. It has an annual spend of £16 billion representing 43 percent of the Defence Budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="case-studies"&gt;Case studies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoe, who comes from London, graduated from University with a degree in Civil Engineering. She has been on the scheme for 2 years and 1 month and is currently on a placement as a project sponsor at RAF Mildenhall. 
Read the case study for Zoe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily graduated from university with a degree in Mathematics, where she was sponsored throughout her degree by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; through the DTUS, having come from Welbeck DSFC. She is currently working as a Systems Analyst with 41 (R) Sqn at RAF Coningsby where she is part of the Fast Jet test and evaluation center. 
Read the case study for Emily&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikas, who comes from Kent, graduated from University with a degree in Mechanical Engineering. He has been on the scheme for 14 months and is now a Defence Analyst on secondment at the Department of Business, Innovation and Skills in the Aerospace, Marine and Defence Team. 
Read the case study for Vikas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caroline has a degree in Mathematics. She’s currently working in the Assement Group within a Project Team at the Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group (&lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment and Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt;), dealing with weapons. 
Read the case study for Caroline&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew graduated from university with a degree in Computer Science, and is now doing an MSc in Explosives Ordnance Engineering. He has been in the &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Graduate Scheme for 18 months. 
Read the case study for Andrew&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desg-technology"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces increasingly depend on scientific and technological advances to maintain their ability to operate effectively. They need equipment and capabilities that give a technological edge over any potential opponent and keep the UK compatible with our Allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countering new types of threats as they emerge will be a key challenge to UK forces in the future. We therefore place a premium on the ability to generate and identify innovative technologies, adopt them for military use and integrate them rapidly into platforms, weapon systems and force structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="taranis-a-bond-worthy-automaton"&gt;Taranis: a Bond-worthy automaton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of this is Taranis, of which the Minister of State for Defence Equipment and Support says: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taranis…is something that would not be out of place in the latest James Bond film - a pilotless combat aircraft for the British Armed Forces that will be capable of delivering weapons to a battlefield in another continent with almost no need for operator input. It does not come much more exciting than that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bloodhound-a-record-breaking-project"&gt;Bloodhound, a record-breaking project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just one more example of work that &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; graduates are a part of is the Bloodhound, supersonic car project. &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; graduates have helped to overcome many technical challenges over the years and the quest for a car that will exceed 1,000 mph is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how most equipment gets to the front line fast? It’s not by boat, nor land, and it’s most definitely not just a simple question of putting it on a sling. The Joint Air Delivery Test and Evaluation Unit (JADTEU) is an example of a team where &lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt; graduates can work. Working on tight time schedules, graduates have been helping solve complex engineering problems ranging from how to parachute someone safely from never attempted heights, speeds or places, to how to transport the latest tanks to the field, and how many we can carry safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;abbr title="The Defence Engineering &amp;amp; Science Group"&gt;DESG&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Phone: 030 679 84320
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56345</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:14:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T15:14:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/launch-of-new-single-government-website"/>
    <title>Launch of new single government website</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The beta website includes a new ‘INSIDE GOVERNMENT’ section containing trial MOD corporate information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time GOV.UK will eventually replace many of the separate departmental sites run by government organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine government departments are taking part in the first phase of GOV.UK’s launch: the MOD, the Department for Communities and Local Government, the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Department for International Development, Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs, the Ministry of Justice, the Department of Health, and the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New MOD corporate content has been redeveloped into a framework designed to make government information more accessible and usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concurrent six-week live test will run from 29 February - 11 April, including a review of the new shared publishing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participating departments will keep adding to the site over the six-week trial period at the end of which there will be a pause and an evaluation of feedback received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 2012, the MOD website will continue to be the official source of defence-related information until a transition date has been agreed. There will then be a period of time when organisations will run both old and new sites in parallel whilst a final date for closure of the old sites is agreed with the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, GOV.UK will eventually replace many of the separate departmental sites run by government organisations, simplifying things for users and saving millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The citizen-facing section of GOV.UK was launched on 31 January 2012 and aims to serve the needs of the mainstream majority better by speeding up and facilitating essential transactions such as registering a birth or renewing car tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its target is to replace both Directgov and Business Link in 2012, reducing costs to the public purse, improving the user’s experience, and making all government information easier to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government part of the site is about meeting the needs of the engaged minority who, like the MOD audience, visit frequently and are likely to spend longer on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New features and interactive opportunities will make life much easier for those frequent users of government websites, focusing on their needs far more than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to the new GOV.UK site will be located on the MOD internet and intranet sites for users to find parallel content easily and quickly. More links will be placed as new content is published and available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56466</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T16:19:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:19:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/soldiers-offer-ground-expertise-to-aerial-assets-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Soldiers offer ground expertise to aerial assets in Afghanistan </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Army &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/equipment/aircraft/1531.aspx" title="Apache"&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt; helicopters are often called upon to neutralise enemy threats, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; plays an equally important role with their impressive fleet of fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fearsome aerial assets fly out of Kandahar and, although the pilots and support crew are based well outside &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/" title="British Army"&gt;Army&lt;/a&gt; circles, they have direct access to all things green courtesy of skilled ground liaison officers (GLOs) who are embedded within their squadrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such personnel act as a link between the 2 Services to ensure those in the air have a clear understanding of the situation below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/tornado.cfm" title="Tornado GR4"&gt;Tornado&lt;/a&gt; Force’s War Week exercise at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/" title="RAF Marham"&gt;RAF Marham&lt;/a&gt;, Captain James Perring of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/24651.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about taking everything that is happening on the ground and translating that into basic speak for the aircrew. They have no idea about the situation on the ground so we talk them through the process. I get involved with anything that is Army-related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to give as much information as possible so when they are up in the sky they know where people are and what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring is now on a four-month deployment with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/9squadron.cfm" title="9 Squadron"&gt;9 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; in Afghanistan and the serviceman was quick to highlight the differences between his roles with the RAF and Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ground Liaison Officer"&gt;GLO&lt;/abbr&gt; is a posting I applied for and is something completely different. I had no idea or appreciation of how air assets work so it has given me great insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is going to be an interesting tour and in a way I will have a greater understanding of the bigger picture in Afghanistan compared to spending 6 months on foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5427/tornadosg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring joined the Tornado Force for the War Week exercise at RAF Marham [Picture: Graeme Main, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working with the RAF has been a bit of a culture shock. Sometimes the bureaucracy can be frustrating but it works for them and it is like that for a reason. It has been hard to adjust but there are positives to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring was not the only soldier involved in War Week. Major Jeremy Higgins of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/23445.aspx" title="Royal Artillery"&gt;Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, a reservist who is a director for Cross Country Trains, was also on hand to offer expert advice and guidance from an Army perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise is designed to test personnel on the scenarios they are likely to face in theatre and the officer was determined to add as much realism as possible. Major Higgins said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to ensure the aircrew get the training they need ahead of the deployment, while tying in with other agencies such as forward air controllers. It is about orchestrating different elements in the air and on the ground so when the jets go out they get the training they require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will be talking to troops in the field beforehand, asking what they need and what they are trying to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The aircrew also highlight the areas they want to work on, such as night missions, and the soldiers come up with different scenarios for them. Effectively we have two serials feeding into one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a close link between the two forces, GLOs are mindful of not overloading their airborne colleagues with unfamiliar Army tactics and thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just UK personnel who benefit from the support offered by the Tornado crews. Major Higgins explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Preparing a Tornado for take off" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5428/tornados3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;RAF personnel preparing a Tornado for take off at Kandahar Airfield (library image) [Picture: Corporal Andy Benson RAF, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It can be quite challenging as we cover the whole of Afghanistan and can be allocated anywhere. It is an international role and we have to get information from soldiers who do not have English as their first language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We give the aircrews some situational awareness and that can be quite important due to the various forces we work with. They have different kit, depending on what they are doing, so a footprint of life on the ground is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Toyota Hilux with guys in the back could be perceived as being the enemy, but it may also be local allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about adding value in any way we can. We may be asked simple questions or ones that completely floor us. We interact with land troops to get a picture of what they want from the fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand for aerial assets is inevitably strong as soldiers maintain the Army’s operational tempo and such requests mean the RAF are on high alert during the training cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Lisa Foy, the acting officer in command of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/aboutus/opswg.cfm" title="RAF Marham - Operations Wing"&gt;RAF Marham’s Operations Wing&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is always more demand than we can meet but we strive to match the requirements from Land whenever possible. We want to benefit the personnel on exercise while training the Tornado crews as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise that the Force needs to train with soldiers and War Week is the perfect opportunity to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A lot of 9 Squadron’s training during this phase has been provided by the Army, and GLOs are critical in bringing everything together. Our expertise is in the air and these guys form a crucial link with the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report by Richard Long is taken from the December 2012 edition of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/soldier-magazine/soldier-magazine.aspx" title="Soldier magazine"&gt;Soldier&lt;/a&gt; - the magazine of the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/56129</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T12:50:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T12:50:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/latest-uk-armed-forces-manning-figures-released"/>
    <title>Latest UK Armed Forces manning figures released</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is up from 97.4 per cent a year ago and shows a continuing upward trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18,630 new recruits have joined the UK Regular Forces in the 12 months to 30 June 2010. This is a decrease of 5,010 from the 12 months to 30 June 2009 as the Armed Forces are now very nearly fully-manned, meaning there is a reduced intake requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics also show that the number of people leaving the trained strength of the UK Regular Forces in the 12 months to 30 June 2010 has fallen by 9.8 per cent (1,990 people) compared with the same period a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As at 1 July 2010, the full-time trained strength of the UK Armed Forces was 178,380, against a target of 178,880. This comprises 173,930 UK Regular Forces, 830 Full-Time Reserve Service personnel and 3,610 Gurkhas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Secretary of State for Defence, Andrew Robathan, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see that a career in our Armed Forces is proving to be a popular choice, so much so that we are at almost 100 per cent of our manning requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our personnel are some of the best in the world and the work they are doing in operational theatres and back in the UK demonstrates this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although the numbers of people we need to recruit have reduced, recruitment continues, and, with more people staying in the Armed Forces too, we continue to strengthen all three Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1 July 2009, the proportion of females in the UK Regular Forces has remained static at 12.1 per cent for officers, and risen from 9.0 per cent to 9.1 per cent for other ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The percentage of UK Regular Forces from ethnic minority backgrounds has remained static at 6.6 per cent of UK Regular Forces since 1 July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/56071</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:43:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:43:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/british-forces-overseas-posting-ayios-nikolaos-cyprus"/>
    <title>British forces overseas posting: Ayios Nikolaos, Cyprus</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayios Nikolaos is about 20 minutes’ drive from Dhekelia Garrison next to the border with the Turkish-occupied north. The station is located in the Eastern Sovereign Base Area (&lt;abbr title="Eastern Sovereign Base Area"&gt;ESBA&lt;/abbr&gt;) on the main road to Famagusta. Our location places us just 20-30 minutes drive from Protaras and Ayia Napa, two of the island’s most renowned night life and tourist areas. The station is home to the majority of &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; Cyprus and its command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All new arrivals receive a briefing about the station. UK dependents and UK based civilians must also attend the new arrival brief, which is held at the Forum. It is compulsory for you and your spouse to attend this brief at the earliest opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="joint-service-signal-unit-cyprus"&gt;Joint Service Signal Unit Cyprus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Service Signal Unit (Cyprus) (&lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit (Cyprus)"&gt;JSSU(Cyp)&lt;/abbr&gt;) was formed in 2003 as a result of the amalgamation of Joint Service Signal Unit (Ayios Nikolaos) and elements of 12 Signal Unit RAF. As part of the Joint Service Signal Organisation, the Joint Service Signal Unit is a static communications organisation maintaining secure links from Cyprus to the rest of the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a fully integrated, proactive and responsive Joint Service Signal Unit, making a key contribution to defence.
The vast majority of the unit’s personnel live and work in Ayios Nikolaos in the Eastern Sovereign Base Area, however the unit also has large detachments at Akrotiri and Episkopi in the Western Sovereign Base Area and at the Retained Site in Troodos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit (Cyprus)"&gt;JSSU(Cyp)&lt;/abbr&gt; is commanded by a Royal Signals Lieutenant Colonel but officers from all three services make up the unit’s hierarchy to ensure tri-service representation. Due to the range of complex communications equipment used it also employs a large number of MOD civil servants and contractors as well as locally employed civilians. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit consists of 3 Squadrons: 1 Squadron is responsible for conducting operations, 2 Squadron for operational engineering support and Headquarters Squadron for defence, infrastructure and logistic support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit has Royal Signals personnel employed variously in the command and training role or as special operators, technicians, drivers and suppliers, and Royal Logistic Corps personnel employed as chefs, drivers and suppliers. Other Army Corps such as the Royal Engineers, Intelligence Corps and Adjutant General’s Corps are also employed at &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; (Cyp). Specialist operators and technicians from the Royal Navy and Royal Air Force work alongside the Army Corps personnel as well as a number of civilian personnel based at &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="accommodation-at-ayios-nikolaos"&gt;Accommodation at Ayios Nikolaos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayios Nikolaos Station has three estates: Seaforth Estate, Cape Estate and Alexander Court. Two of the estates comprise of modern semi-detached houses built in 1995, and have central heating installed with solar panels for heating water. The other estate comprises of older houses which have immersion-heated water and portable gas heaters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the Seaforth and Cape Estates are located on the station, and Alexander Court is located in the village no more than a mile from station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three large barrack blocks provide single accommodation with shared ablutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to arrival your room or quarter will have been marched in for you. For those in quarters a ‘get you in pack’ with bedding, cookware and other necessities will be provided until your household items arrive on the island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sponsor will assist with your initial settlement into Ayios Nikolaos and help with any questions and paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel posted to &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; but detached to Akrotiri, Episkopi and Troodos will reside in accommodation on their detached units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_51801"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16513/Housing.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51801-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16513/thumbnail_Housing.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/16513/Housing.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-51801-accessibility-help"&gt;Accommodation at Ayios Nikolaos (PDF 3.1MB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;3.12 MB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;1 page&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-51801-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Accommodation%20at%20Ayios%20Nikolaos%20%28PDF%203.1MB%29%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Accommodation%20at%20Ayios%20Nikolaos%20%28PDF%203.1MB%29%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;govuk-feedback@digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Accommodation at Ayios Nikolaos (PDF 3.1MB)").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="ayios-nikolaos-medical-facilities"&gt;Ayios Nikolaos medical facilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical care in the &lt;abbr title="Eastern Sovereign Base Area"&gt;ESBA&lt;/abbr&gt; is provided via the Medical Reception Station Dhekelia and the Medical Centre Ayios Nikolaos (Ay Nik). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troodos has only a duty medic for routine ailments; personnel will have to travel to Episkopi for more serious medical problems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Service personnel are automatically registered for treatment upon posting to Cyprus. UK based civilians and all dependents need to register for treatment as soon as possible after arrival. Registration forms are available during normal working hours from the &lt;abbr title="Medical Reception Station"&gt;MRS&lt;/abbr&gt; reception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All service personnel, UK based civilians and their dependents under the age of  26 (or in full-time education) are entitled to primary health care. Civilian visitors including non-dependent family are not entitled to treatment but &lt;abbr title="Medical Reception Station"&gt;MRS&lt;/abbr&gt; Dhekelia does not process insurance claims. EHIC are not valid inside the &lt;abbr title="Eastern Sovereign Base Area"&gt;ESBA&lt;/abbr&gt;..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service hospital is The Princess Mary’s Hospital, RAF Akrotiri. The hospital is manned by specialists and is also visited by specialist consultants from the UK. Travelling time to TPMH is about 2 hrs from Ay Nik. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive range of facilities are available at &lt;abbr title="Medical Reception Station"&gt;MRS&lt;/abbr&gt; Dhekelia including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;smoking cessation  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;physiotherapy  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;smear clinic  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;asthma clinic  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;community psychiatric nurse  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minor operations clinic  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;weight management clinic  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;outpatients clinics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;orthopaedics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paediatrics  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;obstetrics and gynaecology  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Service Health Unit (&lt;abbr title="Joint Service Health Unit"&gt;JSHU&lt;/abbr&gt;) is responsible for ensuring the maintenance of environmental and occupational health standards and will check working areas and accommodation provided for all units and establishments. As part of the service provided &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Health Unit"&gt;JSHU&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide a pest control service to married quarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="schools-and-education"&gt;Schools and education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ayios-nikolaos-primary-school"&gt;Ayios Nikolaos Primary School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayios Nikolaos has its own [infant and primary school], (http://www.school-portal.co.uk/GroupHomepage.asp?GroupID=723205 “Ayios Nikolaos Primary School”) located on the Seaforth Estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="king-richard-secondary-school"&gt;King Richard Secondary School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The King Richard Secondary School (KRS) is located at Dhekelia and serves the whole of the &lt;abbr title="Eastern Sovereign Base Area"&gt;ESBA&lt;/abbr&gt;, for children between 11 and 18 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK qualified teachers who are recruited by the Service Children’s Education Authority (&lt;abbr title="Service Children's Education Authority"&gt;SCEA&lt;/abbr&gt;) staff all schools. And a UK curriculum is taught so SATs and GCSEs still take place for children of the relevant age groups. Further education also takes place on the island and the opportunity for teenagers to do A Levels is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;School finishes around lunchtime but with a very early start. This is due to the hot weather experienced throughout the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="adult-education"&gt;Adult education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult education is also available. Ayos Nikolaos has its own education centre for both service personnel and their dependents to use. The centre runs a variety of local courses and liaises with Dhekelia where you can also take part in courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also very common for personnel to start or continue Open University courses in Cyprus and the Education Centre can help with you with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="amenities-at-ayios-nikolaos"&gt;Amenities at Ayios Nikolaos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the station boundary we have the FORUM community centre inside which you will find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HIVE (information centre)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unit well-being office  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;families clerk  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pass office  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post Office  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;padre’s office  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;estate warden/faults reporting office  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exchange store  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NAAFI Financial (including Abbey National Banking)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Airwaves Rep in the HIVE  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AFF Rep in the HIVE  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legal Aid clinic  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RugRats (parents and tots)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAMEO (come and meet everyone)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;toilets and baby changing facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone has access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gym  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gun club&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;games club&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 banks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;saddle club&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cinema  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;education centre  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;golf club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rugby club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hairdresser  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;various messes  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;swimming pool  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PRI  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kart club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;library  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;theatre club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thrift shop  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ay Nik Tavern (ANT)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ceramics club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;youth club  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;camera club  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="shopping-facilities"&gt;Shopping facilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NAAFI offers a wide range of services in Cyprus. In Dhekelia and Ayios Nikolaos there is a main shopping centre with a grocery hall, and a central services shop for gifts and durables. Dhekelia also sells sports clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be issued with a ration card to enable you to purchase cigarettes and spirits and a ‘yellow card’ to enable you to purchase other duty free goods in the NAAFI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a local supermarket which is 5 minutes’ drive from the station. Local towns offer a wide range of shops and supermarkets all within a short car drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are UK stores here such as Marks &amp;amp; Spencers, Body Shop, Next, Mothercare, Clarks, Dorothy Perkins and Evans, but clothes are slightly marked up in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material is cheap to buy here so if you have a sewing machine bring it with you along with patterns. The tailors here are good and reasonably priced and will often make an outfit for you from a sketch or picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="newsagents"&gt;Newsagents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as the MMG (Mission to Military Garrisons) they sell British newspapers (one day behind), cards, gifts and a limited range of magazines and books. They also provide a book and magazine ordering service but it would be advisable to subscribe to your favourite magazine before arriving in Cyprus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="recreation-at-ayios-nikolaos"&gt;Recreation at Ayios Nikolaos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karting Club – The Kart Club has both an outdoor and indoor circuit and run on a Wednesday and Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golf Club – The station has a 9 hole golf course and the club runs weekly and monthly competitions throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paintball Club – Runs private and public events periodically over the year on station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ay Nik Media Ops – The media team provides coverage of all unit events and delivers a dedicated service on the TV Network on station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycle Club – The club has its own workshop and shop on station and compete in a variety of cycling events on the island all year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bondu Rat’s Motorcycle Club – The club shares space with the cycle club and go out for weekly rides on some of Cyprus’ best roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saddle Club – A stables is located on station and is open for both adults and children to use, for learning or just ride out’s. The club also participates in island wide competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Football – The unit has a &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; Football Team and also several small teams that compete in the ‘Minor Unit’s Competition’. Also a youth football programme is run on a weekly basis for children of all ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ay Nik Stags RFC – The Rugby Team have a clubhouse and meet regularly to compete with other military and civilian teams around the island. The club also runs youth rugby during certain times of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts &amp;amp; Guides – The station has a Scout Group and Rainbows and Brownies, for boys and girls to participate in on a weekly basis. Guide’s is also run at Dhekelia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth Club – Open to kids and teens up to 16, open weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cross Country Team – &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; has a cross-country running team that competes in the island wide competition throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orienteering Team - &lt;abbr title="Joint Service Signal Unit"&gt;JSSU&lt;/abbr&gt; has a orienteering team that compete in the island wide competition throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxing Club – The club runs weekly for both kids and adults, to train and compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="facilities"&gt;Facilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Forum – Houses all family, welfare and HIVE facilities on station, and a weekly CAMEO (Come And Meet Every One) is run in the forum on Thursday mornings. For all station occupants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Library – The station has a small library available to be used by all station occupants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shops – The station has a thrift shop, PRI shop, DVD rental store, bakery, clothes/drycleaner’s store, ERMES (NAAFI), newsagent, kebab/chip shop and a café.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinema – The cinema is open 2-3 times a week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport/Fitness Facilities – The station has a gym, squash courts, swimming pool, volleyball court, netball courts, football pitches (grass &amp;amp; astroturf), rugby pitches and a 400 metre running track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snug Tavern – The Ay Nik Tavern (ANT) is the main station bar open most of the week and serves food. It is a family orientated venue with a children’s play area and events for all ages are run their throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rugby Club – The clubhouse has a bar and is open for spectators on match days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Mist – The Motorcycle Club bar, open to everyone on Friday evenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crèche – The crèche looks after toddlers up to 3 years old on weekday mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rugrat’s – Meet weekly, it’s a chance for parents to meet and socialise while the little ones do the same.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55954</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:21:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:21:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/latest-students-graduate-from-defence-academy"/>
    <title>Latest students graduate from Defence Academy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Academy is the UK’s Defence higher educational establishment. It is responsible for post-graduate education and the majority of command, staff, leadership, Defence management, acquisition, and technology training for members of the UK armed forces and MOD civil servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Advanced Command and Staff Course comprises a number of modules looking at a wide spectrum of military, political and international issues and aims to prepare officers for high grade appointments by giving them a much greater knowledge of Defence as a whole, as well as exposing them to the challenges and complexities posed by working alongside other Government departments, and civilian organisations and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course is also aimed at developing command, analytical and communication skills and providing a broad understanding and knowledge of single-Service, joint and combined operations, and of Defence as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as receiving lectures from the most senior officers and civil servants in the MOD, the Secretary of State for Defence and other Government Ministers have also attended over the last year, thus allowing students to gain insight into the structure and workings of the MOD and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lectures, workshops, discussions, debate, table-top exercises, and external visits are combined with formal assessments and exams throughout the course. Add to that a 15,000 word research paper on a Defence-related subject chosen by the student, and you have a course that is very demanding intellectually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Advanced Command and Staff Course comprises a number of modules looking at a wide spectrum of military, political and international issues" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5413/Latest_students_graduate_from_Defence_Academy_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Advanced Command and Staff Course comprises a number of modules looking at a wide spectrum of military, political and international issues [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The course is undertaken in partnership with King’s College London, and thus, while students gain the Staff College qualification there is also the opportunity to gain a Master’s degree in Military Studies alongside diplomas in Strategic Management and Leadership as part of the academic element of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 286 students (RN/RM 56, Army 72, RAF 63 and UK Govt Depts five) of which 90 are international students from 58 countries represent the top ten per cent of the officer cadre from across UK Defence and the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international students, who are fully integrated into all aspects of the course, come from the full range of NATO, European and Commonwealth countries, as well as a number from the Middle East, and from other countries as far afield as South Africa, Australia, Kazakhstan, Afghanistan, Japan and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commandant of the Joint Services Command and Staff College, Air Vice-Marshal Ray Lock, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Each year the Advanced Command and Staff Course provides a truly world-class education to 300 selected British, International Military and Civilian Officers who represent the top ten per cent of their generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The students’ successful completion of this Master’s-level course is a very significant achievement - it marks the end of an immensely demanding year where they have been challenged in many, many ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Their exposure to military studies, to the higher management of Defence both in the UK and abroad, and to a wide range of global issues will enable them to flourish in the difficult and challenging future we all face, from whichever country they may come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The course has also proved to be an ideal opportunity to improve the relationship and all-round understanding between the UK students and the other 57 countries represented on the course, and it also gains the UK significant international influence. But it is all about the students - and this bunch has been tremendous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55951</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:19:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:19:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/latest-helmet-saves-soldiers-lives-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Latest helmet saves soldiers' lives in Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ranger Silbert Wilson, aged 20, Corporal Tommy Creighton, 25, and Ranger Alan Hawthorne, 23, all from Northern Ireland, walked away unscathed after Taliban bullets aimed at their heads were stopped by the recently-introduced Mark 7 combat helmet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three separate incidents follow another escape by their colleague Ranger Ryan Boyd, 26, also from 1st Battalion The Royal Irish Regiment, who walked away with just a bruise after an insurgent round fired directly at him was stopped by his Osprey body armour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranger Wilson, from Antrim, was the first to test the helmet’s strength. That day he went out with A Company on a normal morning patrol in the Nad ‘Ali district, part of furthering the soldiers’ understanding of the local area and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol had been on task for almost two hours, moving around compounds and interacting with locals, when they suddenly came under enemy small arms fire. The soldiers took cover in a 5-foot-deep (1.5m) irrigation ditch and got ready to return fire - but the incoming rounds then stopped as suddenly as they had started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of minutes’ wait, the patrol was moving out of the ditch into another, shallower irrigation channel when the Taliban fighters opened up on them again, this time with machine gun fire and single rounds coming from at least four different firing points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranger Wilson recalled: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A single round landed about two metres in front of me. I was moving to get into better cover when suddenly it felt like someone punched me on the side of my head. I was pushed off my feet and ended up submerged in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There was no time to think. I got up, fired my weapon back at the enemy firing points; once the magazine was empty I reloaded a fresh magazine, and only then started to check myself. My face first - no blood! I thought ‘thank &lt;em&gt;**&lt;/em&gt;, that was really close!’. I was still confused and a bit dazed. My head was ringing - but I was OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Ranger Silbert Wilson and the Mark 7 combat helmet which saved his life" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5410/Latest_helmet_saves_soldiers__lives_in_Afghanistan_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Ranger Silbert Wilson and the Mark 7 combat helmet which saved his life [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ranger Wilson and the rest of the patrol subsequently conducted a fighting withdrawal out of contact, eventually returning to their checkpoint unscathed. Once they got back it became apparent he was not the only one to have experienced a close call that day - his colleague Lance Corporal Keith Morrison, from Templepatrick, had taken a shot clean through his daysack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Creighton, from Carrickfergus, was the next to feel the benefit of the Mark 7 helmet’s cutting-edge technology. He was out on patrol with B Company in Nad ‘Ali in the early hours of the morning, having been dropped off in a Mastiff vehicle operated by the 2nd Royal Tank Regiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol was not far from a patrol base when they heard the sound of a round being fired in their direction. Corporal Creighton saw movement from a compound wall off to his side and, looking through his weapon sight, he identified an insurgent with a rocket-propelled grenade launcher on his shoulder. When the insurgent noticed that Corporal Creighton had seen him, he panicked, fired off the missile in his general direction and quickly ducked back behind the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullets then started coming at the soldiers from all directions, from multiple firing points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Creighton, along with colleagues Lance Corporal Fraser Stirling and Ranger Kevin McMaster, took cover in a dry drainage ditch and returned fire at identified firing points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Taliban opened up with some accurate small arms fire in our direction, and we were returning fire,” said Corporal Creighton. “As I was observing forward, confirming new enemy positions, it seemed like it happened in slow motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I saw the strike of a round hit the ground in front of me. I could actually see the strike - the dirt lifting. My reaction was to lower my head, tilting it slightly forward, and then I felt the thud against my helmet as the round struck me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought ‘&lt;em&gt;**&lt;/em&gt;!’. My right leg started to shake. But I composed myself, identified the compound from where the round had come and engaged back returning fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contact with the insurgents carried on for a further three hours (a total of four). Eventually an Apache helicopter was called for and engaged the remaining insurgents, bringing the contact to a conclusion.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Creighton added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we got back to the patrol base, the lads were all looking at the helmet and saying how lucky I was. The round had struck me right on my ‘shamrock’ regimental badge, which I guess is kind of symbolic! But at the end of the day it’s a great bit of kit and that’s what it’s designed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranger Hawthorne, from Dromore, was the third Royal Irish soldier to walk away after a bullet to the head. He had been conducting a clearance patrol with C Company in southern Nad ‘Ali and his platoon had taken up position in a local resident’s compound, with the owner’s permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing the soldiers do when they occupy a compound is to secure it and build a good overwatch position. As the one who carries the machine gun, Ranger Hawthorne is usually the first to give protection for the remainder of the patrol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this occasion, just as his section commander had radioed through to confirm they were in place, shots began firing over their heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranger Hawthorne recalled: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we identified muzzle flash from the insurgents’ weapons and located their positions, we returned fire. As I was firing my machine gun, I felt a big thud - it was like someone had dropped a block on my head. It was a shock, but, with the enemy still firing at me, I had no choice but to keep returning fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When things quietened down, my section commander, Corporal Kyle Scott, tapped me on the shoulder - he was pointing to my head. That’s when I realised what had happened. I’d been so involved in the shooting that I had thought nothing more about the thud!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the shooting finished, Corporal Scott called me down from my position. I took my helmet off. Lots of the boys gathered round and they were all pointing at the big gash the bullet had made in the side of my helmet. I have to say, I feel like a lucky boy, but it just shows the quality of the kit we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Jeffrey Herbert, spokesman for 1st Battalion The Royal Irish Regiment, said of all the incidents: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These guys are all entitled to feel pretty lucky after what they’ve been through, but the fact we’ve now had three soldiers saved by this helmet goes to show what fantastic personal protective equipment we now have in the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aside from that though, I think the way all three of the lads kept their composure after being hit and carried on fighting, only thinking to assess the damage after the contact was over, says a great deal about the character of the Royal Irish Regiment. These lads are as much a credit to the British Army as the helmets that saved their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55943</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:16:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:16:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/latest-counter-ied-equipment-showcased"/>
    <title>Latest counter-IED equipment showcased</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Peter Luff, formally opened this year’s show at the Millbrook vehicle testing ground in Bedfordshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Luff was then given a demonstration of some of the latest counter-IED (C-IED) equipment being used by British troops and met soldiers who had survived IED blasts thanks to the heavily armoured vehicles in which they were travelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the event he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling the IED threat is vital for us to make military progress. C-IED is not just about the bomb disposal expert defusing a bomb, vital and dangerous though that role is. It is about making sure that our soldiers have a range of tools, tactics and techniques available to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Luff was given a guided tour of the five pieces of equipment that make up Talisman, the newest military solution to the IED problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five elements consist of two enormous armoured vehicles, a JCB digger, a bomb disposal robot and a UAV (unmanned aerial vehicle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Talisman system is currently being used by Royal Engineers to clear and build safe routes around Helmand province in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Mastiff armoured vehicle and its crew act as Talisman’s eyes, with video screens inside the rear compartment of the truck displaying aerial video footage gathered by a Honeywell T-Hawk UAV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another armoured vehicle known as Buffalo has a remote-controlled, extendable, pronged arm attached to the front, which is used to comb or ‘rummage’ the ground, detecting signs of IEDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Talon remote-controlled robot forms part of the latest counter-IED technology" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5408/Latest_counter-IED_equipment_showcased_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Talon remote-controlled robot forms part of the latest counter-IED technology [Picture: Andrew Linnett, Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The JCB digger is used to fill in ditches or potholes that might prevent soldiers or vehicles from moving forward and the Talon remote-controlled robot gives troops the safer option of remaining out of harm’s way when trying to deal with any devices they find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Paul Ridge, the head of the Military Manouevre Support Team that spent around 18 months developing the Talisman system, said the aim was to enable soldiers to move around the battlefield more easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a range of equipment that has been brought together to make a system which allows early detection and the choice of either avoiding or destroying the IED.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It can be used on its own or in support of other vehicles. And the whole system can be operated from under armour. It’s just one part of the contribution towards counter-IED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldiers from 1st Battalion The Royal Welsh who survived two IED blasts in two days while in Afghanistan met the minister and described how the heavily armoured vehicles in which they were travelling probably saved their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusilier Danny Hughes, who was travelling in one vehicle when it hit a roadside bomb, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Mastiff is worth its weight in gold. The second time it happened there weren’t any injuries either, it was almost a case of ‘here we go again’, that’s another few hours until we can have a cup of tea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle to beat the IEDs is the driving force behind an MOD contract for a tranche of 200 new Light Protected Patrol Vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two companies, SupaCat and Force Protection Europe, are competing for the contract and displayed prototype models of what they hope will be the next generation of Light Protected Patrol Vehicles (LPPVs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicles will be used for a variety of patrols and so must be tough enough to cope with cross-country terrain, but also enable the troops inside to engage with the local people they encounter in more urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, Chief of Defence Materiel and the Head of Defence Equipment and Support, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As well as its protection against blasts, the LPPV must be able to operate in the harsh conditions of the desert and tight urban environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Luff added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will agree a contract for an initial tranche of 200 vehicles under an Urgent Operational Requirement funded from the Treasury Reserve later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first batch of vehicles is required for training by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the DVD event Mr Luff also announced a contract for more than 140 extra Jackal 2A weapons-mounted patrol vehicles in a deal worth about £45m, bringing the number of Jackal vehicles for Defence to over 500, and an extra 28 Wolfhound heavy tactical support vehicles under a £20m deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the MOD is reducing the weight troops on the front line carry with improvements to current and future infantry combat and support kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the average weight of equipment carried by an infantryman is around 66kg, but innovative weight-saving schemes have shaved more than 4.5kg from this. New kit being delivered in October could reduce this by a further 8kg. Measures implemented include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trials of new lightweight patrol rations for troops in the field that weigh less than 1kg, compared with a 24-hour ration pack that weighs around 3kg; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new longer-life batteries to power radios and other equipment; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new battery recharging system which reduces the number of spare batteries required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;After inspecting some of the equipment at the annual DVD event and talking to soldiers and suppliers, Minister for International Security Strategy, Gerald Howarth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While the modern combat soldier is better equipped than ever before, this has brought about its own challenges - mainly an increase in the weight being carried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The welfare of our troops is paramount and so the work being carried out here to reduce this burden is essential to both the physical and mental well-being of our troops fighting on the front line in what can be 50-degree temperatures. The other improvements announced today are a further demonstration of our determination to equip our forces on the front line with the kit they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A newly-formed project team, - the Integrated Soldier System Executive, based at Defence Equipment and Support in Bristol, has been leading on the work to reduce the weight carried on the front line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with lightening a soldier’s load, the welfare of personnel operating in remote locations is being improved through increasing the number of e-bluey computer terminals to enable them to communicate with loved ones and installing more showers, sinks and toilets in forward operating bases. The new ablutions facilities will be sent to Afghanistan later this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/55862</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T10:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T10:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/last-training-on-the-navys-merlin-mk1-helicopter"/>
    <title>Last training on the Navy's Merlin Mk1 helicopter</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eighteen trainee pilots, observers and aircrewmen from 824 Naval Air Squadron at Royal Naval Air Station Culdrose are spending five weeks flying on, off and around aviation training ship Royal Fleet Auxiliary vessel Argus. They are the last crews to train on the Mk1 variant of the aircraft before the Merlin Mk2 joins the Fleet Air Arm later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trainees have completed between two and four years of training and instruction both on simulators and on the genuine article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But their stint on the 28,000-tonne training ship - which doubles as the Navy’s casualty treatment vessel in times of war - is their first taste of operating the Merlin, which is the mainstay of the Royal Navy’s anti-submarine and counter-piracy operations around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aboard Argus, the trainees go from the basics of landing on and taking off from a flight deck at sea to practising search and rescue drills, then on to tactical missions such as hunting submarines or surface ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student pilot Sub-Lieutenant Will Legge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You learn so much more in the real world than you do on a simulation. The real world provides 100 times more variation, things that you can never plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And if things go wrong, you cannot just press ‘reset’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Completing the first deck landing is a milestone. You are pretty nervous beforehand, because the deck looks tiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Merlin Mk1 helicopter on the aircraft lift of RFA Argus" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5382/Last_training_on_the_Navy_s_Merlin_Mk1_helicopter_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Merlin Mk1 helicopter on the aircraft lift of RFA Argus [Picture: LA(Phot) Dave Sterratt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sea Flight Commander and senior 824 Naval Air Squadron instructor aboard RFA Argus, Lieutenant Commander Mike Currie, said of the five-week training spell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is where we put into practice all that has been taught previously - it is almost the final hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have to have a certain temperament to succeed, a certain Fleet Air Arm ethos, but the pilots, observers, aircrewmen, they are all individuals. There’s no one trait and we’re certainly not trying to produce carbon copies of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Gavin Richardson, 824 Naval Air Squadron’s Commanding Officer, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The embarked period is what the squadron team effort works toward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is the crowning glory of a long and arduous road for our students which provides the opportunity to show the investment was worthwhile and that they have metamorphosed into naval aviators, able to operate and fly from that most demanding environment - the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the students come through the training, they will earn their wings in June and go on to join one of three front line Merlin squadrons based at Culdrose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, they will be the last of scores of Merlin crews to pass through the squadron and the impressive simulator and training complex at the air station on the Lizard Peninsula since the late 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merlin was originally introduced as a submarine hunter to replace the venerable Sea King. It has since grown into a general purpose helicopter capable of interdicting pirates and drug runners, saving the lives of stricken mariners, and delivering stores and people, as well as fulfilling its original anti-submarine mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first next-generation naval Merlin, the Mk2, arrives in Cornwall this summer. Although outwardly the helicopter is almost identical, inside the cockpit and the command consoles are entirely new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no comparison with other aircraft out there,” said Lieutenant Commander Currie, who has 1,800 Merlin flying hours under his belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty awesome when it comes to what it can do - especially the variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Things have moved on since the Mk1. It has served us well - and still serves us well - but it’s time to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;824 Naval Air Squadron will learn the ins and outs of the new helicopters first before the rest of the Merlin community gets to grip with them and it begins front line deployments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
