<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Ministry of Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T17:59:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/35698</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T17:59:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:59:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/whole-fleet-management-programme-management-office"/>
    <title>Whole Fleet Management Programme Management Office</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole Fleet Management (&lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt;) allows the Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;) to meet defence outputs through more effective equipment capability management and is crucial to supporting and enabling future training in order to meet operational commitments with smaller fleets whilst offering significant benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; is a continuous improvement change programme, being delivered incrementally, supported by a number of enablers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="joint-asset-management-engineering-solution"&gt;Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution (&lt;abbr title="Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution"&gt;JAMES&lt;/abbr&gt;) is an Information System that provides global and near real-time visibility of asset and engineering data.  The second phase of &lt;abbr title="Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution"&gt;JAMES&lt;/abbr&gt; will give a deployable capability thus providing real-time and global visibility of assets with the inclusion of engineering data and will be rolled out in March 2011. &lt;abbr title="Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution"&gt;JAMES&lt;/abbr&gt; 1 achieved &lt;abbr title="Full operating capability"&gt;FOC&lt;/abbr&gt; in September 2010 which coincided with the implementation of &lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="data-reporting-analysis-corrective-action-system"&gt;Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support Defence Equipment &amp;amp; Support (&lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment &amp;amp; Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt;) Integrated Project Teams (&lt;abbr title="Integrated Project Teams"&gt;IPTs&lt;/abbr&gt;) to identify trends in equipment failure and subsequently change and improve design. Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System (&lt;abbr title="Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System"&gt;DRACAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) are mandated to identify savings of £55 million per annum on behalf of &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; for Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirmatory trials in British Army Training Unit Suffield (BATUS) on air filtration through work initiated by the &lt;abbr title="Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System"&gt;DRACAS&lt;/abbr&gt; Cell has increased distance between failure of Warrior from 858 km to 5100 km with considerable cost savings in filters, engines and repair cost. More significant is the enhanced operational capability this engineering solution provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System"&gt;DRACAS&lt;/abbr&gt; Cell are progressing a further 23 projects in conjunction with &lt;abbr title="Defence Equipment &amp;amp; Support"&gt;DE&amp;amp;S&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Integrated Project Teams"&gt;IPTs&lt;/abbr&gt; and recently reviewed and reduced the servicing requirements for some Urgent Operational Requirement (&lt;abbr title="Urgent Operational Requirement"&gt;UOR&lt;/abbr&gt;) equipments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="theatre-fleet-support-unit"&gt;Theatre Fleet Support Unit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 Theatre Fleet Support Units (&lt;abbr title="Theatre Fleet Support Units"&gt;TFSUs&lt;/abbr&gt;) based in Ashchurch (Gloucestershire) and Ayrshire Barracks (Mönchengladbach Germany) which provide support for the stored fleet in Controlled Humidity Environment (&lt;abbr title="Controlled Humidity Environment"&gt;CHE&lt;/abbr&gt;) sheds. There are a number of additional locations which provide storage to the fleet, they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbroath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chivenor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donnington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stafford&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stirling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="controlled-humidity-environment"&gt;Controlled Humidity Environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of dehumidification (the removal of moisture from the air in order to stop the degradation of equipment) of a shed housing a number of vehicles (Closed &lt;abbr title="Controlled Humidity Environment"&gt;CHE&lt;/abbr&gt;) or a single vehicle (Open &lt;abbr title="Controlled Humidity Environment"&gt;CHE&lt;/abbr&gt;). To assist in the maintenance of equipment a Battery Management System (BMS) is used in conjunction with &lt;abbr title="Controlled Humidity Environment"&gt;CHE&lt;/abbr&gt; to keep batteries fully charged through a trickle feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="land-training-fleet-warminster"&gt;Land Training Fleet (Warminster)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially created to support CT levels 3 and 4 on Salisbury Plain the Land Training Fleet (Warminster) (&lt;abbr title="Land Training Fleet (Warminster)"&gt;LTF(W)&lt;/abbr&gt;) has developed with the addition of the Operational Training Equipment Pack (&lt;abbr title="Operational Training Equipment Pack"&gt;OTEP&lt;/abbr&gt;) which covers the &lt;abbr title="Urgent Operational Requirement"&gt;UOR&lt;/abbr&gt; equipment procured to support ongoing operations. Improvements to the command and control have provided units and formations with a one stop mechanism to provide the capability and resources required to undertake pre deployment training and confirmatory exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; will enhance the operational readiness of the Defence vehicle and equipment fleets and enable their more efficient use. There will be a reduction in the number of vehicles procured, going forward, which in turn will result in a smaller Total Fleet Requirement (&lt;abbr title="Total Fleet Requirement"&gt;TFR&lt;/abbr&gt;), as a result, the practice of issuing units with their full establishment of vehicles has ceased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Units now hold a reduced fleet of vehicles (active fleet) sufficient for low level collective training, these holdings are augmented from training fleets (active fleets) for higher level training. Operational deployments utilise vehicles from the operational pool (stored fleet) which is held in a &lt;abbr title="Controlled Humidity Environment"&gt;CHE&lt;/abbr&gt; to avoid vehicle degradation. Without these changes &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; will not be able to meet future operational and training requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interim &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Interim WFM"&gt;IWFM&lt;/abbr&gt;) was the initial phase of implementation and has been successfully rolled out to the Army, Eqpt Dir Headquarters Land Forces (&lt;abbr title="Headquarters Land Forces"&gt;HQLF&lt;/abbr&gt;) managed the necessary equipment drawdown from units to create Unit Holdings (&lt;abbr title="Unit Holdings"&gt;UH&lt;/abbr&gt;) as endorsed by &lt;abbr title="Headquarters Land Forces"&gt;HQLF&lt;/abbr&gt; and Arms and Service Director (A&amp;amp;SD). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Interim WFM"&gt;IWFM&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been expanded to Tri-Service &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt;) to encompass the Navy and RAF, a Comprehensive &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Comprehensive WFM"&gt;CWFM&lt;/abbr&gt;) option to allow the inclusion of industry in the process was put on hold until the exact requirement can be defined. &lt;abbr title="Unit Holdings"&gt;UH&lt;/abbr&gt; have now been redefined as Basic Unit Fleets (&lt;abbr title="Basic Unit Fleets"&gt;BUF&lt;/abbr&gt;) which have been calculated by A&amp;amp;SD to support CT1 level training activity on local, backdoor training areas and are managed IAW current ES direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-status"&gt;Current Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="interim-wfm-iwfm"&gt;Interim &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Interim WFM"&gt;IWFM&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Interim WFM"&gt;IWFM&lt;/abbr&gt; began in September 2005 and is a single-service propriety phase being implemented across the Army (Regular and Reserve) that rationalised unit holdings and provided initial sites and conditions for the stored fleet, it achieved &lt;abbr title="Full operating capability"&gt;FOC&lt;/abbr&gt; in September 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tri-service-wfm-3wfm"&gt;Tri-Service &lt;abbr title="Whole Fleet Management"&gt;WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministerial approval for the &lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; Main Gate Business Case was received on 14 Mar 2008 and included the approval for the rationalisation of &lt;abbr title="Unit Holdings"&gt;UH&lt;/abbr&gt; across the Navy and RAF. The Stored Fleet when fully established will continue to provide central training and operational pools of vehicles and equipment. &lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; was launched in September 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="milestones"&gt;Milestones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 2011 Commence Tri Service rollout of &lt;abbr title="Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution"&gt;JAMES&lt;/abbr&gt; Land&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-way-ahead"&gt;The way ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although SDSR and PR11 will have an impact on the Programme, the current plan is to progress &lt;abbr title="Tri-Service WFM"&gt;3WFM&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2 distinct phases: first, (in Tranche 2, 2010-2015) to deliver &lt;abbr title="Joint Asset Management Engineering Solution"&gt;JAMES&lt;/abbr&gt; Land, to establish the rules for management of the Stored and Active Fleets and to consolidate existing infrastructure to optimise storage and capacity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in Tranche 3 (2015-2024), to develop the UK vehicle hub. &lt;abbr title="Data Reporting Analysis Corrective Action System"&gt;DRACAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue to deliver benefits throughout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/60044</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-announces-reduction-in-uk-troop-numbers-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prime Minister announces reduction in UK troop numbers in Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="Number 10"&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt; told &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/" title="UK Parliament"&gt;Parliament&lt;/a&gt; that UK forces would shift from mentoring Afghan troops at battalion level to brigade level next year. This reflects the progress made in Helmand and the increasing ability and confidence of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;) to lead security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown, agreed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-security-council" title="National Security Council"&gt;National Security Council&lt;/a&gt; this week, is in line and consistent with both UK military advice and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;North Atlantic Treaty Organization&lt;/a&gt; strategy agreed at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/events_66529.htm" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization Summit, Lisbon 2010"&gt;Lisbon Summit in 2010&lt;/a&gt;, under which &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) forces continue to operate across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK forces will end combat operations by the end of 2014. It is part of transition to an enduring commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement comes as the previously announced reduction of UK force levels from 9,500 to 9,000 is being achieved with service personnel due to arrive home in time for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed work on how force levels will reduce in 2013 is ongoing and will be conducted in line with operational requirements and the transition process which remains on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Afghan forces increasingly take the lead, UK combat operations will give way to an increasing focus on training and advising. By the end of 2013, it is expected that UK forces will not routinely need to mentor Afghan forces below brigade level, allowing the reduction in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real progress being made on the ground in Helmand province will allow us, on current planning, to reduce British troops to around 5,200 by the end of 2013. This is a direct result of the success of the Afghan National Security Forces in assuming a lead role in delivering security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The phased process of transition of security responsibility agreed at the Lisbon Summit is well advanced and on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have consistently said that there will not be a cliff-edge reduction in troop numbers at the end of 2014. This gradual drawdown is firmly in line with the planning of our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; partners and the advice of military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces will continue to operate alongside their Afghan counterparts, albeit in lower numbers, until our combat operations cease at the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There remain huge challenges ahead for the Afghan people. Our combat mission is drawing to a close, but our commitment to the Afghan people is long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Afghan National Army" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5775/JMOCCCT-2012-014_Op_Horhari_Afghan_004.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Afghan National Army take part in an operation in Helmand province (stock image) [Picture: Sergeant Steve Blake RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir David Richards, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Army and Police have greatly improved in the past years. Their capability has increased so that today they enjoy the trust of some 84 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As they develop, and in agreement with the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, the efforts of our Armed Forces will continue to shift from a combat role to one that focuses on training, advice and assistance. That will allow us to make appropriate and measured reductions in our force levels in line with the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; plan and our Chicago commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These drawdown plans are based on military advice and following discussion with General Allen [Commander &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces]. I am confident that the progress we have seen in Helmand and across Afghanistan can be maintained and that we can complete the tasks we have been set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be in the position where we are now able to commit to reducing UK force levels to around 5,200 by the end of next year is testament to the professionalism and courage of those personnel who have served, and continue to serve, in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We must remember that the UK’s commitment to the operation in Afghanistan will continue beyond the end of 2014 as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/" title="Department for International Development"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [Department for International Development] and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign Office&lt;/a&gt; continue to build the government and nation while the UK’s pledge to support the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, including training the military’s officers, will be ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significant progress in Afghanistan continues with 75% of the Afghan population now being secured by the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; and at least 80% of all patrols being &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;-led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 80 UK bases at the start of the HERRICK 16 deployment this April, only 32 remain active with the others having been handed over to Afghan forces or closed. Afghan National Army numbers in Helmand province now stand at about 18,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57526</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-protector-takes-to-the-ice-for-a-charity-santa-run"/>
    <title>HMS Protector takes to the ice for a charity Santa run</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Santas, accompanied by Rudolph, were gathered at 10am for a gentle warm-up led by the Executive Officer, Commander Don Mackinnon, who is currently in command for this Antarctic patrol, before it was ‘on your marks, get set… ho ho ho’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Santa run was conducted on ice in the waters surrounding Deception Island, a dormant, water-filled caldera volcano; one of only two known in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking through a sheet of snow-covered ice before coming to a planned stop, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Ice-Patrol-and-Survey-Ships/HMS-Protector" title="HMS Protector"&gt;HMS Protector&lt;/a&gt; took position and disembarked her personnel to test the ice conditions and drill ice core samples to ensure the ice was safe, before Protector’s eager Father Christmasses followed via the ship’s accommodation ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amid perfect weather conditions, and under the watchful eye of two seals that had taken up post next to the ship, they completed their run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5743/protector2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line, ready for the off [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annually, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.each.org.uk/" title="East Anglian Children's Hospice"&gt;East Anglian Children’s Hospice&lt;/a&gt; conducts nine Santa runs across Essex and East Anglia throughout the festive period, raising thousands of pounds for the charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is traditional for Royal Naval ships to adopt a charity from their affiliated town so that they can fundraise whilst away from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the work that HMS Protector conducts in Antarctica, she has formed a close liaison with a number of organisations in the Cambridge area (amongst them the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.antarctica.ac.uk/" title="British Antarctic Survey"&gt;British Antarctic Survey&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.spri.cam.ac.uk/" title="Scott Polar Research Institute"&gt;Scott Polar Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;) and as such is affiliated to the City of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector has been affiliated with the East Anglian Children’s Hospice since August 2012. The East Anglian Children’s Hospice provides support to families and care for children and young people with life-threatening conditions across Cambridgeshire, Essex, Norfolk and Suffolk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) Royal Navy" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5744/protector3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) gets off to a flying start [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing care and support wherever the family wishes, in families’ own homes, in the community or at the hospices, their care teams help children and their families with the emotional and physical challenges they face, helping them to make the most of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Don Mackinnon stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With 21 hours of daylight in every 24, our working day in Antarctica tends to be a long one. Yesterday for example our first boat group departed the ship at 0830 [8.30am] in the morning and the last one finally got back at 2300 [11pm] that night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With that sort of work pace it’s nice to be able to take a break from operations now and again, and do something both for fun, and also to help our affiliated charity at the same time. Father Christmas’s traditional home might be the North Pole… but as you can see, he has helpers that visit the other one too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector is currently in the Antarctic in order to support an international team conducting formal &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ats.aq/e/ats.htm" title="The Antarctic Treaty"&gt;Antarctic Treaty&lt;/a&gt; inspections of sites across the Peninsula, whilst maintaining a UK Sovereign presence in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5745/protector4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses lie on the ice to spell out EACH [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Led by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/a&gt; and with the support of the British Antarctic Survey and observers from HMS Protector, the international Antarctic Treaty team is inspecting a number of scientific stations, historic sites, cruise vessels and yachts in the Antarctic Peninsula region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector will be operating in and around Antarctica until April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/59911</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-united-kingdom-s-future-nuclear-deterrent-2012-update-to-parliament"/>
    <title>The United Kingdom’s future nuclear deterrent: 2012 update to Parliament</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 May 2011, the Ministry of Defence (MOD) announced that the first milestone (known as Initial Gate) for the Successor deterrent submarine programme had been passed and that a five year-long, £3 billion Assessment Phase had been approved. The main purpose of the Assessment Phase is to refine the design of the successor submarine prior to the main investment decision (known as Main Gate), which will be taken in 2016. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of annual reports that will explain the progress the MOD has made on this programme and set out what is expected to be achieved over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/57431</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T16:20:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:20:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/ministry-of-defence-art-collection"/>
    <title>Ministry of Defence art collection </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection consists of over 1,500 items of fine art and antiques including paintings, drawings, engravings, photographs, clocks and furniture. All the items are in public ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collection exists through the generosity of donors in the 19th and early 20th centuries who made bequests and gifts to the Admiralty and later, the War Office, then the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases the terms of the gift or bequest mean that they may not be sold or otherwise disposed of and the intentions of the donors were that the works should be in public ownership rather than in the private collections of various regimental messes and ward rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection team is responsible for protecting, preserving and conserving these works of art and antiques. In many cases, we display items in the offices of senior officials, in conference rooms and in other public spaces in defence estate buildings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collection has its origins in the Admiralty collection. From the early 19th century successive First Lords and Admiralty Secretaries commissioned portraits and donated or bequeathed items from their private collections with the intention of ensuring that their memories were preserved. The army is less well represented because although hundreds of fine works of art have been commissioned and bequeathed, most still belong to regimental messes and are not public property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also few images of the Royal Air Force as most of the significant paintings depicting RAF personnel and activity belong to the RAF museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection is managed to professional standards by a small team who ensure that loan criteria are strictly adhered to and that conservation is carried out where necessary. The team has two main objectives: first, to maintain the safety and preservation of the items in the collection and second, to display this unique archive within defence establishments and residencies and to maximize public access and visibility wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This A to Z includes some of the very best works of art and historic objects in the archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the Ministry of Defence art collection, its provenance and background are presented in a new book and DVD. Selected high quality prints of paintings in the collection are also available for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-birds-eye-view-of-venice-1740"&gt;A Bird’s Eye View of Venice, 1740&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="francesco-guardi-1712-to-1793"&gt;Francesco Guardi (1712 to 1793)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Bird's-Eye View of Venice, 1740" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4724/guardiwhole_960x600.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This magnificent work by Francesco Guardi was painted around 1740. It was one of the many works bequeathed by John Wilson Croker; Secretary to the Admiralty between 1809 and 1830, and the collection’s main benefactor. Recent cleaning was carried out on the painting when some layers of discoloured varnish were removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="admiral-sir-richard-haddock-1629-to-1715"&gt;Admiral Sir Richard Haddock (1629 to 1715)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="john-closterman-1660-to-1711"&gt;John Closterman (1660 to 1711)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Admiral Sir Richard Haddock (1629 to 1715)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4725/admiral_haddock_480x578.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Admiral Haddock’s legacy is assured within the Royal Navy, perhaps his greatest historical legacy is that his story impressed the Belgian author Hergé sufficiently for the Admiral to be used as the inspiration for a character in The Adventures of Tintin .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admiral Richard Haddock coincides exactly with Hergé’s creation of the fictional Captain Haddock’s flamboyant ancestor Sir Francis Haddock in ‘The Secret of the Unicorn’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the outbreak of the third Anglo-Dutch War in 1672 Richard Haddock became captain of the 100-gun HMS Royal James on 18 January of that year; he was her captain at the Battle of Solebay on 28 May. The Royal James was the flagship of Admiral Sir Edward Montagu, 1st Earl of Sandwich . &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal James led the Blue Squadron and attacked Willem Joseph van Ghent’s ship. She was then engaged by a number of other Dutch warships and fireships. Despite fighting several of them off and forcing Rear-Admiral Jan van Brakel’s ship to disengage, the Royal James was set on fire by the Dutch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admiral Haddock was wounded in the foot and seeing that the ship was doomed attempted to persuade the Earl to abandon ship. Montagu refused and Haddock jumped overboard. He survived to be picked up and transferred to another English warship. Montagu was killed in the wreck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haddock returned to London and attended a meeting with King Charles II. There the King bestowed a mark of favour on Haddock for his actions during the battle, taking a satin cap from his head and placing it on Haddock’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bomb-damage-to-hm-customs-house-london-1942"&gt;Bomb damage to HM Customs House. London, 1942&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="alistair-stewart"&gt;Alistair Stewart&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Bomb Damage to HM Customs House. London, 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4726/customhouse_556x699.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the better known war artists were a small London-based group commissioned to record the effect of bomb damage on well-known buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These artists, employed by the Ministry of Works, were given special access to damaged government buildings - but were hampered by a lack of canvas on which to paint. Alistair Stewart solved the problem by producing paintings such as this one on utility hardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the wartime period a small team of artist-restorers, working for the artists’ section of the Ministry of Works, were responsible for the care and maintenance of public works of art. This team built on a long tradition of employing artists in a dual role as painting conservators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the outset of the London Blitz some of these artists were asked to record damage to significant buildings such as the Tower of London and HM Customs House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official war artists commissioned by the War Artists Advisory Committee were all, at this point, deployed out of London, and among the few people available and capable of undertaking the task were Alistair Stewart and William Hampton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="canadian-infantryman-1918"&gt;Canadian Infantryman, 1918&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="augustus-john"&gt;Augustus John&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Canadian Infantryman, 1918" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4727/augustusjohn_487x600.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Infantryman was painted by Augustus John in 1918 when he accepted a commission with the Canadian Expeditionary Force in order to produce a series of war portraits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the very best portraits in the collection, this portrait by Augustus John of a Canadian infantryman is fascinating because like so many of the war artist’s output, the subject’s identity is unknown. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know nothing of the man - nothing of his background, family, attitude towards what he was doing - he takes on an iconic significance. He symbolizes both the victors and victims of war and has become, for the Armed Forces, our universal ‘Unknown Soldier’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work is signed and dated on the reverse of canvas, and was donated to the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capture-of-the-maria-di-giovanna-january-1941"&gt;Capture of the Maria Di Giovanna, January 1941&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rowland-langmaid"&gt;Rowland Langmaid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Capture of the Maria Di Giovanna, January 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4728/giovanni_803x551.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is appropriate that the central collection of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; should contain works of art depicting both 20th century world wars. Activity during the 1939 to 1945 war is widely represented and again the concentration is on naval activity rather than on land campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This watercolour shows HMS Dainty capturing the Italian merchant ship schooner, the SS Maria Giovanna, off Bardia. SS Maria Giovanna was a 255 ton schooner running supplies to North Africa. HMS Dainty was a D-class British destroyer. At the beginning of World War 2 the HMS Dainty joined the Mediterranean Fleet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 February 1941, when she was cruising off the coasts of Eastern Libya, the HMS Dainty was spotted and bombed by a German aircraft. She was severely damaged and sank off Tobruk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rowland Langmaid was born in Canada on 1 December 1897. He was the eldest son of Captain J Langmaid, who was an engineer in the Royal Navy. Langmaid joined the Royal Navy in 1910 and went to sea at the beginning of the World War 1 serving at the Dardenelles in HMS ‘Agamemnon’ where he made official sketches for landings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the war Rowland Langmaid studied at the Royal Academy School and the Royal College of Art. He held exhibitions at the Royal Academy and in London, New York, and Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Langmaid was a highly accomplished engraver as well as a painter in oil and watercolour with a style similar to the famous marine artist W L Wyllie with whom he collaborated in Sea Fights of the Great War, 1914 to 1918. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Langmaid returned to the active list in 1939 in the rank of Lieutenant Commander and served as official Admiralty artist to the Commander-in-Chief Mediterranean Fleet from 1941 to 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dawn-at-scapa-flow-december-1918"&gt;Dawn at Scapa Flow, December 1918&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="muirhead-bone"&gt;Muirhead Bone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dawn at Scapa Flow, December 1918" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4777/bonescapa_409x529.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This drawing shows activity on board a British patrol visiting a German battle cruiser, at a time when some of the German Fleet was caged in Scapa Flow, a landlocked anchorage in the Orkneys. The artist was commissioned to record activity in and around the British fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muirhead Bone was a master etcher, draughtsman and war artist who was born in Glasgow. He became the first official war artist in 1916 when he was attached to the intelligence branch of the War Office and sent to France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was commissioned as an Honorary 2nd Lieutenant and toured the western front in a chauffeur-driven car. Working at considerable speed his sketches covered a wide range of subjects, mostly behind the lines, including the work of the medical services, the repair and maintenance of big guns and off duty, war weary soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone worked in various media - chalk, charcoal, pencil and pen, sometimes adding touches of watercolour later.  Subsequently, Bone illustrated a 2 volume set of books entitled ‘The Western Front’, published in 1917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muirhead Bone also served as an official war artist in World War 2, by which time he was Sir Muirhead having been knighted by George VI in 1937. Bone was attached to the Admiralty and was not only the first but also the most senior of its artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His work was to become the most widely reproduced official war art of the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="design-for-whitehall-new-government-buildings-1936"&gt;Design for Whitehall, New Government Buildings, 1936&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="emmanuel-vincent-harris"&gt;Emmanuel Vincent-Harris&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Design for Whitehall, New Government Buildings, 1936" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4778/walcot_1200x449.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the collection of architectural drawings are designs for churches and barracks, as well as Robert Adam’s Admiralty screen and other Whitehall-based drawings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally providing accommodation for the Board of Trade and the Air Ministry, ‘Main Building’ was built between 1938 and 1959 to designs by the architect E Vincent Harris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; moved into the building in 1964 when the department was reorganised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This original architectural drawing has hung in the Main Building since its presentation by the architects in 1969. It was rehung in the rotunda area on the building’s re-opening in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="esther-and-king-ahasuerus"&gt;Esther and King Ahasuerus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="english-school-15th-century-alabaster-panel"&gt;English School, 15th century. Alabaster panel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Esther and King Ahasuerus" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4779/alabaster_666x527.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This tiny carving is one of a set of 5, 15th century Flemish alabaster panels from Chicksands Priory in Bedfordshire.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the site became a defence establishment objects from the priory were sent to a local museum.  Following the recent restoration at Chicksands the museum decided to allow the alabasters to return to their original home. They are the oldest pieces within the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="frederik-hendrik-prince-of-orange"&gt;Frederik Hendrik, Prince of Orange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="michiel-jansz-van-miereveld"&gt;Michiel Jansz. van Miereveld&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Frederik Hendrik, Prince of Orange" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4780/frederickhendrik_454x529.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frederik Hendrik was born in 1584, the son of William the Silent. He succeeded his brother Maurits as Stadholder of the United Provinces of the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was the grandfather of William III who, with his wife Mary, became joint monarchs in 1689. Van Miereveld was the official court painter to the princes of Orange throughout the late-16th century and his works were very highly regarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is thought that when William arrived in England he brought portraits such as this one to give to members of the English establishment - in this case, the Lord High Admiral. The portrait currently hangs in a NATO residence in Holland and its first return to its country of origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="gateway-to-the-admiralty-1760"&gt;Gateway to the Admiralty, 1760&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="robert-adam"&gt;Robert Adam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Gateway to the Admiralty, 1760" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4781/screen_1000x412.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection includes two original architectural Robert Adam drawings - showing front and rear elevations for the screen separating the Admiralty building from Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building, built for purpose by Thomas Ripley in 1725, was thought to be too visible to everyday pedestrians in Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two drawings are extremely light sensitive and are protected with ultraviolet light resistant glazing and currently hang within Admiralty House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hms-illustrious-the-attack-on-taranto"&gt;HMS ‘Illustrious’: The Attack on Taranto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rowland-langmaid-1"&gt;Rowland Langmaid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS 'Illustrious': The Attack on Taranto" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4782/taranto_705x340.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Activity during the 1939 to 1945 war is widely represented in the collection but the concentration is on naval activity rather than on land campaigns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The works of the war artists were presented to the Admiralty and to the War Office in 1946 by the War Artists Advisory Committee. The works of art shown here are all on display in various conference rooms and senior offices around Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Battle of Taranto was a naval battle that occurred on the night of 11 November 1940 during World War 2. The Royal Navy launched the first all-aircraft naval battle in history, flying a small number of aircraft from a single aircraft carrier in the Mediterranean and attacking the Italian fleet at Taranto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rowland Langmaid was born in Canada on 1 December 1897. He was the eldest son of Captain J Langmaid, who was an engineer in the Royal Navy. Langmaid joined the Royal Navy in 1910 and went to sea at the beginning of the World War 1 serving at the Dardenelles in HMS ‘Agamemnon’ where he made official sketches for landings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the war Rowland Langmaid studied at the Royal Academy School and the Royal College of Art. He held exhibitions at the Royal Academy and in London, New York, and Paris. Langmaid was a highly accomplished engraver as well as a painter in oil and watercolour with a style similar to the famous marine artist W L Wyllie with whom he collaborated in Sea Fights of the Great War, 1914 to 1918. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Langmaid returned to the active list in 1939 in the rank of Lieutenant Commander and served as official Admiralty artist to the Commander-in-Chief Mediterranean Fleet from 1941 to 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="horatio-herbert-kitchener-1850-to-1916"&gt;Horatio Herbert Kitchener, 1850 to 1916.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="richard-belt"&gt;Richard Belt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Horatio Herbert Kitchener, 1850 to 1916" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4783/kitchener_429x465.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the outbreak of the World War 1 Prime Minister Herbert Asquith appointed Horatio Kitchener as Secretary of War. He became the first member of the military to hold the post and was given the task of recruiting a large army to fight Germany. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of a war poster that featured Kitchener and the words: ‘Join Your Country’s Army’, over 3 million men volunteered in the first 2 years of the war. On 5 June 1916 Horatio Kitchener was drowned when the HMS Hampshire on which he was traveling to Russia struck a mine off the Orkneys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is one of a number of sculptures adding a different dimension to the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="john-wilson-croker-secretary-to-the-admiralty-1809-to-1830"&gt;John Wilson Croker, Secretary to the Admiralty, 1809 to 1830&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="thomas-lawrence"&gt;Thomas Lawrence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="John Wilson Croker, Secretary to the Admiralty, 1809 to 1830" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4784/croker_382x469.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The post of Admiralty Secretary was extremely influential in British politics, especially during the 19th century. Croker, of Irish birth, became Chief Secretary for Ireland and after a series of political coups which assisted the government, was offered the Admiralty Secretary’s job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this capacity he presided over a number of administrative reforms. He is particularly popular with the art collection team because he was one of our greatest benefactors, bequeathing his considerable art collection to the Admiralty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Lawrence was one of England’s greatest portrait painters and his friendship with the sitter is apparent in this sensitive work. This portrait hangs in the dining room of Admiralty House, Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="launch-of-a-60-gun-ship-at-deptford-dockyard"&gt;Launch of a 60-gun ship at Deptford Dockyard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="attrib---john-cleveley-the-elder-c1712-1777"&gt;Attrib - John Cleveley the Elder (c.1712– 1777)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Launch of a 60-gun Ship at Deptford Dockyard" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4793/deptford_1107x600.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This image depicts the Royal Dockyard at Deptford in 1739, during the reign of George II. Deptford was the site of one of four royal dockyards established during the reign of the House of Tudor, the others being Portsmouth, Chatham, and Woolwich. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectively they helped create the first ships of the Royal Navy after Henry VII realised that it was no longer safe for the nation to depend on privateers and traders to protect England’s shores. Deptford yard probably grew around a storehouse hired at Greenwich, possibly at Deptford Strand, then called West Greenwich, in 1486.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collection includes many fine engravings and drawings including some first impressions. These ‘first impressions’ are of extremely fine quality since the engraved lines on the copperplate, from which the engraving was pressed, were sharp. With each subsequent pressing the lines would become gradually less distinct and the value of the finished engraving subsequently lower. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many engravings in the collection are finished by the application of watercolours. All the 18th and 19th century examples, both coloured and monochrome, are extremely sensitive to light and must be displayed in carefully controlled locations under special UV-resistant light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="loading-an-english-carrier-and-the-french-cruiser-gloire-at-algiers-1940"&gt;Loading an English Carrier and the French Cruiser ‘Gloire’ at Algiers, 1940&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="roland-vivian-pitchforth"&gt;Roland Vivian Pitchforth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Loading an English Carrier, and the French Cruiser 'Gloire' at Algiers, 1940" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4794/pitchforth_888x548.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is appropriate that the central collection of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; should contain works of art depicting both 20th century world wars. Activity during the 1939 to 1945 war is widely represented and again the concentration is on naval activity rather than on land campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The works of the war artists were presented to the Admiralty and to the War Office in 1946 by the War Artists Advisory Committee. The works of art shown here are all on display in various conference rooms and senior offices around Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roland Vivian Pitchforth was an official war artist, firstly, for the Ministry of Information, and then later for the Admiralty, under the aegis of the War Artists’ Advisory Committee. In the early months of his appointment he painted coastal boats in action and travelled on convoys to the Azores and Gibraltar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the war Pitchforth was sent out to the Far East, and witnessed the culmination of the Burma campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a temporary captain in the Royal Marines he made numerous watercolours of Colombo Harbour in Ceylon before joining the combined amphibious and airborne attack on Rangoon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his way to the Burmese capital with his commando unit Pitchforth was asked to paint camouflage on to the amphibious craft to minimise the threat of airborne attack, and this proved highly effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This watercolour is particularly interesting for its depiction of ‘dazzle’ painting, a technique designed to disguise the hulls of ships and render them less visible as targets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 18 September 1940 the ‘Gloire’ was intercepted by the British and brought to port in Casablanca where she was neutralized. The artist was commissioned to observe the activity of the Royal Navy in and around the Mediterranean from 1940 to 1944.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="merchant-ships-at-anchor-in-grand-harbour-malta-1943"&gt;Merchant Ships at Anchor in Grand Harbour, Malta, 1943&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bernard-hailstone"&gt;Bernard Hailstone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Merchant Ships at Anchor in Grand Harbour, Malta, 1943" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4795/hailstone_664x547.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The works of the war artists were presented to the Admiralty and to the War Office in 1946 by the War Artists Advisory Committee. The works of art shown here are all on display in various conference rooms and senior offices around Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernard Hailstone belonged to the group of early 20th century artists whose best known work was done during World War 2. He was known for his portraits of royalty, members of the Armed Services, musicians and personalities of stage and screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the most memorable are his portraits of Sir Winston Churchill, Peter Ustinov and Sir John Barbirolli. His portrait of Lord Olivier now hangs in the bar of the Garrick Club. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1941 the War Artists Advisory Committee commissioned Hailstone to paint civil defence subjects. He joined the Auxiliary Fire Services and witnessed at first hand the horrific destruction caused by bombing during the Blitz. He would set up his easel among the bombed London churches and smouldering buildings when there was a lull in the raids. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He supplemented these works with portraits of his colleagues in the fire services and other war workers. His work came to the notice of Kenneth Clark, who in 1941 asked him to become an official war artist to the Ministry of Transport. During this period he recorded the life of the Atlantic and Mediterranean convoys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the rest of the war Hailstone travelled around the Mediterranean and North Africa recording the activities of the mercantile navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="admiral-horatio-nelson-1st-viscount-1758-to-1805"&gt;Admiral Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount (1758 to 1805)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leonardo-guzzardi"&gt; Leonardo Guzzardi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Admiral Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount (1758 to 1805)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4796/guzzardi_800x1196.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;No introduction to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection would be complete without mention of Nelson. This portrait by the Neopolitan artist Leonardo Guzzardi hangs in the Admiralty Board Room off Whitehall. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work was originally owned by Sir William Hamilton. After his death it found its way, via a nephew, to a hotel in Milford Haven - from where it was bought by the Admiralty Board in 1847 in order to balance a portrait of William IV. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamilton said, of this work, “It is, of my friend, the most like”.  Lord Nelson’s physical appearnce has been the subject of scholarly debate for many years.  This portrait is therefore particularly significant in this connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="admiralty-messengers-badge-18245"&gt;Admiralty Messenger’s Badge 1824/5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="joseph-angell"&gt;Joseph Angell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Admiralty Messenger's Badge 1824/5" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4797/badge1_448x604.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This section includes some of the very best works of art and historic objects in the archive, all of which have little in common other than the fact that their provenance usually includes, at some stage, the desire of a previous owner that they should come into the care of the Admiralty, the War Office or, more recently, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collection encompasses a number of medals and badges. Among the best are a series of Admiralty Messengers’ badges. This example is one of a set of 4 made between 1820 and 1827. Each badge is hallmarked and carries the London assay mark. Two of the badges have a pendent greyhound made of silver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marker’s mark is identical on all 4 badges, consisting of the letters ‘JA’ in rectangular cartouche, which identifies them as the work of Joseph Angell. The Admiralty Messengers’ badges identified the bearer and acted as a form of guarantee of despatch and delivery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Admiralty ‘large’ pattern badge displays the various royal emblems of different parts of the United Kingdom: the 3 lions of England in the first and fourth quarters, the lion of Scotland in the second and the harp of Ireland in the third. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is surrounded by a garter bearing the motto “Honi soit qui mal y pense” (Evil to him who evil thinks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-view-of-cape-stephens-in-cooks-straits-new-zealand-with-waterspout-1776"&gt;A View of Cape Stephens in Cook’s Straits (New Zealand) with Waterspout, 1776&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="william-hodges"&gt;William Hodges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A View of Cape Stephens in Cook's Straits (New Zealand) with Waterspout, 1776" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4798/hodges1_700x488.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most significant paintings of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection are those commissioned by the Admiralty from the artists accompanying the voyages of exploration of Captains Cook and Flinders. The best of these are on loan to the National Maritime Museum at Greenwich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hodges’s paintings of the Pacific celebrate British exploration. He was appointed by the Admiralty to record the places discovered on Cook’s second voyage, undertaken in the ‘Resolution’ and ‘Adventure’, 1772 to 1775. Cook’s main purpose on this expedition was to locate, if possible, the much talked-of but unknown Southern Continent and further expand knowledge of the central Pacific islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hodges’ records of coastal profiles were in part important for navigational reasons. This was primarily in the form of drawings, many later converted to engravings in the official account of the voyage. He also completed oil paintings on the voyage but most, especially these larger ones, were painted in London on his return. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Resolution’ shown in a wild storm with three waterspouts, off Cape Stephens, the northernmost point of D’Urville Island, at the top of the South Island. The incident took place in May 1773, during Captain Cook’s second voyage to New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blackened sky is pierced by flashes of lightning which have struck the Maori ‘pa’, or fortified settlement, precariously balanced on the promontory to the right. Four waterspouts appear to be depicted, the principal one in the left foreground spiralling towards the sky and the others near the ‘Resolution’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cape-townshend-and-the-islands-of-shoal-water-bay"&gt;Cape Townshend and the Islands of Shoal Water Bay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="william-westall"&gt; William Westall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cape Townshend and the Islands of Shoal Water Bay" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4799/westalltownshend_529x424.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1801, at the age of 19, landscape artist William Westall found himself aboard the Investigator, the ship that Matthew Flinders was to command on his voyage of discovery to Terra Australis. He, along with a team of artists and botanists produced a splendid visual record of Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flinders’ voyage was intended to capitalise on Cook’s discoveries some years earlier. In particular, Flinders was anxious to discover if Australia was bisected by a navigable waterway which would have huge benefits for trade routes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This voyage, however, was not as successful as Cook’s. Flinders explored Shoalwater Bay in 1802, landing on Akens Island (a small island on the western side) and exploring the head of the bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his return to England he produced 9 landscapes. He worked on them for 3 years, completing the last in 1812. Westall shows scenes emphasising the strangeness of the explorers’ discoveries, as can be seen from this painting, which hangs in Admiralty House, Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westall never fulfilled his early promise of becoming mainly a book illustrator. He died in 1850 aged 68.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="captain-james-cook-1728-to-1779"&gt;Captain James Cook, 1728 to 1779&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="john-sherwin-after-nathaniel-dance-holland"&gt;John Sherwin after Nathaniel Dance-Holland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain James Cook, 1728 to 1779" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4825/cookseal_748x884.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This engraving, after the famous Dance-Holland portrait, is particularly interesting because it is decorated with Cook’s own seal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little is known of its provenance, but it appears to have been a donation in the early 20th century and has hung in a succession of Whitehall offices for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dangerous-work-at-low-tide"&gt;Dangerous Work at Low Tide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eric-ravilious"&gt;Eric Ravilious&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dangerous Work at Low Tide " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4826/ravilious_749x611.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The work of Eric Ravilious is represented by a single work in the collection- but one often considered to be among the very best of his wartime output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 1940 Ravilious visited the Kent coast where he encountered the subject of this painting. One of the few war paintings where human activity is central to the picture, it shows a mini-expedition to defuse a German magnetic mine on the oyster beds at Whitstable, only the second to be washed up on English shores. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this exploit, two naval officers, Commander Obbard and Lieutenant West, were each awarded the Distinguished Service Cross (DSC). The picture was shown at the first War Artist exhibition, under the title of ‘Rendering Mines Safe’, later officially changed to ‘Dangerous Work at Low Tide’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Ravilious was among the most foremost of English artists to emerge between the wars. His body of work was wide ranging and multi-faceted: murals, watercolours, wood engravings, painting, lithographs to ceramic design. His illustrations and designs for Wedgewood still influence a generation of designers today. Ravilious was commissioned as a war artist at the end of 1939. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assigned to the Admiralty along with John Nash, they were both appointed Captain, Royal Marines. Although he produced an extraordinary body of work he was unable to fulfil this great promise due to his tragic death while on service as an Official War Artist in 1942, aged 39.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fort-southwick-1871"&gt;Fort Southwick, 1871&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unknown-artist"&gt;Unknown Artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Fort Southwick, 1871" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4827/southwick1_1787x1273.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the collection of architectural drawings are designs for churches and barracks, as well as Robert Adam’s Admiralty screen and other Whitehall-based drawings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defences at Fort Southwick were thought to be extremely advanced in design, allowing for ease of access to fortification points as well as living quarters which could be easily supplied and cleaned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="french-boulle-bracket-clock"&gt;French Boulle bracket clock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unknown-artist-1"&gt;Unknown Artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="French Boulle bracket clock" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4828/boulle_424x529.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s horological collection is extremely important. It falls into two main parts: the maritime clocks and chronometers with many having specialised functions, and the longcase and bracket clocks. They are in many offices, residencies and meeting rooms and several have been in roughly the same place for a nearly a 100 years or longer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the specialised marine regulators, chronometers and clocks are on long term loan to the Royal Observatory at Greenwich and to various other public collections where access to the general public and to the specialised researcher is easily achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ornate clock was made in France in the later 19th century with decoration invented by Charles Andre Boulle. The preparation of a Boulle case was extremely demanding; patterns of enamel and brass were applied to curved surfaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clock is decorated in red lacquered enamel and gold markings. Surmounted by a gold ornament it has a brass dial with black hands and Roman numerals on white background, enclosed with a glass hinged bezel with a brass surround and a small square hole at the base of the front showing sun dial pendulum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some years this clock has been displayed in the office of the Chief of Defence Staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="george-iii-act-of-parliament-tavern-clock"&gt;George III (Act of Parliament) Tavern Clock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unknown-artist-2"&gt;Unknown Artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="George III (Act of Parliament) Tavern Clock" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4829/tavern_731x1099.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tavern clocks were so called because of their easily legible dials. In the late 1790s the government, anxious to increase revenue, levied a tax on the ownership of clocks. In order to alleviate the unpopularity of the tax, certain clocks were nominated for public access.  This example, the Admiralty’s clock, hung in Whitehall for public consultation and remains there today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clock has a large black circular dial with gilt hands and gilt Roman numerals/seconds. The dial is enclosed by a glass hinged bezel with wooden surround and an ebonised/ lacquered oak case with door to the front, for access to the interior. Heavily detailed decorative patterns and floral lozenges above and below a coat of arms. There are also small pocket doors to each side of the dial and is weight driven with an 8 day movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="global-power"&gt;Global Power&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="dean-fausett"&gt;Dean Fausett&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Global Power" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4830/global_800x401.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, since the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection exists to preserve its current items rather than to spend scarce cash on acquiring new ones, contemporary peacekeeping activities of the Armed Forces are not well represented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hoped that in future years the collection might expand to include more images of early 21st century operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Painted during the Cold War, Global Power is a dramatic painting which depicts a fleet of B-47 jet bombers flying high above the American continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This painting was presented to the Royal Air Force by the United States Air Force. Fausett died in December 1998 at the Mountain View Centre in Rutland, Vermont.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guards-memorial"&gt;Guards Memorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="henry-jenkins"&gt;Henry Jenkins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Guards Memorial" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4831/guardsmem_800x670.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Portland stone cenotaph was erected in 1926 on Horse Guards Parade and dedicated to the 5 Foot Guards regiments of World War 1. The bronze figures were cast from guns from the Great War. This small watercolour is one of a set of 6 within the Collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="krakatoa-an-island-in-the-china-seas-1784"&gt;Krakatoa, an Island in the China Seas, 1784&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="john-webber"&gt;John Webber&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Krakatoa, an Island in the China Seas, 1784" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4832/krakatoa_592x499.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most significant paintings of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection are those commissioned by the Admiralty from the artists accompanying the voyages of exploration of Cook and Flinders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best of these - mainly the works of the artist William Hodges, showing the discoveries of Cook’s second voyage - are on loan to the National Maritime Museum at Greenwich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the survivors of Cook’s team returned from their third voyage of exploration, Cook himself having been killed in a skirmish in Hawaii, they were famous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pictures and descriptions of strange and exotic lands, people and animals gave rise to a thriving business in the sale of engravings. This painting and others in the series were exhibited by Webber in the Royal Academy Exhibition over several years. As part of the commission the original paintings reverted to Admiralty ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view is of two huts, the large one containing stores, and an open air trestle with objects.  A century later one of the most powerful volcanic explosions in the history of the world occured at Krakatoa, a volcanic island located between Java and Sumatra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1883 there was a series of eruptions from May until 27 August 1883, when an explosion blew the island apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="la-phare-de-calais-eglise-du-courgrain-maritime"&gt;La Phare de Calais: Eglise du Courgrain-Maritime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="thomas-hennell"&gt;Thomas Hennell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="La Phare de Calais: Eglise du Courgrain-Maritime" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4833/calaishennell_625x472.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June 1944, the War Artists Advisory Committee sent many of its artists to France, to witness and record the D-Day and the Normandy invasion first hand. After painting images of the preparation for invasion in Allied bases in England, Thomas Hennell arrived in Normandy on 16 June, just as the Allied breakout from the coast began. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calais, the scene of so much bombardment, was especially badly damaged. Hennell was particularly affected by the desolation of the area surrounding the church, while the Phare - the lighthouse, on the left of the picture, remained standing in spite of substantial damage from continued shelling. Hennell said “…there is a real splendour about fresh battlefields which quickly fades.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breakout lasted well into August with vicious and desperate fighting leaving devastation across the French summer countryside. Following the Allies, sometimes only a few miles behind the front line, Hennell recorded the aftermath of the towns caught in the wake of destruction. He painted images such as the captured V-bomb launch sites, German coastal defences, Pegasus Bridge and several scenes around Nijmegen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Burma Hennell painted scenes of the liberated British soldiers and their prison camps. At the end of the war he stayed on with friends in Indonesia where he was caught up in the Indonesian uprising against the Dutch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 1945 Thomas Hennell was officially reported missing. There were reports that he was mistaken for Dutch and held hostage before being killed by hostile Indonesians in the jungle but nothing was substantiated. In death, as in life, this artist remained enigmatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="longcase-clock"&gt;Longcase Clock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="thomas-tompion"&gt;Thomas Tompion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Longcase clock" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4834/tompion_600x800.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The non-maritime horological collection includes many masterpieces including this Tompion regulator presented to Queen Anne during her appointment as Lord High Admiral in 1708. It is a longcase regulator with a 24 hour graduated chapter ring, counter balance minute hand and a silvered dial with black hands and Roman numerals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a moulded mahogany case with panelled plinth and arched trunk door, the hood with canted corners and brass ball finials and with a presentation inscription: ‘Presented to Queen Anne’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Tompion (1639 to 1716), who worked in London’s Fleet Street, was one of the greatest clock and watchmaker’s whose attention to detail was legendary. His work represents the supremacy of English horology in the 18th century. His achievements include making the first clocks for the Greenwich Observatory in 1676.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="longcase-regulator-clock"&gt;Longcase Regulator Clock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="edward-john-dent"&gt;Edward John Dent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Longcase Regulator clock" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4835/portclock1thumb_1000x750.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This technical clock is displayed in the Historic Dockyard at Portsmouth. It was made in London during the 1820s by the clockmaker E Dent. Regulators are extremely accurate clocks and designed as the standard by which other timepieces are set. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most regulators, including this example, are weight-driven and have a deadbeat anchor escapement which maintains power. This particular model is known as the ‘Portsmouth Standard’ and was originally connected by a wire to the Portsmouth post office and then to the Royal Observatory at Greenwich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="maquette-for-nelsons-column"&gt;Maquette for Nelson’s Column&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="edward-hodges-baily"&gt;Edward Hodges Baily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Maquette for Nelson's Column" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4836/maquette_393x529.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1843, public acclamation of Nelson as hero was at its height. A public subscription was set up and the sculptor Edward Hodges Baily was commissioned to produce a statue of the Admiral, to be placed in a square named after his most famous battle. The result was the production of Nelson’s Column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sculptor gave his model - also known as a maquette - to the Admiralty. It now stands on the foyer of the former Old Admiralty Building, Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="naval-gun-at-ladysmith-1900"&gt;Naval Gun at Ladysmith, 1900&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hc-seppings-wright"&gt;HC Seppings Wright&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Naval Gun at Ladysmith, 1900" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4837/ladysmith_529x354.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection includes many paintings showing battle scenes, particularly naval battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battle scenes were potentially lucrative for artists, particularly in the late 18th and 19th centuries as engravings found a ready and apparently unquenchable market. The paintings themselves were avidly commissioned and collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladysmith was subjected to a 4-month siege during the second Boer War and was relieved in February 1900 by Lord Roberts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At anchor off Capetown were two British cruisers, HMS Powerful and HMS Terrible. General Sir George White VC, the British Commander in Natal, signalled the cruisers for assistance, particularly with their long-range guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for General White, Captain P Scott RN of the Terrible was a gunnery expert and he quickly designed a carriage that could hold the 6-inch , 4.7 inch and 12 pounder naval guns in transit and into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carriages were then speedily manufactured at the Durban Railway workshops. The contingent was soon ready: 280 officers and men with two 4.7 inch guns, 4 long range 12 pounder’s and 4 maxim guns (early machine guns).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Naval Brigade, as they were now called, went by rail from Durban to Ladysmith with all their guns, ammunition, provisions and equipment. Their train was the last to complete the journey to Ladysmith on 30 October just as the bombardment started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Naval Brigade were soon in action against the Boer artillery and their long range guns were very effective in countering the enemy batteries and holding them at bay throughout the siege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="raf-venoms-over-arabia-1956"&gt;RAF Venoms over Arabia, 1956&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pamela-drew"&gt;Pamela Drew&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Venom's over Arabia, 1956" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4838/venoms_800x761.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, since the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection exists to preserve its current items rather than to spend scarce cash on acquiring new ones, contemporary peacekeeping activities of the Armed Forces are not well represented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aerial reconnaissance is shown here in Pamela Drew’s ‘RAF Venoms over Arabia’. It gives a strong sense of the geographical hostility of some of the environments in which our Armed Forces work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary role of the Venom was that of a short range, single seat fighter/bomber. With its 20mm cannons in the nose and provision for bombs or rocket projectiles the Venom could be used effectively in either the fighter or the bomber role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the 31 October 1956 Venoms were used in action during the Suez operations to attack Egyptian airfields. They saw action once again in the summer of 1957 when Nos 249 and 8 Squadrons, based at Khormaksar in Aden, were used against Omani rebels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other operators of land based fighter bomber Venoms included New Zealand, Iraq, Venezuela and Switzerland. The last Venoms in service were finally retired in 1983.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sha-tau-kok"&gt;Sha Tau Kok&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ken-howard"&gt;Ken Howard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sha Tau Kok" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4839/shatao_878x600.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This small watercolour shows routine patrols on the Chinese border early in 1977. The work currently hangs in Government House, Sandhurst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="table-centrepiece-sea-monster-and-other-creatures"&gt;Table Centrepiece; Sea Monster and other Creatures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unknown-artist-3"&gt;Unknown artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Table Centrepiece; Sea monster and other creatures" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4840/candlefish_539x394.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This extraordinary item, which takes the form of a mythical sea-creature surrounded by very detailed crustacea, was among the collection of items commissioned by Mrs Fish for the Admiralty in order to commemorate the death of Nelson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Fish’ collection included many extraordinary pieces of furniture, all distinguished by their inclusion into the design of mythical sea creatures and was in use in Admiralty House, Whitehall for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-departure-of-henry-viii-from-calais-25-july-1544"&gt;The Departure of Henry VIII from Calais, 25 July 1544&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="engraved-by-james-basire-after-a-painting-by-s-grimm"&gt;Engraved by James Basire after a painting by S Grimm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Departure of Henry VIII from Calais, 25 July 1544" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4841/henry1_607x330.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many engravings in the collection are finished by the application of watercolours; all the 18th and 19th century examples, both coloured and monochrome, are extremely sensitive to light and must be displayed in carefully-controlled locations under special UV-resistant light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This engraving was made by James Basire (1730 to 1802) from a drawing by S H Grimm, which in turn was taken from an original coeval painting. It was published according to Act of Parliament on 5 July 1781.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Anglo-French peace of 1514 plans were laid for a meeting between the English and French kings as the final act of reconciliation between the two realms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These plans were delayed with the deterioration of relations after the accession of Francis I in 1515. However, the Treaty of London in 1518 decreed that Henry VIII would confer with the new King of France at a meeting in the early summer of 1520. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This immensely lavish meeting was due to take place on the French/Calais border at the Field of Cloth of Gold, the focus of which was a series of tournaments designed to end the prolonged hostility between England and France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This engraving actually depicts Henry VIII’s embarkation at Dover with his troops, his retinue comprised over 4,500 men and Queen Catherine (of Aragon) took a similar number, including her ladies of the bed chamber. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three thousand horses were shipped over not merely for transportation purposes but also for use in the chivalrous entertainment that was to follow the historic meeting. The two kings finally met on Corpus Christi day - 2 June 1520. Trumpets sounded, the monarchs embraced, and 3 weeks of festivity, gluttony and hypocrisy began. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a few weeks later, after all the staggeringly expensive splendour had faded, Henry VIII made a secret agreement with Charles V, King of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor, not to ally with King Francis. England was once more at loggerheads with France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-gauntlet-1994"&gt;The Gauntlet, 1994&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="peter-howson"&gt;Peter Howson&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Gauntlet, 1994" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4842/gauntlet_800x487.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This chilling image shows British troops in Bosnia.  They form part of a set of 3 Howson works in the possession of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection, and currently hang in a senior Whitehall office. Peter Howson was commissioned in spring 1993 by the Imperial War Museum and Times Newspapers to go to Bosnia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made two visits to the country in June and December, travelling with the British forces participating in the United Nations Protection Force. In June he went to Travnik, Gornji Vakuf, Prozor and Vitez, but was forced to return early because of illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he returned to Bosnia in December 1993 he was accompanied by his friend Ian MacColl who made a video diary of their experiences. In addition to the places he had seen in June, he went to Zenica and observed the work of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-opening-of-sheerness-docks-5-september-1823"&gt;The Opening of Sheerness Docks, 5 September 1823&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="engraved-by-e-way-after-a-william-huggins-painting"&gt;Engraved by E Way after a William Huggins painting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Opening of Sheerness Docks, 5 September 1823" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4843/sheerness_620x415.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the second half of the eighteenth century the tradition arose that an engraver producing an image of an Admiralty subject would present one of the first finished engravings to the First Lord. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘first impressions are of extremely fine quality since the engraved lines on the copperplate, from which the engraving was pressed, were sharp. With each subsequent pressing the lines would become gradually less distinct and the value of the finished engraving subsequently lower. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheerness is a commercial port and main town of the Isle of Sheppey and owes much to its origins as a Royal Naval dockyard town. John Rennie was the 19th century engineer who surveyed and designed a new dockyard for Sheerness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work commenced in December 1813 and the Duke of Clarence who later became King William IV formally opened the completed dockyard on 5 September 1823. It served the Navy until 1960.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-reverend-james-inman-1776-to-1859"&gt;The Reverend James Inman (1776 to 1859)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unknown-artist-4"&gt;Unknown artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Reverend James Inman (1776 to 1859)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4844/inman_480x600.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection includes several 100 portraits of varying finesse and interest. All, even those of a lesser artistic technique and political sophistication are cherished and hung in locations appropriate to their subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Inman was associated with the Matthew Flinder’s expedition of 1801. Born in 1776 in Yorkshire, he was appointed to the position of astronomer on the ‘Investigator’ voyage. In 1808 the Admiralty established the Royal Naval College at Greenwich where Inman took up the post of Professor of Mathematics and Naval Architecture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later he moved to the Naval Academy at Portsmouth where he produced possibly the most famous textbook of the Royal Navy: ‘Navigation and Nautical Astronomy for the use of British Seaman’ in 1821.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accompanying tables - ‘Inman’s Nautical Tables’ - underpinned the standard system in the Royal Navy and in many other navies for many years, well into the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-right-honourable-sir-james-grigg"&gt;The Right Honourable Sir James Grigg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eric-kennington"&gt;Eric Kennington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Right Honourable Sir James Grigg" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4845/grigg_455x644.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir James Grigg was Secretary of State for war in the Coalition Administration during World War 2. A civil servant who became a minister of Cabinet rank, he also later became a city magnate. Percy James Grigg or ‘PJ’ as he was widely known among his friends, was a brilliant administrator. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This painting is set in one of the principal offices of state in the old War Office where Grigg operated at the height of his powers. This portrait is also significant not only for the fact that it is the only one in existence of a War Office civil servant, but also that it is painted by Eric Kennington - a war artist who usually painted military portraits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-war-boats-of-the-island-of-otaheite-tahiti-and-the-society-islands-with-a-view-of-part-of-the-harbour-of-ohameneno-haamanino-may-1774"&gt;The War-Boats of the island of Otaheite (Tahiti), and the Society Islands, with a view of part of the Harbour of Ohameneno (Haamanino), May 1774&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="william-hodges-1"&gt;William Hodges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The War-Boats of the island of Otaheite (Tahiti), and the Society Islands, with a View of part of the Harbour of Ohameneno (Haamanino), May 1774" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4846/hodgeswarboats_700x462.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most significant paintings of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection are those commissioned by the Admiralty from the artists accompanying the voyages of exploration of Cook and Flinders. The best of these are on loan to the National Maritime Museum at Greenwich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hodges’s paintings of the Pacific celebrate British exploration. He was appointed by the Admiralty to record the places discovered on Cook’s second voyage, undertaken in the ‘Resolution’ and ‘Adventure’, 1772 to 1775. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cook’s main purpose on this expedition was to locate, if possible, the much talked-of but unknown Southern Continent and further expand knowledge of the central Pacific islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This huge painting is Hodges’ largest from the voyage and illustrates ‘one of the most magnificent sights in the South Sea’. Hodges depicts three war canoes, part of the Tahitian fleet preparing for a punitive expedition against the neighbouring island of Moorea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hodges’ records of coastal profiles were in part important for navigational reasons. This was primarily in the form of drawings, many later converted to engravings in the official account of the voyage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also did oil paintings on the voyage but most, especially these larger ones, were painted in London on his return. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="various-types-of-birds-with-viaduct"&gt;Various types of Birds with Viaduct.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tobias-stranover"&gt;Tobias Stranover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Various types of Birds with Viaduct" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4847/birds_800x683.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This painting was part of a large restoration project undertaken on 8 extraordinary bird paintings that hang in Amport House. The work was carried out by the conservation studio of Alexandra Walker whose painstaking work uncovered the signature of Tobias Stranover on 3 of the paintings. In each case, several layers of late 19th century varnish were removed and consolidation work undertaken to the painted surface beneath. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several of the paintings were relined before being placed on new stretchers. The finished paintings are now stable and will need no further restoration for many years. They have been returned to Amport House in Andover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="view-of-murrays-islands-with-natives-offering-to-barter"&gt;View of Murray’s Islands with natives offering to barter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="william-westall-1"&gt;William Westall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="View of Murray's Islands with natives offering to barter" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4848/westallbarter_400x280.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1801, at the age of 19, landscape artist William Westall found himself aboard the Investigator, the ship that Matthew Flinders was to command on his voyage of discovery to Terra Australis.  Along with a team of artists and botanists, he produced a splendid visual record of Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flinders’ voyage was intended to capitalise on Cook’s discoveries some years earlier; in particular, Flinders was anxious to discover if Australia was bisected by a navigable waterway, which would have huge benefits for trade routes. This voyage, however, was not as successful as Cook’s and ended in shipwreck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his return to England Westall produced 9 landscapes. He worked on them for 3 years completing the last in 1812.  Westall shows scenes emphasising the strangeness of the explorers’ discoveries, as can be seen from this painting, which hangs in Admiralty House, Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westall did not fullfil his early promise becoming mainly a book illustrator. He died in 1850 aged 68 while working on a painting of the shipwreck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="whitehall-and-the-admiralty-screen-1810"&gt;Whitehall and the Admiralty Screen, 1810&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="augustus-charles-pugin"&gt;Augustus Charles Pugin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Whitehall and the Admiralty Screen, 1810" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4849/pugin_1000x567.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the collection of architectural drawings are designs for churches and barracks as well as Robert Adam’s Admiralty screen and other Whitehall-based drawings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Augustus Charles Pugin, a refugee from the French Revolution, was a gifted draughtsman who produced 2 illustrated works on Gothic architecture, which greatly influenced his son (Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin) - the driving force behind the design and ornamentation of the Palace of Westminster.  In this sketch the elder Pugin displays an architect’s view of the street and currently on loan to the office of the Adjutant General.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rue-dallent-st-omer-celebrations-and-sewer-mending"&gt;Rue d’Allent, St Omer; Celebrations and Sewer mending&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="thomas-hennell-1"&gt;Thomas Hennell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rue d'Allent, St Omer; Celebrations and Sewer mending" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4850/sewermending_418x529.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This wonderful work shows the destruction suffered after the fall of France. Hennell was much affected by the courage of the French in their efforts to rebuild their infrastructure and this watercolour is is a powerful evocation of the French spirit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently liberated townspeople, in spite of the ruined infrastructure of their city, are already flying the flags of liberation and working to rebuild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the war Hennell stayed with friends in Indonesia, where he was caught up in the Indonesian uprising against the Dutch. In November 1945 Thomas Hennell was officially reported missing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were reports that he was mistaken for Dutch and held hostage before being killed by hostile Indonesians in the jungle but nothing was substantiated. In death, as in life, this artist remained enigmatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-battle-of-jutland-from-the-air-1916"&gt;The Battle of Jutland from the Air, 1916.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="norman-howard"&gt;Norman Howard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Battle of Jutland from the Air, 1916" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4851/jutland_1000x544.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection includes many paintings showing battle scenes, particularly naval battles. Battle scenes were potentially lucrative for artists, particularly in the late 18th and 19th centuries as engravings found a ready and apparently unquenchable market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paintings themselves were avidly commissioned and collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This naval battle, which has attracted a huge amount of academic interest in recent years, established the strategic control of the North Sea by the British fleet and is believed to be one of the first aerial views of a battle. The work is accompanied by a sketch and it hangs in the Joint Services Command and Staff College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-fleet-at-sea-1688"&gt;The Fleet at Sea, 1688&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="willem-van-der-velde-the-younger"&gt;Willem van der Velde the Younger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Fleet at Sea, 1688" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4852/vandervelde_1000x375.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Little is known about the circumstances surrounding the origins of this painting. It was probably made for a private commission to show all the ships commanded by a particular captain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not appear to depict any particular naval event. The painting is signed and dated and came into the ownership of the Admiralty from the collection of Sir Phillip Stevens, Admiralty Secretary from 1763 to 1795. It hangs in the Admiralty Board Room, just off Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-gentlemen-at-arms-the-royal-bodyguard-1892"&gt;The Gentlemen at Arms (The Royal Bodyguard), 1892&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arthur-felix-temple-clay"&gt;Arthur Felix Temple Clay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Gentlemen at Arms (The Royal Bodyguard), 1892" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4853/gents_at_arms_600x739.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This huge group portrait - the figures are a little over life size - shows the gentlemen standing around the throne in St James’ Palace. Each officer appointed to this role (an honorary one) had served either in the Crimean War or in the Indian Mutiny. The artist presented the portrait to the War Office in 1902 where it hung for many years outside the office of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff. It now hangs in a military establishment in Wiltshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-german-high-sea-fleet-caged-in-scapa-flow-1919"&gt;The German High Sea Fleet, Caged in Scapa Flow, 1919&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="w-l-wyllie"&gt;W L Wyllie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The German High Sea Fleet, Caged in Scapa Flow, 1919" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4854/wyllie_1000x435.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During World War 1, Sir Arthur Balfour, the First Lord of the Admiralty, gave permission for Wyllie to cruise in Royal Navy ships. In the North Sea, Harwich, Rosyth, Cromarty, and Scapa Flow, he made hundreds of studies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyllie witnessed the German fleet surrender in the Forth and went with the last convoy of battleships to Scapa Flow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as this large oil painting, a number of etchings and drypoints resulted from all these cruises. Although not an official war artist during World War I, Wyllie had access to many naval bases and contributed to two books. They were the ‘Sea Fights of the Great War: Naval incidents during the first nine months’, 1918 and 1919. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the mid-1870s Wyllie travelled the length and breadth of the Thames and Medway on a barge, converted into a floating studio, filling sketch books and painting evocative scenes of the naval and merchant shipping. He was elected ARA in 1889, following an exhibition of watercolours at the Fine Art Society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyllie’s output was prolific, covering all kinds of maritime subjects but with a great interest in the Royal Navy and historic occasions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, Trafalgar caught his imagination and shortly before his death he began work on a huge panoramic painting of the Battle of Trafalgar. The painting took 13 months to paint and was unveiled by King George V in 1930 in what is now the Royal Naval Museum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyllie painted almost to the day he died and is buried in Portchester Castle overlooking the Solent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-grand-fleet-1916"&gt;The Grand Fleet, 1916&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="muirhead-bone-1"&gt;Muirhead Bone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Grand Fleet, 1916" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4855/bone1_800x402.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Muirhead Bone was a master etcher, draughtsman and war artist who was born in Glasgow. He became the first official war artist in 1916 when he was attached to the intelligence branch of the War Office and sent to France.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working at considerable speed his sketches covered a wide range of subjects, mostly behind the lines, including the work of the medical services, the repair and maintenance of big guns and off duty war weary soldiers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He worked in various media - chalk, charcoal, pencil and pen - sometimes adding touches of watercolour later. Subsequently, Bone illustrated a 2 volume set of books entitled ‘The Western Front’ which was published in 1917. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muirhead Bone also served as an official war artist in the World War 2, by which time he was Sir Muirhead, having been knighted by George VI in 1937. Bone was attached to the Admiralty and was not only the first but also the most senior of its artists. His work was to become the most widely reproduced official war art of the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This panoramic view of the Firth of Forth shows no human figures as Bone was more concerned with the positioning of the ships.The fleet rests quietly, preparing as best it can for the unknown.  The fleet was based in Scapa Flow, a land-locked area of water in the middle of the Orkney Islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The channel between Scapa and the Scottish mainland is the Pentland Firth. While waiting for the German high seas fleet to ‘come out’, divisions of battleships would go to sea in turn to do ‘battle-practice firings’ at a target towed – at a very respectful distance – by a tug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="trafalgar"&gt;Trafalgar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="john-christian-schetky"&gt;John Christian Schetky&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Trafalgar" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4856/schetky_810x519.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Battle of Trafalgar in 1805 was the deciding event in the Napoleonic naval wars and probably the most depicted battle in British history. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection includes 3 significant versions and this one is probably the best. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The painting is accompanied by the artists’ sketch, which suggests that he was present at the battle itself, although we have been unable to confirm this. The work was commissioned by a contemporary naval captain and bequeathed to the Admiralty in 1926.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ustazi-1994"&gt;Ustazi, 1994&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="peter-howson-1"&gt;Peter Howson&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Ustazi, 1994" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4857/ustazi_762x589.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This chilling image shows British troops in Bosnia. They form part of a set of three Peter Howson works in the possession of the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; art collection and currently hang in a senior Whitehall office. Howson was commissioned in spring 1993 by the Imperial War Museum and Times Newspapers to go to Bosnia. He made two visits to the country in June and December, travelling with the British forces participating in the United Nations Protection Force. In June he went to Travnik, Gornji Vakuf, Prozor and Vitez but was forced to return early because of illness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he returned to Bosnia in December 1993 he was accompanied by his friend Ian MacColl who made a video diary of their experiences. In addition to the places he had seen in June, he went to Zenica and observed the work of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="view-of-north-bastion-tower-of-london-1941"&gt;View of North Bastion, Tower of London, 1941.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="william-hampton"&gt;William Hampton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="View of North Bastion, Tower of London, 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4858/tower_650x873.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the better known World War 2 artists were a small London-based group commissioned to record the effect of bomb damage on well-known buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These artists, employed by the Ministry of Works, were given special access to damaged government buildings - but they were hampered by a lack of canvas on which to paint. William Hampton solved the problem by producing paintings such as this one on utility hardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the wartime period a small team of artist-restorers, working for the Artists’ Section of the Ministry of Works, were responsible for the care and maintenance of public works of art. This team built on a long tradition of employing artists in a dual role as painting conservators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the outset of the London Blitz, some of these artists were asked to record damage to significant buildings such as the Tower of London and HM Custom House. The official war artists commissioned by the War Artists Advisory Committee were all, at this point, deployed out of London, and among the few people available and capable of undertaking the task were Alistair Stewart and William Hampton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information about the Ministry of Defence Art Collection please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="angela-lock-business-manager"&gt;Angela Lock (Business Manager)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tel: 020 7218 7394&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="simon-campbell-bird-collection-manager"&gt;Simon Campbell Bird (Collection Manager)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tel: 020 7218 4106&lt;br&gt;
email: &lt;a href="mailto:simon.bird780@mod.uk"&gt;simon.bird780@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.edisposals.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/WFS/Disposals-Aom-Site/-/-/-/Default-Start"&gt;Ministry of Defence Art Collection shop - book/DVD/prints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Ministry of Defence Art Collection
&lt;br&gt;Level 1, Zone A, Desk 43
&lt;br&gt;Main Building
&lt;br&gt;Horseguards Avenue
&lt;br&gt;Whitehall
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1A 2HB
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.edisposals.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/WFS/Disposals-Aom-Site/-/-/-/Default-Start"&gt;Ministry of Defence Art Collection shop - book/DVD/prints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thepcf.org.uk"&gt;the Public Catalogue Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/arts/yourpaintings"&gt;BBC - Your Paintings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.openhouse.org.uk"&gt;Open House 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iwm.org.uk"&gt;Imperial War Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmm.ac.uk"&gt;National Maritime Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gac.culture.gov.uk"&gt;Government Art Collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavalmuseum.org"&gt;Royal Naval Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.national-army-museum.ac.uk"&gt;National Army Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalmarinesmuseum.co.uk"&gt;Royal Marine Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57532</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:49:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:49:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-joy-for-old-soldier-who-finally-got-his-medal"/>
    <title>Christmas joy for old soldier who finally got his medal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Army veteran Joe McKenna, 72, who volunteers at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/" title="Duke of Lancaster's Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum"&gt;Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Preston, left the military in 1970 just months before his Northern Ireland service medal was minted and eventually decided to track down his medal after years of attending parades where he was the only veteran not wearing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Bob Dixon, from 2 Medical Regiment and a fellow volunteer at the museum, offered to help Joe claim his honour. Sergeant Major Dixon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had been helping some visitors at the museum with enquiries about their service medals and so I offered to help Joe too. I got all the paperwork together, went around to his house, and we filled in the documents before sending them off to the MOD Medal Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We got a reply within 2 months, the quickest I’ve ever known; I think the turnaround was so fast because he still lives at the same address that appeared on his service papers back in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe enlisted in the Loyal Regiment, a forebear to the North West’s current infantry regiment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/3477.aspx" title="The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;The Duke of Lancaster’s&lt;/a&gt;, almost exactly 51 years ago and served in Kenya, Swaziland, Cyprus and Malta as well as in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern Ireland service medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5711/Joe_smedal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Joe McKenna's Northern Ireland service medal [Picture: Sergeant Mark Garry, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After he left the Army as a Lance Corporal in 1970, Joe worked for more than 30 years as an &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; driver, married Josie, with whom he had his children Sandra and Peter, and is now a grandfather of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said until recently the distractions of day-to-day life meant he just never got around to claiming what was his: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was only when I was marching at the Armed Forces Day parade in Preston last summer when I thought ‘I’m getting on a bit now and I should really get my medal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think my son would like to have it when I’m gone; he and my daughter think that it is marvellous that it’s finally here. It’s the best Christmas present ever and it makes me very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe’s wife Josie added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It really was something special to see his face when he received the medal; it was as if all his Christmases had come at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe now plans to wear his medal at his regiment’s Kimberley Day service and parade in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/57555</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:23:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:23:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-sutherland-returns-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Sutherland returns in time for Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship was greeted by cheering and waving families and friends wearing festive hats and holding banners with loving messages at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;HM Naval Base Devonport&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth on Saturday 15 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship’s Culdrose-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopter flight arrived back separately at the Helston air station on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Sutherland" title="HMS Sutherland"&gt;HMS Sutherland&lt;/a&gt; has been busy conducting anti-piracy and terrorism patrols as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/Combined-Maritime-Forces" title="Combined Maritime Forces"&gt;Combined Maritime Forces&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring the sea lanes and waters east of Suez and off the Horn of Africa are safe for seafarers to conduct their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship conducted boarding operations on suspect vessels and also reassurance visits to build relationships with mariners and obtain information on pattern of life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="AS(ME) Dale Plumpton kissing Terri Layden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5729/Sutherland5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Able Seaman (Marine Engineering) Dale Plumpton receives a welcome home kiss from Terri Layden [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crew also exercised with coalition and allied forces in the region to strengthen ties and improve methods of working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland’s Commanding Officer, Commander Al Wilson, said it was a ‘magic’ time to come home at Christmas. He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The huge variety and diversity of task that Sutherland has fulfilled whilst on operations illustrates the inherent flexibility of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; in protecting and promoting UK interests worldwide, whether it is preventing piracy or terrorism at sea or strengthening bonds with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, I could not have achieved this without an efficient, capable and highly motivated ship’s company and, as always, I am highly proud of what my team has achieved over the last 6 months whilst remaining cheerful and utterly professional throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My team and myself are now looking forward to spending Christmas at home with our loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Navy personnel on board HMS Sutherland" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5730/Sutherland4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Petty Officer on board HMS Sutherland waves to the waiting families on the dockside as the ship comes into port [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Able Rate (Communication Information Specialist) Peter Hodgkin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland is my first ship and I joined her 3 months prior to deploying on operations. With this being my first deployment and first time away from the UK I was nervous, but excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There have been some tough times, but overall I have really enjoyed it, especially the team spirit of the ship and all the good work that we have achieved on operations. My most memorable moment was helping out at an orphanage in Tanzania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having handed over duties to sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;HMS Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; at the end of November, the crew of HMS Sutherland is now looking forward to spending Christmas at home and time with families and friends before a busy 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/59972</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:10:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:10:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/depleted-uranium"/>
    <title>Depleted uranium</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="uk-depleted-uranium-policy-and-development"&gt;UK depleted uranium policy and development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK policy is that depleted uranium (&lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt;) can be used in weapons because it would be wrong to deny our Armed Forces a legitimate and effective capability that can help them achieve their objectives as quickly and safely as possible. Claims of serious health and environmental effects by a very small number of people attract media attention but are disputed by most scientists and international agencies. Whether other countries use &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions or not is a matter for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; is a heavy metal 70% more dense than lead and with the ability to self-sharpen on impact with armour. This makes it ideal for use in armour-piercing ammunition and reduces the combat risk to UK tank crews as it allows them to engage an enemy from greater distances. It was always recognised that the risks and benefits from using &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions needed to take account of the fact that &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; is toxic in high doses and weakly radioactive. Risk assessments show very little or no chemical or radiation risk to most troops and civilians and instructions are provided to reduce the already low risk as far as is reasonably practicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest assessments of the risks of using &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions was by the US in 1974. The UK benefited from this work when they began their own &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions development in 1979. Since then the US have completed a major piece of research (known as Capstone) and many other independent organisations have published their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reports by the Royal Society, European Commission, United Nations Environment Programme, International Atomic Energy Agency and World Health Organisation are on the world wide web. Although some of these were produced some time ago, more recent work shows their conclusions are still valid. &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and European Commission summaries were published in 2009 and 2010 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK development was at Eskmeals in Cumbria and Kirkcudbright in Dumfries and Galloway. Safety arrangements were discussed with health and safety and environmental protection regulators before test firing began. Personal and environmental monitoring confirms that the original development work and subsequent small-scale firings to ensure the continuing safety and serviceability of the ammunition do not present a hazard to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the highly publicised European Parliament or &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; resolutions calling for more research or a ban on &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions affect the information provided above. The UK opposes such resolutions because &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; has not been shown to have, and indeed is very unlikely to have, any significant impact on the local population or veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions is not prohibited under current or likely future international agreements and international concern is not as great as some suggest. Only 15 countries contributed to a &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; report published in 2008 and only 4 suggested the possibility of widespread or extreme health risks. Canada and the Netherlands opposed a &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions ban. A review carried out in accordance with Article 36 of the First Protocol of 1977 Additional to the Geneva Conventions of 1949 (Additional Protocol I) concluded that the UK’s only &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munition (CHARM 3) is capable of being used lawfully in international armed conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allegations about ‘increasing evidence’ of extreme health risks are untrue. There has been nothing to affect the most recent (2008) International Commission on Radiological Protection conclusion that, although the body of information on the health effects of radiation has expanded since 1990, there are few significant changes to our understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misunderstandings or misinterpretations of the significance of various resolutions, legal processes and research have been used to suggest that the UK government position is flawed. The Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;)’s response to the outcome of a recent Coroner’s Inquest into a death alleged to have been caused by &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; exposure is in the National Archive. This explains that the weight of independent scientific opinion supports the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; position rather than the Jury’s verdict and why, having examined the Coroner’s recommendations, inquest transcript and scientific evidence, &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; does not accept the recommendations arising from the Inquest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggestions that doses from the ‘photoelectric effect’ are important and being ignored are shown to be in error by recent peer-reviewed work which shows that ‘photoelectric effect’ doses are broadly comparable with natural background radiation levels and hence of no practical significance in the calculation of radiation risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1979/mar/08/depleted-uranium-ammunition"&gt;Written Answers, Woodall/Mulley, Depleted Uranium Ammunition, Hansard Official Record, Column 777, 8 March 1979, Her Majesty’s Stationery Office, London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://iopscience.iop.org/0952-4746/22/2/301/pdf/0952-4746_22_2_301.pdf"&gt;The Royal Society, The health effects of depleted uranium munitions - Summary, Document 6/02, ISBN 0 85403 5753, March 2002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/environmental_risks/docs/scher_o_123.pdf"&gt;Scientific Committee on Health and Environmental Risks (SCHER), Opinion on the Environmental and health risks posed by depleted uranium 18th May 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bandepleteduranium.org/en/docs/52.pdf"&gt;Effects of the use of armaments and ammunitions containing depleted uranium, Report of the Secretary General, A/63/170, United Nations General Assembly (2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="du-munitions-health-monitoring"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions health monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no reliable scientific or medical evidence to suggest that &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; has been responsible for ill-health in UK Forces’ personnel or civilians. However the government will carefully consider any emerging data. Epidemiological studies suggesting &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt;-induced cancers and birth defects have flaws and the people proven to have the highest &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; exposures, ie those in or on vehicles when they were hit by &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions, do not have any &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt;-related health effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ongoing studies of the health of a group of US veterans known to have been exposed to &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; during the 1991 Gulf conflict. The most recent report of this work was published in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans with embedded &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; fragments excrete elevated concentrations of uranium but no significant evidence of clinically important changes are observed in kidney or bone. These are the two principal target organs for any form of uranium. Continued surveillance is recommended due to ongoing mobilization of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; from the embedded &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-information-1"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.va.gov/RAC-GWVI/docs/Committee_Documents/GWIandHealthofGWVeterans_RAC-GWVIReport_2008.pdf"&gt;Research Advisory Committee on Gulf War Veterans’ Illnesses, Gulf War Illness and the Health of Gulf War Veterans: Scientific Findings and Recommendations, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington DC (2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.experts.scival.com/jhu/pubDetail.asp?t=pm&amp;amp;id=21432717&amp;amp;n=Melissa+Mcdiarmid&amp;amp;u_id=2754"&gt;McDiarmid MA, Engelhardt SM, Dorsey CD et al, Longitudinal Health Surveillance in a Cohort of Gulf War Veterans 18 Years After First Exposure to Depleted Uranium, Journal of Toxicology and Environmental Health-Part A-Current Issues, Volume 74, Issue 10, Pages 678-691, 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="du-munitions-environmental-monitoring"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions environmental monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK surveys in areas where &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions were used have not shown &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; at levels likely to have any detectable health impact. There are only some very limited and localised areas, such as in armoured vehicles hit by &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions, where precautions to prevent &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; inhalation would be sensible if long-term exposures were likely. Similar results have been found by independent international bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; carries out terrestrial and marine environmental monitoring surveys on and around the firing ranges where &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions were developed. Air sampling is also carried out when firing is in progress. The survey methods are agreed with environmental regulators. A summary of the terrestrial and marine results was published in 2002. Subsequent results are in complete agreement with the early findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; surveys in Kosovo, Bosnia and southern Iraq. The results and conclusions are consistent with work by the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Environment Programme in the Balkans and by the International Atomic Energy Agency in Kuwait. Information has been provided to assist the civilian administration and international relief agencies in carrying out any monitoring they might wish to undertake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-information-2"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56269"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37031/eemp_rec_report.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56269-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37031/thumbnail_eemp_rec_report.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37031/eemp_rec_report.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56269-accessibility-help"&gt;Report of a Reconnaissance Visit to Develop an Enhanced Environmental Monitoring Programme in the British-led Sector in Kosovo PDF &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;1.31 MB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56269-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Report%20of%20a%20Reconnaissance%20Visit%20to%20Develop%20an%20Enhanced%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20Programme%20in%20the%20British-led%20Sector%20in%20Kosovo%20PDF%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Report%20of%20a%20Reconnaissance%20Visit%20to%20Develop%20an%20Enhanced%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20Programme%20in%20the%20British-led%20Sector%20in%20Kosovo%20PDF%20%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Report of a Reconnaissance Visit to Develop an Enhanced Environmental Monitoring Programme in the British-led Sector in Kosovo PDF ").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.colloquium.fr/06IRPA/CDROM/docs/P-210.pdf"&gt;Smith D and Brown R, Radiological Assessment of Depleted Uranium Impact Locations in Iraq, Session TA6 - Radiation Protection of the Public and the Environment, Second European International Radiation Protection Association Congress, Paris (2006)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56270"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37032/uk_bosnia_survey.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56270-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37032/thumbnail_uk_bosnia_survey.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37032/uk_bosnia_survey.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56270-accessibility-help"&gt;UK &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Environmental Monitoring in Bosnia August 2002 Survey Report - August 2002 survey report PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;1.55 MB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56270-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20UK%20MOD%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20in%20Bosnia%20August%202002%20Survey%20Report%20-%20August%202002%20survey%20report%20PDF%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27UK%20MOD%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20in%20Bosnia%20August%202002%20Survey%20Report%20-%20August%202002%20survey%20report%20PDF%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("UK &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; Environmental Monitoring in Bosnia August 2002 Survey Report - August 2002 survey report PDF").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_56271"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37033/ke_env_mon.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56271-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37033/thumbnail_ke_env_mon.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/37033/ke_env_mon.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-56271-accessibility-help"&gt;Comparison of Kirkcudbright and Eskmeals Environmental Monitoring Data with Generalised Derived Limits for Uranium PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;516 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;39 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-56271-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Comparison%20of%20Kirkcudbright%20and%20Eskmeals%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20Data%20with%20Generalised%20Derived%20Limits%20for%20Uranium%20PDF%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Comparison%20of%20Kirkcudbright%20and%20Eskmeals%20Environmental%20Monitoring%20Data%20with%20Generalised%20Derived%20Limits%20for%20Uranium%20PDF%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;DMC-MODFeedback@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Comparison of Kirkcudbright and Eskmeals Environmental Monitoring Data with Generalised Derived Limits for Uranium PDF").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://web.peacelink.it/tematiche/disarmo/u238/documenti/consdukos2.pdf"&gt;Smith DM, Environmental Surveillance in Kosovo, DRPS Report 240/2001, UK Ministry of Defence, DERA Radiation Protection Services, 28 July 2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hpa.org.uk/webc/HPAwebFile/HPAweb_C/1194947370003"&gt;National Radiological Protection Board, Generalised Derived Limits for Radioisotopes of Polonium, Lead, Radium and Uranium, Documents of the NRPB, Volume 11 Number 2, 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="du-munitions-personal-monitoring"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions personal monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the thousands of troops monitored worldwide, very few have had any detectable &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; exposure and the vast majority of these were in or on vehicles when they were attacked with &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt;. Monitoring is also available for personnel concerned about possible &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; exposures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; has been detected in the vast majority (more than 99.5%) of the almost 1000 UK veterans tested by collection and analysis of urine samples. &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; was only detected in a very small number of veterans who were in or on vehicles when they were attacked with &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions and this &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; is at levels at which no adverse health effects are expected. Similar results have been obtained by other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK monitoring is based on independent advice from the &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; Oversight Board (&lt;abbr title="DU Oversight Board"&gt;DUOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) who state that their testing is sufficiently sensitive to detect a &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; exposure that would have ‘material implications for health’. The &lt;abbr title="DU Oversight Board"&gt;DUOB&lt;/abbr&gt; comprised expert members from a variety of medical and scientific institutions and lay members. Veterans and &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; were represented and nominated their own scientific advisors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report of the work can be accessed below. Some key points of test result interpretation and risk modelling were disputed by a small minority of &lt;abbr title="DU Oversight Board"&gt;DUOB&lt;/abbr&gt; members who produced a minority statement within the main report. &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; accept the majority view that this statement is ‘seriously flawed scientifically’. The care needed to obtain meaningful analysis results was shown by &lt;abbr title="DU Oversight Board"&gt;DUOB&lt;/abbr&gt; work and is the subject of a peer-reviewed scientific article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-information-3"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/tna/+/http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/HealthandSafetyPublications/Uranium/FinalReportOfTheDepletedUraniumOversightBoard.htm"&gt;Final report of the &lt;abbr title="DU Oversight Board"&gt;DUOB&lt;/abbr&gt; submitted to the Under-Secretary of State for Defence - February 2007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10524504"&gt;Hooper FJ, Squibb KS, Siegel EL, McPhaul K and Keogh JP, Elevated Urine Uranium Excretion by Soldiers with Retained Uranium Shrapnel, Health Physics, Volume 77, Number 5, 512-519, November 1999&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10647980"&gt;Ejnik JW, Carmichael AJ, Hamilton M, McDiarmid M, Squibb K, Boyd P, and Tartiff W, Determination of the isotopic composition of uranium in urine by Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometry, Health Physics, Volume 78, Number 2, 143-146, February 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11219540"&gt;McDiarmid MA, Engelhardt SM, Oliver M, Urinary uranium concentrations in an enlarged Gulf War veteran cohort, Health Physics, Volume 80, 270 - 273, 2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11908516"&gt;Ough EA et al, An Examination of Uranium Levels in Canadian Forces Personnel who served in the Gulf War and Kosovo, Health Physics, 527-532, Volume 82, Number 4, April 2002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/du/docu/ge010229a.pdf"&gt;Roth P, Werner E and Paretzke HG, Research Into urinary Excretion of Uranium, Verification of Protective Measures in the German KFOR Army Contingent, GSF - Forschungszentrum fur Umwelt und Gesundheit, Institut fur Strahlenschutz, Neuherberg, GSF Report 3/01 January 2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpd.oxfordjournals.org/content/105/1-4/157.abstract"&gt;Roth P, Hollriegl V, Werner E and Schramel P, Assessment of Exposure to Depleted Uranium, Radiation Protection Dosimetry, Vol 105, No 1-4, 157-161, 2003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-depleted-uranium-use"&gt;UK depleted uranium use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; round impacts on a hard surface, some dust is released. This can be a health hazard in some circumstances. However, all the research to date indicates that these circumstances are extremely unlikely to occur, and, if they do, will only affect very small groups who will be at much greater risk from the other hazards associated with armed conflict. Recent work - including the monitoring of veterans and battlefields - confirms this. The UK used very limited quantities (less than 2.9 tonnes) of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; in two armed conflicts in 1991 and 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only use of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions in peacetime is in test firings. In conflict, 120 mm anti-tank &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions (known as CHARM) and 20 mm &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; rounds used in the Royal Navy’s PHALANX Close-In Weapon System (a system for defending against missile attacks) were fired in the Gulf in 1991 and 2003. The total weight of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; in the munitions was less than 2.9 tonnes. Use of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; in PHALANX ended in 2005, leaving the anti-tank round as the UK’s only &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clean-up after a conflict is a matter for a country’s civilian administration but UK Forces provide information through signs and leaflets of the explosive or other risks associated with touching any battlefield debris. They also assist with ordnance disposal which includes removal of surface-lying &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has, and will continue to, provide help and advice to assist the civilan administration and relief agencies in carrying out any monitoring they want to undertake. &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided information on its use of &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; munitions and on its monitoring in Iraq in 2003. &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; officials participated at a UNEP seminar at which &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; matters, including environmental monitoring and sampling techniques, were discussed with Iraqi scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; provided Iraqi scientists with protective equipment to carry out &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; contamination surveys and with information on the composition of the &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; used in UK munitions. Both the World Health Organisation and International Atomic Energy Agency state that &lt;abbr title="depleted uranium"&gt;DU&lt;/abbr&gt; risks can be controlled with simple countermeasures conducted by national authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
