<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-defence.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Ministry of Defence</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/65367</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-lynx-aids-capture-of-suspected-pirates"/>
    <title>Royal Navy Lynx aids capture of suspected pirates</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A Lynx helicopter and a crew from the Royal Navy have helped arrest 12 armed suspected pirates off the coast of Somalia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flight 217 of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; is currently deployed on board the French frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/News-and-Events/Latest-News/2013/January/03/121220-Blog-Surcouf" title="Read the blog from 815 Lynx Squadron on board the French frigate Surcouf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf&lt;/a&gt; as part of Operation Atalanta, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s counter-piracy mission off the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lynx was sent ahead by the French warship to find the suspected pirates after the &lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Halyburton, operating as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.manw.nato.int/page_operation_ocean_shield.aspx" title="Operation Ocean Shield web page"&gt;Operation Ocean Shield&lt;/a&gt;, received a distress call from a merchant vessel reporting she was under attack from 6 men armed with rocket-propelled grenades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6008/20130110surcouf3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel as Flight 217's Lynx helicopter hovers above [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;abbr title="Merchant Ship Characteristic"&gt;MSC&lt;/abbr&gt; Jasmine, sailing 260 miles off the Somali coast, managed to repel the attack themselves, a German &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; maritime patrol aircraft was scrambled to track the suspect vessel, which was by then towing another boat with several more men on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy Lynx sped to the scene and ordered the vessels to stop while French commandos from Surcouf arrived alongside in a fast boat and quickly boarded, resulting in the suspected pirates swiftly surrendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon searching the pirates’ boats, the commandos also discovered containers of diesel and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 12 suspects are now being held on board &lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf for evidence collection in order to fully assess the possibility of prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="French frigate Sucouf seen from Lynx helicopter cockpit" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6009/20130110surcouf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of the French frigate Sucouf from the Lynx helicopter cockpit of Flight 217 from 815 Naval Air Squadron [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commander of Flight 217, Lieutenant Mike Curd, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The whole operation was an excellent exercise in teamwork, with the US ship and Surcouf co-ordinating their efforts, including both units’ helicopters, to successfully track the 2 suspect vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our Lynx actually performed the ‘stop’ and support to boarding of both the suspect vessels and provided airborne support to the subsequent boarding operations. It was a long and tiring day that began before dawn, but by the end of it we were proud of a job well done; the procedures and routines we’d practised so many times worked extremely efficiently and by nightfall we knew we had played a large part in the successful apprehension of a dozen suspected pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of the Royal Navy’s Lynx on board the Surcouf is the first of its kind as part of the terms of the Lancaster House Treaty. Under this the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; and France agreed military co-operation to assure their international commitments and strengthen their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/65345</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-health-partnership-awards-launched"/>
    <title>2013 Health Partnership Awards launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nominations are now open for this year's Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards which were launched today in Cardiff and Edinburgh.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ceremony honours the people, projects and initiatives that provide serving military personnel, including reservists, and their families and veterans with the very best in healthcare and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awards are open to civilian health staff and military medics working within the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-medical-services" title="Defence Medical Services website"&gt;Defence Medical Services&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/" title="NHS website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and private or voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 awards ceremony, to be held on 21 May, is being hosted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/" title="Welsh Government website"&gt;Welsh Government&lt;/a&gt; and, from today, people can nominate individuals or teams who provide care and support to Service personnel. Nominations close on 21 February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two launch ceremonies took place today - one at the Army’s Dreghorn Barracks in Edinburgh and one at the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/11018.aspx" title="203 Field Hospital web page"&gt;203 (Welsh) Field Hospital&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards provide a great opportunity to pay tribute to the dedication and fantastic results that our military and civilian colleagues achieve by working together to improve military health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to encourage people to visit the website to nominate all those who have provided the very best health and social care to our Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the awards in Cardiff, Welsh Health Minister Lesley Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud Wales is hosting the 2013 awards. The awards celebrate the hard work, commitment and dedication shown by health professionals from across the public, private and voluntary sectors in caring for the men and women of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important we recognise the immense contribution the Armed Forces and veterans have made to our country. We owe them a huge debt of gratitude and a duty of care, particularly those who have developed health problems as a result of their military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Tri-Service healthcare specialists" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6006/hqscot-2013-001-4476.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The awards honour the people who provide military personnel with the best health and social care [Picture: Mark Owens, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also vital we acknowledge the role of those who care for and support Service personnel and veterans, especially in recent years when the Armed Forces have been heavily engaged overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would encourage people to consider nominating either themselves or others for these awards as it is important we recognise their contribution to improving the lives of Service personnel and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Health Minister Dr Dan Poulter said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These awards will shine a light on the efforts of the military, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Service charities to make sure members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans have the best care possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such important work should not go unnoticed. I urge people to put themselves or their colleagues forward to have their efforts and achievements in caring for our Armed Forces, their families and veterans recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;203 Field Hospital was founded in 1914 and consists of reservist volunteers made up of civilian, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and military medics. The unit has already begun preparations for its upcoming deployment to Afghanistan in support of the Regular Army on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event included a demonstration of the treatment of a casualty from ambulance to resuscitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Lesley Griffiths was accompanied by Surgeon Rear Admiral Calum McArthur, Brigadier Philip Napier, Commander of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/28224.aspx" title="160 (Wales) Brigade web page"&gt;160 (Wales) Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, and Colonel Tina Donnelly, Commanding Officer of 203 Field Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the awards, including how to apply or nominate, are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org/" title="Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards website"&gt;www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/65312</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sailors-help-african-community"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sailors help African community</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During a break from anti-piracy and maritime security operations off the east coast of Africa, sailors from HMS Northumberland helped villagers to renovate their community centre.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;25 volunteers from the Plymouth-based frigate’s company headed to the village of Kigamboni while their ship was berthed in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. The sailors helped to install windows and doors in the community centre building, repaired fencing, and built ‘hugle beds’, which will be used to grow vegetables in dry conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Physical Trainer Andrew Davidson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All my shipmates were moved by the day at the &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt;. We felt a great sense of achievement knowing that we’d helped in every way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6001/N-land_sailor_2013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship’s captain Commander Paddy Dowsett said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our visit to Dar es Salaam has been a real success.  Not only has it reaffirmed and strengthened the commitment the United Kingdom has to Tanzania, it has also allowed my team to give something to the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community centre was set up in 2006 to offer shelter and education to children, but also runs a mobile library and promotes adult learning initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sign of their appreciation the community centre members performed an impressive musical and acrobatic dance – demonstrating just some of the skills they’re taught at Kigamboni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The centre’s founder, Festo Chengula, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The place looks great after all the hard work. The &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt; members love having guests and you are all welcome to visit again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A young boy squeezes a sailor's face" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6002/N-land_Tanzania_child_2013.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A young boy squeezes a sailor's face in a gesture of affection  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an exchange of gifts &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; donated 85 football shirts, courtesy of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavyfa.com/" title="Royal Navy Football Association website"&gt;Royal Navy Football Association&lt;/a&gt;, together with a rugby ball, football and Northumberland crest and commemorative coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship is still in the early stages of a patrol of the Indian Ocean and due home in Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/65317</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:17:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sails-into-london-boat-show"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sails into London Boat Show</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Royal Navy looks set to be a major draw at the London Boat Show, which opens at the ExCel exhibition centre this weekend.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an island nation, the UK’s prosperity and security is dependent on its ability to access the sea. That is why the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk" title="Royal Navy website"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; is globally deployed and has a range of versatile ships, submarines and aircraft operated by professional sailors, aviators and Royal Marine Commandos. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy will be at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonboatshow.com/2013/home.aspx" title="London Boat Show website"&gt;London Boat Show&lt;/a&gt; from 12 to 20 January, where visitors can learn more about naval life and how, every minute of every day, somewhere in the world they are protecting the nation’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cougar beach landing rehearsal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5921/offshoreraidingcraft.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from 45 Commando Royal Marines and marines from HMS Bulwark carry out a beach assault in Plymouth. [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as celebrating the Navy’s rich heritage, show visitors can learn how they operate across a variety of missions from anti-terrorism, counter-narcotics, disaster relief and peacekeeping operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy stand will include an opportunity to get up close to an advanced Offshore Raiding Craft (&lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt;). Measuring 9 metres long and able to travel in excess of 35 knots, the craft were part of the Navy’s commitment to keeping the public safe during the Olympic Games. The &lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt; can also be equipped with general purpose machine guns, making them a highly-flexible and potent deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Boat Show, a Navy search and rescue Mark 5 Sea King will take to the skies beside ExCeL at 1400hrs on Saturday, 12 January, to illustrate what a rescue operation entails. The renowned Mark 5 is now the Navy’s workhorse of choice, operating in extreme conditions and ready to respond at a moment’s notice in an emergency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A four-man crew from 771 Naval Air Squadron in Cornwall will manoeuvre the helicopter with precision to make a simulated rescue from the dock. The helicopter will return on Sunday, 13 January, for a further demonstration at 1130hrs before heading back to its Cornish base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the show, the search and rescue crew will be at the C180 stand to meet the public and answer questions about the service, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/About-the-Royal-Navy/The-Navy-and-the-Environment/In-the-Air" title="Fleet Air Arm web page"&gt;Fleet Air Arm&lt;/a&gt; and the wider Royal Navy. There will also be the opportunity to attend a free daily presentation exploring the role of search and rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The London Boat Show takes place at Excel Arena from 12 to 20 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/65313</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:25:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-armed-forces-covenant"/>
    <title>The armed forces covenant</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>The armed forces covenant and the armed forces covenant: today and tomorrow.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The armed forces covenant and the armed forces covenant: today and tomorrow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:FatalityNoticePresenter/65197</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T22:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T22:04:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/fatalities/sapper-richard-reginald-walker-killed-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Sapper Richard Reginald Walker killed in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>Fatality notice</category>
    <summary>It is with great sadness that the Ministry of Defence must confirm that Sapper Richard Reginald Walker from 28 Engineer Regiment, attached to 21 Engineer Regiment as part of the Task Force Helmand Engineer Group, was killed in Afghanistan on Monday 7 January 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was shot in an apparent ‘insider attack’ by a member of the Afghan National Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;) at Patrol Base Hazrat in the Nahr-e Saraj district of Helmand province on Monday 7 January 2013. He was working on a construction task with other military engineers from his Troop, as part of the preparations to hand the camp over to Afghan security forces, when the Afghan soldier turned his weapon on &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; soldiers at the base. The incident resulted in a number of casualties, all of whom were extracted to the Bastion Role 3 medical facility where Sapper Walker was pronounced dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sapper-richard-reginald-walker-corps-of-royal-engineers"&gt;Sapper Richard Reginald Walker, Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sapper Richard Walker [Picture: via MOD]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5924/130107-NRI-TFH_Engr-Eulogy-WALKER.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sapper Richard Walker&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sapper Richard Walker was born on 7 February 1989 in Leeds. He worked as a technician for Vauxhall before joining the Army in July 2008. Upon joining the Royal Engineers he completed his basic training at the Army Training Regiment Bassingbourn before moving on to Gibraltar Barracks, Minley, where he completed his Phase Two Combat Engineer Training. He then moved to the Defence School of Transport Leconfield where he completed his trade training to become a driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He joined his first unit, 28 Engineer Regiment in Hameln, Germany, in September 2009, deploying with them to Canada and then Kenya on major exercises. His Troop, from 42 Field Squadron, was attached to 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron (73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt;) based in Ripon, North Yorkshire for Operation Herrick 17. His Troop joined 73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt; in August 2012 and deployed with the Squadron to Afghanistan at the start of September as part of the Task Force Helmand Engineer Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was a valued member of 73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt; and deployed on every single Troop task. He was a popular and well respected member of his Troop and upon joining the Squadron he quickly gained friends across the spectrum of ranks; a testament to his likeable character and willingness to join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An avid football fan, Sapper Walker represented his Regiment at football and spent endless hours in the gym. He even managed to spend some time trying to learn to play the guitar albeit one chord at a time. Above all he was a devoted father and would talk for hours on end about his love for his daughter Lilly-Faith who sadly he only knew for 18 months before his deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was destined to go on to greater things – his willingness to learn, unswerving sense of duty and personal motivation to pursue a successful career would have seen him progress far. Above all he will be remembered for his charisma and team spirit; a true all-rounder, his loss will be felt for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker’s family paid the following tribute to their son and brother:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richard held two things close to his heart – his daughter and his colleagues in the Army. A proud, patriotic man, he died doing a job he loved, supporting his friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Chas Story &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Commanding Officer, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was the epitome of a true Sapper, one who would roll up his sleeves and get on with the task in hand no matter what, but importantly he would do it with great humour. He made sure that he made the most of every opportunity, both in the Army and at home; it is without doubt that he had a lot to offer and a bright future. He was hugely respected as a fit, professional soldier with a massive character. This was his first tour of Afghanistan but anyone would have thought he was a seasoned expert, such was his ability and professionalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our thoughts and prayers are with his family, including his young daughter Lilly-Faith, at this very difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jack Nicholson &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Commanding Officer, 21 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the short time that Sapper Walker served with my Regiment he struck me as being a driven young man, full of ambition and oozing with professional pride and confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An outstanding soldier in the best traditions of The Corps of Royal Engineers, he made an immediate impact on all those who had the privilege of serving alongside him. Although on his first operational tour, he acted like a veteran of many years’ experience and clearly relished the challenges he faced with his Troop in Afghanistan. Hard working and utterly loyal to his mates, he was a real character who had established himself as a man of action within his adopted Squadron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His tragic loss has stunned the whole Engineer Group and we are all trying desperately to come to terms with this awful event. Our heartfelt condolences are with his family and friends at this terrible time, most especially his young daughter Lilly-Faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Chloe Plimmer &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Officer Commanding, 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron, 21 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I first met Sapper Walker when he arrived with his Troop to join our Squadron for the forthcoming deployment to Afghanistan. He immediately struck me as a very likeable character; a polite and motivated young soldier who was very keen to deploy on his first operational tour. He saw it as the culmination of all his training and was excited about the prospect of operational service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the initial months spent in theatre Sapper Walker was a key member of his Troop and was crucial to facilitating every task that they undertook; he had the skill-set to operate a number of critical vehicles. His enthusiasm for his role and the success that the Troop achieved during this time were undoubtedly testament to his professionalism; always keen to be involved, he would give his best at all times even when under considerable pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whenever I saw Sapper Walker he always made a point of saying ‘hello’ and I felt that I got to know him better than many other soldiers in the Squadron. I never once doubted his motivation and he always said he was ‘living the dream’. He was a bright, cheerful, fun soldier who was relishing the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We in 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron have been hugely privileged to have Sapper Walker’s Troop attached to us and as an individual he was a shining example to all ranks across the board. His positive attitude and excellent performance ensured that he was seen as one of our own, and our heartfelt sympathies go out to all of those in his Troop and also his friends and colleagues in 42 Field Support Squadron and 28 Engineer Regiment back in Germany. He was one of the very best and we are all left feeling hollow and saddened by his loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To his family, there are no amount of words that can reduce the pain of losing such a brave son, brother and doting father to Lilly-Faith. Our deepest condolences are with them at this extremely difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Brad Southall &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Support Troop Commander, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was a shining star. When I took command of my troop I was struck by his charisma, his devotion to duty and his immense capability; he was the older brother whom everyone looked up to. To his friends he was hugely loyal and he was headstrong too. I could discuss tasks with him at length but he would always end up doing things his way; he was so determined. I began to accept that over time it was his view that counted and I learned to trust him immeasurably. He was passionate and committed to his work – a consummate professional. He died doing the job he loved and I am proud to have served alongside him; a fellow Sapper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He spoke often of his daughter, Lilly-Faith, and was a proud and devoted father. My thoughts and condolences are with his family and friends at this most tragic time. The Regiment has lost one of its best men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Sean Eaton, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have had the privilege of knowing Sapper Richie Walker for well over a year now. Firstly in my Troop in Kenya last year and now on Operation Herrick 17. Sapper Walker was a character and always present to give a small quip when required. As a soldier he remained professional in all that was asked of him. He had started a physical training regime with the aspiration to box on return from Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker has a young daughter, Lilly-Faith, who was never far from his mind. He would often speak about her with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I only knew Richie for a short time, but he has left a lasting impression on me and will never be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My thoughts go out to his family at this difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Corporal Terry Burke, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve have had the privilege of knowing Richie since he joined 28 Engineer Regiment through the Regimental Football Team. However, I really got to know him throughout the last year when I joined his Troop in 42 Squadron back in Hameln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I class Richie as a close friend who was always there with a smile on his face, especially when he was talking about his daughter Lilly-Faith; he was a very proud dad. I had only spoken to him on 3 January 2013 while on R&amp;amp;R and he told me how much he had enjoyed spending time with his daughter at the beginning of December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As well as being in the next bed space to me out here, we tended to go the gym together where Richie was keen on getting the perfect six-pack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of the lads that have ever met Richie know what a great friend he was. He will be sorely missed. All our thoughts are with his daughter Lilly-Faith at this sad time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Liam Ballantyne, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I first met Richie in October 2009 when I joined 42 Field Squadron. I was allocated a bed space in the same room and we hit it off as friends immediately. Richie was always willing to assist me with anything that I needed having come straight from Training Regiment myself. It was clear to me from the start that he was an extremely caring and thoughtful individual to all around him and he immediately became a very loyal friend. We would have done anything for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the years, we visited each other in our home towns and we got to know each other’s families during these visits. We enjoyed some great times and his family always extended their greatest hospitality to me whenever I stayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie was a devoted father who would have done anything for his daughter, Lilly-Faith. He never stopped talking about her wherever we were. I even remember being on stag in the Kenyan bush with him and all he could talk about was his daughter, despite the ever present threat of lions roaming close by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie, you were a truly wonderful person and that is why people were naturally drawn towards you as a friend. You were a true brother to me; you will never be forgotten and you will be sadly missed by all who knew you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Matthew Cunningham, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Richie ‘Guns’ Walker – comrade, friend, father and much-loved son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I knew Richie for 3 years and was privileged to be able to call him my best mate. He was thoughtful, funny and a big character in any group he found himself amongst, but he always put others first. He was very wise and mature for such a young lad. I have so many good memories from over the last three years but the one that stands out the most for me was the day that he christened his daughter Lilly-Faith. He was so proud of her; that day I remember him standing that extra inch taller and his smile beaming more than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You will be sorely missed brother, gone but never forgotten until we meet again at the bar in the sky… RIP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all members of 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We had the privilege of knowing and working with Richie from the start of Operation Herrick 17. In this time we have found out that he is a joy to work with, plus an amiable character amongst the Troop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie was always talking about his daughter, Lilly-Faith, and from this you could tell he was a devoted father and loved his little Princess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He was a top bloke and our condolences go out to his family; he will be sorely missed by all who were fortunate enough to have known him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Defence, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was deeply saddened to learn of the death of Sapper Richard Walker. The tributes of his colleagues speak of a popular, committed soldier who was devoted to his unit and a dedicated family man. I send my deepest condolences to his family and loved ones at this sad time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64330</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/libya-operation-recognition-for-naval-air-squadron-personnel"/>
    <title>Libya operation recognition for Naval Air Squadron personnel</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy personnel from 815 Naval Air Squadron have received medals for their part in the NATO-led Libya operation in 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 4 servicemen from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; are among 1,500 Royal Navy personnel to receive medals for their part in the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;-led Libya operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aircrew and engineers, based at Royal Naval Air Station Yeovilton, were presented with &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; Operation Unified Protector medals for their participation in the Libya operation while serving with 217 Flight on board &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Decommissioned-Units/HMS-Liverpool" title="HMS Liverpool web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Naval Air Squadron personnel with their Operation Unified Protector medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5919/HMS_Liverpool_Flight_NATO_Medals_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: Lieutenant Alastair Crawford, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Lieutenant Craig Farquharson with their Operation Unified Protector medals [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The four who received medals for the operation were Lieutenant Alistair Crawford, Lieutenant Craig Farquharson, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Air Engineering Technician Matthew Parker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Crawford, from Yeovil, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;217 Flight and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool made a vital contribution to Operation Unified Protector, always at the forefront of helping to protect Libyan civilians and just show the flexibility of the Royal Navy and Fleet Air Arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer Perry, from Worcester, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud to have had the opportunity to help the Libyan civilians and put my years of experience to the best possible use. Medals are nice but that is the real reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They formed part of the high-profile &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; task force to provide maritime embargo operations and to control the no-fly zone to help protect the Libyan civilian population. The Flight were pivotal to the success of the maritime operation as they provided surface search and routine maritime patrols to counter the threat posed by pro-Gaddafi forces in laying mines in the vicinity of Libyan ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of the oldest warships in the Royal Navy, the team of aircrew and engineers regularly operated at high readiness, which required them to be on 15 minutes’ standby to launch over many nights, and all this achieved in spite of the sustained exposure to the harsh environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all of the problems they encountered, their aircraft flew over 270 hours in support of the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; mission, including 75 hours in August 2011 alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout their 8-month operational deployment, 217 Flight continually demonstrated an unquestionable commitment in support of the overall task group output. The engineering effort was pivotal to the exceptional aircraft availability enjoyed by &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool’s command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticlePresenter/64320</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:13:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/marines-train-to-tackle-pirates"/>
    <title>Marines train to tackle pirates </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Marines based on the deployed warship HMS Monmouth have been practising their ship-boarding skills to combat pirates and smugglers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the ship’s company of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; is a detachment of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="The Royal Marines website"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt;, vital for &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s tasking at sea. One of the major roles of the Marines is conducting boarding missions against suspected pirates and smugglers. To hone these skills they used their time on land to visit a specialist ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ facility owned by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5912/20130109commandos02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ recreates a realistic section of a ship in which ‘room clearance’ drills may be practised and perfected with a dramatic sense of realism. High-powered Airsoft simulation weapons are used in the facility, which range from rifles, shotguns and pistols to claymore mines. They really pack a punch, so much so that personal protective equipment must be worn when magazines are fitted and rounds are flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team of Royal Marines are on detachment from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/43-Cdo-Fleet-Protection-Group" title="43 Commando Fleet Protection Group Royal Marines website"&gt;43 Commando Fleet Protection Group&lt;/a&gt;, based at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Clyde" title="Her Majesty's Naval Base Clyde website"&gt;HM Naval Base Clyde&lt;/a&gt;, Faslane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5914/20130109commandos04.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Will Hall, Officer Commanding &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s Royal Marines detachment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My Marines really benefited from the training provided by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard at their facility in Bahrain - the instructors were incredibly hospitable and approachable, whilst the use of Airsoft weapons added a level of realism to the scenarios that is difficult to achieve in the training environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The team is now prepared and ready to put their skills to use during boarding operations in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5913/20130109commandos01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Marines’ exercise comes after a busy time at sea over Christmas and has given the rest of the ship’s company time to recharge their batteries in preparation for the challenges of the New Year in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth continues her 7-month deployment of the region, conducting maritime security patrols the Arabian Sea, the northern Indian Ocean and the Gulf of Aden. Whilst deployed, Monmouth will also be carrying out security patrols and exercises with coalition forces in the region to strengthen ties with foreign allies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuidePresenter/64283</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:19:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-defence-training-and-education-capability-programme"/>
    <title>The defence training and education capability programme</title>
    <category>Detailed guidance</category>
    <summary>The defence training and education capability (DTEC) programme takes an enterprise approach to training and simulation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence training and education capability"&gt;DTEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme was born from the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Defence and Security Review"&gt;SDSR&lt;/abbr&gt; 2010 that stated that the Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;) should embrace a step change in its exploitation of modern simulation training systems in order to increase operational effectiveness, reduce costs and minimise the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s environmental footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key aspect of the change is to increase the pace of &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s acquisition processes to better exploit rapidly improving technology and to address the broader cultural barriers to the use of simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="current-activities"&gt;Current activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence training and education capability"&gt;DTEC&lt;/abbr&gt; is reviewing a number of its activities including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An end-to-end approach to training led by operational needs and front line commands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A systems approach to training products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards and networking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and possible industry input to &lt;abbr title="Defence training and education capability"&gt;DTEC&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A need to overhaul procurement arrangements to enable rapid acquistion of off-the-shelf solutions and applications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wider exploitation of networked training and learning systems to support mission planning/preparation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capability test, experimentation and evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For &lt;abbr title="Defence training and education capability"&gt;DTEC&lt;/abbr&gt; project support contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Brooking
email: &lt;a href="mailto:DESPTG-DTSI-PSF-ABMgr@mod.uk"&gt;DESPTG-DTSI-PSF-ABMgr@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tel: 030 679 30428&lt;br&gt;
Mob: 07747 898124  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Bailey
email: &lt;a href="DESPTG-DSTI-PSF-RSMgr@mod.uk"&gt;DESPTG-DSTI-PSF-RSMgr@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tel: 030 679 71321&lt;br&gt;
Mob: 07787 526920  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PolicyPresenter/64300</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:11:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"/>
    <title>Countering weapons proliferation </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Securing global safety by preventing countries and terrorists access to the materials needed for weapons of mass destruction.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of weapons of mass destruction (&lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;) poses a threat to the UK and the international community. Indiscriminate trade in conventional arms and the use of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (&lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt;) weapons and ballistic missiles raises serious humanitarian and security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working around the world to champion and implement UK policies as set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the spread of &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; weapons and ballistic missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works with international partners and through organisations such as the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, G8, NATO and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce terrorists’ ability to create, obtain or use &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; materials and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the FCO’s tools to combat these threats is our Counter-Proliferation Programme. In the financial year 2012 to 13, the value of the programme is £3 million. This funding is used to support projects around the world which increase political will or technical capacity to reduce the threat of weapons proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-counter-proliferation-strategy"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in March 2012. The strategy’s main aims are to deny terrorists the materials and expertise to make and use &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;; to stop countries such as Iran and North Korea from obtaining &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt; or advanced conventional weapons; and to build up the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/About/"&gt;International Atomic Energy Agency (&lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; and other organisations and treaties that help us meet our goals through the international community and which help to protect global security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemical-weapons"&gt;Chemical weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the destruction of remaining chemical weapons stocks and works to encourage full national implementation of the Chemical Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;) by all countries. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/the-chemical-weapons-convention"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention&lt;/a&gt; bans the development, production, stockpiling and use of chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biological-weapons"&gt;Biological weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has signed up to the global implementation of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/04FBBDD6315AC720C1257180004B1B2F?OpenDocument"&gt;Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of the convention is to help prevent states acquiring or keeping biological and toxin weapons, and prevent them ever being used by states or terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt; doesn’t have a verification system like that of the &lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Participating countries are required to submit relevant data and declarations, or confidence-building measures, to the United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs. This increases openness and gives participating countries confidence that others are complying with the convention. The UK’s confidence building measures are published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/CEC2E2D361ADFEE7C12572BC0032F058?OpenDocument"&gt;Implementation Support Unit website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-weapons"&gt;Nuclear weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;. The UK is one of 189 states that have signed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The treaty aims to stop the spread of nuclear weapons and ultimately eliminate them. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; has three equally important ‘pillars’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to work towards non-proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to champion nuclear disarmament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nuclear-security"&gt;Nuclear security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK will continue work to strengthen international nuclear security by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the security of fissile materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing the number of sites containing nuclear and radiological material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing the acquisition of proliferation-relevant information and expertise by terrorists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through the successful development of the UK’s Global Threat Reduction Programme we are reducing the threats posed by nuclear and radiological materials and expertise in vulnerable locations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting the full implementation of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sc8076.doc.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Resolution 1540&lt;/a&gt;, which requires all states to refrain from supporting non-government agents from developing, acquiring, manufacturing, possessing, transporting, transferring or using nuclear, chemical or biological weapons and their delivery systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK also supports and contributes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nti.org/treaties-and-regimes/global-partnership-against-spread-weapons-and-materials-mass-destruction-10-plus-10-over-10-program/"&gt;Global Partnership Against the Spread of Weapons and Materials of Mass Destruction&lt;/a&gt;, agreed at the G8 Summit at Kananaskis, Canada in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-programmes"&gt;State programmes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the international legal framework, conventions and treaties, some countries have active programmes to develop and produce &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Of particular concern is Iran’s nuclear programme; the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s nuclear programme and willingness to provide weapons to other countries; and Syria’s possession of chemical and biological weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works through various international organisations to seek peaceful means to reduce the threat from these programmes and the networks that support them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arms-trade-treaty"&gt;Arms Trade Treaty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a legitimate arms trade, there is also an urgent need for more effective and coherent international regulation of that trade. The UK is working to achieve an international arms trade treaty to provide clearer and more effective control of the illegal arms trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; conference in July 2012 was unable to adopt an Arms Trade Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, the UK will continue to play a leading role in future negotiations to help to secure one. An &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to reduce the flow of weapons from legitimate trade to the illicit market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; process towards an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; and submissions from states (including the UK’s views on an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/first/63/documentation.shtml"&gt;United Nations General Assembly website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="export-licensing"&gt;Export licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has joined other governments around the world to pursue &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/3849543/eu-arms-export"&gt;collective implementation of export controls&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the proliferation of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The 4 main export control regimes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.australiagroup.net/en/index.html"&gt;Australia Group&lt;/a&gt; - designed to harmonise export control measures aimed at curtailing the unhindered proliferation of chemical weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mtcr.info/english/index.html"&gt;Missile Technology Control Regime&lt;/a&gt; - an informal and voluntary association of countries that share the goal of non-proliferation of unmanned delivery systems of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/Leng/default.htm"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt; - responsible for making sure nuclear export controls work in practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt; - established to promote transparency and greater responsiblity in transfers of conventional arms and dual-use goods and technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read further details about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s regulatory authority responsible for assessing and issuing strategic export licences to UK exporters is the Export Control Organisation (ECO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS). Read more about the UK’s policies and procedures for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2"&gt;controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;) was born out of fear that the Cold War era would lead to a nuclear arms race and is still the basis of the international nuclear non-proliferation regime. All states are now party to it apart from India, Israel, Pakistan and South Sudan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; provides for a Review Conference every 5 years, both to review developments over the previous 5 years and to look ahead to the future. At the last &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;Review Conference in 2010&lt;/a&gt; a series of action plans were agreed to enhance implementation of the treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/"&gt;The International Atomic Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt; was set up as the world’s ‘Atoms for Peace’ organisation in 1957 within the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; family, and supports the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The agency is at the centre of international efforts to address Iran’s nuclear dossier and to ensure the benefits of safe and secure peaceful nuclear energy are accessible to everyone, not just to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thenuclearsecuritysummit.org/eng_main/main.jsp"&gt;Seoul Nuclear Security Summit&lt;/a&gt; assembled 53 countries, the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; and Interpol, to continue work to secure vulnerable nuclear material around the world within 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 December 2008 in the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly, 133 States voted in favour of a draft resolution ‘Towards an Arms Trade Treaty’. There was a clear majority view that, working together, the international community can shape an Arms Trade Treaty into an effective legally binding mechanism to regulate the international trade in arms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our detailed guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-embargoes-and-restrictions"&gt;sanctions, embargoes and restrictions.&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/current-arms-embargoes-and-other-restrictions"&gt;Current arms embargoes and other restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the Common Foreign and Security Policy (&lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; applies restrictive measures in pursuit of the specific &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; objectives set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/treaties/index.htm"&gt;Treaty on European Union.&lt;/a&gt; (see particularly Article 11)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; External Action website&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of restrictive measures adopted in the framework of the &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; that are currently in force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/sc/committees/list_compend.shtml"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Sanctions Committees website&lt;/a&gt; contains links to the latest versions of all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council targeted sanctions lists. The individuals and entities included in these lists are subject to the relevant measures imposed by the Security Council, and all member states are obliged to implement these measures. Each separate list is maintained by the relevant Security Council Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
